<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: Of the Effect of Gratiola in Madness</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title>IV. Von der Wirkung der Gratiola im Wahnsinn; i. e. Of the Effect of Gratiola in
              Madness, by L. F. B. Lentin. See Journal der Practischen Heilkunde; i. e. Journal of
              Practical Medicine and Surgery, published by C. W. Hufeland, Professor of Medicine at
              Jena, Vol. I. Jena, 1795.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Annals of Medicine , for the year 1796. Exhibiting a concise view of the latest
              and most important discoveries in medicine and medical philosophy. By Andrew Duncan,
              Sen. M. D. and Andrew Duncan, Jun. M. D. Fellows of the Royal College of Physicians,
              Edinburgh.</title>
            <author>Andrew Duncan, Sen. M. D. and Andrew Duncan, Jun. M. D.</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh : Printed by J. Pillans &amp; Sons, for W. Mudie, South Bridge;
                  and for G. G. and J. Robinson, London.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1796</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">1</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">41-43</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108918448</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T193457</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ4_v1_0041">
    <body>
      <pb n="41"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>IV. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>Von der Wirkung der Gratiola im Wahnſinn; i. e. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>Of the Effect of Gratiola in Madneſs, by <hi rend="roman">L. F. <lb/>B. Lentin</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>See Journal der Pracliſchen Heilkunde; i. e. <lb/>Journal of Practical Medicine and
        Surgery, <lb/>publiſhed by <hi rend="roman">C. W. Hufeland</hi>, Profeſſor of <lb/>Medicine
        at Jena, <hi rend="roman">Vol. I</hi>. <hi rend="roman">Jena, 1795.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">D</hi>R <hi rend="sc">Lentin</hi> obſerves, that, although we
        <lb/>have deſerted the uſe of hellebore <lb/>in madneſs, it is ſtill an axiom among old
        <lb/>phyſicians, to treat that diſeaſe in moſt caſes <lb/>with emetics and purgatives; and
        that we <lb/>are only too timorous, or too bold, in our <lb/>choice of them. Our author has
        been ſo <lb/>fortunate, as to derive great advantage, in <lb/>three ſucceſſive caſes, from
        the powder of <lb/>Gratiola. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Two of the patients were brothers, whoſe <lb/>father was not actually mad, but only
        <lb/>crazy. Their uncle was completely de- <pb n="42"/>
        <lb/>ranged, and continued ſo till his death, in his <lb/>65th year. Both brothers were
        ſeized, at <lb/>an early period of life, after unuſually hard <lb/>ſtudy. Praiſe and reward
        ſharpened their <lb/>deſire of honour; and, redoubling their in- <lb/>duſtry, they denied
        themſelves ſleep, and <lb/>every invigorating recreation. A miſtaken <lb/>enthuſiaſm
        prevailed over reaſon, and would <lb/>not liſten to any remonſtrance. At firſt <lb/>every
        action perfectly reſembled Addiſon's <lb/>deſcription of a dream: <q rend="diple quotes">The
          ſoul, in dreams, <lb/>converſes with numberleſs beings of her <lb/>own creation, and is
          tranſported into ten <lb/>thouſand ſcenes of her own raiſing. She <lb/>is herſelf the
          theatre, the actors, and the <lb/>beholder; </q> and beſides, the patient always
        <lb/>plays the moſt important and conſpicuous <lb/>part. Every thing paſſed hitherto pretty
        <lb/>quietly; the nights alone were ſleepleſs, and <lb/>ſpent in frequent changes of ideas.
        At laſt <lb/>the delirium of one of the brothers increa- <lb/>ſed ſo much, that he attacked
        his mother <lb/>and attendants, and leapt out of his win- <lb/>dow, though without being
        materially hurt. <lb/>Dr Lentin did not obſerve in him the ſymp- <lb/>toms deſcribed by
        Auenbrugger, the retrac- <pb n="43"/>
        <lb/>tion of one or both teſticles, which is ſaid <lb/>to take place. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The patient was at firſt copiouſly bled; <lb/>and as none of the uſual remedies were
        <lb/>ſtrong enough to procure the neceſſary eva- <lb/>cuations, he was made to vomit with
        from <lb/>three to five grains of white vitriol, after <lb/>he had gotten a ſtimulating
        clyſter. Dr <lb/>Lentin now preſcribed for him half a ſcruple <lb/>of powdered Gratiola
        every morning, and <lb/>as much every evening, with a decoction <lb/>of graſs-root for his
        drink. This was con- <lb/>tinued, until the returning irritability of the <lb/>viſcera
        rendered a diminution of the doſe <lb/>neceſſary. After the evacuation of a great
        <lb/>quantity of bilious matter, he was completely <lb/>reſtored; as were alſo the other
        two, by the <lb/>ſame method of treatment. They were all <lb/>of a temperament which
        indicated the uſe of <lb/>ſtrong ſtimulating remedies. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
