<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Pearson: A Case of Obstinate Constipation of the Bowels</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Dr Pearson</persName>
            </author>
            <title>III. A Case of Obstinate Constipation of the Bowels, cured by Calomel.
              Communicated to Dr Pearson, by Dr David Hosack, New York.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Annals of Medicine , for the year 1796. Exhibiting a concise view of the latest
              and most important discoveries in medicine and medical philosophy. By Andrew Duncan,
              Sen. M. D. and Andrew Duncan, Jun. M. D. Fellows of the Royal College of Physicians,
              Edinburgh.</title>
            <editor>Andrew Duncan, Sen. M. D. and Andrew Duncan, Jun. M. D.</editor>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh : Printed by J. Pillans &amp; Sons, for W. Mudie, South Bridge;
                  and for G. G. and J. Robinson, London.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1796</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">1</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">310-317</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108918448</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T193457</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ4_v1_0310">
    <body>
      <pb n="310"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>III. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>A Caſe of Obſtinate Conſtipation of the Bowels, <lb/>cured by Calomel. Communicated to
        Dr Pear- <lb/>ſon, by Dr <hi rend="roman">David Hoſack</hi>, New York. </head>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi>
        <hi rend="sc">Constipation</hi> of the bowels is a diſ- <lb/>eaſe familiar to every
        phyſician; but <lb/>when it has been of long continuance, and at <lb/>laſt removed, it is of
        importance to become <lb/>acquainted with the means of cure: Every <lb/>caſe of this kind is
        inſtructive and uſeful, al- <lb/>though it may only ſerve to confirm us in <lb/>principles
        already known. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Samuel Denton, clerk in dry-goods ſtore, <lb/>aged twenty, of a bilious habit of body,
        ſent <lb/>for me on the morning of September 28. <lb/>1795. He complained of great
        uneaſineſs <lb/>and griping in his bowels, attended with <lb/>ſlight chill, a coldneſs of
        his extremities, and <lb/>a ſmall but regular pulſe. Upon inquiry, <lb/>he told me he had
        been attacked in the <lb/>night; and aſcribed his complaint to ſome <lb/>honey he had taken
        in the evening at his <pb n="311"/>
        <lb/>tea; adding, that it had frequently ſerved <lb/>him ſo before, and that he was ſubject
        to <lb/>colic and coſtiveneſs upon any irregularity of <lb/>diet, or upon imprudent expoſure
        to cold. <lb/>He informed me, that about five days before, <lb/>he had had a ſlight attack
        of the ſame ſort, <lb/>brought on in the ſame way; and that, <lb/>ſince that time, his
        ſtools had been much <lb/>more watery than uſual. From this laſt cir- <lb/>cumſtance, I am
        diſpoſed to date his diſeaſe <lb/>from September 23. the time of the firſt at- <lb/>tack,
        ſeeing that his ſtools, ſince that time, <lb/>were not of their proper conſiſtence; but
        <lb/>leſt there be any error in the calculation, I <lb/>ſhall date it from September 28. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Early on the morning of the 28th, upon <lb/>which I firſt viſited him, he had taken an
        <lb/>ounce of caſtor-oil, which at two o'clock in <lb/>the afternoon had not operated. Imme-
        <lb/>diately I ſent him the following mixture, di- <lb/>recting him to drink freely of thin
        chicken- <lb/>broth. <floatingText>
          <body>
            <p rend="indentall hanging">
              <lb/>℞. Pulv. rhei, ʒij. <lb/>Magneſ. alb. ʒj <lb/>Aq. Menthæ, ℥iij. M. Sumt. dimi-
              <lb/>diam ſtatim et alteram partem ter- <lb/>tia hora poſtea, ſi opus ſit. </p>
          </body>
        </floatingText>
        <pb n="312"/>
        <lb/>At four o'clock, his pains increaſing, I or- <lb/>dered enemas of warm water, ſweet
        oil, and <lb/>molaſſes, to be adminiſtered every two hours, <lb/>until his bowels ſhould be
        emptied: they <lb/>were accordingly exhibited, but without <lb/>any good effect. At eight
        o'clock in the <lb/>evening, I gave him ten grains of calomel. <lb/>In the night, his pain
        and other ſymptoms <lb/>became ſo violent, as to threaten inflamma- <lb/>tion of his bowels;
        his pulſe, as is common <lb/>in inflammations of this ſort, was ſmall and <lb/>tenſe. I
        immediately opened a vein in the <lb/>arm, and, obſerving his pulſe to riſe, I drew
        <lb/>between ſixteen and twenty ounces of blood, <lb/>which in a few minutes became covered
        <lb/>with a ſtrong ſizy coat. I ordered a large <lb/>bliſter to be applied to his belly; the
        gly- <lb/>ſters to be repeated with an addition of <lb/>Glauber's ſalts, and to be thrown up
        in large <lb/>quantities. On the 29th, ſymptoms of great <lb/>inflammation ſtill continuing,
        I again bled <lb/>him very largely; gave him a ſcruple of <lb/>calomel, with one grain of
        opium: I order- <lb/>ed the injections to be repeated every hour, <lb/>and flannels wrung
        out of warm water to <lb/>be applied to his belly every quarter of an <pb n="313"/>
        <lb/>hour: All which were done with the moſt <lb/>ſcrupulous attention. In the afternoon,
        the <lb/>calomel was repeated without the opium. <lb/>In the evening, finding no proſpect of
        re- <lb/>lief, I though it neceſſary to have the ad- <lb/>vice of ſome other phyſicians,
        when Profeſ- <lb/>ſors Bayley and Poſt were called in. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It was propoſed by thoſe gentlemen to <lb/>employ the warm-bath, and to take away a
        <lb/>few more ounces of blood; which were ac- <lb/>cordingly done. By theſe meaſures, the
        <lb/>inflammation was ſubdued, but without ef- <lb/>fecting any diſcharge from the bowels:
        the <lb/>injections were continued from time to time, <lb/>but came away as they were
        exhibited, with- <lb/>out the ſmalleſt feculent ſmell. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The calomel was repeated in doſes of ten <lb/>grains every ſix hours, which ſat well
        upon <lb/>his ſtomach. It may be proper here to re- <lb/>mark, that throughout the whole of
        his <lb/>complaint, his ſtomach was remarkable re- <lb/>tentive, compared with the uſual
        irritability <lb/>of the organ in diſeaſes of this nature; ſo <lb/>much ſo, that the calomel
        was not rejected <lb/>in any one inſtance. 30th, The calomel, <lb/>warm-bath, and
        injections, were continued. <pb n="314"/>
        <lb/>Without a tedious detail of each day's pre- <lb/>ſcriptions, ſuffice it to obſerve,
        that after <lb/>continuing this plan of treatment for ſeve- <lb/>ral days without benefit,
        it was thought ex- <lb/>pedient to adminiſter other purgative me- <lb/>dicines in addition
        to the calomel, and to <lb/>vary the compoſition of the injections. Ac- <lb/>cordingly, we
        had recourſe to pills compoſed <lb/>of jalap and cream of tartar, of each equal <lb/>parts,
        whitc are much eſteemed in obſtinate <lb/>coſtiveneſs; but in this inſtance they were
        <lb/>exhibited for ſeveral days without any appa- <lb/>rent advantage. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Still continuing the uſe of the calomel as <lb/>before, we next made trial of the
        caſtor- <lb/>oil: when he had taken to the quantity of <lb/>about a pound of this medicine,
        it became <lb/>offenſive to his ſtomach; and we deſiſted <lb/>from its further uſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As his bowels appeared to have loſt all <lb/>ſenſibility to the operation of theſe
        medi- <lb/>cines, we had recourſe to thoſe of a more <lb/>active nature, viz. the pill
        cocciæ and gam- <lb/>boge, combined with jalap: Theſe were <lb/>given in conſiderable
        quantities; but they <lb/>heated his ſyſtem to ſuch a degree, that we <pb n="315"/>
        <lb/>thought it hazardous to proceed further in <lb/>the uſe of them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Soap being recommended by ſome of his <lb/>friends as an infallible remedy in
        conplaints <lb/>of this ſort, with the view to their gratifica- <lb/>tion, it alſo was given
        in large quantities. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But none of theſe medicines appeared to <lb/>produce any good effects with our patient.
        <lb/>The injections were alſo varied: inſtead of <lb/>the warm water, ſweet oil, molaſſes,
        and <lb/>Glauber's ſalts, we made uſe of warm wa- <lb/>ter, caſtor-oil, and molaſſes, with
        Glauber's <lb/>ſalts, and a few ſpoonfuls of the infuſion of <lb/>tobacco: injections of
        tobacco-ſmoke were <lb/>alſo tried: And, laſtly injections of ſtrong <lb/>ſoap-ſuds, which
        in leſs violent caſes fre- <lb/>quently afford relief. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The tobacco-ſmoke, and the compoſition <lb/>containing the infuſion of tobacco,
        occaſion- <lb/>ed conſiderable griping, with narcotic effects, <lb/>and alſo greatly
        weakened our patient, but <lb/>without producing any evacuation from his <lb/>bowels. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There are many inſtances recorded of <lb/>the good effects of daſhing cold water upon
        <lb/>the extremities in caſes of obſtinate conſti- <pb n="316"/>
        <lb/>pation; but in the preſent inſtance, which <lb/>appeared to challenge the whole Materia
        <lb/>Medica, this alſo proved unſucceſsful. Thus <lb/>foiled, we concluded to rely upon the
        ca- <lb/>lomel, and to ſolicit its operation by occa- <lb/>ſional mild glyſters. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Such was the plan of treatment from the <lb/>30th of September until the 19th of Octo-
        <lb/>ber, when he firſt began to complain of ſore- <lb/>neſs of his gums, atteded with a
        rumbling <lb/>of his bowels, and inclination to go to ſtool: <lb/>at this time he had taken
        480 grains of ca- <lb/>lomel, and of the beſt quality, beſide the me- <lb/>dicines already
        related. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>We now conſidered the ſituation of our <lb/>patient to be more favourable; for I
        believe <lb/>it is a general remark among practitioners, <lb/>that when the calomel affected
        the mouth, it <lb/>is attended with a correſponding operation <lb/>upon the bowels, and
        ſhortly after produces <lb/>a diſcharge by ſtool. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Accordingly, upon the morning of the day <lb/>following, viz. the 20th of October, the
        22d <lb/>day of his diſeaſe, his injections came away <lb/>covered with fœculent matter; in
        the even- <lb/>ing, they were followed with moderate diſ- <pb n="317"/>
        <lb/>charges of fœces, in ſmall hard lumps, and <lb/>extremely fœtid. On the 21ſt, his
        ſtools be- <lb/>came frequent, but in lumps of hard conſiſt- <lb/>ence; and thus continued
        for three or four <lb/>days. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>We now deſiſted from the uſe of the ca- <lb/>lomel; ordered him the free uſe of broths
        <lb/>and gruels, which, throughout his diſeaſe, <lb/>had been allowed him but in ſmall
        quanti- <lb/>ties. In eight or ten days, his bowels ap- <lb/>peared to have recovered their
        natural ſtate; <lb/>his ſtrength returned; and he paid a viſit <lb/>to his friends and
        relations in the country, <lb/>who were equally rejoiced and aſtoniſhed at <lb/>his
        recovery. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
