<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Of inoculating the Small-Pox</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Of inoculating the Small-Pox; occasioned by its now raging in several large Towns.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine: and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed by Edw. Cave, at St John's Gate.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1737</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">7</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">561</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ESTC">P1956</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1737_GM_0561">
    <body>
      <pb n="561"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/>Of inoculating the <hi rend="sc">Small-Pox</hi>; occa- <lb/>ſioned by its now raging in
        ſeveral large <lb/>Towns. </head>
      <p>
        <lb/>1. <hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi>LL Mankind (very few excepted) <lb/>being once in Life liable
        to the <lb/>Small-Pox, the Fear thereof is to many a <lb/>one a great Uneaſineſs, and even
          <hi rend="italic">that <lb/>Fear alone</hi> ſo very diſturbing, that a Re- <lb/>medy
        thereof muſt needs be very ac- <lb/>ceptable. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>2. If the Dread of that Diſtemper only <lb/>be ſo very troubleſome, the Danger muſt
        <lb/>be much more affecting. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>3. It ſeizes the Beauty, the pregnant, <lb/>the young, the Adult, and the Aged; Tra-
        <lb/>vellers alſo, when abroad, in dangerous <lb/>Times and Circumſtances; who then (and
        <lb/>Reaſon good) think their Non-inoculation <lb/>an Omiſſion, and wiſh it had been duly
        <lb/>done. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>4 Whenever it comes, there is always <lb/>Pain more or leſs in it, and often Danger. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It hinders near and dear Friends and <lb/>Relations that have not had it, from vi-
        <lb/>ſiting and aſſiſting each other, in their ſo <lb/>great Need of Aid and Succour. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>5. It is apt to continue long in a <lb/>Town after its firſt Invaſion, to the great
        <lb/>Terror and Loſs of the Inhabitants. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><sic>7.</sic> It commonly ſeizes upon Childhood, <lb/>and is found to be ſafer then
        than in ri- <lb/>per Years. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>8. They that eſcape it (if Servants) <lb/>are often not acceptable to good Services,
        <lb/>till it is over with them, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Since therefore an early and ſeaſonable <lb/>Inoculation is a ſure Relief in ſome of
        <lb/>the preceding Caſes, and makes the <lb/>aforeſaid Perſons eaſy all their Days, ſince
        <lb/>it the ſooner frees a Town from the Di- <lb/>ſtemper, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> otherwiſe
        is apt to continue <lb/>long. For had a general Inoculation <lb/>been in Uſe heretofore,
        none, at this <lb/>Time, but the young ones, would have <lb/>wanted it, and <hi
          rend="italic">Tamworth</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Chipping-Norton</hi>, <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Reading</hi>, and other Towns that have had <pb n="562"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>it almoſt a Year, had been free from it <lb/>long ago. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Q.</hi> Whether a general Inoculation of <lb/>Infants when it firſt
        enters a Town, be <lb/>not therefore a good Expedient for ob- <lb/>viating the aforeſaid
        Inconveniences, and <lb/>(imploring the divine Benediction) a pro- <lb/>vident Act of Mercy,
        and a Duty pious, <lb/>prudent, and therefore practicable? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>'Tis true, it don't always anſwer Expec- <lb/>tation, and as true y<hi rend="sup"
          >t</hi> no one Expedient ever <lb/>yet did.— A Perſon may be ſeized <lb/>with an
        uninoculated Sort during his In- <lb/>oculation, which no Mortal can foreſee <lb/>or
        prevent. As to other Accidents that <lb/>may ſeem to diſcourage the Practice.—— <lb/>The
        Inoculator acts according to the beſt <lb/>of his Skill (which frequent Practice and
        <lb/>Obſervation will improve) and according <lb/>to 7th Note above, which is a providen-
        <lb/>tial Indication of the Time of Life when <lb/>it ought to be done, and therefore not to
        <lb/>be then omitted.— He only makes <lb/>an innocent, no mortal Inciſion, plants <lb/>his
        Inoculate with a ſalutary, no wicked <lb/>or inſidious Intention in the leaſt, but to
        <lb/>preſerve his little Patient from all the Mi- <lb/>ſeries it would otherwiſe be liable
        to. <lb/>The reſt he commits to Providence, which <lb/>always acts for the beſt, whatever
        ſhort- <lb/>ſighted Mortals may imagin. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Phyſician, when he gives a Vomit <lb/>or a Purge, or opens a Vein for the Pre-
        <lb/>vention of future Uncertain Ills, is not al- <lb/>ways ſure of the Succeſs, or juſt
        Doſe, <lb/>and the Point of his Lancet goes out of <lb/>his Sight. All other good Deſigns
        what- <lb/>ever have their Accidents that do attend <lb/>them, and bad ones too ſometimes;
        nay, <lb/>even holy Matrimony not excepted. That <lb/>has its Allay now and then, and is
        another <lb/>Inoculation that mortifies ſometimes. Yet <lb/>who foregoes it therefore? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>So that he that inoculates for the <lb/>Small-Pox, does no more than all Man- <lb/>kind
        in ſome Meaſure every Day do, in <lb/>every particular Action of Life whatever, <lb/>and
        ſetting (as in the preſent Caſe) natu- <lb/>ral Affection or Life and Death aſide, are
        <lb/>every way as criminal. If it be a Crime, <lb/>it is only owing to this, That we don't
        <lb/>behold Futurity; and indeed it was never <lb/>deſign'd we ſhould, but to wait upon, and
        <lb/>be ſubmiſſive in all Things to that uner- <lb/>ring Wiſdom that does. Every good De-
        <lb/>ſign or Action ſeems to differ chiefly in <lb/>Degree, and in a Senſe may be called or
        <lb/>accounted, as it were, an Inoculation, <lb/>and every Man an Inoculator, that is, he
        <lb/>projects and acts with good Intentions, <lb/>but the Iſſue does not always anſwer Ex-
        <lb/>pectation: It is not fit it always ſhould <lb/><hi rend="italic">his</hi> that can't
        determine what is beſt. For <lb/>the Lot is caſt into the Lap, but the whole <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>Diſpoſal thereof is done by an inviſible <lb/>Hand that <hi rend="italic">can</hi>
        juſtly determine. And <lb/>what is he that deſires a Mercy, and does <lb/>not truſt in that
        ſupreme Diſpoſer, who <lb/>will moſt certainly grant that Mercy <lb/>(with due Submiſſion
        implored) or one <lb/>ſuperior to it; which is the happy Lot <lb/>of every inoculated
        Infant, whether he <lb/>ſurvive his Inoculation or not; inſo- <lb/>much, that an Infant (fit
        for it) ſuſtains <lb/>no manner of Loſs by Inoculation. Is it <lb/>not a Neglect therefore,
        and Shame as <lb/>great, to ſuffer a poor Child to go abroad <lb/>before it be inoculated,
        that is, with that <lb/>Impurity in it, which Nature one Time <lb/>or other, will throw off,
        as to let it run <lb/>out of Doors in a Diſ—habille, now we <lb/>are taught to diſcharge
        that peccant Hu- <lb/>mour to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> future Eaſe, Safety and Comfort <lb/>of
          y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Child? The Objection of a Return <lb/>after Inoculation is nothing;
        for ſo it <lb/>does ſometimes after the natural way; <lb/>however the ſecond Invaſion is
        found to <lb/>be more favourable. And tho' at preſent <lb/>all cannot come into the
        Practice, yet af- <lb/>ter Time and Experience have improved <lb/>it to a greater Security
        and Convenience, <lb/>'tis poſſible it may have the ſame Fate <lb/>with other Notables at
        their firſt En- <lb/>trance; as the Uſe of Hops, Tobacco, <lb/>the Bark, Wiggs, Shaving the
        Beard, <lb/><hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> For once upon a Time each of <lb/>theſe was
        criminal, and many a little <lb/>Argument muſter'd up againſt them; <lb/>till a better
        Acquaintance and Experience <lb/>at laſt prevailed over Scruples, which in <lb/>Time
        vaniſhed and dwindled into no- <lb/>thing. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
