<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Remarks on the Observations on the Effects of Tea</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Remarks on the Observations on the Effects of Tea</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine: and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed by Edw. Cave, at St John's Gate.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1737</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">7</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">424</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ESTC">P1956</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1737_GM_0424">
    <body>
      <pb n="424"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <head rend="italic align-center">
        <lb/>Remarks on the <hi rend="sc">Observations</hi> on the <lb/>Effects of Tea. <hi
          rend="roman">[See p. 213.]</hi>
      </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE Author of theſe Obſervations <lb/>in his ſecond Paragraph
        ſays, <q rend="quotes">When <lb/><hi rend="italic">Engliſhmen</hi> go to the <hi
            rend="italic">Eaſt-Indies</hi>, the Diet <lb/>there is ſo different from ours here, that
          <lb/>notwithſtanding the <hi rend="italic">Engliſh</hi> on the Spot <lb/>have Naturalized
          it as much as poſſible, <lb/>yet Multitudes die. </q> This is not owing <lb/>to the Change
        of Diet, but to the Violent <lb/>Heat of the Country. He goes on; <q rend="quotes">Here
          <lb/>it may be obſerved, that the Diſorders <lb/>which happen to the <hi rend="italic"
            >Indians</hi> upon uſing <lb/>our Country Diet, are of the Inflamma- <lb/>tory Sort; and
          the Diſorders which hap- <lb/>pen to the <hi rend="italic">Engliſh</hi> upon uſing theirs,
          are of <lb/>the Colliquative Sort. </q> 'Tis well known <lb/>that the Animal Diet of our
        own Country <lb/>often produces the like Diſorders among <lb/>us, epſecially when joyn'd
        with large <lb/>Quantities of Salt, which our Country- <lb/>men to their great Detriment
        always do; <lb/>and as to our uſing their Diet cauſing <lb/>Colliquative Diſorders in us, it
        is falſe; <lb/>for what does he think of Rice, Sago, <lb/>and the like, which are often uſed
        by <lb/>our Phyſicians, for People in a waſting <lb/>Condition? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Lines following are, <q rend="quotes">moſt Peo- <lb/>ple can diſcern, that Rice is
          of a more in- <lb/>ſipid Nature than Wheat, it has leſs nutri- <lb/>tive oily Parts, and
          does produce weaker <lb/>Blood, and poorer Spirits. The Poorneſs of <lb/>their Diet is
          undoubtedly the Cauſe of the <lb/>Feebleneſs and Effeminacy of their Per- <lb/>ſons. </q>
        Here he condemns himſelf, for <lb/>he ſays before that the Produce of all <lb/>Countries is
        ſuited to their Inhabitants. <lb/>How then is the Produce of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Indies</hi>
        <lb/>ſuited to their Inhabitants, if it brings <lb/>on them Feebleneſs and Effeminacy, a
        <lb/>Maraſmus, and many Colliquative Diſor- <lb/>ders? You ſay the Vegetables and Ani-
        <lb/>mals of other Countries are not fit for <lb/>their Diet: What is fit? I think that as
          <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>God has peopled that Part of the World, <lb/>he has ſent ſomething for their Diet. But
        <lb/>he is in an Error; for their Feebleneſs <lb/>and Effeminacy are cauſed from the
        <lb/>Heat of their Country, not by their Diet, <lb/>for that in a great Meaſure prevents it.
        <lb/>Indeed there is not quite ſo much Nutri- <lb/>tive Oil in their Rice as our Corn, yet
        it <lb/>adds much to the Solids, and greatly <lb/>ſtrengthens them, nay, more than our
        <lb/>Corn, tho' it does not make one ſo Fat: <lb/>And if their Solids were not from their
        <lb/>Diet Increaſed, Strengthened, and Sup- <lb/>plied with Fat, they in a ſhort Time from
        <lb/>the Heat of the Country would periſh. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">If I am not miſinformed </q>, ſays he, <q> the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Indians</hi> drink for Pleaſure very little of <lb/>Spirituous Things, but moſtly Tea,
          Salop, <lb/>Sago, and Rice-Gruels, and ſuch like warm <lb/>watry Liquids </q>. I wiſh,
        with all my heart, <lb/>our People wou'd do the ſame; then <lb/>we ſhould have the Weekly
        Bills leſs, and <lb/>not ſo many Murders, and yet not loſe a <lb/>Grain of our <hi
          rend="italic">Engliſh</hi> Spirit, or become <lb/>daſtardly. In the next Paragraph he
        <lb/>recommends Beer, Ale, and Cyder, the <lb/>laſt of which is very good for all ſorts of
        <lb/>People. As for Beer and Ale, they are <lb/>only fit for very hard Laborious People,
        <lb/>and for the Valetudinary and Studious <lb/>are very hurtful. The Remainder of this
        <lb/>Author's Obſervations are falſe Prejudices <lb/>againſt Tea, and an Invective againſt
        the <lb/>Drinkers of it, which has nothing to do <lb/>with the Virtues. Any thing may fall
        <lb/>into abuſe; Who can help it? What can <lb/>be more abuſed than Spirituous Liquors,
        <lb/>Wine, Beer, and Ale? And I think theſe <lb/>laſt, which ſpoil — Servants, require
        <lb/>more y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Conſideration of the Parliament <lb/>than Tea. His
        Prejudices and the <hi rend="italic">Far- <lb/>ther Obſervations on the Ill <choice>
            <corr>Effects</corr>
            <sic>Fffects</sic>
          </choice> of this <lb/>Liquor by a Learned Phyſician</hi>, p. 214, <lb/>who ſays it
        increaſes the Quantity of Bile, <lb/>and that too frequent Drinking Tea ren- <lb/>ders both
        Sexes leſs Fruitful, and ends his <lb/>Obſervations in Praiſe of Sage, I will an- <lb/>ſwer
        together. That Phyſician's whole <lb/>Doctrine is falſe; for Tea is the Preſerver <lb/>of
        Beauty, makes the Old look Young, <lb/>fills the Body with Life and Spirit, good <lb/>Blood,
        and makes the Barren Fruitful: <lb/>There is hardly a Virtue it does not poſ- <lb/>ſeſs.
        'Tis in great eſteem among the Na- <lb/>tives of <hi rend="italic">China</hi>, and <hi
          rend="italic">Japan</hi>, and other <lb/>Places which produce it, for its Sanative
        <lb/>Properties: They uſe it in almoſt all <lb/>their Complaints; and live to a Health-
        <lb/>ful old Age by its Benefit. <hi rend="italic">Schroder</hi>, or <lb/>his Editors, have
        been at the Pains, in his <lb/>Account of this Plant, to give its Uſe and <lb/>Virtues in
        various Languages: Part of <lb/>which I will tranſcribe here. <q rend="quotes">The <pb
            n="425"/>
          <cb n="1"/>
          <lb/>Property of this Herb is to diſcuſs and diſ- <lb/>ſipate or drive away the thineſt
          Humours: <lb/>Whence it follows, that in all Caſes, <lb/>when any are affected with
          Rheums, and <lb/>thin and moiſt Humours, it may to good <lb/>Purpoſe be uſed; whether to
          preſerve <lb/>from, or to cure them of the ſame; eſpe- <lb/>cially in thoſe Diſtillations
          of Humours <lb/>which are called Catarrhs, from whence <lb/>proceed Infirmities of the
          Head and Breaſt, <lb/>Running of the Eyes, Heavineſs of the <lb/>Head, Noiſe in the Ears,
          Shortneſs of <lb/>Breath, Palpitations of the Heart, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
          <lb/>'Tis alſo uſeful in the lower Parts of the <lb/>Body, for weak Stomachs, and in want
          <lb/>of Digeſtion; in the Weakneſs of the <lb/>Joints it is likewiſe ſerviceable, as alſo
          <lb/>for the Gout. In ſhort, the Inhabitants <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">China</hi>, who uſe
          it much, are free from <lb/>the Diſeaſes of the Joints and Reins. <lb/>'Tis good to take
          off the ill Effects of <lb/>hard Drinking, and will enable a Perſon <lb/>to continue a
          long Time without Sleep. <lb/>To Sum up all </q>, ſays he, <q rend="quotes"> it is
          eſteemed the <lb/>great Augmenter of human Strength, <lb/>preſerving from the Accidents
          which <lb/>proceed from ill Air or otherwiſe; to <lb/>which Purpoſe, divers Ambaſſadors,
          re- <lb/>ſiding in thoſe Quarters, uſe it in the <lb/>Morning. </q> This Herb is
        wonderfully <lb/>ſerviceable after Crapula's, by gradually <lb/>helping off the viſcid
        Remains which <lb/>nauſeate and ſicken the Stomach, and a- <lb/>gain, by drawing up its
        Fibres to their <lb/>due Tone. Its Uſe after Dinner, or <lb/>Eating, is of great Service in
        aſſiſting Di- <lb/>geſtion, and preventing the Uneaſineſs <lb/>which attends a full, weakly
        Stomach. <lb/>It ſates the Blood and Juices with ſuch <lb/>gently deterging Parts, as keep
        clean all <lb/>the Emunctories; and it reckon'd by ſome <lb/>to carry its Influences to the
        moſt re- <lb/>mote Parts, and prevents Arthritic Pains. <lb/>It promotes Urine, prevents the
        Stone <lb/>and Gravel, and many Hyſterical Diſor- <lb/>ders. <hi rend="italic">Bohea</hi>
        Tea is of later Diſcovery <lb/>than the <hi rend="italic">Green</hi>, is very Balſamic,
        Analep- <lb/>tic, and Nouriſhing, and good in all Con- <lb/>ſumptions, inward Waſtings,
        Decays, and <lb/>Ulcerations of the Lungs, which has <lb/>made ſome Empirical Pretenders
        impoſe <lb/>upon the World a pretended Spirit of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Bohea</hi> Tea. He
        ſpeaks much in praiſe <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Sage</hi>, as indeed moſt Authors have be-
        <lb/>fore him, tho' it does not deſerve it, and <lb/>tho' it has a few Medical Virtues, is
        not <lb/>fit to be brought into Diet, from the ma- <lb/>ny Miſchiefs that attend it, as
        Colliqua- <lb/>tive Diſorders, Feveriſh Conſumptions, <lb/>and many other Diſeaſes according
        to the <lb/>different Habits of the People that uſe it, <lb/>and is very dangerous to Women
        with <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>Child. I knew a hale ſtrong luſty young <lb/>Man, who uſed Sage for his Breakfaſt,
        <lb/>and as Drink to his Meals; for 2 or 3 <lb/>Days at firſt Uſe, it made him heavy and
        <lb/>dull as if he had been Drunk; after this <lb/>was over, he was ſeemingly in good
        <lb/>Health till about 2 Months, when Pim- <lb/>ples came out on his Face, he began to
        <lb/>loſe his Complection, grew coſtive, was <lb/>very weak, and had violent Pains in his
        <lb/>Back and Reins, and the lower part of <lb/>his Belly; he had frequent motions to
        <lb/>make Water; his Pains encreaſed, his Coſ- <lb/>tiveneſs grew worſe, ſo that at laſt he
        <lb/>had not a Diſcharge that way for five <lb/>Days, which was to be procured only by
        <lb/>ſtrong Cathartics and Clyſters, and with <lb/>ſuch Pain that it flung him into a Fever,
        <lb/>of which he was with great Difficulty <lb/>cured. All the time of uſing Sage Tea he
        <lb/>had a greater Stomach than ever, yet <lb/>was much thinner: He now drinks <lb/>Green
        Tea for his Breakfaſt and in an <lb/>Afternoon, and is in perfect Health. I <lb/>am near 50,
        have Drank Tea twice a <lb/>Day ever ſince I can remember, and ne- <lb/>ver found any Hurt
        by it, nor never have <lb/>had any Diſeaſe ſince I was 10 Years old, <lb/>which was a Fever.
        My Wife alſo drinks <lb/>Tea, and enjoys a perfect State of Health; <lb/>we have had 14
        Children, 9 of which are <lb/>living, all ſtrong and healthy. So I hope <lb/>all ſuch
        Perſons as uſed to drink Tea will <lb/>continue the ſame, and thoſe that did not <lb/>won't
        be frighted from its Uſe by ill- <lb/>grounded Suſpicions. </p>
      <signed rend="italic space align-right">
        <lb/>A Wellwiſher of the Health of <hi rend="roman">Great Britain</hi>. </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
