<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Observation on the Effects of Tea.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Grubstreet Journal, No. 379. Observation on the Effects of Tea.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine: and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed by Edw. Cave, at St John's Gate.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1737</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">7</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">213</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ESTC">P1956</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1737_GM_0213">
    <body>
      <pb n="213"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <dateline rend="align-center">
        <lb/><hi rend="blackletter">Grubſtreet Journal</hi>, Nº 379. </dateline>
      <head rend="italic align-center space">
        <lb/>Obſervations on the Effects of <hi rend="roman">TEA</hi>. </head>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>He Matter of Diet, in every Coun- <lb/>try throughout the World,
        conſiſts <lb/>chiefly of ſuch Animals and Vegetables <lb/>which Experience has proved to be
        nou- <lb/>riſhing, without giving any Diſturbance <lb/>to the Body. Animal Food is of the
        high- <lb/>eſt Kind, for Nouriſhment and Pleaſure <lb/>alſo, while the Appetite laſts; but
        when <lb/>that is ſatiated, Meat is too rich to be con- <lb/>tinued any longer out of
        Pleaſure. Fiſh <lb/>indeed is of a lower and poorer Nature; <lb/>yet even that is
        ſufficiently Rich to clog <lb/>the Appetite before the Stomach can be <lb/>ſaid to be full.
        Vegetables may be eaten <lb/>after either: For there are very few which <lb/>are ſo
        ſatiating, but a Perſon may fill his <lb/>Stomach with them after his Appetite has <lb/>been
        ſatisfied with Fiſh or Fleſh. Hence <lb/>we may obſerve, that no Diet which is <lb/>very
        nouriſhing can be eat to Fullneſs: <lb/>Becauſe thoſe Parts which nouriſh are oy- <lb/>ly
        and very ſatiating, as Fleſh, Eggs, &amp;c. <lb/>but that Diet which is leſs nouriſhing
        <lb/>may, as Vegetables in general. There is <lb/>however in them a very great Difference.
        <lb/>Providence has been ſo bountiful as to fur- <lb/>niſh every Country with a Mixture of
        <lb/>theſe pleaſant Things, along with thoſe <lb/>which are for our real Support; and this
        <lb/>ſeems to be a Matter of Neceſſity: For as <lb/>we ſee the different Climates frame very
        <lb/>different Appetites and Conſtitutions; ſo <lb/>it is very natural to expect, that our
        Pro- <lb/>duce for Food in this Northern Iſle, ſhould <lb/>be unfit for thoſe in the
        Southern Parts. <lb/>A Pound of roaſt Beef and a Quart of <lb/>Ale, which is a common Meal
        for a hearty <lb/>Man here, could hardly be eaten by, <lb/>or if eaten, might endanger the
        Life of, <lb/>an <hi rend="italic">Eaſt-Indian</hi>. On the other Hand, a <lb/>Piece of
        Sugar-cane, and a Cup of Wa- <lb/>ter, which is a very good Meal there, <lb/>would reduce an
          <hi rend="italic">Engliſh-man</hi> ſome Pounds <lb/>lighter and much weaker in a few Days.
        <lb/>So that our Diet ſhould undoubtedly be <lb/>of home growth, </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There ſeems as great a Neceſſity too, <lb/>that our pleaſant Eatables and Drinkables
        <lb/>ſhould be of home growth: For in <hi rend="italic">Bri- <lb/>tain</hi> where we have
        much wet and cold, <lb/>our very Appetites and Paſſions muſt be <lb/>very different from
        thoſe in <hi rend="italic">India</hi>, where <lb/>they have very little Wet, and almoſt no
        <lb/>Cold. The pleaſant Herbs and Fruits of <lb/>each Country muſt alſo be ſo different in
        <lb/>their Qualities, that it is not reaſonable <lb/>to expect, that they ſhould agree with
        the <lb/>different Inhabitants. We ſee this is true <lb/>by Experience: When <hi
          rend="italic">Engliſhmen</hi> go to <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Eaſt-Indies</hi>, the Diet
        there is ſo differ- <lb/><sic>rent</sic> from ours here, that notwithſtanding <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Engliſh</hi> on the Spot have naturalized <lb/>it as much as
        poſſible, yet Multitudes dye. <lb/>Here it may be obſerved, that the Diſor- <lb/>ders which
        happen to <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi> upon uſing <lb/>our Country Diet, are of the
        Inflammato- <lb/>ry Sort; and the Diſorders which happen <lb/>to the <hi rend="italic"
          >Engliſh</hi> upon uſing theirs, are of <lb/>the colliquative Sort. This ſhews, that
        <lb/>our Diet is richer and ſtronger than theirs; <lb/>and that a changing of ours for
        theirs does <lb/>not only hazard our Health, but enfeeble <lb/>our Conſtitutions. Moſt
        People can diſ- <lb/>cern, that Rice is of a more inſipid Na- <lb/>ture than Wheat: It has
        leſs nutritive oily <lb/>Parts, and ſo does produce weaker Blood <lb/>and poorer Spirits.
        The Poorneſs of their <lb/>Diet is undoubtedly the Cauſe of the Fee- <lb/>bleneſs and
        Effeminacy of their Perſons. <lb/>On the contrary, our <hi rend="italic">Engliſh</hi> Beef
        and <lb/>Wheat-pudding for Eatables, and good <lb/>Ale for Drinkables, has very probably
        been <lb/>the Foundation of the antient <hi rend="italic">Engliſh</hi>
        <lb/>Strength and Courage; the Decreaſe of <lb/>which I cannot mention without much
        <lb/>regret. If I am not miſinformed, the <hi rend="italic">In- <lb/>dians</hi> drink for
        Pleaſure very little of ſpi- <lb/>rituous Things, but moſtly Tea, Salop, <lb/>Sago, and Rice
        Gruels, and ſuch like <lb/>warm watry Liquids: And their pleaſura- <lb/>ble Eatables are
        ſuch as Musk and Water- <lb/>melons, Oranges, Citrons, Pomegranates, <lb/>Sugar-cane,
        &amp;c. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>We in <hi rend="italic">Britain</hi> formerly uſed only fer- <lb/>mented Liquors for
        Pleaſure, as Beer, Ale, <lb/>Cyder, Wine, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> and the lower Rank,
        <lb/>who drank the three former of our own <lb/>Produce, were generally a hearty robuſt
        <lb/>People as any in the World; but the richer <lb/>Sort who drank Wine, were liable to ma-
        <lb/>ny Diſeaſes, the Gout and Stone in parti- <lb/>cular: hence it appears plain, that our
        <lb/>Eatables and Drinkables, both for Suſte- <lb/>nance and Pleaſure, ſhould be ſuch as ei-
        <lb/>ther do, or would grow at Home. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Tea</hi> is the Leaf of a ſmall Shrub of <lb/>the Kind of our
        Dog-tree, of an auſtere <lb/>bitter aſtringent Taſte, without any aro- <lb/>matic Warmth. It
        has but very little <lb/>Oyl in it, and that which it has is of the <lb/>reſiny Kind, is
        narcotic and ſtupefactive: <lb/>It has alſo but very little Salt, and that is <lb/>of the
        fixed Kind. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If we conſider the Nature of <hi rend="italic">Tea</hi> with <lb/>the Nature of <hi
          rend="italic">Engliſh</hi> Diet, as mentioned <lb/>before, no one can think it a proper
        Ve- <lb/>getable for our Diet. We ſee this by <lb/>common Experience: the firſt Time Per-
        <lb/>ſons drink it, if they are full grown, it <lb/>generally gives them a Pain at the Sto-
        <lb/>mach, Dejection of Spirits, cold Sweats, <lb/>Palpitation at the Heart, Trembling,
        Fear- <lb/>fulneſs; taking away the Senſe of Full- <lb/>neſs, though preſently after Meals,
        and <lb/>cauſing a Hypocondriac gnawing Appetite<choice>
          <corr>.</corr>
          <sic/>
        </choice>
        <pb n="214"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>Theſe Symptoms (which are very little <lb/>Inferior to what the moſt poiſonous Ve-
        <lb/>getables we have in <hi rend="italic">England</hi> would occa- <lb/>ſion when dryed and
        uſed in the ſame <lb/>Manner) do not however always follow <lb/>the Uſe of it: But
        habituating one's ſelf <lb/>to drink it often, thoſe Effects decreaſe, <lb/>and at length,
        if the Conſtitution is ſtrong, <lb/>quite ceaſe; unleſs the uſual Doſe be increaſ- <lb/>ed,
        and then it diſturbs as before. This is <lb/>the Caſe of Tobacco, and of moſt other
        <lb/>Narcotics, ſuch as Poppies, Nightſhade, <lb/><hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        <hi rend="italic">Tea</hi> is alſo like them in another Effect, <lb/>which it has upon all
        Perſons, that when <lb/>they have accuſtomed themſelves to drink <lb/>it plentifully, they
        cannot with any quiet <lb/>of Mind leave it off. Which is an Argu- <lb/>ment againſt the
        Wholſomeneſs of it, full <lb/>as ſtrong as any of the others: For there <lb/>is Nothing
        which is fit for Food, which ſo <lb/>alters the Body, that the leaving it off <lb/>gives
        diſquiet. And here I may obſerve, <lb/>that although it is a powerful Alterative, <lb/>yet
        the Phyſicians cannot bring it into any <lb/>ſteady Practice. Forty Years ago it was
        <lb/>cried up vaſtly for Conſumptions, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> it <lb/>was tried,
        when the Phyſicians knew much <lb/>leſs from Obſervations on its Effects than <lb/>they do
        now: But neither their former <lb/>Trials on the Sick, <choice>
          <corr>nor</corr>
          <sic>uor</sic>
        </choice> their ſucceeding <lb/>Obſervations of its Effects on the Well, <lb/>have given it
        any Place in Practice. I <lb/>conclude then, that <hi rend="italic">Tea</hi> is utterly
        impro- <lb/>per for Food, hitherto uſeleſs in Phyſick, <lb/>and therefore to be ranged among
        the <lb/>Poyſonous Vegetables. Were it entirely <lb/>wholſome as Balm or Mint, it were yet
        <lb/>Miſchief enough to have our whole Po- <lb/>pulace uſed to ſip warm Water in a min-
        <lb/>cing effeminate Manner once or twice a <lb/>Day; which hot Water muſt be ſupped
        <lb/>out of a nice Tea-cup, ſweetened with Su- <lb/>gar, biting a Bit of nice thin Bread and
        <lb/>Butter between whiles: This mocks the <lb/>ſtrong Appetite, relaxes the Stomach, ſa-
        <lb/>tiates it with trifling light Nick-nacks, <lb/>which have little in them to ſupport
        hard <lb/>Labour. In this Manner the Bold and <lb/>Brave become daſtardly, the Strong be-
        <lb/>come weak, the Women become barren; <lb/>or if they breed, their Blood is made ſo
        <lb/>poor, that they have not the Strength to <lb/>ſuckle, and if they do, the Child dies of
        <lb/>the Gripes. The poor People's Children <lb/>which are bred with it, as they really are
        <lb/>in the Cities and Towns, are only fit for <lb/>Footmen and Chambermaids. May not
        <lb/>this ill Diet be a great Cauſe of the Want <lb/>we have of labouring Servants, the Riſe
        <lb/>of their Wages, and the Prodigality which <lb/>the common Servants have ſhewn within
        <lb/>theſe laſt fifty Years? It is now become <lb/>a Part of the Covenant with labouring <cb
          n="2"/>
        <lb/>Servants truely, that they muſt be allow- <lb/>ed <hi rend="italic">Tea</hi> for
        Breakfaſt. If this unwholſome <lb/>Weed is not in ſome Degree prohibited by <lb/>the
        Government, I can expect Nothing <lb/>leſs, in one Generation more, but that we <lb/>muſt
        hire Foreigners, as they do in <hi rend="italic">Spain</hi>, <lb/>to do our hard Labour; and
        for the De- <lb/>fence of the Nation. I leave any one to <lb/>judge what Soldiers we are
        like to have. <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Spaniards</hi> very likely had felt the <lb/>Force
        of <hi rend="italic">Engliſh</hi> Beer within this laſt 20 <lb/>Years, if the Uſe of it had
        not been ex- <lb/>changed for warm Water bewitch'd with <lb/><hi rend="italic">Indian</hi>
        Poyſon. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The laſt Thing I remark is, that the <lb/>Numbers which drink <hi rend="italic"
          >Tea</hi> are vaſtly great: <lb/>Our home Conſumption plainly ſhews, <lb/>that it is a
        general Practice. Dram-drink- <lb/>ing has been a practice <choice>
          <corr>among</corr>
          <sic>anomg</sic>
        </choice> the poorer <lb/>Sort, becauſe they could be made merry <lb/>with diſtill'd Spirits
        cheaper than they could <lb/>with any other Liquor; and their Want of <lb/>Conduct, has hurt
        the Conſtitutions of <lb/>many. But of whom? why, of a few <lb/>poor Creatures chiefly in
        the City of <hi rend="italic">Lon- <lb/>don</hi>; perhaps 10 in a Pariſh would lie at
        <lb/>the Diſtillers Houſes, and be drunk every <lb/>Day. Suppoſe that there were 5000
        <lb/>which conſtantly uſed theſe hot Liquors <lb/>immoderately in this City, and 15,000
        <lb/>more round about the Nation; what are <lb/>theſe to the Numbers which are daily hurt
        <lb/>by drinking <hi rend="italic">Tea</hi>, Green or Bohea? A third <lb/>Part of the whole
        Nation, computed at <lb/>about three Millions of People, may be <lb/>ſuppoſed to uſe <hi
          rend="italic">Tea</hi> conſtantly every Day: <lb/>and I have heard Perſons in the phyſical
        <lb/>Way aſſert, that moſt of them are hurt <lb/>by it. If now ſuch a very great Number
        <lb/>as three Millions of People, both rich and <lb/>poor, are in a conſtant Uſe of a Liquor
        <lb/>which enfeebles and enervates their Con- <lb/>ſtitutions; it is ſurely of much greater
        <lb/>Conſequence, that as ſtrict a Reſtraint be <lb/>put upon drinking ſuch a noxious
        Liquor, <lb/>as there is now upon the drinking of Spi- <lb/>rituous Liquors; which it is
        hoped may <lb/>deſerve the Notice of our Parliament. </p>
      <signed rend="italic align-right">
        <lb/>Yours, <hi rend="sc">South Briton</hi>. </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
