<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Marshall: An extraordinary Case of a Fœtus, 13 Years in the Body of a
          Woman.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>John Marshall</persName>
            </author>
            <title>from the Champion, Sept. 6. No 67. An extraordinary Case of a Fœtus, 13 Years in
              the Body of a Woman.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine: and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed by Edw. Cave, jun. at St John's Gate:</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1743</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">13</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">484</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ESTC">P1956</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1743_GM_0484">
    <body>
      <pb n="484"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <head rend="align-center size(0.8)">
        <lb/>From the <hi rend="blackletter">Champion</hi>, Sept. 6. N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 67. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>An extraordinary Caſe of a <hi rend="roman">Fœtus</hi>, 13 <lb/>Years in the Body of a
        Woman. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>N the Month of <hi rend="italic">July</hi>, 1731, I was
        <lb/>call'd to the Woman mentioned <hi rend="italic">p.</hi>
        <lb/>443, and found her Body very large and <lb/>hard, and under great Complaints, as
        <lb/>tho' it were Travel-Pains that occaſion'd <lb/>the Diſorder; but, as I perceived no
        <lb/>Opening of the <hi rend="italic">Os Uteri Intern.</hi> by the <lb/>Touch, nor any other
        Symptoms of De- <lb/>livery, I gueſs'd the Caſe to be a <hi rend="italic">Schirrus</hi>
        <lb/>of the Womb, together with an Infla- <lb/>tion of the Abdominal Muſcles; and ac-
        <lb/>cordingly directed a Plaiſter of <hi rend="italic">Gum <lb/>Galb.</hi> and carminative
        Glyſters, by which, <lb/>ſeemingly, ſhe was relieved.—Thus <lb/>ended my Attendance for that
          Time<sic>,</sic>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 28th of <hi rend="italic">July</hi> laſt paſt I was <lb/>again employ'd, and
        found her Body up- <lb/>on the utmoſt Stretch, accompanied with <lb/>an anaſarcous Swelling
        in the lower <lb/>Limbs, therefore judged it to be an <hi rend="italic">Aſ- <lb/>cites</hi>,
        and that Day tapped her, and <lb/>took away four Gallons and a half of <lb/>Liquor, much
        reſembling the Matter <lb/>that is uſually diſcharged from ripe Im- <lb/>poſthumes, but
        thinner in Conſiſtence, <lb/>which was all I durſt draw off then; and, <lb/>as her Strength
        failed faſt, ſo I deſiſted <lb/>from further Attempts. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 13th Inſtant (<hi rend="italic">Auguſt</hi>) ſhe de- <lb/>parted, and was by me
        open'd, when I <lb/>made the following Obſervations.— <lb/>On dividing the outer Teguments,
        I met <lb/>with an adventitious Membrane, of the <lb/>Thickneſs of a Crown-Piece, immedi-
        <lb/>ately under the <hi rend="italic">Peritoneum</hi>, and cloſely <lb/>adhering thereto,
        in the Forepart of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>, wherein was contain'd above
        <lb/>five Gallons of the aboveſaid Matter, <lb/>which was left there when I perform'd
        <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Paracenteſis</hi>, and, in that Liquor, <lb/>the Bones and many
        other Parts of a <pb n="485"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>full-grown <hi rend="italic">Fœtus</hi>.—The ſaid Mem- <lb/>brane or Cover, ſeem'd to
        be the right <lb/><hi rend="italic">Tuba Fallopiana</hi> diſtended to the enor- <lb/>mous
        Size of holding not only the <lb/>Child, but alſo the Quantity of ten Gal- <lb/>lons of
        Water.—The Bottom-part of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Capſula</hi>, near the <hi
          rend="italic">Ovarium</hi>, was <lb/>more than half an Inch thick, and of a <lb/>blackiſh
        Colour, appearing on the In- <lb/>ſide, as if a <hi rend="italic">Placenta</hi> had grown
        thereto. <lb/>—The other Part of the ſaid Cover, <lb/>behind, adhered to the <hi
          rend="italic">Meſentery</hi>, and, <lb/>by its Bulk, had forced the Guts, <hi
          rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        <lb/>backward, cloſe to the <hi rend="italic">Diaphragma</hi>, in <lb/>ſuch Manner that it
        was with much <lb/>Difficulty, after the Child, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> were
        <lb/>removed, that I found them.—Af- <lb/>ter the before-mention'd Cover was di- <lb/>vided
        from the <hi rend="italic">Peritoneum</hi>, and not <lb/>ſooner, I met with the <hi
          rend="italic">Uterus</hi>, which <lb/>was ſound, about as large as an Hen's <lb/>Egg, with
        a Cavity not capable of hold- <lb/>ing above an Ounce of Liquid.—The <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Os Tincæ, Vagina, <hi rend="roman">&amp;c.</hi></hi> appear'd as in a <lb/>healthy
        State.—The Bones of the <lb/>Child's Head, Arms, Thighs, Legs, and <lb/>many others, were
        looſe, and diveſted of <lb/>their <hi rend="italic">Perioſtea, <hi rend="roman"
          >&amp;c.</hi></hi> but thoſe of the <lb/>Neck, as well as the <hi rend="italic"
          >Vertebræ</hi> of the <lb/>Back and Loins, were well ranged, and <lb/>join'd to a flabby
        Maſs of Fleſh, and with- <lb/>in it the Heart, Lungs, Liver, Stomach, <lb/>and Guts, of the
        ſaid Child, all natu- <lb/>rally ſituated, were found in a tolerable <lb/>Condition, without
        any offenſive Smell. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I keep all the Parts of the Child, as <lb/>alſo the Caſe that held it, and likewiſe
        <lb/>the Parts of Generation which belong'd <lb/>to the Woman, in order to demonſtrate
        <lb/>the Reality of this Story; and with a <lb/>View of having them delineated, if pro-
        <lb/>per Encouragement could be obtained <lb/>for that Purpoſe; for, I believe, a Caſe
        <lb/>exactly tallying herewith, is ſcarcely to <lb/>be met with; at leaſt I have not met
        <lb/>any thing like it, within my twenty eight <lb/>Years Practice in Midwifry.— </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Nurſe who kept her in her Lying- <lb/>in tells me, that the Woman, our pre-
        <lb/>ſent Subject, thought herſelf with Child <lb/>in the Winter-Seaſon, 1730; that ſhe felt
        <lb/>her Child ſtir briskly, prepar'd all things <lb/>convenient for Lying in, and, at the
        Ex- <lb/>piration of Nine Months. <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi> in <hi rend="italic"
          >July</hi>
        <lb/>firſt above-mentioned, fell into ſtrong <lb/>Labour, had her Midwife and Neigh-
        <lb/>bours call'd to her, not only once but <lb/>many Times, and was every Time under
        <lb/>ſevere Throws, as tho' her Infant was <lb/>upon the Point of coming into the
        <lb/>World.—She farther ſaith, that the <lb/>Woman got freed, in the ſaid <hi rend="italic"
          >July</hi>, after <lb/>my Attendance ceas'd, from ſeveral Pie- <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>ces of clotted Blood, and Portions of <lb/>Fleſh, reſembling Veal, which the good
        <lb/>Woman call'd a falſe Conception.— <lb/>After this Diſcharge ſhe gradually grew
        <lb/>better, but remain'd with as large a <lb/>Belly, in all Appearance, as before, and
        <lb/>ever after complain'd of a great Weight <lb/>and Lump, like a Piece of Lead, or a
        <lb/>Child's Head in her Body, which fell <lb/>from one Place to another, according to
        <lb/>her Change of Poſture.—In this <lb/>Condition ſhe remain'd to her Death; <lb/>tho' ſhe
        was deliver'd of three Children <lb/>afterwards, namely, in <hi rend="italic">April</hi>,
        1733, in <lb/><hi rend="italic">March</hi>, 1734, and in <hi rend="italic">October</hi>,
        1739, as ap- <lb/>pears by the Regiſter; yet ſhe ſeem'd as <lb/>much with Child after every
        Delivery <lb/>as before it. </p>
      <signed rend="italic align-right">Yours, <hi rend="roman">&amp;c,</hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">John Marshall. </hi>
      </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
