<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Surprising Instances of the Effects of Musick in acute
          Fevers</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Surprising Instances of the Effects of Musick in acute Fevers, and for the Cure
              of the Bite of the Tarentula.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine: and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed by Edw. Cave, jun. at St John's Gate:</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1743</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">13</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">422</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ESTC">P1956</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1743_GM_0422">
    <body>
      <pb n="422"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/>Surpriſing Inſtances of the Effects of Muſick <lb/>in acute Fevers, and for the Cure of
        the <lb/>Bite of the <hi rend="roman">Tarentula</hi>. </head>
      <salute rend="italic indent space">
        <lb/>SIR, </salute>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi>S the Effects of <hi rend="italic">Muſick</hi> in the Cure of
        <lb/>ſeveral Diſorders are worthy the <lb/>Curioſity of the publick, and may on ſome
        <lb/>Occaſions be of great Uſe to Mankind; it <lb/>will not be unentertaining to your Rea-
        <lb/>ders to ſee ſome well atteſted Inſtances <lb/>of this Kind upon which the learned may
        <lb/>comment at their Leiſure, and give us <lb/>ſome Explanation of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Phenomena</hi>, that <lb/>muſt unavoidably ſurprize thoſe who are <lb/>leſs acquainted
        with the Laws of Nature. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The firſt of theſe Inſtances is atteſted <lb/>by M. <hi rend="italic">Dodart</hi>
        <note n="*" rend="size(0.8) italic" place="bottom">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Hiſt. <hi rend="roman">de l'Academie Royale des Sciences.</hi>
            <lb/>An. 1707. p. 8. </p>
        </note> whoſe skill is too well <lb/>known to be impoſed upon, and whoſe <lb/>Teſtimony is
        otherwiſe unqueaſtionable. <lb/>It is as follows.—A famous Maſter of Mu- <lb/>ſick, an
        eminent Compoſer, was taken ill <lb/>of a Fever which daily increaſed, till the <lb/>ſeventh
        Day, when he fell into an high <lb/>Delirium almoſt without any Intermiſ- <lb/>ſion,
        attended with Cries, Tears, Trem- <lb/>bling and continual Watchings. On <lb/>the third Day
        of this Delirium, by one <lb/>of thoſe Inſtincts, which teach Animals <lb/>when ſick the
        Herbs proper for their <lb/>Cure, he deſired to hear a little Concert <lb/>in his Room. His
        Phyſician with ſome <lb/>difficulty conſented to indulge him in his <lb/>Requeſt. The <hi
          rend="italic">Cantata</hi>'s of M. <hi rend="italic">Bernier</hi>
        <lb/>were ſung to him. On hearing the firſt <lb/>Notes, his aſpect grew calm, his Eyes
        <lb/>loſt their Wildneſs, his Convulſions quite <lb/>left him, he ſhed Tears of Pleaſure,
        and <lb/>ſhowed, that Muſick had never been ſo <lb/>charming to him as then. He had no
        <lb/>feveriſh Symptoms during the whole <lb/>Time of the Performance, but as ſoon as it
        <lb/>ceaſed, he felt a Relapſe. It was there- <lb/>fore thought proper to continue the Uſe
        <lb/>of a Remedy, the Succeſs of w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> had been ſo <pb n="423"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>viſibly happy, tho' unexpected, and by the <lb/>Uſe of which his Fever and Delirium
        ſtill <lb/>abated during the Operation; ſo that Mu- <lb/>ſick became ſo neceſſary to the
        Patient, <lb/>that at Night he made a Kinſwoman who <lb/>attended him, ſing and dance, tho'
        her <lb/>Concern made her yield with Pain to <lb/>oblige him. One Night when only <lb/>his
        Nurſe ſat up with him, he obliged <lb/>her to ſing an old Ballad, which gave him <lb/>ſome
        Eaſe. To conclude, in ten Days by <lb/>the Continuance of Muſick he grew en- <lb/>tirely
        well, without any other Remedies <lb/>but two Bleedings in the Foot, the laſt of <lb/>which
        was followed by a ſtrong Purge. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The ſecond Inſtance of the extraordi- <lb/>nary Effect of Muſick in the Cure of this
        <lb/>Diſeaſe is a Fact related by M. <hi rend="italic">Fon- <lb/>tenelle</hi>
        <note n="†" place="bottom" rend="size(0.8) italic">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="roman">†</hi> Hiſt. <hi rend="roman">de l'Academie Royale des
              Sciences.</hi>
            <lb/>An. 1708. p. 27. </p>
        </note>, who had it from M. de <hi rend="italic">Manda- <lb/>jor</hi> Mayor of <hi
          rend="italic">Alais</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Languedoc</hi>, a Gen- <lb/>tleman of Senſe
        and Merit. A Dancing- <lb/>Maſter of that Town, during the Carni- <lb/>val of 1708, had ſo
        over-heated himſelf <lb/>with the agreeable Duties of his Profeſſi- <lb/>on, that he fell
        ſick the Beginning of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Lent</hi> of a violent Fever which the 4th or
        <lb/>fifth Day turn'd to a <hi rend="italic">Lethargy</hi> and held <lb/>him a long Time.
        When this Symptom <lb/>diſappeared he grew ſullenly Mad, ma- <lb/>king conſtant Efforts to
        leap out of Bed, <lb/>threatning with his Head and Countenance <lb/>thoſe who held him or
        ſtood about him, and <lb/>obſtinately refuſing to ſpeak or take any <lb/>Remedies offered
        him. M. de <hi rend="italic">Mandajor</hi>, <lb/>who ſaw him in this Condition, took a
        <lb/>Fancy, that perhaps Muſick might com- <lb/>poſe his diſordered Imagination, and pro-
        <lb/>poſed it to his Phyſician, who did not <lb/>diſlike the Thing, tho' he objected to the
        <lb/>Redicule that might attend ſuch a Reme- <lb/>dy, eſpecially if the Patient ſhould
        chance <lb/>to die in the Operation. A Friend of the <lb/>Dancing-maſter's, who was leſs
        ſcrupu- <lb/>lous and play'd a good Fiddle, took up <lb/>that of his ſick Friend, which lay
        in the <lb/>Room, and began to play the Tunes he <lb/>knew he lov'd beſt. The Company im-
        <lb/>mediately took him to be the greater Mad- <lb/>man of the two, and began to chide him.
        <lb/>But the ſick Man ſuddenly ſate up, like <lb/>one agreeably ſurpriz'd, and by his Mo-
        <lb/>tion endeavour'd to keep Time with the <lb/>Airs, but as he was ſtill held by his Arms
        <lb/>he could only ſhow his Satisfaction by his <lb/>Head. However thoſe who held him
        <lb/>finding him no way furious, by degrees <lb/>gave him more Liberty, till in a Quarter
        <lb/>of an Hour he fell faſt aſleep, and had a <lb/>Criſis, which put him paſt all Danger. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Let us know ſee a third Example of the <lb/>Force of Muſick, which ſurpaſſes the two
          <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>former in the ſurpriſing Manner of <unclear>its</unclear>
        <lb/>Effects. Few Perſons are Strangers to the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Tarentula</hi>
        <note n="‡" rend="size(0.7) italic" place="bottom">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="roman">‡</hi> The <hi rend="roman">Tarentula</hi> is a large Spider,
            hairy and <lb/>about the ſize of an Acorn, its colour various, with <lb/>8 Eyes and 8
            Feet, from its Mouth ariſe 2 Horns <lb/>or Trunks, a little crooked, the Tips
            exceedingly ſharp <lb/>thro' which it conveys its Poiſon: It is found near <lb/><hi
              rend="roman">Tarento</hi>, whence it takes its Name, and is to be <lb/>met with in
            other Parts of <hi rend="roman">Italy</hi> eſpecially the Iſle <lb/>of <hi rend="roman"
              >Corſica</hi>. Thoſe of <hi rend="roman">Apulia</hi> are the moſt venemous, <lb/>and
            in general thoſe of the Plains are moſt dangerous, <lb/>becauſe the Air of <hi
              rend="roman">Calabria</hi> is <choice>
              <corr>better</corr>
              <sic>botter</sic>
            </choice> in the Plains <lb/>than in the Mountains. See Hiſt. <hi rend="roman">de
              l'Academ. <lb/>Royale des Sciences.</hi> An. 1702. p. 20. </p>
        </note>, and the terrible Symptoms <lb/>that attend its Bite, but the extraordinary
        <lb/>Remedy uſed to alleviate and diſpell them <lb/>is not perhaps ſo well known. This Re-
        <lb/>medy is Muſick, applied in the Manner <lb/>we ſhall deſcribe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Soon after the Bite of the <hi rend="italic">Tarentula</hi>, <lb/>which cauſes a
        Senſation like the ſtinging <lb/>of a Bee or Ant, the Patient finds in the <lb/>Part a very
        ſharp Pain, which in ſome <lb/>Hours is followed with a Tumour. In a <lb/>ſhort Time he
        grows melancholy, with a <lb/>Difficulty of Breathing, faint Pulſe, and <lb/>wild Look, and
        if not ſpeedily aſſiſted he <lb/>loſes all Senſe and Motion, and dies. Such <lb/>are the
        Symptoms of this Poiſon. The <lb/>beſt and ſureſt Means of Cure yet diſco- <lb/>vered are as
        follow. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When the Patient is arrived at the laſt <lb/>Symptoms of being inſenſible or motion-
        <lb/>leſs, a Muſician tries different Tunes, till <lb/>he hits on one whoſe Modulation and
        <lb/>Notes ſuit the Perſon affected, ſo that he <lb/>begins to ſtir, to move his Fingers in
        <lb/>Cadence, next his Feet and at laſt recovers <lb/>his Limbs, ſo as riſe and dance to the
        <lb/>Air, ſtill continuing the Exerciſe with <lb/>greater Violence. There are ſome Pati-
        <lb/>ents will dance thus for ſix Hours without <lb/>Intermiſſion. When exhauſted with this
        <lb/>Fatigue the Patient is put to Bed, and af- <lb/>ter repoſing a while, he is awaked with
        <lb/>the ſame Tune to renew his Dancing, <lb/>continuing this Method for ſome Days
        <lb/>(often five, ſix, or ſeven) till the Patient <lb/>finds he has no more Inclination to
        dance, <lb/>which is a Sign of his Cure. For while <lb/>the Effect of the Poiſon laſts, he
        would if <lb/>left to himſelf, dance without intermiſſion <lb/>till he kill'd himſelf. As
        ſoon as he finds <lb/>himſelf wearied he recovers by Degrees <lb/>his Senſes and Judgment,
        and like one <lb/>awakened from a deep Sleep remembers <lb/>nothing of what had paſſed in
        his De- <lb/>lirium. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Sometimes the Patient is cured on his <lb/>coming out of the firſt Fit. But if other-
        <lb/>wiſe, he ſtill is ſubject to a deep Melan- <lb/>choly, and Forgetfulneſs. He ſhuns Com-
          <pb n="424"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>pany, loves Solitude, and if not carefully <lb/>watch'd, is apt to drown himſelf. An
        <lb/>Averſion for the Colours of Black and <lb/>Blue, and a Fondneſs for White, Red <lb/>and
        Green, are ſome of the odd Symp- <lb/>toms of this Diſtemper. If the Patient <lb/>dies not
        in the Interval, the Fit returns <lb/>about the ſame Time twelvemonth the <lb/>Bite
        happened, and Muſick and Dancing <lb/>muſt be again called in. Some have had <lb/>theſe
        regular Relapſes for 20 or 30 Years <lb/>together. Each Patient has his particular
        <lb/>ſpecific Tune, but in general, thoſe found <lb/>effectual are brisk and lively. Theſe
        par- <lb/>ticulars are well atteſted, and were con- <lb/>firmed to the <hi rend="italic"
          >Royal Academy</hi> not only by <lb/>M. <hi rend="italic">Geoffroy</hi>, who had informed
        himſelf <lb/>on the Spot, but by the Letters of a Fa- <lb/>ther Jeſuit of <hi rend="italic"
          >Toulon</hi> to P. <hi rend="italic">Gouye</hi>, in which <lb/>he relates the Cure of an
          <hi rend="italic">Italian</hi> Soldier <lb/><unclear><sic>bid</sic></unclear> by a <hi
          rend="italic">Tarentula</hi>, whom he had ſeen <lb/>dance for ſeveral Days ſucceſſively. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Theſe Facts may explain the Caſe of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Saul</hi> who found his
        Indiſpoſition relieved <lb/>by the Muſick of <hi rend="italic">David</hi>; a Caſe which
        <lb/>has nothing in it more wonderful or ex- <lb/>traordinary than thoſe related. I even
        <lb/>think, that the Effects of Muſick on the <lb/>diſordered Brain of a Man bit with the
          <lb/><hi rend="italic"><choice>
            <corr>Tarentula</corr>
            <sic>Tarantula</sic>
          </choice></hi>, has ſomething more inexplica- <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>ble more incomprehenſibly ſtrange in it. <lb/>Some Philoſophers have attempted to ac-
        <lb/>count for theſe <hi rend="italic">Phenomena</hi>, but the ſecret <lb/>Cauſes of them
        are too concealed for us <lb/>to diſcover. O Nature! Nature! how <lb/>Myſterious and
        inſcrutable are thy Ways? <lb/>How feeble and bounded our Knowledge. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/>As Muſick has in the above mentioned <lb/>Inſtances been found to be a very ſucceſsful
        <lb/>Remedy in the ſeveral Diſorders in which <lb/>it was applied; ſo it is not perhaps
        impro- <lb/>bable, that it might be found efficacious in <lb/>other Diſorders ſuch as the
        Bite of a Mad <lb/>Dog; eſpecially if a Time could be hit upon <lb/>to make the Patient
        dance and ſweat: <lb/>Since the Evacuation in this Manner of the <lb/>inflammatory Fluid is,
        according to Dr <lb/><hi rend="roman">Mead</hi>, the Cauſe of Cure in the Bite of the
        <lb/>Tarentula, the <choice>
          <corr>Vibrations</corr>
          <sic>Vibratious</sic>
        </choice> made on the <lb/>Nerves by Tunes rightly modelled opera- <lb/>ting as really on
        the Nerves, as the <hi rend="roman">Im- <lb/>perium Voluntaris</hi> can do. And M. <hi
          rend="roman">Geof- <lb/><sic>frov</sic></hi> ſays, <q rend="diple roman">the poiſonous
          Juice giving the <lb/>Nerves a Degree of Tenſion equal to <lb/>that of ſome Strings of an
          Inſtrument <lb/>puts the Nerves in Uniſon to certain <lb/>Tones; and after being agitated
          by the <lb/>Undulations and Vibrations of the Air <lb/>proper to thoſe Tones obliges them
          to <lb/>ſhake. </q>
      </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
