<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Account of the *Plague by Procopius</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Account of the *Plague by Procopius</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine: and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed by Edw. Cave, jun. at St John's Gate:</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1743</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">13</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">425</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ESTC">P1956</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1743_GM_0425">
    <body>
      <pb n="425"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <head rend="align-center">Account of the <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.8) italic">
          <p>
            <lb/>* See the Plague of <hi rend="roman">Marſeilles</hi> a Poem, p. 211. </p>
        </note>
        <hi rend="italic">Plague</hi> by <hi rend="italic">Procopius</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="italic space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(1.5)">A</hi>T this Time, when the Viſitation of <lb/>Heaven upon the
        Iſland of <hi rend="roman">Sicily</hi> has <lb/>ſpread ſuch general Apprehenſions, and
        <lb/>Mankind are inquiſitive about former peſti- <lb/>lential Contagions, it may not be
        amiſs to <lb/>give our Readers a Paſſage from <hi rend="roman">Procopius</hi>, <lb/>as
        related by Dr <hi rend="roman">Howell</hi>, and quoted by Dr <lb/><hi rend="roman"
          >Friend</hi> in his Hiſtory of Phyſic. The <lb/>Plague he ſpeaks of began in <hi
          rend="roman">Procopius</hi>'s <lb/>own Time, in the Reign of <hi rend="roman"
          >Juſtinian</hi>; con- <lb/>tinued after his Death, in all 52 Years; <lb/>travell'd all
        over the Globe, and almoſt un- <lb/>peopled the whole Face of it. That of <hi rend="roman"
          >A- <lb/>thens</hi>, deſcribed by <hi rend="roman">Thucydides</hi>, ſeems to <lb/>have
        been leſs terrible. The curious may <lb/>conſult Dr <hi rend="roman">Friend</hi>'s Remarks
        on it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This was a Plague, which almoſt con- <lb/>ſumed Mankind, of which, <hi rend="italic"
          >Procopius</hi> con- <lb/>cludes, there was no other Cauſe than <lb/>the immediate Hand of
        God himſelf. For <lb/>it neither came upon one Part of the <lb/>World alone, nor in one
        Seaſon of the <lb/>Year, whence ſubtile Wits (as he ſaith) <lb/>might fetch Pretenſions. It
        afflicted the <lb/>whole World, and all Conditions of Men, <lb/>tho' of never ſo contrary a
        Nature, and <lb/>Diſpoſition; ſparing no Conſtitution nor <pb n="426"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>Age. The Difference of Men, as to their <lb/>Places of Dwelling, Diet, Complexions,
        <lb/>Inclinations, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> did no Good in this <lb/>Diſeaſe. Some it
        took in Summer, ſome <lb/>in Winter, and others in other Seaſons. <lb/>It began among the
          <hi rend="italic">Ægyptians</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Peluſi- <lb/>um</hi>, and ſpread to
          <hi rend="italic">Alexandria</hi> with the <lb/>Reſt of <hi rend="italic">Ægypt</hi> one
        Way, and the other to <lb/>thoſe Parts of <hi rend="italic">Paleſtine</hi>, which border
        <lb/>upon <hi rend="italic">Ægypt</hi>. From thence it travell'd to <lb/>the utmoſt Bounds
        of the World, as by <lb/><unclear>ſet</unclear> Journies and Stages, making De-
        <lb/>ſtruction its only Buſineſs, and ſparing <lb/>neither Iſland, Cave, nor Top of Moun-
        <lb/>tain, where Mankind inhabited; for if it <lb/>leap'd over a Country, returning after-
        <lb/>wards, it left it no Cauſe to rejoice above <lb/>its Fellows. It began ſtill at the
        Sea- <lb/>craft, and thence went to the inland <lb/>Parts. In the ſecond Year of its
        Progreſs <lb/>it arriv'd in <hi rend="italic">Conſtantinople</hi>, about the <lb/>Middle of
        the Spring, where it was the <lb/>Fortune of <hi rend="italic">Procopius</hi> then to
        reſide. Ap- <lb/>paritions of Spirits, in all Shapes human, <lb/>were ſeen by many, who
        thought the <lb/>Man they met ſtruck them in ſome Part <lb/>of the Body; and ſo ſoon as they
        ſaw the <lb/>Spirit, they were ſeized with the Diſeaſe. <lb/>At firſt when they met them,
        they re- <lb/>peated divine Names, and fled into <lb/>Churches to no Purpoſe. Afterwards
        <lb/>they were afraid to hear their Friends call <lb/>them, locking themſelves up in their
        <lb/>Chambers and ſtopping their <unclear>Ears</unclear>. Some <lb/>dreamed they ſaw ſuch
        Sights, others <lb/>heard a Voice tell them they were enroll- <lb/>ed in the Number
        appointed to die: But <lb/>moſt without Warning became feveriſh <lb/>ſuddenly: Their Bodies
        changed not <lb/>colour, nor were hot; the Fever being <lb/>ſo remiſs 'till Evening, that
        neither the <lb/>Patient nor Phyſician, by his <hi rend="italic">Pulſe</hi>, could
        <lb/>apprehend any Danger. Yet to ſome the <lb/>ſame Day, to others the next, or many
        <lb/>Days after, aroſe a <hi rend="italic">Bubo</hi> either in the Groin, <lb/>the
          <unclear>Arm</unclear>-holes, under the Ear, or in <lb/>other Parts: Theſe were the
        general <lb/>Symptoms which happened alike to all <lb/>the viſited Perſons. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There were others different; whether <lb/>ſo made by the Diverſity of Bodies, or
        <lb/>the Will and Pleaſure of him that ſent the <lb/>Diſtemper, our Author cannot ſay. Some
        <lb/>were ſeized with Drowſineſs and Slum- <lb/>bering, others with a ſharp Diſtraction:
        <lb/>The Slumberers forgot all Things: If <lb/>they were look'd to, ſome would eat;
        <lb/>ſome, that were neglected, ſtarved to <lb/>Death. Thoſe who were diſtracted were
        <lb/>vexed with Apparitions, crying there <lb/>were Men to kill them, and running a-
        <lb/>way; being ſo troubleſome and unruly, <lb/>that their keepers were pitied as much as
          <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>they themſelves. No Phyſician or other <lb/>caught the Diſeaſe by touching ſick or
        <lb/>dead Bodies; many ſtrangely continuing <lb/>free, though they tended and buried in-
        <lb/>fected Perſons, and many catching it they <lb/>knew not how, and dying inſtantly.
        <lb/>Many leapt into the Water, though not <lb/>for Thirſt; and ſome into the Sea. Some,
        <lb/>without Slumbering or Madneſs, had <lb/>their <hi rend="italic">Bubo</hi> gangrened,
        and died with ex- <lb/>treme Pain; which doubtleſs happen'd <lb/>alſo to thoſe that had the
        Phrenſy, tho' <lb/>being not themſelves they underſtood it <lb/>not. Some Phyſicians
        hereupon concei- <lb/>ving the Venom and Head of the Diſeaſe <lb/>to lie in thoſe
        Plague-ſores, opened the <lb/>dead Bodies, and ſearching the Sores <lb/>found an <choice>
          <corr>huge</corr>
          <sic>kuge</sic>
        </choice> Carbuncle growing in- <lb/>ward. Such whoſe Bodies were ſpotted <lb/>with black
        Pimples the Bigneſs of a Len- <lb/>tile, lived not a Day. Many died of vo- <lb/>miting
        Blood. Some that were given over <lb/>by the moſt eminent Phyſicians, unex- <lb/>pectedly
        recovered; others, of whoſe <lb/>Recovery they thought themſelves ſecure, <lb/>ſuddenly
        periſhed: No Cauſe of this <lb/>Sickneſs could be reached by Man's Rea- <lb/>ſon. Some
        received benefit by <hi rend="italic">Bathing</hi>, <lb/>others it hurt. Many died for Want
        of <lb/>Relief, others eſcaped without it: In a <lb/>Word, no Way could there be found of
        <lb/>Preſervation, either by preventing the <lb/>Sickneſs, or maſtering the Diſeaſe, no
        <lb/>Cauſe appearing either of their falling <lb/>ſick, or of their Recovery. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Women with child which were viſit- <lb/>ed, certainly died; ſome miſcarrying, <lb/>ſome
        fairly delivered, and periſhing with <lb/>their Children: <hi rend="italic">Three</hi> Women
        only were <lb/>ſafely brought to Bed and recovered, <lb/>their Children dying; and one died
        whoſe <lb/>Child had the hap to live. Such as had <lb/>their Sores great, and running
        plentiful- <lb/>ly, eſcaped; the Violence of the Car- <lb/>buncle being thereby aſſwaged;
        and this <lb/>was the moſt certain Sign of Health. <lb/>Such whoſe Sores ſtaid as they firſt
        aroſe, <lb/>underwent the miſerable Accident for- <lb/>merly mentioned. Some had their
        <lb/>Thighs withered, when the Sores roſe <lb/>upon them and did not run. Some eſca-
        <lb/>ped with diminiſhed Tongues, and lived <lb/>ſtammering, or uttering Sounds without
        <lb/>Diſtinction all their Days. In <hi rend="italic">Conſtanti- <lb/>nople</hi> this
        Peſtilence laſted <hi rend="italic">four</hi> Months, <lb/>raging <hi rend="italic"
          >three</hi> Months with all Extremity. <lb/>In the Beginning few died more than
        <lb/>uſual: Then it growing hotter and hot- <lb/>ter, it came to <hi rend="italic"
        >five</hi>, and at laſt to <hi rend="italic">ten <lb/>thouſand</hi> every Day. At firſt they
        buried <lb/>their Dead carefully, but at length all <lb/>came to Confuſion, and many lay
        long <lb/>unburied. Servants were without Maſ- <pb n="427"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>ters; rich Men had none to attend them. <lb/>In the afflicted City was little to be
        ſeen <lb/>but empty Houſes; no Trade going, or <lb/>Shops open. The Emperor was much
        <lb/>concerned, as he had Reaſon, and com- <lb/>mitted the Overſight of the Poor to <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Theodorus</hi>, one of the <hi rend="italic">Referendarii</hi> that ſub-
        <lb/>ſcribed the Emperor's Anſwers to Peti- <lb/>tions; who, to thoſe that were in Want,
        <lb/>diſtributed Money out of the Treaſury. <lb/>To theſe Paſſages <hi rend="italic"
          >Procopius</hi> adds, that <lb/>many, out of Fear, left their bad Courſes <lb/>of Life,
        and conſecrated themſelves to <lb/>God; and many, when the Danger was <lb/>over, fell to
        their old deſpiſing of God <lb/>again. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
