<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Freeman: An Epistle on the Passing the Gin Bill</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Simon Freeman</persName>
            </author>
            <title>From the Champion, March 1. An Epistle on the Passing the Gin Bill</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed by Edw. Cave, jun. at St John's Gate:</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1743</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">13</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">137</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ESTC">P1956</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1743_GM_0137">
    <body>
      <pb n="137"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>From the <hi rend="blackletter">Champion</hi>, March 1. </head>
      <head rend="italic align-center space">
        <lb/>An Epiſtle on the Paſſing the Gin-Bill. </head>
      <epigraph rend="italic indentall space">
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Infeliciter ægrotat, cui plus Periculi <lb/>a <hi rend="roman">Medico</hi>, quam a
            <hi rend="roman">Morbo</hi>. </p>
      </epigraph>
      <salute rend="italic space indent">
        <lb/>My L—d, </salute>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">Y</hi>OUR late ſtrenuous Oppoſition to <lb/>the Gin Bill demands our
        publick <lb/>Thanks; whether we conſider it as pro- <lb/>ceeding from your diſtinguiſh'd
        Zeal to <lb/>promote Religion and Virtue;—from <lb/>your laudable Reſolution to diſcourage
        <lb/>Profaneneſs and Immorality;—from your <lb/>tender Regard for the Welfare of your
        <lb/>Fellow Subjects and <hi rend="italic">their Poſterity</hi>; or, <lb/>from a previous
        Concern for the Peace <lb/>of this Kingdom in general, and the Se- <lb/>curity of our moſt
        excellent Conſtitution: <lb/>For howſoever trifling and inconſiderable <lb/>the paſſing this
        Bill may ſeem in the <lb/>Eyes of ſome ſhort-ſighted Gentlemen, <lb/>the Conſequences of it
        appear to us to <lb/>be dreadful, ſhocking, and of the utmoſt <lb/>Importance; and whether
        the Grievance <lb/>it is deſigned to redreſs, is in any Way <lb/>equivalent to the Miſchief
        it will produce, <lb/>deſerves our moſt ſerious Conſideration. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Intention of this Bill, (as we, with- <lb/>out Doors, are informed) is to raiſe a
        <lb/>large Sum of M—y, <hi rend="italic">Part of which</hi> is to <lb/>be applied to the
        carrying on of the War <lb/>upon the Continent. A Scheme, allow- <lb/>ed by all Parties to
        be expenſive, im- <lb/>practicable, and fundamentally wrong.— <lb/>The Method whereby this
        S—y muſt <lb/>be advanced is, to encourage V—ll—ny, <lb/>to licence D-b—ch-ry, and to
        propagate <lb/>In-qu-ty. A Method impolitic, dangerous, <lb/>and altogether antichriſtian.
        Poiſe the <lb/>Miſeries of <hi rend="italic">our own People</hi>, unreſtrained <lb/>from
        drinking ſpirituous Liquors; ener- <lb/>vating themſelves, enfeebling their Chil- <lb/>dren,
        and impoveriſhing their Families, <lb/>with the innate Pride, inflexible Diſpoſi- <lb/>tion,
        and unavoidable Sufferings of a <hi rend="italic">fo- <lb/>reign Queen</hi>, and you muſt
        make many <lb/>Grains of Allowance from common Pru- <lb/>dence, brotherly Love, and
        Chriſtian <lb/>Charity to make the Scales equal; for <lb/>tho' the Fury of a diſtant Enemy
        may <lb/>fall heavy upon many Particulars, yet the <lb/>diſmal Conſequences of an inteſtine
        De- <lb/>pravity, are more epidemical and more <lb/>permanent. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is a melancholy Proſpect, My L—d, <lb/>to look forward, and reflect upon the
        <lb/>great Miſchiefs which may one Day poſſi- <lb/>bly befal this Nation, from a Number of
        <lb/>its Inhabitants being intoxicated and in- <lb/>flamed with this <hi rend="italic"
          >Liquid Fire</hi>, and thereby <lb/>made capable of perpetrating the moſt <lb/>enormous
        Wickedneſs; if they ſhould at <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>any Time hereafter (which Heaven avert) <lb/>pour forth unexpectedly from their gloo-
        <lb/>my Cells, as from the Body of the <hi rend="italic">Trojan <lb/>Horſe</hi>, with Deſign
        to lay the City in <lb/>Flames, that they might ſhare in the <lb/>Plunder, to ſubvert the
        A—n, and to <lb/>ſtrike at the very Foundations of Church <lb/>and State. And, altho' we
        ſhould be <lb/>very much concern'd, we ſhould not be <lb/>ſo much ſurpris'd to hear, that
        the chief <lb/>Pr'm't'r of this pernicious B-ll was him- <lb/>ſelf a—ted by the deſperate
        Hands <lb/>of ſome of his own <hi rend="italic">Licenciates</hi>. Such <lb/>and ſo terrible
        are the Effects of Profliga- <lb/>cy, Madneſs, and Miſery, when they are <lb/>blended
        together! </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Nor are theſe, my L—d, the only <lb/>Miſchiefs which may be apprehended <lb/>from the
        late Indulgence; with regard to <lb/>Poſterity there are ſtill greater; for, in <lb/>leſs
        Time than half a Century, <hi rend="italic">Britons</hi>
        <lb/>will probably be diſtinguiſhable from o- <lb/>ther Nations by Name and Language
        <lb/>only; their Form, Strength, and Courage, <lb/>which were the Glory of their Anceſtors,
        <lb/>and the Terror of their Enemies, will be <lb/>loſt; their Size will dwindle, their Vi-
        <lb/>gour will decay, and their Spirits will be <lb/>broken, by the Debauchery and Drunk-
        <lb/>enneſs of their Parents. Our Succeſſors <lb/>will, by theſe Means, be render'd unca-
        <lb/>pable of defending themſelves, or even <lb/>of guarding their own Coaſts, and muſt
        <lb/>inevitably forfeit their Freedom, quit <lb/>their hereditary Poſſeſſions, and be made
        <lb/>a Sacrifice to ſome foreign Invader. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Diſmal and deſtructive as theſe Events <lb/>naturally appear, they are paſs'd over w<hi
          rend="sup">th</hi>
        <lb/>indifference, and look'd upon as inconſi- <lb/>derable; and if it be not too harſh and
        <lb/>ſhocking for your L—d—p to hear, ſuffer <lb/>us to repeat what was thrown out by a
        <lb/>R—t Hon—ble Advocate for this B-ll be- <lb/>fore a certain a-g-ſt Aſſ-mbly, with Re-
        <lb/>ſpect to the ill Conſequences which might <lb/>hereby be devolv'd to Poſterity. <q
          rend="diple">My <lb/>L—ds, ſays he, the chief Argument <lb/>which I have heard urged
          againſt the <lb/>paſſing this Bill is, that in forty Years <lb/>Time, the Race of Mankind
          in this <lb/>Iſland will be ſo degenerated, by the <lb/>exceſſive drinking of ſp—s Li—rs,
          <lb/>that they will not be able to raiſe any <lb/>Thing better among their own Inhabi-
          <lb/>tants than an Army of <hi rend="italic">Lilliputians</hi> for <lb/>their Security and
          Defence. But how <lb/>vain is this Argument? or how can that <lb/>affect us? We ſhall be
          gone, let our <lb/>Succeſſors take care of themſelves, and <lb/>make the beſt of a bad
          Bargain, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi><unclear>'</unclear>
        </q>
        <lb/>Now, my L—d, what better could be <lb/>expected from ſuch Principles as theſe? <lb/>Are
        ſuch Perſons proper G—rd—ns for <pb n="138"/>
        <cb n="1 2"/>
        <lb/>the Liberties of the People? Surely, No. <lb/>They who have ſo little Regard for the
        <lb/>Welfare and Intereſt of their own Chil- <lb/>dren, will have much leſs for thoſe of the
        <lb/>C—n. And we ſhould forbear any <lb/>longer to think <hi rend="italic">Mahomet</hi> an
        Impoſtor, and <lb/>muſt receive the <hi rend="italic">Koran</hi> for Goſpel, if we
        <lb/>could be convinced, that <hi rend="italic">our own temporal <lb/>Happineſs</hi> is the
          <hi rend="italic">Summum Bonum</hi>, the on- <lb/>ly End we ought to be ſolicitous after.
        <lb/>And theſe honourable Perſonages, my <lb/>L—d, would certainly act more confor-
        <lb/>mable to their Characters, if they would <lb/>procure an A— of P—t to extirpate
        <lb/>the Name of Proteſtant out of this King- <lb/>dom, before they grant any more L-c-nc-s
        <lb/>for Vice. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But alas! my L—d, thoſe who ſtudy <lb/>to be <hi rend="italic">Great</hi> by all Means,
        muſt by all <lb/>Means forget to be <hi rend="italic">Good</hi>: Avarice and <lb/>Ambition
        know no Confinement; their <lb/>Deſires are not only inſatiate, but admit <lb/>of any Sin
        that will promote their Ends; <lb/>nor is it in the Power of human Rheto- <lb/>rick, or even
        of the Tongues of Angels <lb/>to keep them within due Bounds. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Yet certainly, my L—d, the generality <lb/>of Mankind is much miſtaken in the Va-
        <lb/>lue of Power and Grandeur, which is ſo <lb/>much thirſted after. They look upon its
        <lb/>Glory, but forget its Frailty; they gaze <lb/>upon its Colour, but take no Notice of
        <lb/>its Weight, nay, if all thoſe gay Things, <lb/>which they fondly fancy to themſelves,
        <lb/>were really to be found in Greatneſs, that <lb/>Perſon pays too dear who forfeits his
        <lb/>Heaven for it; and he who thus buys a <lb/>ſhort Bliſs gives not twenty or a hundred
        <lb/>Years Purchaſe, but, perhaps, Eternity. </p>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <dateline rend="space">
        <lb/>Feb. 5. </dateline>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <signed rend="italic">
        <lb/>I am, Your <hi rend="roman">L—d—p</hi>'s <lb/>Moſt obedient Servant, <lb/><hi rend="sc"
          >Simon Freeman</hi>, jun. </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
