<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: The Plague of Marseilles</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>The Plague of Marseilles</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine: and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed by Edw. Cave, jun. at St John's Gate:</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1743</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">13</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">211</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ESTC">P1956</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1743_GM_0211">
    <body>
      <pb n="211"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <head rend="italic align-center">
        <lb/>The PLAGUE of <hi rend="sc">marseilles</hi>. </head>
      <lg>
        <l><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">H</hi>Igh thron'd in power the everlaſting <hi rend="sc">Fear</hi>, </l>
        <l rend="hanging"><lb/>Summon'd ten thouſand hoſts from ev'ry <lb/>ſphere. </l>
        <l><lb/>Fiercely he look'd and bent his awful brow, </l>
        <l><lb/>And ſpoke deſtruction to the world below. </l>
      </lg>
      <q rend="diple">
        <lg>
          <l rend="indent"><lb/>Shall man ſtill dare with haughty pride defy </l>
          <l><lb/>My common voice, which thunders thro' y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſky? </l>
          <l><lb/>Shall lightnings flaſh in vain? ſhall ſigns no more </l>
          <l><lb/>Make nations tremble and the earth adore? </l>
          <l><lb/>Is <hi rend="italic">Greece</hi> at length forgot? Are <hi rend="italic"
              >Ægypt</hi>'s crimes </l>
          <l><lb/>Lock'd in the womb of unrecorded times? </l>
          <l><lb/>Or is my arm made ſhort, unſkill'd to throw </l>
          <l><lb/>Death-pointed vengeance on the rebel foe?—</l>
          <l><lb/>Be witneſs ev'ry power, how much I bear, </l>
          <l><lb/>To puniſh ſlow, and ever ſwift to ſpare. </l>
          <l><lb/>But ſee, how juſt my deſtin'd judgments fall, </l>
          <l><lb/>So great the weight of vice, of virtue ſmall. </l>
        </lg>
      </q>
      <lg>
        <l rend="indent"><lb/>He ſaid, and took y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcales, in which he weigh'd </l>
        <l><lb/>This pond'rous globe when firſt from nothing made. </l>
        <l><lb/>In this the earth was thrown, the adverſe ſide </l>
        <l><lb/>The leaſt angelick form in heav'n, ſupplied. </l>
        <l><lb/>When lo! the deep foundations upward bore, </l>
        <l><lb/>As if by fate from th' inmoſt centre tore. </l>
      </lg>
      <q rend="diple">
        <lg>
          <l rend="indent"><lb/>'Tis well—go hateful <hi rend="italic">Plague</hi> thy ſtrength
            employ, </l>
          <l><lb/>Fly ſwift as thought, and, as you fly, deſtroy. </l>
          <l><lb/>Each ſoul diſtreſs; but chief o'er yonder plain <hi rend="dc(4)">}</hi>
          </l>
          <l rend="hanging"><lb/>Where mirth and noiſe their boundleſs ſway <lb/>maintain, </l>
          <l><lb/>Let <hi rend="italic">waſte</hi>, <hi rend="italic">confuſion</hi> and wild <hi
              rend="italic">horrour</hi> reign. </l>
        </lg>
      </q>
      <lg>
        <l rend="indent"><lb/>Sphere'd in a duſky cloud the <hi rend="italic">fiend</hi> deſcends </l>
        <l><lb/>Joy adds to ſpeed, and ſpeed to vigour lends. </l>
        <l><lb/>Thus the gay chariot at th' olympick games </l>
        <l><lb/>Rolls ſwift, and as it rolls, itſelf inflames. </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
        <l rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Maſſilia</hi>'s tow'rs ſhe ſeiz'd, then paus'd
          awhile, </l>
        <l><lb/>Survey'd her charge and grinn'd a ghaſtly ſmile. </l>
        <l><lb/>Large compaſſes ſhe held, ætherial mold, </l>
        <l><lb/><hi rend="italic">Vulcanian</hi> work, the maſs of burniſh'd gold. </l>
        <l><lb/>One leg was fix'd, the other circling round </l>
        <l><lb/>Inclos'd the walls, the fields and neighb'ring ground. </l>
        <l><lb/>So wide the <hi rend="italic">peſt</hi> diſtends the yielding ſide, </l>
        <l><lb/>That had not Fate, almighty Fate deny'd, </l>
        <l><lb/>The ſpring ſhe'd burſt, and paſs'd divine commands, </l>
        <l><lb/>And ſtretch'd the line of death to diſtant lands. </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
        <l rend="indent"><lb/>But hark! alas! I hear <hi rend="italic">Maſſilia</hi> groan, </l>
        <l><lb/>And curſe the Plague confin'd to her alone. </l>
        <l><lb/>Fierce mountain beaſts in toils to fury turn, </l>
        <l><lb/>And rays condens'd with double vigour burn. </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
        <l rend="indent"><lb/>At firſt in ſeeming form the <hi rend="italic">Fury</hi> ran, </l>
        <l><lb/>And paſs'd with eager ſtrides from man to man. </l>
        <l><lb/><hi rend="italic">Amazement</hi> wild with out-ſtretch'd eye-balls glar'd, </l>
        <l><lb/>With horrour ſhook, but knew not what he fear'd. </l>
        <l><lb/>Unſeen in air the pois'nous arrows go, </l>
        <l><lb/>Unſeen the hand, which twangs the fatal bow. </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
        <l rend="indent"><lb/>But now by Ruin fed ſhe ſtronger grows, </l>
        <l><lb/>Renews the ſtroke and wields redoubled blows. </l>
        <l><lb/>From ev'ry ſide there's one tumultuous cry, </l>
        <l><lb/>A thouſand pray for death, a thouſand curſing, dye. </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
        <l rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Art</hi>, the
          ſkilful hand employs, </l>
        <l><lb/><hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> ſubmits, and <hi rend="italic">Art</hi> itſelf
          deſtroys. </l>
        <l><lb/>In vain the ſublimated ſpirits roll, </l>
        <l><lb/>Search ev'ry vein and penetrate the ſoul. </l>
        <cb n="2"/>
        <l><lb/>The tort'ring flames with ſtrengthned vigour burn </l>
        <l><lb/>And ſtreams of fire th' exhauſted juices turn. </l>
        <l><lb/>In vain the artiſt ſtrove; but not in vain, </l>
        <l><lb/>Death ſaw th' unfruitful labours of his brain. </l>
        <l><lb/>Thrice ſteep'd in bane, he choſe a pois'nous dart, </l>
        <l><lb/>Direct it flew and pierc'd his trembling heart. </l>
        <l><lb/>The rav'nous hawk thus wheeling thro' the ſky, </l>
        <l><lb/>Obſerves the bed where th' unfledg'd pheaſants lye; </l>
        <l><lb/>Swiftly he fails with levell'd pinnions down, </l>
        <l><lb/>Diſtends his claws and claims the young alone: </l>
        <l><lb/>When lo! the tender parent homeward flies, </l>
        <l><lb/>And hov'ring round in mournful accents cries, </l>
        <l><lb/>Unmov'd the plunderer bears upon the prey, </l>
        <l><lb/>Firſt ſtrikes the dam, then ſweeps the brood away. </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
        <l rend="indent"><lb/>What hand can draw, what pow'r of numbers tell </l>
        <l><lb/>How ſlaughter'd thouſands ev'ry moment fell? </l>
        <l><lb/>Here heaps on heaps in blended ruin lye, </l>
        <l><lb/>And ceaſe to breathe, or breatheing poiſon, dye. </l>
        <l><lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Fury</hi> ſwells by <hi rend="italic">Deſolation</hi> fed, </l>
        <l><lb/>Each dying gaſp adds mountains to the dead. </l>
        <l><lb/>As when to ſtorm ſome long contending town </l>
        <l><lb/>A bomb deſcends, like fiery comet, down, </l>
        <l><lb/>In dizzy rings it ſpins and ploughs the ground, </l>
        <l><lb/>At length to ſhivers burſts, and ſcatters death around. </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
        <l rend="indent"><lb/>Here ſons and fathers, wives and infants groan, </l>
        <l><lb/>And friends in death, as well as life, are one. </l>
        <l><lb/>A ſoldier there by rage extatick driven, </l>
        <l><lb/>Springs from the earth and charges partial heav'n. </l>
        <l><lb/>Have I for this ſo oft in battle ſtood, </l>
        <l><lb/>Its thunder heard, and bath'd in reeking blood? </l>
        <l><lb/>Have I for this to diſtant nations led </l>
        <l><lb/>To die inglorious on a gallick bed? </l>
        <l><lb/>Rather again let <hi rend="italic">Britiſh</hi> lyons roar, </l>
        <l><lb/>And <hi rend="italic">Marlbro'</hi> wave his ſword from ſhore to ſhore. </l>
        <l><lb/>Is't thus, O ſovereign pow'r! you juſtice ſhow, </l>
        <l><lb/>And teach mankind to practiſe here below? </l>
        <l><lb/>Why groans the north w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> mighty numbers preſt? </l>
        <l><lb/>Or why unnumber'd millions load the <unclear>e</unclear>aſt? </l>
        <l><lb/>Nor altars ſmoke, nor fumes of incenſe riſe </l>
        <l><lb/>In circling clouds, to gain the fav'ring ſkies. </l>
        <l><lb/>This the reward of virtue? This the praiſe? </l>
        <l><lb/>Is this the juſt man's promiſe, length of days? </l>
        <l><lb/>Or bare thy arm where none thy godhead own, </l>
        <l><lb/>Or lay in peace thy mutt'ring thunder down. </l>

        <l><lb/>Thus he blaſphemous rav'd; but rav'd in vain, </l>
        <l><lb/>Swift judgment ſeiz'd and ſtretch'd him on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> plain. </l>
        <l><lb/>The pamper'd ox thus ſtruck for ſacrifice, </l>
        <l><lb/>Uprears his head and bellows to the ſkies; </l>
        <l><lb/>Th' affrighted prieſt renews the fatal blow, </l>
        <l><lb/>He ſinks w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> quiv'ring limbs and lays his frontlet low. </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
        <l rend="indent"><lb/>Say, Muſe, you ſaw how firſt the plague began, </l>
        <l><lb/>What part it ſeiz'd to cruſh aſpiring man. </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
        <l rend="indent"><lb/>The head confeſs'd ſtrong agonizing pain, </l>
        <l><lb/>Each fibre ſwell'd and ſhook the tortur'd brain. </l>
        <l><lb/>Wild wand'ring thoughts in dizzy mazes play, </l>
        <l><lb/>Run round in whirls and tear their ſeat away: </l>
        <l><lb/>Unuſual viſions dance before their eyes, </l>
        <l><lb/>A thouſand phantoms ſink, a thouſand riſe. </l>
        <l><lb/>Hell wide unfolds its everlaſting doors, </l>
        <l><lb/>The chains reſound, and hoarſe <hi rend="italic">Cocytus</hi> roars. </l>
        <l><lb/>Pale <hi rend="italic">Fear</hi> and ghaſtly <hi rend="italic">Terror</hi> ſtalk
          around, </l>
        <l><lb/>And black <hi rend="italic">Deſpair</hi> attends from wound to wound. </l>
        <l><lb/>Fantaſtick forms, by rage and phrenſy bred; </l>
        <l><lb/>And ſprung abortive from the lab'ring head. </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
        <l rend="indent"><lb/>From thence in haſty courſe the fury glides, </l>
        <l><lb/>Corrupts the heart and taints the vital tides. </l>
        <l><lb/>The infant ſucks the alimental blood, </l>
        <l><lb/>He ſucks, but loathing caſts the baleful food; </l>
        <l><lb/>Th' infected juices turn to noiſome phlegm, </l>
        <l><lb/>And life and death flow out in ev'ry ſtream; </l>
        <pb n="212"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <l><lb/>The ſwelling tongue diſtills with putrid gore, </l>
        <l><lb/>And rhet'rick's ſelf is heard to ſpeak no more. </l>
        <l><lb/>Intolerable fate! to feel the pain, </l>
        <l><lb/>Yet want th' unenvied power to complain. </l>
        <l><lb/>No rage of heat th'exteriour ſurface ſhews; </l>
        <l><lb/>Within, an unextinguiſh'd <hi rend="italic">Ætna</hi> glows; </l>
        <l><lb/>Nor head, nor heart, nor limbs their office know, </l>
        <l><lb/>All feel at once the univerſal woe! </l>
        <l><lb/>The peſt aſſumes an unreſiſted throne, </l>
        <l><lb/>And rules o'er all, unbounded and alone: </l>
        <l><lb/>Nor ſtone, nor gout, nor ſwelling dropſies ſtay, </l>
        <l><lb/>They ſeek in diſtant lands the healthy prey. </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
        <l rend="indent"><lb/>But what art thou, O <hi rend="italic">Plague</hi>, whoſe noxious
          breath </l>
        <l><lb/>Diſpells the tardy miniſters of <hi rend="italic">Death</hi>? </l>
        <l><lb/>Sad cure alas! which thus the fates employ, </l>
        <l><lb/>And treach'rous ſave, the ſwifter to deſtroy. </l>
        <l><lb/>As when ſtaunch hounds perſue the trembling deer </l>
        <l><lb/>Thro' groves and lawns and now ſurvey him near, </l>
        <l><lb/>By chance a lyon breaks the neighb'ring wood, </l>
        <l><lb/>They fly, he tears the prey, and drinks the vital blood, </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
        <l rend="indent"><lb/>And now to glut y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> all-devouring grave, </l>
        <l><lb/>A meager ſhape forbad the plague to ſave, </l>
        <l><lb/>As death it came, with dreadful ſtrides along, </l>
        <l><lb/>And rag'd reſiſtleſs, thro' the vulgar throng. </l>
        <l><lb/>Far off at firſt its viſage grim I view'd, </l>
        <l><lb/>Deep lines intrench'd, like gaping furrows ſhew'd; </l>
        <l><lb/>As near it came, large characters I ſpy'd, </l>
        <l><lb/>The marks I trembling read, and <hi rend="sc">famine</hi> cry'd. </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
        <l rend="indent"><lb/>What hopes of ſafety, when ſuch mighty foes </l>
        <l><lb/>Leagu'd in the bands of deſolation roſe? </l>
        <l><lb/>As if the king of beaſts ſhould join the bear, </l>
        <l><lb/>To ſtorm the folds and bleating lambkins tear, </l>
        <l><lb/>Such havock made th' infernal fiends around, </l>
        <l><lb/>So mourn'd the youth, expiring on the ground. </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
        <l rend="indent"><lb/>Wherever death diſſolves their black deſpair, </l>
        <l><lb/>Untomb'd they lye and taint the putrid air. </l>
        <l><lb/>The vulturs ſnuff the wind, and ſcent the prey, </l>
        <l><lb/>But e'er they reach, wing back the liquid way. </l>
        <l><lb/>As where hell yawning wide in rage diſplodes </l>
        <l><lb/>Sulphureous vapours on the gath'ring clouds: </l>
        <l><lb/>If near by chance ſome airy wanderer flies, </l>
        <l><lb/>Or ſwift he turns, or ſuffocated, dyes. </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
        <l rend="indent"><lb/>If any yet, if any yet ſurvive, </l>
        <l><lb/>'Tis hard to ſay if dead, or if alive, </l>
        <l><lb/>Here's one, t'himſelf the monumental clay, </l>
        <l><lb/>The tomb is left, the index wip'd away; </l>
        <l><lb/>Whatever ſchemes th' imagination form'd, </l>
        <l><lb/><hi rend="italic">Oblivion</hi> enter'd and the ſtore-houſe ſtorm'd. </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
        <l rend="indentall hanging"><lb/>How vain thy thoughts, O man! how vain thy <lb/>cares! </l>
        <l><lb/>One breath diſſolves the labour'd work of years! </l>
        <l><lb/>Down, down then mighty pride, not made for man, </l>
        <l><lb/>Exiſtence ſhort! the emblematick ſpan! </l>
        <l><lb/>Be proud the oak—his branching head he rears, </l>
        <l><lb/>O'er-tops the clouds, and ſcorns a thouſand years. </l>
        <l><lb/>Be proud yon everlaſting rock, that braves </l>
        <l><lb/>Stern <hi rend="italic">Neptune</hi>'s power and breaks the daſhing waves. </l>
        <l><lb/>But let not man be proud, nor vainly boaſt </l>
        <l><lb/>High reaſon's claim, ſo ſoon to reaſon loſt. </l>
        <l><lb/>View well this animated trunk, ſurvey </l>
        <l><lb/>Mankind in him, the bubble of a day: </l>
        <l><lb/>Creation's lord himſelf ſurviving ſee, </l>
        <l><lb/>Is this his boaſted immortality? </l>
        <l><lb/>Is this?—But hold my Muſe, ceaſe, ceaſe to blame, </l>
        <l><lb/>Nor add thy inſults to the raging flame.—</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
        <l rend="indent"><lb/>If chance the head eſcap'd the fatal blow </l>
        <l><lb/>The fury mov'd the ſiege and rag'd below; </l>
        <l><lb/>Or legs or arms from th' active maſs diſjoyn'd, </l>
        <l><lb/>Leave the ſad ſenſe of life and woe behind: </l>
        <l><lb/>As when loud <hi rend="italic">Auſter</hi> from deep caverns broke, </l>
        <l><lb/>Invades with bluſt'ring noiſe ſome mountain oak, </l>
        <cb n="2"/>
        <l><lb/>In vain he roars, in vain invokes the pow'rs </l>
        <l><lb/>Of ratt'ling thunders and impetuous ſhow'rs; </l>
        <l><lb/>The trunk ſtill bears the blaſts and ſtormy rain; </l>
        <l><lb/>But leaves and ſhatter'd branches ſtrew the plain. </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
        <l rend="indent"><lb/>Where, beauteous city, are thy honours fled! </l>
        <l><lb/>The old deſtroy'd, and future ages dead! </l>
        <l><lb/>Oh! plague tremendous! at thy blaſting call </l>
        <l><lb/>Deep-rooted trees and tender bloſſoms fall! </l>
        <l><lb/>Let hiſtory be dumb, no annals tell </l>
        <l><lb/>How great <hi rend="italic">Maſſilia</hi> ſtood, how wretched fell! </l>
        <l><lb/>Ye winds be ſilent! or with tainted breath </l>
        <l><lb/>Convey at once the tale and ſpeedy death: </l>
        <l><lb/>Leaſt idol nations, in perdition born, </l>
        <l><lb/>Th' omnifick wiſdom and his temples ſcorn. </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
        <l rend="indent"><lb/>But ſee! th' almighty quells th' infernal fiends, </l>
        <l><lb/>Infection's blaſted and deſtruction ends. </l>
        <l><lb/>May all confeſs the wonder-working God, </l>
        <l><lb/>May he ne'er wave, nor we provoke the rod, </l>
        <l><lb/>Leſt unregarded judgments vainly hurl'd </l>
        <l><lb/>Involve in plagues the univerſal world. </l>
      </lg>
      <signed rend="sc align-right">Maro. </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
