<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - T.M.: An Account of an Extraordinary Alimentary Powder</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>T.M.</persName>
            </author>
            <title> An Account of an Extraordinary Alimentary Powder, and its Effects</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for D. Henry, and R. Cave, at St John's Gate.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1755</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">25</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">7</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1755_GM_0007">
    <body>
      <pb n="7"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <div>
        <salute rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. </hi><hi rend="sc">Urban</hi>,</salute>
        <p rend="italic space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(1.5)">I</hi>Obſerved ſometime ago in the London <lb/>news papers and
          article from France, in <lb/>which, either from ignorance or raillery, a<lb/> diſcovery
          lately made by a French ſurgeon,<lb/> was repreſented as an expedient to live <lb/>without
          food ; it was, I believe, treated by<lb/> many as a fable, but was founded on a<lb/> fact,
          of which I ſend you a particular and<lb/> faithful account, for the more rational
          en-<lb/>tertainment of your numerous readers.</p>
        <signed rend="align-center">
          <lb/>I am, Sir, Yours, &amp;c. <hi rend="roman align-right">T. M. </hi>
        </signed>
      </div>
      <div>
      <head rend="italic align-center">
        <lb/>An Account of an Extraordinary Alimenta- <lb/>ry Powder, and its Effects. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">E</hi>Xperiments of this powder have <lb/>been made firſt on three
        ſoldiers at <lb/><hi rend="italic">Liſle</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Flanders</hi>, and
        afterwards on ſix <lb/>penſioners in the royal hoſpital of in- <lb/>valids at <hi
          rend="italic">Paris</hi>, and ſix ounces in ſome- <lb/>thing leſs than a pint of water,
        were <lb/>found to be ſufficient aliment, or meat <lb/>and drink, for one man during one
        day; <lb/>the ſix invalids had no other proviſion <lb/>than this quantity of the powder <hi
          rend="italic">per <lb/>diem.</hi> for 15 days, in the month of <hi rend="italic">Oct.</hi>
        <lb/>laſt, and all continued hearty and well, <lb/>tho' one was upwards of 70, the others
        <lb/>were young men, but had loſt ſome of <lb/>their limbs. Neither old or young ſuffer'd
        <lb/>any inconvenience either from faintneſs <lb/>or hunger: they were employ'd in ſuch
        <lb/>bodily exerciſe as ſuited their years and <lb/>ſtrength, ſome walking daily many hours,
        <lb/>others digging; yet many times they did <lb/>not eat their whole allowance, and to
        <lb/>prevent any fraud they were conſtantly <lb/>attended by a centinel wherever they
        <lb/>went. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This powder, before it was adminiſ- <lb/>ter'd, was prepared every day in the fol-
        <lb/>lowing manner; Count <hi rend="italic">de la Serre</hi>, gov. <lb/>Count <hi
          rend="italic">de la Chark</hi>, lieut. the phyſicians, <lb/>ſurgeons, and other officers
        of the hoſpi- <lb/>tal being preſent: ſix ounces of the pow- <lb/>der being brought in a
        little bag was ſha- <lb/>ken by degrees into boiling water, which <lb/>at the ſame time was
        ſtirred briſkly with a <lb/>ſpoon, and in as little time as would ſuf- <lb/>fice to dreſs an
        egg, was fit to be eaten, <lb/>having acquired the conſiſtence of a thin <pb n="8"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>Panada, and the colour of gingerbread. <lb/>When the powder is firſt ſtirred into the
        <lb/>water a light ſcum riſes like that which <lb/>happens in boiling bran; it ſmells alſo
        <lb/>partly like toaſted bread, and partly like <lb/>cummin-feed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is inſipid to the taſte, but not diſa- <lb/>greeable. It cannot be abſolutely
        affirm- <lb/>ed to be merely farinaceous, but it does <lb/>not appear to be compounded of
        any a- <lb/>nimal ſubſtance, tho' ſome grains of a ve- <lb/>ry fine ſand have been
        diſcover'd in it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In a ſhort time this panada grows much <lb/>thicker, the powder imbibing all the wa-
        <lb/>ter, and when it is cold it is quite hard. <lb/>It may be prepared with cold water, but
        <lb/>then in a ſhort time it will become ſour. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This powder may be uſed to great <lb/>advantage, ſuppoſing the compoſition to <lb/>be
        cheap and eaſily preſerved, as well at <lb/>ſea, when other proviſions fall ſhort, as by
        <lb/>an army during forced marches, a garri- <lb/>ſon in a beſiged town, and the poor in
        <lb/>times of great ſcarcity. It is gueſſed to <lb/>be <hi rend="sc">Turky Corn</hi> roaſted
        and powder- <lb/>ed, and mix'd with a ſmall quantity of <lb/>ſea ſalt; ſome chryſtals of
        which have <lb/>been diſcovered in it; and is the in- <lb/>vention of M. <hi rend="italic"
          >Boueb</hi>, ſurgeon major of a <lb/>regiment in <hi rend="italic">France</hi>. </p></div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
