<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: An Account of some new Experiments on Human Blood</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Account of some new Experiments on Human Blood.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for D. Henry, and R. Cave, at St John's Gate.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1755</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">25</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">66</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1755_GM_0066">
    <body>
      <pb n="66"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <head rend="italic align-center">
        <lb/>An Account of ſome new Experiments on <lb/>Human Blood. By M. <hi rend="roman"
          >Eller</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">M</hi>R <hi rend="italic">Eller</hi> conſidering that medici- <lb/>nal
        drugs produce their various <lb/>effects on the human body, by acting <lb/>upon the blood in
        a manner not to be <lb/>diſcovered by the ſight, was determin- <lb/>ed to try, what
        appearances an imme- <lb/>diate admixture of them with that fluid <lb/>would produce. For
        theſe experiments <lb/>he choſe the blood of perſons in perfect <lb/>health, which was
        received in proper <lb/>veſſels placed in a balneum, regulated <lb/>exactly to the heat of
        the effluent blood <lb/>during each experiment; and the ſub- <lb/>ſtances to be mixed with
        it were like- <lb/>wiſe heated in the ſame degree. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>1. A ſolution of <hi rend="italic">vitriol</hi>, both of <hi rend="italic">iron</hi>
        <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">copper</hi>, changed the fine red colour <lb/>of the blood into a
        pale grey in an <lb/>inſtant, and a muddy precipitation en- <lb/>ſued. The microſcope ſhewed
        the glo- <lb/>bules of the blood to be transformed <lb/>into a kind of filaments, here and
        there <lb/>ſpeckled with red. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>2. A ſolution of <hi rend="italic">alum</hi> changed the <lb/>blood into a deep red,
        but of an uni- <lb/>form mixture; a coagulation ſuddenly <lb/>ſucceeded, but without any
        alteration <lb/>of the colour. By the microſcope the <lb/>ſmall globules were ſeen every
        where in <lb/>contact, and formed an obſcure contex- <lb/>ture, with hardly any
        tranſparency. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>3. A ſolution of <hi rend="italic">ſea ſalt</hi> heightened <lb/>and much improved the
        natural red of <lb/>the blood. The mixture was not uni- <lb/>form at firſt, but ſoon united
        into a <lb/><choice>
          <corr/>
          <sic>a </sic>
        </choice>tranſparent jelly. By the microſcope <lb/>the globules were perceived to be diſ-
        <lb/>joined, but orderly ranged, of a yel- <lb/>lowiſh hue, and tranſparent. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>4. A ſolution of <hi rend="italic">nitre</hi> or <hi rend="italic">ſalt-petre</hi> ex-
          <pb n="67"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>hibited much the ſame phænomena, <lb/>except that the colour of the blood <lb/>was
        ſtill more exalted, and the coagu- <lb/>lation did not take place till the whole <lb/>was
        cold. The microſcope ſhewed the <lb/>globules tranſparent, well ranged, and <lb/>disjoined
        from each other. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>5. A ſolution of <hi rend="italic">fixt alkaline ſalt</hi> chan- <lb/>ged the colour of
        the blood to a deep <lb/>red, and communicated and extraordi- <lb/>nary fluidity to the
        mixture, which <lb/>ſubſiſted ſeveral days without the leaſt <lb/>alteration. The globules
        appeared diſ- <lb/>joined in the microſcope, a little yel- <lb/>lowiſh, and pellucid. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>6. A ſolution of <hi rend="italic">ſalt of hart's-horn</hi>, a <lb/>volatile alcali,
        ſhewed the ſame appear- <lb/>ances, except that the mixture was <lb/>ſomewhat more fluid;
        the colour and <lb/>the fluidity laſted ſeveral days; and the <lb/>ſmall globules were ſeen
        in the microſ- <lb/>cope perfectly disjoined, of a fine red, <lb/>and tranſparent. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>7. A ſolution of <hi rend="italic">ſal armoniac</hi> produced a <lb/>red ſtill deeper
        than either of the fore- <lb/>going: But the mixture, which was at <lb/>firſt very thin,
        ſoon ſtiffened into an u- <lb/>niform jelly of the ſame colour. The <lb/>microſcope at firſt
        ſhewed the globules <lb/>pretty red and tranſparent, but they <lb/>ſoon changed their
        ſpherical figure, <lb/>becoming oblong and a little flatted, <lb/>and ſeemed to roll over
        one another, <lb/>but ſtill retained their red colour. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>8. A ſolution of <hi rend="italic">borax</hi> gave the blood <lb/>a fine bright red;
        but the mixture pre- <lb/>ſently coagulated, tho' without ſenſibly <lb/>altering the colour.
        The globules were <lb/>ſeen very much ſeparated in the mi- <lb/>croſcope; but as to their
        colour, they <lb/>were perfectly white and tranſparent. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>9. A ſolution of <hi rend="italic">cream of tartar</hi> did <lb/>not at firſt produce
        any ſenſible altera- <lb/>tion; but in a little while both the co- <lb/>lour and conſiſtence
        of the mixture <lb/>were changed, the ſmaller portion of <lb/>it, which roſe to the top of
        the vial, <lb/>was a tranſparent reddiſh ſerum, under <lb/>which was a flocky unequal
        coagulum, <lb/>of a blackiſh red, which did not eaſily <lb/>ſhift its place upon inverting
        the glaſs. <lb/>At firſt the little globules appeared <lb/>pretty round in the microſcope,
        whitiſh, <lb/>and tranſparent; but they ſoon flatten- <lb/>ed, and every where appeared to
        ſlide <lb/>over one another. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>10. A ſolution of <hi rend="italic">vitriolated tartar</hi>
        <lb/>mixed with the blood, made it more <lb/>fluid, and of a beautiful carnation co-
        <lb/>lour, which laſted many days, without <lb/>the leaſt appearance of coagulation.
        <lb/>The microſcope ſhewed the globules <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>pale, yellow, tranſparent, and diſtinct- <lb/>ly ſeparated. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>11. A ſolution of <hi rend="italic">ſal polychreſtum</hi> gave <lb/>the ſame phænomena.
        The microſcope <lb/>ſhewed the globules yellow and tranſ- <lb/>parent. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>12. A ſolution of <hi rend="italic">Epſom ſalt</hi> render'd <lb/>the mixture perfectly
        fluid, and of a <lb/>fine even red colour. When it was cold <lb/>the fluidity laſted many
        days without <lb/>alteration. The microſcope exhibited <lb/>the globules exceeding ſmall, of
        a pale <lb/>yellow, and tranſparent. The <hi rend="italic">ſel de <lb/>Seigneitte</hi>
        produced nearly the ſame ap- <lb/>pearances. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>13. A ſolution of <hi rend="italic">Glauber's ſal mira- <lb/>bile</hi> offered the ſame
        phænomena as to <lb/>the fluidity at the firſt; but the mix- <lb/>ture coagulated as ſoon as
        it became <lb/>cold. The little globules however con- <lb/>tinued fluid, and being examined
        by <lb/>the microſcope appeared whitiſh. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>14. <hi rend="italic">Sel d'Oſeille</hi> deſtroyed the red co- <lb/>lour in an inſtant,
        and changed it into <lb/>a livid pale and confuſed concrete; <lb/>tho' when viewed with the
        microſcope, <lb/>the little globules were perceived to be <lb/>regularly ranged, yellowiſh,
        and pellucid. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>15. To diſcover what effect would be <lb/>produced by mixing ſeveral of the moſt
        <lb/>noxious drugs with the blood, he pre- <lb/>pared a ſolution of <hi rend="italic"
          >arſenic</hi>, which thick- <lb/>ened it inſtantly, but gave it a fine <lb/>bright red.
        The microſcope ſhewed the <lb/>globules very minute, and as it were diſ- <lb/>ſolved, but in
        motion, among which <lb/>were diſcovered, floating here and there, <lb/>chryſtals with
        triangular points, like <lb/>little javelins. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>16. A ſolution of <hi rend="italic">corroſive ſublimate</hi>
        <lb/>changed the colour to a reddiſh brown, <lb/>or liver colour, yet the fluidity conti-
        <lb/>nued even after cooling. The little <lb/>globules viewed in the microſcope ſeem-
        <lb/>ed, while the mixture continued warm, <lb/>to be deſtroyed; but as it grew cold
        <lb/>theſe ſmall ſpherical bodies became a- <lb/>gain viſible, being white and tranſpa-
        <lb/>rent, and ſeemed to move and unite <lb/>together, ſo as to form a kind of flocks
        <lb/>like ſnow, among which were diſſemi- <lb/>nated ſome red ſphericles. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>17. His next experiments were on <lb/>corroſive acid ſpirits. A few drops of <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">oil of vitriol</hi> made the mixture in a mo- <lb/>ment extremely hot, and
        converted it <lb/>into an hard, ſolid maſs, of a dark- <lb/>brown colour; yet the globules
        of the <lb/>blood did not appear to be deſtroyed, <lb/>as might reaſonably have been expec-
        <lb/>ted; but in the microſcope were plain- <lb/>ly diſtinguiſhed of a yellow colour. </p>
      <pb n="68"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>18. <hi rend="italic">Spirit of nitre</hi> thickened it conſi- <lb/>derably, yet
        without the total deſtruc- <lb/>tion of its fluidity: It became livid like <lb/>blue clay;
        but the microſcope diſco- <lb/>vered the globules in their natural <lb/>ſhape, of a milky
        white. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>19. <hi rend="italic">Spirit of ſea ſalt</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">common ſalt</hi>,
        <lb/>produced the ſame appearance as to <lb/>colour, but the mixture ſoon became <lb/>an
        hard maſs; the globules looking <lb/>white and tranſparent in the microſ- <lb/>cope. From
        theſe experiments it ap- <lb/>pears, that the ſtrongeſt corroſives do <lb/>not exert ſo much
        of their force on the <lb/>fluid, as on the ſolid parts of our bodies. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>20. He alſo made ſeveral experiments <lb/>on ſuch eſſences or tinctures as have
        <lb/>gained credit as medicines. Theſe are <lb/>the reſinous parts of drugs, whether
        <lb/>ſimple, or diſſolved in ſpirit of wine. <lb/>The chief are the tinctures of <hi
          rend="italic">myrrh</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">ſaffron</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
          >alces</hi>, <hi rend="italic">opium</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ellebore</hi>, <hi
          rend="italic">rhubarb</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">yellow amber</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
          >caſtor</hi>, <hi rend="italic">jalap</hi>, <hi rend="italic">quinquina</hi>, <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">caſcarilla bark</hi>, <hi rend="italic">tincture of antimony</hi>, and
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Sydenham's liquid laudanum</hi>. Theſe <lb/>eſſences have this in
        common, that <lb/>upon being mixed with the blood, they <lb/>immediately produce more or
        leſs of a <lb/>coagulation, which doubtleſs ariſes from <lb/>the ſalt which the reſinous
        particles <lb/>meet with in the vital fluid. The co- <lb/>lour of theſe coagulations differs
        great- <lb/>ly. That produced by eſſence of <hi rend="italic">aloes</hi>, <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">opium</hi>, <hi rend="italic">myrrh</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ſaffron</hi>,
        and <hi rend="italic">amber</hi>, is livid <lb/>and diſagreeable. The concretion from
        <lb/>the eſſence of <hi rend="italic">caſtor</hi> and <hi rend="italic">jalap</hi> is a
        brown <lb/>red, and that of <hi rend="italic">ellebore</hi> a reddiſh yel- <lb/>low. The
        coagulation of the eſſences <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">quinquina</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
          >caſcarilla</hi> retain ſome <lb/>degree of fluidity; the colour being of <lb/>a dirty
        grey, and the globules ſeem diſ- <lb/>ſolved or white. <hi rend="italic">Tincture of
          antimony</hi>
        <lb/>gives a fine bright red coagulation, and <lb/>the globules appear of an elegant flame
        <lb/>colour, and very diſtinct, in the microſ- <lb/>cope. The mixture with <hi rend="italic"
          >Sydenham's <lb/>laudanum</hi> remains fluid, of a reddiſh <lb/>brown, and the globules
        coaleſce, but <lb/>are tranſparent and white. It is re- <lb/>markable that the globules of
        the blood <lb/>in the thick mixture formed by the eſ- <lb/>ſence of <hi rend="italic"
          >opium</hi>, ſeem to be deſtroyed <lb/>as to their nature; at leaſt the microſ- <lb/>cope
        repreſents them under a very con- <lb/>fuſed coheſion. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>21. The eſſences, or rather the ex- <lb/>tracts and decoctions of the gumous <lb/>parts
        of ſimples, made with common <lb/>water, produce no great alteration when <lb/>mixed with
        the blood, except in the <lb/>colour, which is more or leſs varied, <lb/>according to the
        quantity or quality of <lb/>the thing employed; but the globules <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>examin'd by the microſcope are appa- <lb/>rently the ſame. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
