<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Continuation of the account of English Poisonous
          plants.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Continuation of the account of English Poisonous plants.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for D. Henry, and R. Cave, at St John's Gate.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1755</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">25</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">270</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1755_GM_0270">
    <body>
      <pb n="270"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <head rend="italic align-center">
        <lb/>Continuation of the account of <hi rend="roman">Engliſh</hi> poi- <lb/>ſonous Plants.
        (See p. 211.) </head>
      <head rend="hanging space">
        <lb/>VI. <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="dc(1.5.)">S</hi>Olanum lethale</hi>. Dwale or deadly
        <lb/>night-ſhade. </head>
      <div rend="italic">
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>Synonyma. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Bella donna Cluſti pan. 504. Ray. Syn. <lb/>Stirp. Ed. 3d. p. 265. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>— majoribus foliis et floribus Tourn. <lb/>Inſt. R. H. 77. Boer. Hort. Lugd. Bat. 69. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Solanum majus, ſive herba bella donna, <lb/>Mathiol. p. 756. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Solanum bacciferum quartum ſive Mela- <lb/>noceraſos, C. B. pin. 166. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Solanum manicum multis, ſeu Bella don- <lb/>na. J. B. 3. 611. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Solanum lethale Ger. em. 340. Park. 346. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Atropa Linn. Hort. Cliff. 57. Hilt. Hiſt. <lb/>Plant. p. 287. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>— caule herbaceo foliis ovatis inte- <lb/>gris, Linn. Spec. Pl. p. 181. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>Claſſical Diſtribution. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This plant belongs to the <hi rend="italic">Herbæ bac- <lb/>ciferæ</hi> according to
          the ſyſtems of <hi rend="italic">Ray</hi>
          <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">Boerhaave</hi>; to the <hi rend="italic">Pentandria mo-
            <lb/>nagynia</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Linnæus</hi>, among the plants of <lb/>the fourth
          diviſion, having declinated <lb/>ſtamina; to the <hi rend="italic">Herbæ Oligantheræ ſta-
            <lb/>minibus pericarpio multi loculari</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Van <lb/>Royen</hi>.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>Deſcription. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The root is compoſed of a number of <lb/>oblong tuberous bodies, of a brown
          <lb/>colour, ſucculent, and of a very diſa- <lb/>greeable ſmell. The radical leaves are
          <lb/>a foot long and five inches broad. The <lb/>ſtalk riſes to three or four feet high,
          <lb/>and is very much devaricated and <lb/>branched; the leaves ſtand alternately <lb/>on
          it, and at ſmall diſtances; they are <pb n="271"/>
          <cb n="1"/>
          <lb/>five or ſix inches long, and more than <lb/>half as much in breadth, of a duſty
          <lb/>green colour, and a paler green under- <lb/>neath, hairy on both ſides, and not ſi-
          <lb/>nuated at the edges. The flowers are <lb/>very numerous, they ſtand in the <hi
            rend="italic">alæ</hi> of <lb/>the leaves, and are large, of a campa- <lb/>nulated
          figure, and ſtriated, of a duſky <lb/>purple colour within, with a yellow va-
          <lb/>riegated baſe: the outer ſurface is of a <lb/>greeniſh red and hairy; after the
          flower <lb/>is fallen there ſucceeds a fine beautiful <lb/>and large berry, which is black
          when <lb/>ripe. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>Place. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It is not very common; it is chiefly <lb/>found growing in uncultivated places,
          <lb/>in church-yards, about old buildings, <lb/>among rubbiſh, and about dunghills,
          <lb/>and ſometimes on barren ſandy heaths<choice>
            <corr>.</corr>
            <sic>,</sic>
          </choice>
          <lb/>It is mentioned in Mr <hi rend="italic">Ray</hi>'s <hi rend="italic">Synopſis</hi> to
          <lb/>have been found in the church-yard <lb/>and lanes about <hi rend="italic"
            >Fulbourn</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Cambridge- <lb/>ſhire</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
            >Sutton-Cofield</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Warwickſhire</hi>; in <lb/>the <hi
            rend="italic">Downs</hi>, where it grows very ſmall; <lb/>in <hi rend="italic"
            >Cuchſtone</hi>, near <hi rend="italic">Rocheſter</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Kent</hi>,
          all <lb/>the yards and backſides are over-run <lb/>with it. Dr <hi rend="italic"
            >Deering</hi> found it upon <hi rend="italic">Clif- <lb/>ton-hill</hi> near <hi
            rend="italic">Nottingham</hi>; alſo in a <lb/>quarry not far from the cold bath at
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Mansfield</hi>; in <hi rend="italic">Currenwood Kins</hi> near
            <hi rend="italic">Bur- <lb/>ton</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Kendal</hi>, and other places
          in <hi rend="italic">Weſt- <lb/>moreland</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Wilſon</hi>'s Synopſis.
          Dr <hi rend="italic">Wilmer</hi>
          <lb/>found it among the bogs goingdown to <lb/><hi rend="italic">Darking, Surrey</hi>,
          plentifully; in <hi rend="italic">Preſton</hi>
          <lb/>church-yard, near <hi rend="italic">Feverſham, Kent</hi>. Mr <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Watſon</hi> found it by the road ſide, under <lb/>the park wall, between <hi
            rend="italic">Temsford</hi> mills <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">Welwyn, Hertfordſhire</hi>.
          Mr <hi rend="italic">Black- <lb/>ſtone</hi> found it in a ſhady gravel-pit near <lb/>the
          old park-wood at <hi rend="italic">Harefield</hi>, and in <lb/>the gardens at <hi
            rend="italic">Moor</hi> park near <hi rend="italic">Rick- <lb/>manſworth</hi>,
          plentifully, <hi rend="italic">Specimen Botan. <lb/>p. 93.</hi> It hath been found about
            <hi rend="italic">Grace- <lb/>Dieu</hi> abbey in <hi rend="italic">Leiceſterſhire</hi>,
          but ſparing- <lb/>ly; alſo in the church-yard and elſe- <lb/>where about <hi rend="italic"
            >North Luffenham</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Rutland</hi>, <lb/>from whence I received a
          ſpecimen this <lb/>ſpring by a friend, who was informed, <lb/>that a child ſome time ago
          had been <lb/>poiſoned at that place by eating the <lb/>berries of the plant. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>Obſervations. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>We have many fatal inſtances upon <lb/>record, in various authors, of the in-
          <lb/>toxicating and poiſonous quality of this <lb/>plant; of the berries eſpecially. Such
          <lb/>indeed as occur have in general hap- <lb/>pened to children, who being allured
          <lb/>by their beautiful appearance and ſweet <lb/>taſte, have eaten of them. Almoſt all
          <lb/>the antient botanic and medical writers <lb/>have remarked its narcotic and de- <cb
            n="2"/>
          <lb/>ſtructive quality. <hi rend="italic">Theophraſtus</hi>, one of <lb/>the moſt antient
          writers extant, upon <lb/>the ſubject of vegetables, has deſcribed <lb/>
          <note n="(1)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.8)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(1) Hiſt. Plant. lib. 9. c. 12. </p>
          </note> two ſpecies of nightſhade, to both <lb/>which he aſcribes a narcotic quality,
          <lb/>and of the one particularly obſerves, <lb/>that if the root be given to the quanti-
          <lb/>ty of three or four drams it proves fa- <lb/>tal. <hi rend="italic">Dioſcorides</hi>
          <note n="(2)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.8)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(2) Lib. 4. c. 69. After deſcribing the plant <lb/>he ſays <q rend="diple quotes"
                >Radix <unclear>diuchmæ</unclear> unius pondere po- <lb/>ta ex vino, facit ſpecies
                vanas, imaginatio- <lb/>neſque non injucundas obverſari; ſed du- <lb/>plicatus hic
                modus, ad tres uſque dies, men- <lb/>tis alienationem affert: quadruplicatus in-
                <lb/>terimit </q> and then adds, <q rend="diple quotes">Remedio eſt <lb/>aqua mulſa
                copioſius pota, &amp; vomitione re- <lb/>jecta. </q>
            </p>
          </note> deſcribes four ſpecies, <lb/>one of which he calls Στρύχνος μανικος, <lb/>and
          which by ſeveral authors is thought <lb/>to be the very plant we have deſcribed, <lb/>but
          the deſcriptions of the antients are <lb/>frequently ſo ſhort, vague, and inde-
          <lb/>terminate, that it is difficult, not to ſay <lb/>impoſſible, at this time, in many
          in- <lb/>ſtances, to fix upon the particular ſpe- <lb/>cies they meant to deſcribe. <hi
            rend="italic">Dioſcori- <lb/>des</hi> attributes the ſame poiſonous effects <lb/>to this
          plant as <hi rend="italic">Theophraſtus</hi> had done, <lb/>as likewiſe does <hi
            rend="italic">Pliny</hi>, <note n="(3)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.8)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(3) Hiſt. Nat. lib. 21. c. 31. </p>
          </note> who alſo <lb/>enumerates four ſpecies, and ſeems <lb/>to have taken his account of
          the <lb/>plant from <hi rend="italic">Theophraſtus</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Dioſcori-
            <lb/>des</hi>, with very little variation. Later <lb/>authors have more accurately
          obſerved <lb/>and recorded its poiſonous faculty. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Matthiolus</hi>,
          an author of great credit, <lb/>informs us from his own knowledge, <lb/>of ſome children
          poiſoned by eating the <lb/>berries of the plant. <hi rend="italic">Sennertus</hi>, <note
            n="(4)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.8)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(4) Matthiol. in Dioſcorid. p. 756 Ed. 1598. </p>
          </note> in <lb/>his account of vegetable poiſons, <note n="(5)" place="bottom"
            rend="size(0.8)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(5) Oper. omnia, vol. 2d. p. 1054. </p>
          </note>
          <lb/>has quoted <hi rend="italic">Tragus</hi> for an inſtance of a <lb/>man, who having
          eat of its berries <lb/>went mad the next day. From <hi rend="italic">Fuſch-
            <lb/>ſius</hi> he informs us of two boys who were <lb/>poiſoned by the ſame; and from
            <hi rend="italic">Lobel</hi>'s <lb/><hi rend="italic">Adverſaria</hi>, that ſome youths
          who had <lb/>eaten of them became ſtupefied, fell <lb/>aſleep, and died, as from an
          over-doſe of <lb/>opium. <hi rend="italic">Gerard</hi>
          <note n="(6)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.8)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(6) Ger. emac. p. 341. </p>
          </note> informs us of <q rend="diple quotes">three <lb/>boys of <hi rend="italic"
              >Wiſbick</hi> in the iſle of <hi rend="italic">Ely</hi>, who <lb/>eat the berries of
            this plant, two <lb/>whereof died in leſs than eight hours, <lb/>the third, by having
            honey and wa- <lb/>ter given him, and vomiting often, <lb/>recovered. </q> Mr <hi
            rend="italic">Ray</hi>, when men- <lb/>tioning the bad quality of this plant, <lb/>ſays,
            <note n="(7)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.8)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(7) Syn. Stirp. Brittan. ed. 3d, p. 226. </p>
          </note>
          <q rend="italic">Baccas pueris eſitantibus ſæpius <pb n="272"/>
            <cb n="1"/>
            <lb/>mortiferas fuiſſe legimus et audivimus </q>. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Boerhaave</hi>
          <note n="(8)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.8)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(8) Hiſt. Plant. Lugd. Bat. p. 510. as fol- <lb/>lows: <q rend="diple">Hæc planta
                venenatiſſima, nam ſi <lb/>homo unicam baccam comedat, ilico con- <lb/>vellitur, ſi
                plus, moritur.—Hic in Batavia <lb/>contigit, ut pueri allecti pulchritudine ha-
                <lb/>rum baccarum comederit, et brevi ſuffocati <lb/>mortui ſint. Sic in Aula
                Hetruſca accidit, <lb/>ubi tres pueri inde mortui ſunt. </q>
            </p>
          </note> produces inſtances of ſe- <lb/>veral children poiſoned by the ſame. <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">See alſo Gent. Mag. for <hi rend="roman">Auguſt 1747</hi></hi>, an
          <lb/>account of a child at <hi rend="italic">Cambridge</hi>, who <lb/>by eating one berry
          died in 12 hours <lb/>after. The very next month ſeveral <lb/>children at <hi
            rend="italic">Edinburgh</hi> having eaten of <lb/>theſe berries, ſwelled and were thrown
          <lb/>into ſtrong convulſions, and two of <lb/>them died the next day. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Another remarkable inſtance of the <lb/>effects of theſe berries we have in the
          <lb/>Magazine for <hi rend="italic">Sept.</hi> 1748, of a coach- <lb/>man who was killed
          by eating three or <lb/>four of them, which he gathered in a <lb/>lane near <hi
            rend="italic">Peterborough</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Wepfer</hi> alſo <note n="(9)"
            place="bottom" rend="size(0.8)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(9) Hiſtoria Cicutæ aquat<unclear>.</unclear> cap. 17. </p>
          </note>
          <lb/>relates the caſe of a child about ten <lb/>years old, who by eating the berries
          <lb/>was thrown into a great variety of con- <lb/>vulſive ſymptoms, but proper care be-
          <lb/>ing taken, by vomiting and giving a- <lb/>lexipharmics and anti-epileptics, he re-
          <lb/>covered. Mr <hi rend="italic">Millar</hi> has quoted <hi rend="italic">Bucha-
            <lb/>nan</hi> for one of the moſt remarkable and <lb/>memorable inſtances of the
          intoxica- <lb/>ting nature of this plant, in which he <lb/>gives an account of the
          deſtruction of <lb/>the army of <hi rend="italic">Sweno</hi>, when he invaded <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Scotland</hi>, by mixing a quantity of the <lb/>juice of theſe berries
          with the drink <lb/>which the <hi rend="italic">Scots</hi>, by their truce, were to
          <lb/>ſupply them with, which ſo intoxicated <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Danes</hi>, that
          the <hi rend="italic">Scots</hi> fell upon them <lb/>in their ſleep, and killed the
          greateſt <lb/>part of them, ſo that there were ſcarcely <lb/>men enough left to carry off
          their <lb/>king. <note n="(10)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.8)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(10) See Gardener's dictionary under the <lb/>word Bella donna. The paſſage may
              be found <lb/>in Buchanan Rerum Scoticarum, lib. 7. and <lb/>is quoted alſo by
              Johnſton in his Thaumatogra- <lb/>phia naturalis, part. 5th, cap. 38, De Solano,
              <lb/>inter admiranda Plantarum. </p>
          </note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The leaves and root of this herb <lb/>have been recommended and exter- <lb/>nally
          uſed in cataplaſms and ointments <lb/>for inflammatory ſwellings, and in ul- <lb/>cers
          even of a cancerous nature. But <lb/>even their external uſe ſeems not ad- <lb/>viſeable,
          as appears from the following <lb/>remarkable hiſtory of the effects of the <lb/>leaves,
          quoted by Dr <hi rend="italic">Van Swieten</hi>, <note n="(11)" place="bottom"
            rend="size(0.8)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(11) Vide Comment. in Aph. Boerh. Aph. <lb/>1061. Alſo Ray Syn. Stirp. Brittan.
              Edit. 3d. <lb/>p. 266. </p>
          </note>
          <cb n="2"/>
          <lb/>from Mr <hi rend="italic">Ray</hi>'s hiſtory of plants, to con- <lb/>firm his
          opinion, that ſome poiſons may <lb/>induce palſeys, even externally applied. <lb/>The caſe
          was this: A lady of quality ap- <lb/>plied a bit of the green leaf to a ſmall <lb/>ulcer
          which ſhe had near her eye, and <lb/>which was thought to be cancerous. <lb/>This in one
          night's time ſo relaxed the <lb/>uvea, that ſhe could not contract the <lb/>ſight; the
          pupil, even in the moſt gla- <lb/>ring light, appearing more than four <lb/>times larger
          than that of the other eye, <lb/>but by degrees, the leaf being removed, <lb/>it recovered
          its former elaſticity. And <lb/>that this was not accidental, appears <lb/>from the
          experiment being repeated <lb/>three times, the ſame effect conſtantly <lb/>following. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>To conclude, ſo many inſtances of <lb/>the direful effects of this plant natu-
          <lb/>rally ſuggeſt the expediency of endea- <lb/>vouring to deſtroy it wherever it is
          <lb/>found, about villages eſpecially, as <lb/>children may eaſily be tempted to eat
          <lb/>of the berries from their ſweet taſte and <lb/>alluring appearance. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
