<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Life of a Modern Physician</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Life of a Modern Physician</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for D. Henry, and R. Cave, at St John's Gate.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1755</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">25</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">74</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1755_GM_0074">
    <body>
      <pb n="74"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <epigraph>
        <p rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>Totus mundus agit hiſtrionem. </p>
      </epigraph>
      <salute rend="italic indent">
        <lb/>Mr <hi rend="sc">Urban</hi>, </salute>
      <dateline rend="align-right"><hi rend="italic">B—</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Feb.</hi> 8, 1755. </dateline>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi> Am a conſtant reader of all the <lb/>public papers of
        amuſement, and <lb/>obſerve, that although divinity and law <lb/>have fallen under the
          <unclear>laſh</unclear> of many an <lb/>anonymous author, yet the abſurdities <lb/>of
        phyſick have been but ſlightly <lb/>touched. I am myſelf a phyſician, and <lb/>as I have the
        honour of the profeſſion <lb/>as well as the health of his majeſty's <lb/>ſubjects very much
        at heart, I am de- <lb/>ſirous as well to promote the ſtudy of <lb/>that important ſcience,
        as to correct <lb/>the reigning fopperies of the profeſſion, <lb/>and this I ſhall attempt
        by an account <lb/>of my own life. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I had the misfortune to be the <lb/>younger ſon of a gentleman in the eaſt <lb/>riding
        of <hi rend="italic">Yorkſhire</hi>, who had a nume- <lb/>rous family and a ſmall fortune:
        my <lb/>diſpoſition was always contemplative, <lb/>which determined my father to bring
        <lb/>me up to the profeſſion of phyſick. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Having finiſhed my claſſical learning <lb/>under the auſpices of a neighbouring
        <lb/>clergyman, I was ſent to the univerſity <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Cambridge</hi>, where
        I continued till I <lb/>received both my maſter of arts and <lb/>doctor's degrees. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I was as remarkable at college for <lb/>my contempt of all polite amuſements <lb/>as
        for my cloſe application to ſtudy, <lb/>ſingularities out of which ſome attempt- <lb/>ed to
        rally and ſome to reaſon me. <lb/>Theſe gave me the name of young <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Hippocrates</hi>, and thoſe repreſented the <lb/>bad effects of a ſedentary life, and ur-
        <lb/>ged the examples of many young phy- <lb/>ſicians, whom I knew to be men of great
        <lb/>abilities, though ſmall practice, owing, <lb/>as they ſaid, to their too cloſe
        application <lb/>to ſtudy, and conſequent ignorance of <lb/>the world. However, neither
        raillery <lb/>nor reaſoning produced any alteration <lb/>in my conduct, being fully
        perſuaded <lb/>that a deep knowledge of the ſcience I <lb/>was to profeſs, was the only way
        to pro- <lb/>feſs it with reputation. The more I <lb/>knew, the more I thirſted after know-
        <lb/>ledge, ſo that I went from <hi rend="italic">Cambridge</hi> to <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Edinburgh</hi>, where I continued 4 years; <lb/>and from <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh</hi>
        to <hi rend="italic">London</hi>, where <lb/>I attended the publick hoſpitals, and <lb/>had
        the good fortune to be introduced <lb/>to ſeveral of the moſt eminent amongſt <lb/>the
        faculty, whoſe private practice I <lb/>was in a particular manner permitted <lb/>to ſee.
        From <hi rend="italic">London</hi> I went to <hi rend="italic">Leyden</hi>, <lb/>and <hi
          rend="italic">Paris</hi>, where I continued a conſi- <lb/>derable time, aſſiduouſly
        engaged in <lb/>the proſecution of my ſtudies, with ſuch <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>ſucceſs, that I had particular honours <lb/>paid me by almoſt every profeſſor. Be-
        <lb/>ing now fully qualified for practice, I <lb/>returned home, determined to fix my-
        <lb/>ſelf hi the firſt agreeable ſituation that <lb/>ſhould offer. A vacancy ſoon happened
        <lb/>in a polite town in one of the ſouthern <lb/>counties; the ſituation was excellent,
        <lb/>and the neighbourhood good. Being <lb/>confident of my own abilities as a phy-
        <lb/>ſician, I was the leſs ſollicitous to pro- <lb/>cure recommendatory letters, and ſo
        <lb/>contented myſelf with only one addreſſ- <lb/>ed to a worthy alderman of the town.
        <lb/>Upon my arrival I was very politely re- <lb/>ceived by the gentleman to whom I was
        <lb/>recommended, and in a few weeks had <lb/>been introduced to almoſt every perſon <lb/>of
        condition in the town and neigh- <lb/>bourhood. I now expected to reap in <lb/>gold what I
        had ſowed in learning, but <lb/>after a twelve months expectation, I <lb/>found my whole
        practice had center'd <lb/>amongſt the poorer ſort of people, who <lb/>had nothing beſides
        their bleſſings to <lb/>beſtow. I muſt confeſs I was extream- <lb/>ly chagrin'd to ſee
        people of diſtinction <lb/>have daily recourſe to a neighbouring <lb/>phyſician, who had
        nothing but old age <lb/>and formality to recommend him. I <lb/>now began to reflect upon
        the warnings <lb/>of my fellow ſtudents at <hi rend="italic">Cambridge</hi>, e-
        <lb/>ſpecially as I found myſelf every day <lb/>committing groſs abſurdities in beha-
        <lb/>viour, which I had reaſon to imagine <lb/>from the ſmart repartees of the tea
        <lb/>table, conſiderably leſſened my character <lb/>as a man of ſenſe. However, that I
        <lb/>might no longer ſuffer the torments of <lb/>doubt, I aſk'd the opinions of ſuch
        <lb/>friends as I knew were beſt acquainted <lb/>with the rites and ceremonies which
        <lb/>faſhion has impoſed on ſocial life; by <lb/>them I was unanimouſly complimented <lb/>on
        my merit as a phyſician, but blamed <lb/>for not ſetting it off by a better addreſs.
        <lb/>One very judiciouſly obſerved, that as <lb/>age and wiſdom were generally reputed
        <lb/>to be inſeperable, I had not taken care <lb/>to appear as wiſe as I might by hiding
        <lb/>my youth under the deep ſhadow of a <lb/>medical perriwig; another condemned <lb/>the
        ſlovenlineſs of my cloaths; a third <lb/>blamed the aukwardneſs of my manner, <lb/>and a
        fourth hinted at my ignorance of <lb/>whiſt and dancing, by ſaying, that for <lb/>his part
        he thought them no ſmall teſts <lb/>of merit. My eyes now began to open, <lb/>and the
        flattering illuſions that had <lb/>danced before me, vaniſhed in a mo- <lb/>ment; but alas!
        though I diſcovered <lb/>and regretted my miſtake, yet I found <lb/>myſelf unable to
        retrieve it; I could <pb n="75"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>indeed have put on a voluminous wig, <lb/>and worn a typical cane, but theſe were
        <lb/>only partial improvements, and would <lb/>only have render'd my other defects <lb/>more
        conſpicuous; I therefore deter- <lb/>mined to leave the place, and betake <lb/>myſelf to <hi
          rend="italic">London</hi> in queſt of thoſe me- <lb/>dical qualifications which in the
        pride <lb/>of my heart I had neglected to procure. <lb/>When I arrived, I took an elegant
        ſet <lb/>of lodgings near <hi rend="italic">St James</hi>'s, in the <lb/>neighbourhood of an
        eminent phyſi- <lb/>cian, that I might have an opportunity <lb/>of tranſplanting from him
        what was <lb/>wanting in myſelf. I learn'd to dance of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Pierot</hi>,
        and to fence of <hi rend="italic">Bond</hi>: My cloaths <lb/>were made in the true medical
        taſte, <lb/>by <hi rend="italic">Lambert</hi>; my wigs by <hi rend="italic">Shevreau</hi>,
        and <lb/>my cane and ſnuff box were purchaſed <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Tomkins</hi>. Thus
        equipp'd, I ſaun- <lb/>ter'd from one coffee-houſe to another, <lb/>gleaning politicks from
        ſome, and a- <lb/>theiſm from others. At <hi rend="italic">Sadler's Wells</hi>
        <lb/>and the midnight oratory I learn'd <lb/>grimace, and at the publick theatres <lb/>I
        improved in aſſurance. <hi rend="italic">Hoyle</hi> tutor'd <lb/>me in the ſeveral games at
        cards, and <lb/>under the name of guarding me from <lb/>being cheated, inſenſibly gave me a
        taſte <lb/>for ſharping. At laſt, to give the fi- <lb/>niſhing ſtroke to my medical
        character, <lb/>I learn'd the various methods of in- <lb/>trigue, under the ingenious Mrs
          <hi rend="italic">Doug- <lb/>laſs</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Covent Garden</hi>. Thus
        having, <lb/>tho' late, ſupplied the defects of my <lb/>education, and happily finiſh'd my
        ſtu- <lb/>dies, I once more left <hi rend="italic">London</hi>, and at- <lb/>tempted a
        ſettlement in the ſecond city <lb/>in the kingdom. I immediately put in <lb/>practice all
        the new arts I had learned, <lb/>and my ſucceſs ſo much exceeded my <lb/>expectations, that
        in a few months I <lb/>had deprived an eminent phyſician of <lb/>the ſame place, of the
        greater part of <lb/>his patients, beſides having obtained a <lb/>conſiderable number of my
        own. I had <lb/>the pleaſure to be univerſally well re- <lb/>ceived; I took great care never
        to <lb/>give the reins to my fancy, even before <lb/>my moſt intimate acquaintances, and
        <lb/>was particularly attentive to preſerve in- <lb/>violated the reverential awe which the
        <lb/>exuberance of my wig and the gravity <lb/>of my deportment had acquired. Be-
        <lb/>ſides, in order to be as much as poſſible <lb/>of a piece, I compoſed a heterodox ſort
        <lb/>of language, of <hi rend="italic">Greek</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Latin</hi>, <hi
          rend="italic">French</hi>, <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">Engliſh</hi>: My philoſophy was an
        aſ- <lb/>ſemblage of every ſyſtem that has illu- <lb/>minated the world ſince <hi
          rend="italic">Moſes</hi>, and my <lb/>religion was neither <hi rend="italic"
          >Chriſtian</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Turkiſh</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Jewiſh</hi>, nor
          <hi rend="italic">Heathen</hi>, but a compound <lb/>of all. My cane became an emblem of
        <lb/>wiſdom, and every hair of my wig <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>ſhewed the extent of my erudition. <lb/>Are not theſe, in this diſcerning age, <lb/>the
        juſt criterions of a good and learned <lb/>phyſician? and are they not of more <lb/>ſervice
        to the poſſeſſor than turning o- <lb/>ver, at midnight hours, the ſacred vo- <lb/>lumes of
        antiquity? The world delights <lb/>in externals, and he who expects the <lb/>world to pleaſe
        him, muſt pleaſe the <lb/>world. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In antient times when wiſdom and <lb/>learning were in faſhion, the profeſſors <lb/>of
        phyſic were grave and rigid in their <lb/>morals, decently plain in their dreſs,
        <lb/>aſſiduous in public, and laborious in <lb/>their private ſtudies. View the modern
        <lb/>phyſician in the morning, and you will <lb/>ſee him picking his nails, and ſoftening
        his <lb/>delicate hands with almond paſte; trace <lb/>him from place to place thro' the hur-
        <lb/>ry of the day, and you will ſee him <lb/>ſcrupulouſly attentive to every minute
        <lb/>punctilio of addreſs, every ſpecies of <lb/>obſequious flattery and officious com-
        <lb/>plaiſance, attentive only to write his <lb/>preſcriptions with an air of importance,
        <lb/>and take his fee with a good grace. <lb/>And view him at night you will ſee <lb/>him
        either lolling at eaſe in an eaſy <lb/>chair, by his own fire, muſing over a <lb/>pack of
        cards, or circulating his toaſt <lb/>in a bumper, while the caſes of the pa- <lb/>tients he
        has viſited never enter his <lb/>thoughts, and the books that might <lb/>enable him to
        reſtore their health, lie <lb/>covered with cobwebs upon his ſhelf. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But he who endeavours to appear <lb/>neither older nor younger than he is, <lb/>and
        addreſſes the judgment and not <lb/>the caprices of mankind, is alone wor- <lb/>thy of
        eſteem and confidence. Hypo- <lb/>criſy and diſguiſe brought me into eſ- <lb/>teem when
        merit failed me, but it was <lb/>happy for many of my friends, that I had <lb/>merit to
        diſguiſe. Phyſic is neither got- <lb/>ten by inſpiration nor entailed upon age; <lb/>nor can
        any man approach the temple <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Æſculapius</hi>, but by hard ſtudy,
        quick <lb/>apprehenſion, and ſound judgment. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From this extraordinary picture of <lb/>myſelf I am confident many of your <lb/>readers
        will be deſirous of knowing my <lb/>name, and leſt they ſhould unluckily <lb/>miſtake me for
        a neighbour of their <lb/>own, I freely tell them that my name is </p>
      <signed rend="sc align-right">
        <lb/>Ubique. </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
