<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Account of poisonous English Plants</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Account of poisonous English Plants</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for D. Henry, and R. Cave, at St John's Gate.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1755</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">25</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">29</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1755_GM_0029">
    <body>
      <pb n="29"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <div>
        <salute rend="italic indent">
          <lb/>Mr <hi rend="sc">Urban</hi>, </salute>
        <dateline rend="align-right">Jan. 18, 1755. </dateline>
        <p rend="italic space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(1.5)">T</hi>HE courſe of my reading ſome time ago, <lb/>having led me to
          the ſubject of vegeta- <lb/>ble poiſons, and ſeeing ſeveral melancholy <lb/>accounts of
          their fatal effects, I was indu- <lb/>ced, for my own amuſement, to draw up <lb/>ſuch an
          account of the poiſonous plants of <lb/>our own country, as my ſmall collection of
          <lb/>books would permit: If you think it will <lb/>be acceptable to the publick, and a
          proper <lb/>ſubject for your <hi rend="roman">Magazine</hi>, I will endea- <lb/>vour to
          ſend hereafter what I have col- <lb/>lected upon the ſubject, if I ſee the following
          <lb/>in your next. </p>
        <signed rend="align-right">I am, Sir, yours, &amp;c. </signed>
      </div>
      <div>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/>1. <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="dc(1.5)">C</hi>Icuta</hi>. Common <hi rend="italic"
            >Hemlock</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">Kex</hi>. <lb/>The ſeveral ſynonyma by which
          <lb/>this plant is diſtinguiſhed, are as follow. </p>
        <p rend="indent italic">
          <lb/>Cicuta Tragi. Matthioli. Fincheii. Do- <lb/>donæi. Lob. Icon. 732. Ger. 903. Raij
          <lb/>Synop. Pl. Ed. 3d. pag. 215. </p>
        <p rend="indent italic">
          <lb/>Cicuta Major. Cordi Hiſt. C. B. Pin. <lb/>160. Mor. Hiſt. III. 290. Tourn. Inſt.
          <lb/>306. Boerh. Ind. alt. I. p. 56. </p>
        <p rend="indent italic">
          <lb/>Cicuta Vulgaris Major. Park. 933. </p>
        <p rend="indent italic">
          <lb/>— Veteribus et Neotericis. J. B. III. <lb/>2. 275. </p>
        <p rend="indent italic">
          <lb/>Cicuta Serotina caule maculato Hat. Bat. </p>
        <p rend="indent italic">
          <lb/>Conium. Hill. Hiſt. Plant. p. 329. </p>
        <p rend="indent italic">
          <lb/>— Seminibus ſtriatis Linn. Hort. <lb/>Cliff. Royen. Prod. p. 107. Linn. Flor.
          <lb/>Succ. No. 226. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Claſſical Diſtribution. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>This plant, according to Mr <hi rend="italic">Ray</hi>'s <lb/>method of claſſing,
          belongs to the 5th <lb/>diviſion of <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.8)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Umbilliferous herbs are ſuch as have tufts <lb/>of flowers, forming themſelves
              into ſomething <lb/>of a regular ſhape reſembling an umbrella; <lb/>as carrots,
              parſnips, parſley, fennel, angeli- <lb/>ca, &amp;c. </p>
          </note> umbilliferous herbs; that <lb/>is, ſuch as have channelled ſeeds. Ac- <lb/>cording
          to <hi rend="italic">Boerhaave</hi>'s method, it be- <lb/>longs to his <hi rend="italic"
            >Gymnodiſpermæ Umbilliferæ</hi>. <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Linnæan</hi> ſyſtem makes it
          under the <cb n="2"/>
          <lb/>5th diviſion of the <hi rend="italic">Pentandria Digynia</hi>, <lb/>containing all
          ſuch as have two naked <lb/>ſeeds, with an univerſal and a partial <lb/>umbil. It belongs
          to the <hi rend="italic">Umbilliſeræ <lb/>Involucro Duplici</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Van
            Royen</hi>. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Deſcription. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>It is deſcribed by <hi rend="italic">Hill</hi> as follows: The <lb/>root is large,
          oblong, and white, often <lb/>a foot in length, and of the thickneſs <lb/>of a moderate
          parſnip, of a fungous <lb/>ſubſtance, and ſtrong ſmell, but of an <lb/>agreeable taſte.
          The radical leaves are <lb/>very large, a foot and an half long, <lb/>and as much in
          diameter at the baſe: <lb/>They are compoſed of a multitude of <lb/>ſhort ſerrated broad
            <hi rend="italic">Pinnæ</hi>, of a dark <lb/>green, and bad ſmell. The ſtalk is
          <lb/>round, ſmooth, joynted, and branched <lb/>at the top: It grows to an inch in dia-
          <lb/>meter at the baſe, and to five feet high; <lb/>it is uſually variegated in a
          beautiful <lb/>manner with purple ſpots on a dark <lb/>green ground: The leaves upon the
          <lb/>ſtalks ſtand ſingle, and are like the ra- <lb/>dical ones, but ſmaller: The umbels
          <lb/>ſtand on the top of the branches; they <lb/>are very large: The flowers are mo-
          <lb/>derately large, and white. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>There are few people, I imagine, <lb/>who do not know this common plant;
          <lb/>however, to ſuch as are entire ſtrangers <lb/>to it, the moſt ſtriking and obvious
          <lb/>marks, conſidering it as an umbillife- <lb/>rous herb, are, the largeneſs of the
          <lb/>plant, the ſpotted ſtalk, the multitude <lb/>of ſegments, of which the leaves are
          <lb/>compoſed, and its diſagreeable ſmell. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Place. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>It grows plentifully in moſt parts of <lb/><hi rend="italic">England</hi>, near
          villages, in uncultivated <lb/>places, about hedges, ditches, and old <lb/>walls,
          eſpecially in ſhady places, and <lb/>flowers in <hi rend="italic">June</hi> and <hi
            rend="italic">July</hi>. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Obſervations. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>We have as early an account of the <lb/>poiſonous quality of Hemlock, as the
          <lb/>times of <hi rend="italic">Theophraſtus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Dioſcorides</hi>;
          <lb/>and though it be uncertain whether the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Grecian</hi> Hemlock
          was the ſpecies here <lb/>deſcribed, yet it is certain the <hi rend="italic">Greeks</hi>
          had <lb/>a poiſon called <hi rend="italic">Cicuta</hi>, which was in uſe <lb/>at <hi
            rend="italic">Athens</hi> for killing condemned crimi- <lb/>nals. Both <hi rend="italic"
            >Boerhaave</hi>
          <note n="(1)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.8)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(1) <hi rend="italic">Hiſt. Plant. Horti Leyd. Bat. p. 92.</hi>
            </p>
          </note> and <hi rend="italic">Mead</hi>
          <note n="(2)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.8)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(2) Treatiſe on poiſons, edit. 3d. p. 228. </p>
          </note>
          <lb/>ſuppoſe that it was with a preparation <lb/>of this plant, compounded, perhaps,
          <lb/>with other ingredients, that the divine <lb/><hi rend="italic">Socrates</hi> was
          poiſoned. We need not, <lb/>however, recur ſo far back to prove the <lb/>poiſonous effects
          of this plant. <hi rend="italic">Senner- <pb n="30"/>
            <cb n="1"/>
            <lb/>tus</hi>
          <note n="(3)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.8)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(3) <hi rend="italic">Opera omnia Lugd. Edit. 1656. Vol. 2. 1054.</hi>
            </p>
          </note> quotes <hi rend="italic">Tragus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Cardanus</hi>, <hi
            rend="italic">Mat- <lb/>thiolus</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Scaliger</hi>, to prove its
          bad <lb/>effects; and our own countryman, <hi rend="italic">Ge- <lb/>rard</hi>, mentions
          its noxious quality. <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">German</hi> Ephemerides contain ſe-
          <lb/>veral inſtances of its virulent property. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Boerhaave</hi>
          <note n="(4)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.8)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(4) <hi rend="italic">Loco citato</hi>. </p>
          </note> ſays, that only the ſmell <lb/>of the bruiſed herb cauſed ſuch a ver- <lb/>tigo in
          himſelf, that he could ſcarcely <lb/>ſtand; and that they who eat this plant <lb/>not only
          fall into convulſions, but ge- <lb/>nerally die. Elſewhere <note n="(5)" place="bottom"
            rend="size(0.8)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(5) <hi rend="italic">Haller</hi>'s tranſlation of the Inſtitutes. </p>
          </note> he tells us <lb/>of eight children who eat Hemlock; <lb/>they were delirious,
          almoſt ſuffocated <lb/>with a quinſy, vomited, and convulſed <lb/>every one of them. He
          immediately <lb/>gave them <hi rend="italic">Vitriolum Album</hi>, after which <lb/>all
          thoſe who vomited recovered. The <lb/>Philoſophical Tranſactions, No. 473, <lb/>(<hi
            rend="italic">See alſo <hi rend="roman">Gent. Mag.</hi> for <hi rend="roman">May,
              1744</hi></hi>) <lb/>inform us, that ſix <hi rend="italic">Dutch</hi> ſoldiers, quar-
          <lb/>tered at <hi rend="italic">Waltham-Abbey</hi>, gathered ſome <lb/>of this plant among
          other herbs, boiled <lb/>and eat it, two of whom died very ſoon <lb/>after. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It cannot be amiſs to obſerve once <lb/>for all, that in theſe melancholy caſes
          <lb/>the firſt indication of cure is to eject the <lb/>poiſon by vomit, if poſſible: If
          the ef- <lb/>fect of the poiſon itſelf is emetic, it is <lb/>to be promoted by plentiful
          draughts <lb/>of warm milk, with oil of ſweet al- <lb/>monds; which at the ſame time that
          <lb/>they promote the firſt intention of eva- <lb/>cuating the poiſon, tend to anſwer the
          <lb/>ſecond, by ſheathing the Spiculæ, and <lb/>defending the firſt paſſages from the re-
          <lb/>maining acrimony. Afterwards plen- <lb/>tiful dilution with watery and oily
          <lb/>drinks, and if the poiſon has a narcotic <lb/>effect, acidulated liquors will be
          proper. <lb/>If the poiſon is newly taken, and does <lb/>not of itſelf produce vomiting,
          it ſhould <lb/>be effected, if poſſible, by giving about <lb/>half a dram of white
          vitriol, or ſome <lb/>other ſpeedy emetic, and then proceed <lb/>as above. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This method, if the poiſon has not <lb/>reached beyond the <hi rend="italic">Primæ
            Viæ</hi>, or was <lb/>not taken in ſuch an extraordinary <lb/>quantity as to bring on
          immediate death, <lb/>has frequently ſaved the patient; but <lb/>when the poiſon has
          ſpread itſelf thro' <lb/>the whole habit, its effects are various, <lb/>and often very
          ſurpriſing, according to <lb/>the nature of the poiſon, and the par- <lb/>ticular viſcus
          which is moſt injured, and <lb/>in this caſe requires the moſt ſkilful <lb/>treatment.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
