<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - B.J.: Dr Pinard's Account of the Epidemic Disease</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>B.J. </persName>
            </author>
            <title>Dr Pinard's Account of the Epidemic Disease which raged at Rouen in 1753.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for D. Henry, and R. Cave, at St John's Gate.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1755</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">25</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">462</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1755_GM_0462">
    <body>
      <pb n="462"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <div>
        <floatingText rend="italic">
          <body>
          <salute rend="indent">
            <lb/>Mr <hi rend="sc">Urban</hi>, </salute>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(1.5)">A</hi>S your uſeful Magazine is become the proper
            <lb/>repoſitory for every thing that tends to enlarge <lb/>ſcience, or preſerve health,
            I would recommend <lb/>particularly to your notice the deſcription lately <lb/>publiſhed
            in <hi rend="roman">France</hi> by Dr <hi rend="roman">Pinard</hi>, of the epi-
            <lb/>demic diſeaſe which raged at <hi rend="roman">Rouen</hi> in <hi rend="roman"
              >Norman- <lb/>dy</hi> during the months of <hi rend="roman">November</hi> and <hi
              rend="roman">Decem- <lb/>ber</hi> 1753, and which alarmed all <hi rend="roman"
              >Europe</hi>. In <lb/><hi rend="roman">England</hi> the current report was <hi
              rend="roman">(ſee Vol. xxiv. <lb/>p. 44.)</hi> that it ſwept away thouſands, and that
            <lb/>the contagion was ſo violent as to putrify the meat <lb/>in the butchers ſhops,
            which news ſo affected the <lb/>miniſtry, that orders were on the point of being
            <lb/>iſſued out for prohibiting all commerce with <hi rend="roman">Rouen</hi>, <lb/>had
            not a certificate from the <hi rend="roman">Engliſh</hi> ambaſſador <lb/>at <hi
              rend="roman">Paris</hi> been obtained, in order to ſet the matter <lb/>in a true
            light. So accurate a deſcription, there- <lb/>fore, of the riſe, progreſs, and means
            made uſe of <lb/>for the cure of this diſtemper, muſt be of infinite <lb/>advantage to
            poſterity; for as Dr <hi rend="roman">Pinard</hi> has <lb/>obſerved, there is but one
            diſeaſe in the whole hiſ- <lb/>tory of epidemics that had the leaſt reſemblance <lb/>to
            this at <hi rend="roman">Rouen</hi>, for which reaſon he has traced <lb/>it thro' all
            its ſtages with the utmoſt nicety and <lb/>preciſion. </p>
          <signed rend="align-center">
            <lb/>I am, Sir, yours, &amp;c. <hi rend="roman align-right">B. J. </hi>
          </signed></body>
        </floatingText>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>[<hi rend="italic">In compliance with our kind correſpondent's <lb/>hint, we have
            extracted from Dr <hi rend="roman">Pinard's</hi> curious <lb/>letter all that relates to
            the cauſe, deſcription, and <lb/>cure of this diſtemper; but we muſt refer our me-
            <lb/>dical readers to the original for his judicious re- <lb/>flections and reaſoning
            upon ſo intereſting a ſubject.</hi>] </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Dr <hi rend="roman">Pinard</hi>'s Account of the Epidemic Diſ- <lb/>eaſe which raged
          at <hi rend="roman">Rouen</hi> in 1753. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>He continual northerly winds of the <lb/>year 1752 occaſioned
          a long and dry <lb/>winter. The enſuing <hi rend="italic">March</hi> was mild and
          <lb/>rainy, but in <hi rend="italic">April</hi> the wind fixed again in <lb/>the northern
          quarter, and made the ground <lb/>ſo hard, that the hopes of a plentiful harveſt
          <lb/>which <hi rend="italic">March</hi> ſeemed to promiſe were then <lb/>much abated. <hi
            rend="italic">May</hi> brought on great heats, <lb/>which continued all <hi
            rend="italic">June</hi>, <hi rend="italic">July</hi>, and the be- <lb/>ginning of <hi
            rend="italic">Auguſt</hi>, during which ſpace there <lb/>were for the moſt part
          ſoutherly winds, with <lb/>very little rain. It is remarkable however, that <lb/>on <hi
            rend="italic">June</hi> 23 the thermom. was ſomething below <lb/>the freezing point, and
          the cold ſo ſharp, that <lb/>the plants were frozen on our hot beds, and ma- <lb/>ny
          ſheep, which had been lately ſhorn, died in <lb/>the meadows. But ſuddenly again the heat
          <lb/>and drought was ſo conſiderable, that the <lb/>herdſmen were obliged to fetch water
          for their <lb/>cattle from the rivers. The corn ripened ſo <lb/>faſt<choice>
            <corr>,</corr>
            <sic>.</sic>
          </choice> as to be cut a month before the uſual <lb/>time; and the vine-dreſſer had the
          ſatisfac- <lb/>tion of filling his caſks by the 20th of <hi rend="italic">Sep- <pb n="463"/>
            <cb n="1"/>
            <lb/>tember</hi>. The autumn proved ſo dry as to laſt <lb/>till <hi rend="italic"
            >November</hi>, but then inceſſant rains came <lb/>on, except ſeven or eight days of
          hard froſt. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A thick fog aroſe the 21ſt of this month, <lb/>in the morning, of a very ſtinking,
          ſulphu- <lb/>reous ſmell, which increaſed to that degree in <lb/>the evening, that the
          lights could not be diſ- <lb/>cerned in the ſtreets. I am apt to think it <lb/>was much
          thicker in ſome places than in o- <lb/>thers, and that though it might be over a-
          <lb/>bout eight o'clock in ſome ſtreets, yet in <lb/>many it laſted all night, for I could
          diſcern <lb/>nothing of it in the <hi rend="italic">Rue aux Ours</hi>, but when <lb/>I was
          got into that of <hi rend="italic">Fordeau</hi>, not far from <lb/>the other, I found
          myſelf ſurrounded with it <lb/>again. I ground my firſt conjectures on the <lb/>ſingular
          diſtribution of the diſeaſe in the city. <lb/>It ſeized only the weſtern half, in which
          two <lb/>ſeveral pariſhes were almoſt exempt from it. <lb/>Moreover it was remarked, that
          in the eaſtern <lb/>ſide, where the three largeſt and moſt popu- <lb/>lous pariſhes are,
          they were at this time unu- <lb/>ſually healthy. Three or four days after this <lb/>fog
          our epidemic diſeaſe made its firſt ap- <lb/>pearance, and advanced ſo rapidly as to
          threa- <lb/>ten a great mortality; but, as before obſerv'd, <lb/>its tyranny ended with
          that year, few having <lb/>felt any of its effects ſince. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Young perſons of both ſexes were in a <lb/>manner the ſole objects of its rage, who
          for <lb/>five, ſix, ſeven, or eight days together, com- <lb/>plained of laſſitudes, ſlight
          pains in the arms <lb/>and legs, and of a head-ach which increaſed <lb/>daily. They had
          almoſt continual ſhiverings, <lb/>with ſome loſs of appetite. Theſe ſymptoms,
          <lb/>however, did not at firſt reſtrain them from <lb/>following their affairs; but they
          were ſoon <lb/>confin'd to their beds, where they were for <lb/>the moſt part ſeized with
          a bilious or ſerous <lb/>looſeneſs, often accompanied with nauſea's <lb/>and vomitings.
          Moſt of them bled frequent- <lb/>ly at the noſe, but in a ſmall quantity. The
          <lb/>head-ach became violent, with a hard ſmall <lb/>pulſe. The fever, which was ſlight at
          firſt, <lb/>became violent, eſpecially if the veſſels had <lb/>been emptied. The blood
          which had been <lb/>taken away appeared deſtitute of ſerum, and <lb/>of a gelatinous
          conſiſtence. The region of <lb/>the ſtomach and hypochondria was tumified, <lb/>and in two
          days a conſiderable tenſion of the <lb/>belly ſucceeded; but the patients felt little
          <lb/>or no pain when handled. This tenſion was <lb/>conſtantly followed by ſome degree of
          a de- <lb/>lirium, which was only ſymptomatic. The <lb/>tongue was often brown or black,
          but moiſt, <lb/>tho' ſometimes beſet with little green ulcers, <lb/>or <hi rend="italic"
            >apthæ</hi>, ſome of which I have alſo ſeen <lb/>on the lips: In the progreſs of the
          diſeaſe <lb/>many had a puffineſs of the face, hands, and <lb/>legs. Few perfectly
          recovered in leſs than <lb/>30 or 40 days. When the tenſion of the <lb/>belly did not
          yield to remedies, the delirium <lb/>increaſed, the breaſt became greatly oppreſſed,
          <lb/>and the patients died on the fifth, ſeventh, <lb/>or 11th day after taking their
          beds. Howe- <lb/>ver all were not carried off in ſo ſhort a time; <lb/>ſeveral held out
          till the 17th or 21ſt day, if <lb/>the inflammation of the lower belly did not <lb/>come
          on before the 10th or 12th day of the <lb/>fever; ſome of theſe had ſlight miliary e-
          <lb/>ruptions, which were only ſymptomatic. </p>
        <cb n="2"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Opening the dead bodies plainly indicated <lb/>the ſeat of the diſorder, and the true
          cauſe <lb/>of death. In every one the ſtomach was of <lb/>a reddiſh brown complexion,
          livid, and be- <lb/>ſprinkled with ulcers of the ſize of large len- <lb/>til ſeeds. The
          inteſtinal canal was mortified <lb/>in different places, and its villous membrane
          <lb/>looked as if it had been boiled, with ulcers <lb/>here and there, like thoſe of the
          ſtomach. <lb/>Several had a tumifaction of the meſenteric <lb/>glands. The membranes and
          ſubſtance of <lb/>the brain afforded nothing remarkable, even <lb/>in thoſe that had been
          moſt delirious. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The diſeaſe I have been deſcribing was not <lb/>the only one we had to deal with; the
          mil- <lb/>liary fever, of which we have always had <lb/>more or leſs for 30 years paſt,
          was obſerved <lb/>to be more frequent and dangerous at this <lb/>time than for ſeveral
          years before. The <lb/>chief part of thoſe who were attacked with <lb/>it ſweated much
          leſs than uſual; the eruption <lb/>of the puſtles, which ordinarily happens not
          <lb/>before the 11th, 14th, or 17th day, was al- <lb/>moſt in all on the 5th, 6th, or 7th,
          and <lb/>ſometimes ſooner, and quickly after the e- <lb/>ruption, the ſkin grew burning
          and dry, which <lb/>brought on an inquietude, that ſoon termi- <lb/>nated in death, and
          that moſtly without any <lb/>of the common previous ſymptoms, ſuch as <lb/>head-achs,
          deliriums, coma's, twitchings of <lb/>the tendons, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The ſymptoms of this epidemic diſeaſe are <lb/>ſtrong characteriſtics of a putrid
          fever, where- <lb/>in the corroſive ſulphurous particles which <lb/>occaſioned it,
          directed their action principally <lb/>upon the glands of the ſtomach and inteſtines,
          <lb/>exciting inflammations there, whereof the <lb/>tenſion of the belly, <hi
            rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> were neceſſary con- <lb/>ſequences. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The curative indications which preſented <lb/>themſelves were all carefully purſued
          in the <lb/>beginning, but without the expected ſucceſs, <lb/>and we may ſay, with the
          great <hi rend="italic">Sydenham</hi>, <lb/>who ſpent moſt of his days in ſtrictly obſerv-
          <lb/>ing the nature of epidemics, that <hi rend="italic">notwith- <lb/>ſtanding the moſt
            prudent precautions, the firſt pa- <lb/>tients which fall under our care in epidemic
            diſ- <lb/>orders will be in a dangerous ſituation, till by <lb/>cloſe reflection we are
            able to diſcover the true <lb/>nature and genius of the diſtemper</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Our college met twice whilſt this rife diſ- <lb/>eaſe was making its havock; every
          one <lb/>gave an account of his particular practice and <lb/>the reſult thereof, without
          the leaſt reſerve. <lb/>Upon conſidering duly the evacuation which <lb/>nature ſeemed to
          indicate by ſtool, and the <lb/>ſmall degree of pain about the region of the <lb/>belly,
          it was determined amongſt us to pro- <lb/>ceed in the following manner. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>As ſoon as we were called in, we ordered <lb/>bleeding once or twice in the arm,
          according <lb/>to the violence of the ſymptoms, and the <lb/>fullneſs of the veſſels. When
          the patients <lb/>complained of nauſea's it was thought ne- <lb/>ceſſary to examine if
          there were a tenſion of <lb/>the ſtomach and hypochondries. If theſe <lb/>were found in
          their natural ſtate, we preſcribed <lb/><hi rend="italic">Tartárum Stibiatum</hi> in a
          draught, which ge- <lb/>nerally procured large evacuations, and abated <lb/>the fever; but
          if, on the other hand, the fe- <pb n="464"/>
          <cb n="1"/>
          <lb/>ver increaſed, bleeding in the arm was again <lb/>repeated, and ordered alſo in the
          foot when <lb/>the head-ach was violent, as likewiſe when <lb/>the hæmorrhage at the noſe
          was frequent, <lb/>without a remiſſion of the ſymptoms. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>When the belly was much inflated and <lb/>hard, the more abundant the evacuations by
          <lb/>ſtool were, the more the tenſion was taken <lb/>off, the fever abated, and the ſkin
          freed from <lb/>its burning heat. If the patient continued <lb/>not lax the next day, it
          was neceſſary to <lb/>throw in clyſters of <hi rend="italic">mel violatum</hi> diſſolved
          in <lb/>whey or ſome emollient decoction; notwith- <lb/>ſtanding which precaution the
          tenſion would <lb/>very frequently return, if purgatives were <lb/>not repeated every two
          or three days. That <lb/>which I adminiſtered moſt ſucceſsfully was <lb/>an ounce of pulp
          of caſſia diluted in a pint <lb/>of whey, wherein two drams of ſome vege- <lb/>table ſalt
          had been diſſolved; this doſe was <lb/>divided into five draughts, to be taken every
          <lb/>half hour. If ſufficient evacuations were not <lb/>procured this way, two grains of
          ſtibiated <lb/>tartar were added: Sometimes the <hi rend="italic">Kermes
              <lb/><unclear>mineral</unclear></hi> given in a ſmall doze, in draughts <lb/>made of
          the diſtilled water of <hi rend="italic">Oxytriphyllum</hi>, <lb/>ſyrup of peach flowers,
          and oil of almonds, <lb/>anſwered well, eſpecially if care was taken <lb/>not to order it
          but when the heat was mode- <lb/>rate, and the pulſe not hard. When it was
          <lb/>apprehended that this medicine might prove <lb/>too harſh, ſyrup of <hi rend="italic"
            >diacodium</hi> was added, which <lb/>wrought the deſired effect, by relaxing the
          <lb/>nervous fibres of the ſtomach and guts. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Whey and fomentations were not omitted <lb/>in this method, both being of uſe, as it
          was <lb/>eſſentially neceſſary to ſouple the ſolids, which <lb/>purgatives are often apt
          to irritate. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>By theſe helps, prudently adminiſtered, <lb/>and varied according to the different
          circum- <lb/>ſtances deduced from the degree of the ſymp- <lb/>toms, and the age and
          temper of the patients, <lb/>we had the ſatisfaction of recovering a very
          <lb/>conſiderable number. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
