<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: On the Neglect of the Operation for the Bubonocele*
          Incarcerata</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>On the Neglect of the Operation for the Bubonocele* Incarcerata.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for D. Henry, and R. Cave, at St John's Gate.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1755</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">25</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">204</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1755_GM_0204">
    <body>
      <pb n="204"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <head rend="italic align-center">
        <lb/>On the Neglect of the Operation for the <lb/><hi rend="roman">Bubonocele <note n="*"
            place="bottom" rend="size(0.8) align-left">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* A Bubonocele is a tumour of the groin, <lb/>from a deſcent of the inteſtines or
              caul thro' the <lb/>annular aperture of the epigaſtric muſcles. </p>
          </note> Incarcerata</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">W</hi>HEN I conſider the frequent <lb/>failure of other means in this
        <lb/>too fatal diſorder, and the almoſt total <lb/>neglect of ſo rational an operation, it
        is <lb/>to me, I confeſs, a matter of ſurprize <lb/>and concern. It is true, the ill ſucceſs
        <lb/>which has ſometimes attended it has <lb/>led ſome of our <hi rend="italic">Engliſh</hi>
        chirurgical wri- <lb/>ters into enquiries after new methods, <pb n="205"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>but then theſe were propoſed to take <lb/>place in due time, before the impend-
        <lb/>ing neceſſity of the operation, as the <lb/>laſt reſource; practice, however, has by
        <lb/>no means warranted the ſufficiency of <lb/>any of them, but, on the contrary, has
        <lb/>ſhewn, in numerous inſtances, that they <lb/>have ſerved only to render the patient's
        <lb/>caſe deſperate, by protracting time till <lb/>even all hopes of ſucceſs from the ope-
        <lb/>ration itſelf were cut off. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the confined bubonocele there is <lb/>an obſtinate ſtricture of the abdominal
        <lb/>ring, or rather of the neck of the her- <lb/>nial ſack, wherein there are not want-
        <lb/>ing the marks of a true inflammation; <lb/>but the prolaps'd inteſtine is violently
        <lb/>inflamed by the compreſſing ſtricture, <lb/>and its coats thickened and tumefied,
        <lb/>a ſmall portion of blood paſſing for- <lb/>ward by arteries, but none returning <lb/>by
        the veins; ſo that the obſtruction is <lb/>every moment increaſed and extended <lb/>to the
        neighbouring parts. In caſes <lb/>thus circumſtanced, if the ſtricture can- <lb/>not be
        taken off, it is much to be <lb/>dreaded, that every attempt but the <lb/>operation itſelf
        will be in vain. All <lb/>other milder methods, if practicable <lb/>without much loſs of
        time, ought firſt <lb/>to be tried. Bleeding largely, or even <lb/><hi rend="italic">ad
          deliquium animi</hi>, glyſters, warm ba- <lb/>thin, <hi rend="italic">Heiſter</hi>'s <hi
          rend="italic">Clyſma fumoſum</hi>, ſuſpend- <lb/>ing the patient by the heels, and then
        <lb/>endeavouring to return the inteſtine, <lb/>may, ſome of them, poſſibly ſucceed.
        <lb/>But then theſe, in moſt caſes, muſt not <lb/>be tried beyond 36 hours at the moſt.
        <lb/>In ſome, indeed, the ſymptoms may <lb/>admit of a longer delay; but the <lb/>means
        proving ineffectual, the operation <lb/>ought to take place to prevent a gan- <lb/>grene. I
        would, with the honeſt and <lb/>judicious <hi rend="italic">Wiſeman</hi>, aſk our country
        ſur- <lb/>geons, if in ſuch a caſe it be not more <lb/>reaſonable to propoſe in conſultation
        <lb/>the laying open the production, than to <lb/>ſuffer the patient to periſh inevitably
        <lb/>under his miſerable complaint? What <lb/>can be expected from purgatives? can <lb/>any
        good enſue from ſtimulating the <lb/>guts, already inflamed beyond meaſure? <lb/>If calomel
        has been found efficaceous <lb/>in many obſtructions of the guts, muſt <lb/>it not yet be
        deadly in this particular <lb/>one? If puncturing the tumefied in- <lb/>teſtine be thought
        on this cannot re- <lb/>lax the ſtricture, and probably may <lb/>haſten the gangrene. If
        ſnow or cold <lb/>water can take place, it muſt be howe- <lb/>ver in the beginning, and
        after large <lb/>bleeding, elſe a mortification may be <lb/>expected inſtead of relief. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is objected to the operation, that it <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>ſeldom ſucceeds, and this cannot be de- <lb/>nied if we appeal to the reſult of hoſpi-
        <lb/>tal practice; but it ought to be conſi- <lb/>dered, that there it is performed for
        <lb/>the moſt part, under diſadvantageous <lb/>circumſtances, often late, and after paſ-
        <lb/>ſing through the hands of country ſur- <lb/>geons, among whom, notwithſtanding, <lb/>it
        has been often remembered to have a <lb/>happy iſſue. It would be therefore <lb/>highly
        laudable to inquire how it ever <lb/>comes about to be ſucceſsful; for this <lb/>might
        probably lead to diſcover why it <lb/>often is not ſo, and point out the way <lb/>of
        avoiding danger. Above all things, <lb/>the habit and conſtitution of the pa- <lb/>tient
        ſhould be carefully conſidered. <lb/>We ſee that in well-conditioned ſub- <lb/>jects, wounds
        of the bladder, a part al- <lb/>moſt entirely membraneous, digeſt with- <lb/>out much
        inflammation; why may not <lb/>thoſe of the abdominal ring and perito- <lb/>næum do ſo too?
        Mending the quality <lb/>of an inflamed ſizy blood by leſſening its <lb/>quantity before the
        operation, recruit- <lb/>ing the perſon with demulcent food, and <lb/>proceeding to the
        operation in time, <lb/>ſeem to promiſe faireſt for a good di- <lb/>geſtion of the wound. On
        the contra- <lb/>ry, purgations and punctures of the in- <lb/>teſtines muſt ſurely be bad
        preparatives <lb/>for the operation. And let it be re- <lb/>membered, that if it be deferred
        till a <lb/>gangrene comes on, ſphacelous mem- <lb/>branes ſeparate very difficultly, though
        <lb/>ſometimes, indeed, ſurprizing ſepara- <lb/>tions of the mortified <choice>
          <corr>inteſtines</corr>
          <sic>inteltines</sic>
        </choice> and o- <lb/>mentum have happened <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.8)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* The collection of ſuch caſes is now be- <lb/>come pretty large: See <hi
              rend="italic">Le Dran</hi>'s obſervations, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Cheſelden</hi>, and
            all the writers of note. </p>
        </note> after this ope- <lb/>ration; an argument of an uncommon <lb/>power in nature. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Country ſurgeons have frequent and <lb/>preſſing opportunities of exerting their
        <lb/>ſkill to advantage in this important <lb/>caſe, as having the patient under their
        <lb/>own proper management from the be- <lb/>ginning. Is the operation in itſelf ſo
        <lb/>very difficult? by no means, if due <lb/>care be conjoined with a right know-
        <lb/>ledge of the anatomy of the parts con- <lb/>cerned. Is it more ſevere than that of
        <lb/>cutting for the ſtone? No, nor perhaps <lb/>one half ſo painful; and yet how fre-
        <lb/>quently is that practiſed with ſucceſs; <lb/>nay, how ſeldom does it
          fail<unclear>!</unclear> In a <lb/>word, when life is at ſtake, the ſurgeon <lb/>loſes no
        reputation if his honeſt and <lb/>well-meant efforts ſhould not anſwer <lb/>his wiſh: he is
        conſcious that he acts a <lb/>human and a chriſtian part, and this <lb/>ſhould make him eaſy
        at all events. </p>
      <signed rend="sc align-right">
        <lb/>P— n. </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
