<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Account of English poisonous Plants</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Account of English poisonous Plants, continued from p. 272</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for D. Henry, and R. Cave, at St John's Gate.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1755</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">25</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">308</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1755_GM_0308">
    <body>
      <pb n="308"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <head rend="italic align-center">
        <lb/>Account of <hi rend="roman">Engliſh</hi> poiſonous Plants, con- <lb/>tinued from <hi
          rend="roman">p. 272.</hi>
      </head>
      <head rend="hanging space">
        <lb/>VII. <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="dc(1.5)">H</hi>Yoſcyamus niger</hi>, Common or
        <lb/>black Henbane. </head>
      <div rend="italic">
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>Synonyma. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Hyoſcyamus niger, Dod. Lob. Ger. 283, <lb/>Park. 362. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>— flavus Fuſch. icon. 480. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>— vulgaris vel niger, C. B. pin. <lb/>169. Boerh. Lugd. Bat. 1. p. 229. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>— vulgoris J. B. 3. 627. Ray's <lb/>Syn. Ed. 3d. p. 274. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>—foliis amplexicaulibus. Lin. Hort. <lb/>clif. 36. Flor. Suec. No. 184. Mat. Med.
          <lb/>No. 86. Royen. Flor. Lugd. 422. Hill. Hiſt. <lb/>pl. 286. Linn. Spec. pl. p. 179.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>Claſſical Diſtribution. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This belongs to the firſt order of the <lb/>18th claſs, according to Mr <hi
            rend="italic">Ray</hi>'s me- <lb/>thod, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> ſuch plants as have
          a regu- <lb/>lar monopetalous flower, ſucceeded by <lb/>one ſingle dry ſeed-veſſel.—To the
            <hi rend="italic">Plan- <lb/>tæ diangiæ polyſpermæ</hi> of <hi rend="italic"
            >Boerhaave</hi>.— <lb/>To the ſame claſs and order as the laſt <lb/>deſcribed plant,
          according to the ſyſ- <lb/>tems of <hi rend="italic">Van Royen</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
            >Linnæus</hi>. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>Deſcription. </head>
        <p>
          <lb/>The root is a foot long, half an inch in <lb/>diameter, white within, but brown on
          <lb/>the ſurface, being hard, woody, divi- <lb/>ded into ſeveral branches, and of very
          <lb/>little ſmell. The radical leaves are a <lb/>foot long and five inches broad, deeply
          <lb/>ſinuated at the edges, pointed at the <lb/>extremity, of a bluiſh green colour,
          <lb/>ſomewhat hoary, of an unctuous clam- <lb/>myneſs to the touch, and of a very diſ-
          <lb/>agreeable ſmell. The ſtalk is thick and <lb/>ſtrong, round, hard and woody, half an
          <lb/>inch in diameter, and grows to two feet <lb/>high, or more, dividing towards the
          <lb/>top into ſeveral branches; the leaves <lb/>are large and like thoſe at the root;
          <lb/>they ſtand alternately. The flowers are <lb/>half an inch in diameter, and more in
          <lb/>length, of a duſky browniſh colour, <lb/>with a deep purple baſe, and a multi-
          <lb/>tude of purple lines all over them. <lb/>The cup of the flower is hairy and the
          <lb/>capſula large, containing a great num- <lb/>ber of ſeeds. The flowers are very nu-
          <lb/>merous, and ſtand in long ſeries on the <lb/>upper ſides of the branches. <hi
            rend="italic">Hill.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This is the only ſpecies of Henbane <pb n="309"/>
          <cb n="1"/>
          <lb/>growing ſpontaneouſly in <hi rend="italic">England</hi>, and <lb/>it grows likewiſe
          in moſt parts of <hi rend="italic">Europe</hi>. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>Place. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It is a biennial plant, and is very <lb/>common in uncultivated places, eſpeci-
          <lb/>ally about dunghills, by the road ſides, <lb/>and on the banks of ditches, flowering
          <lb/>in <hi rend="italic">May</hi> and <hi rend="italic">June</hi>. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>Obſervations. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The deſtructive faculty of this plant <lb/>has been ſo long known, that it ſeems
          <lb/>to have derived both its <hi rend="italic">Greek</hi> and <hi rend="italic">En-
            <lb/>gliſh</hi> name from its pernicious effects. <lb/>Our <hi rend="italic"
            >Engliſh</hi> name Henbane <hi rend="italic">(the bane of <lb/>hens)</hi> is very
          evidently derived from <lb/>the obſervation of its effects, perhaps of <lb/>the ſeeds,
          upon <note n="(1)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.8)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(1) Aves qui hujus herbæ ſemen ederint, <lb/>præcipue quæ in gallinaceo habentur
              genere, <lb/>non multo poſt tempore pereunt, quemadmo- <lb/>dum et piſces. Matthiol.
              in Dioſcorid. p. 751. </p>
          </note> hens, and other <lb/>fowls. The <hi rend="italic">Greek</hi> word comes from
            <lb/><unclear>ΰς</unclear>
          <hi rend="italic">ſus</hi>, and κύαμος <hi rend="italic">faba, quaſi faba ſuilla</hi>,
          <lb/>becauſe in this animal its deleterious <lb/>quality was firſt diſcovered. <hi
            rend="italic">Ælian</hi>, in <lb/>his hiſtory of animals, declaring that <lb/>the wild
          boars by eating it were ſeized <lb/>with convulſions and other violent <lb/>ſymptoms.
            <note n="(2)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.8)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(2) Matthiol. loco citato. Ray in Etymo- <lb/>log. nominum ad calcem catalog.
              plant. Can- <lb/>tab. p. 59. </p>
          </note>
          <hi rend="italic">Dioſcorides</hi>, who enu- <lb/>merates three ſpecies of Henbane <note
            n="(3)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.8)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(3) Dioſcorid. lib. 4. cap. 64. where after <lb/>mentioning the black and yellow
              henbane, <lb/>he adds, <q rend="diple quotes">Ambo inſanium gignunt, et ſopo-
                <lb/>rem, ideo in communi uſu damnantur. </q>
              <lb/>Elſewhere alſo he ſays, <q rend="diple quotes">Hyoſcyamum po- <lb/>tum, aut
                comeſum, ſimilem ebriis abaliena- <lb/>tionem movet, ſed facile medicamentis ce-
                <lb/>dit. lib. 6. cap. 15. </q> The white henbane, <lb/>notwithſtanding Dioſcorides
              calls it mitiſſimum <lb/>genus, and Pliny ſays of it <q rend="diple quotes">hoc
                recepere <lb/>medici </q> was known alſo to partake of the <lb/>nature of the black,
                <q rend="diple quotes">Cocta olerum modo <lb/>folia ſi acetabuli menſura manduntur
                medi- <lb/>ocrem inſaniam gignunt. </q> Dioſcorid. lib. 4. <lb/>cap. 64. </p>
          </note>
          <lb/>was acquainted with its narcotic and <lb/>dangerous quality, and condemns the
          <lb/>uſe of it. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The ſame obſervation of its effects <lb/>we find in <hi rend="italic">Pliny</hi>
          likewiſe. <note n="(4)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.8)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(4) Pliny enumerates four ſpecies of Hen- <lb/>bane; after having mentioned three
              kinds, <lb/>among which the black is one, he adds <q rend="diple quotes">Om- <lb/>nia
                inſaniam gignentia, capitiſque vertigi- <lb/>nes. </q> Then he mentions a fourth,
              which <lb/>is the white henbane, and which he ſays is <lb/>uſed in phyſic. Hiſt. Nat.
              lib. 25. cap. 4. </p>
          </note> Later in- <lb/>ſtances and more accurate obſervations <lb/>have fully confirmed
          their opinion and <lb/>proved even its deadly quality. <hi rend="italic">Mat-
            <lb/>thiolus</hi> affirms that he was witneſs him- <lb/>ſelf to the effects of the ſeeds
          eaten by <cb n="2"/>
          <lb/>ſome children, <note n="(5)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.8)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(5) Viderim in Amaniæ vallis montibus <lb/>pueros qui Hyoſcyami ſemen comederant
              adeo <lb/>deſipientes factos, ut parentes et vicini eos <lb/>crederent a cacodæmonibus
              vexatos eſſe. Com- <lb/>ment. in Dioſcorid. p. 751. </p>
          </note> who were ſo depra- <lb/>ved in their ſenſes, that their parents <lb/>and
          neighbours (agreeable to the ſu- <lb/>perſtitious foibles of the times) believ'd <lb/>they
          were bewitch'd. <hi rend="italic">Parkinſon</hi>, <note n="(6)" place="bottom"
            rend="size(0.8)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(6) Theatr. Botan. p. 364. </p>
          </note>
          <lb/>mentions the caſe of a friend of his <lb/>who having eaten of the roots of Hen-
          <lb/>bane, which unwarily were boiled with <lb/>ſome parſnips for ſupper, was very
          <lb/>ſhortly after taken with a moſt intolle- <lb/>rable thirſt, a total ſtoppage of his
          u- <lb/>rine, and vertiginous ſymptoms in his <lb/>head, affecting his ſight very much.
          <lb/>We find in <hi rend="italic">Wepfer</hi> alſo <note n="(7)" place="bottom"
            rend="size(0.8)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(7) Wepfer cicutæ aquaticæ hiſtoria et <lb/>noxæ, cap. 18. </p>
          </note> a relation <lb/>of a whole company at an evening en- <lb/>tertainment being thrown
          into a varie- <lb/>ty of convulſive ſymptoms by eating, <lb/>though but ſparingly, of the
          roots of <lb/>Henbane, which by miſtake were boiled <lb/>with the roots of ſuccory.
          Another <lb/>inſtance of its pernicious effects Mr <lb/><hi rend="italic">Miller</hi>
          gives us as follows: <note n="(8)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.8)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(8) See the Gardener's dictionary, under the <lb/>word Hyoſcyamus. </p>
          </note>
          <q rend="diple quotes">In the <lb/>year 1729 there were three children <lb/>poiſoned with
            eating the ſeeds of this <lb/>plant, near <hi rend="italic">Tottenham</hi> court; two of
            <lb/>which ſlept two days and two nights <lb/>before they could be awakened, and
            <lb/>were with difficulty recovered; but <lb/>the third being older and ſtronger,
            <lb/>eſcaped better. </q>
          <hi rend="italic">Geoffroy</hi> alſo <note n="(9)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.8)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(9) Tractat. de mat. med. vol. 3d. Ed. <lb/>1741. p. 598-601. </p>
          </note>
          <lb/>when treating upon this plant, produces <lb/>ſeveral inſtances from the <hi
            rend="italic">German Ephe- <lb/>merides Naturæ Curioſorum</hi>, of its narco- <lb/>tic
          and dangerous quality. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The philoſophical tranſactions No. <lb/>451, article 8. contain an extract of a
          <lb/>letter from Dr <hi rend="italic">Patouillat</hi>, phyſician at <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Toucy</hi> in <hi rend="italic">France</hi>, to M. <hi rend="italic">Geoffroy</hi>, F.
          R. S. <lb/>and of the royal academy at <hi rend="italic">Paris</hi>, gi- <lb/>ving an
          account of nine perſons, who <lb/>upon eating the roots of Henbane, <lb/>which were
          miſtaken for parſnips, were <lb/>all ſeized with the ſymptoms of being <lb/>poiſoned, with
          this difference however, <lb/>that ſome were ſpeechleſs, and ſhewed <lb/>no other ſigns of
          life than by convul- <lb/>ſions, contortions of the limbs, and the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >riſus Sardonicus</hi>, all having their eyes <lb/>ſtarting out of their heads, and
          their <lb/>mouths drawn backwards on both <lb/>ſides. Others had all the ſymptoms
          <lb/>alike. Proper care being taken of <pb n="310"/>
          <cb n="1"/>
          <lb/>them by giving them vomits, theriaca, <lb/>and ſalt of rue in warm milk, they were
          <lb/>all recovered in a few days. Dr <hi rend="italic">Patou- <lb/>illat</hi> has not
          ſpecified whether theſe ef- <lb/>fects were owing to the black or white <lb/>henbane,
          though whichever kind it was <lb/>is not material, as the white partakes, <lb/>tho' in a
          leſs degree, of the ſame nox- <lb/>ious quality. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Another and a later inſtance of the <lb/>bad conſequences attending the eating
          <lb/>of the leaves of this plant, we find in <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Philoſophical
            Tranſactions</hi> likewiſe, <lb/>in a letter from Dr <hi rend="italic">Stedman</hi> at
            <hi rend="italic">Edin- <lb/>burgh</hi>, to Dr <hi rend="italic">Pringle</hi>, giving an
          account <lb/>of five men and two women, belonging <lb/>to the Grey's who were then
          cantoned <lb/>at the village of <hi rend="italic">Vucht</hi> near <hi rend="italic"
            >Boiſleduc</hi> in <lb/><hi rend="italic">Dutch Brabant</hi>. From the neareſt con-
          <lb/>jecture there were from fifteen to twenty <lb/>leaves boiled in about ten quarts of
          <lb/>water, and tho' they did not eat one <lb/>half, the poiſon diſcovered itſelf in ſome
          <lb/>of them in half an hour; they were all <lb/>ſeized with a giddineſs and ſtupor as
          <lb/>if drunk. Three of the men were be- <lb/>come quite inſenſible in three hours af-
          <lb/>ter taking it, talked incoherently, and <lb/>were in as high a delirium as people in
          <lb/>the rage of a fever. By proper care in <lb/>vomiting them, and giving warm water
          <lb/>and oil, they were all ſaved, tho' ſome <lb/>of them complained of feebleneſs,
          <lb/>weight at their ſtomachs, others gripes, <lb/>ſtitches, and head-achs, and all of
          them <lb/>were vertiginous at times for near a <lb/>month after the accident. Dr <hi
            rend="italic">Stedman</hi>
          <lb/>had attributed theſe effects to the white <lb/>henbane, but Mr <hi rend="italic"
            >Watſon</hi>, in his remarks <lb/>upon the account, when read before <lb/>the royal
          ſociety, obſerved that it muſt <lb/>be the black ſort, not only from Dr <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Stedman</hi>'s own deſcription of the plant, <lb/>but from the place in
          which it grew, as <lb/>the white is not found naturally wild <lb/>in ſo northern a
          latitude as <hi rend="italic">Dutch Bra- <lb/>bant</hi>. <note n="(10)" place="bottom"
            rend="size(0.8)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(10) Vol. 47. article 27. </p>
          </note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The leaves and roots both of the <lb/>black and white henbane have hereto- <lb/>fore
          been uſed in the ſhops, and ſtand <lb/>recommended by many authors as uſe- <lb/>ful in
          inflammatory ſwellings, and in <lb/>eaſing the pains of the gout externally <lb/>uſed. For
          theſe intentions the white is <lb/>recommended by <hi rend="italic">Dioſcorides</hi>
          himſelf, <lb/>
          <note n="(11)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.8)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(11) <q rend="diple quotes">Folia omnibus medicamentis dolo- <lb/>rem ſedantibus,
                per ſeſe, et ex p<unclear>o</unclear>lenta uti- <lb/>liſſime imponuntur:
                  <unclear>r</unclear>ecentia ad mitigan- <lb/>dos omne genus dolores oblinuntur.
              </q> Dioſ- <lb/>corid. lib. 4. cap. 64. </p>
          </note> and even the leaves of the black <lb/>henbane had a place in the <hi rend="italic"
            >London Diſ- <cb n="2"/>
            <lb/>penſatory</hi> before the laſt emendation of <lb/>the college. <hi rend="italic"
            >Proſper Alpinus</hi>
          <note n="(12)" place="below" rend="size(0.8)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(12) Proſperi Alpini de plantis Ægypti, <lb/>Patavii edit. 1640, p. 131. Alpinus
              thought <lb/>this Ægyptian henbane different from the <lb/>common white, as it had
              larger, broader, <lb/>thicker, and whiter leaves, but Veſlingius in <lb/>his notes and
              obſervations thinks it the ſame, <lb/>and ſays it grows with the yellow ſort all over
              <lb/>the country among the pyramids. He de- <lb/>ſcribes the plant, and then mentions
              the uſe <lb/>of the ſeeds in reſtraining fluxes of blood, <lb/>and mitigating pain,
              whether in the head, <lb/>pleura, or inteſtines. p. 59. </p>
          </note> ſays, <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Ægyptians</hi> uſe the white as they uſe <lb/>the
            <hi rend="italic">ſtramonium</hi>, to procure ſleep, bruiſing <lb/>the leaves and
          applying them to the <lb/>temples and other parts. The ſeeds of <lb/>the white henbane
          have been particu- <lb/>larly recommended in ſpittings of blood, <lb/>and entered into the
          compoſition of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Philonium Romanum pilulæ de Cyno- <lb/>gloſſo,
            &amp;c.</hi> of the former diſpenſatories, <lb/>but a more extenſive and particular
          <lb/>experience of their effects, and the <lb/>knowledge of better medicines, have
          <lb/>now ſuperſeded the uſe of them. I am <lb/>convinced from my own experience, <lb/>that
          their internal uſe is not adviſeable. <lb/>The quantity of two drams of theſe <lb/>ſeeds,
          and two drams of the ſeeds of <lb/>white poppies being made into an e- <lb/>lectuary with
          conſerve of roſes, the <lb/>whole making about four ounces, of <lb/>which the quantity of
          a nutmeg being <lb/>taken two or three times a day, brought <lb/>on ſuch a continual and
          troubleſome <lb/>vertigo before half the electuary was ta- <lb/>ken, that it ſeemed
          dangerous to con- <lb/>tinue the uſe of it any longer. Thoſe <lb/>who are acquainted with
          the nature of <lb/>theſe two ingredients will, I am per- <lb/>ſwaded, readily attribute
          the far greater <lb/>ſhare in producing this effect to the <lb/>henbane rather than the
          poppy ſeeds. <lb/>It is not improbable, indeed, but the <lb/>ſeeds here uſed might be of
          the black <lb/>kind, as there is reaſon to think, that <lb/>they are moſt commonly
          ſubſtituted for <lb/>the white. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
