<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Ready: Remarkable case in Surgery</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>J. Ready</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Remarkable case in Surgery</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for D. Henry, and R. Cave, at St John's Gate.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1755</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">25</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">12</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1755_GM_0012">
    <body>
      <pb n="12"/>
      <cb n="2 3"/>
      <div>
        <salute rend="indent">
          <lb/>Mr <hi rend="sc">Urban</hi>, </salute>
        <p rend="italic space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(1.5)">I</hi> Send you a remarkable caſe in ſurgery, <lb/>with the bone
          itſelf that came away; <lb/>(See the Fig.) and if you think it will be <lb/>acceptable to
          your readers, it is at their <lb/>ſervice. I am, Sir, yours, &amp;c. </p>
        <cb n="2"/>
        <dateline rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Glouceſter, <lb/>Dec. 18. 1754. </dateline>
        <cb n="3"/>
        <signed rend="sc space align-right">
          <lb/>J. Ready. </signed>
      </div>
      <div>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">E</hi><hi rend="italic">Lizabeth</hi>, the daughter of <hi
            rend="italic">Edward <lb/>Avery</hi>, of this place, aged about <lb/>eight years, was a
          little before <hi rend="italic">Lady-day</hi>
          <lb/>1749 ſeized with an inflammatory diſ- <lb/>order in the fore part of her left leg,
          <lb/>extending from a little below her knee <lb/>almoſt to her toes: It appeared more
          <lb/>like the eryſipelatous than phlegmonoide <lb/>kind; the parts affected were very
          tenſe, <lb/>hot, and red; the ſwelling not great, <lb/>but the pain almoſt intolerable,
          and <lb/>attended with a pretty high fever. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>For the ſpace of three or four days <lb/>attempts were made to diſperſe it, but
          <lb/>without effect; and the next intention <lb/>of cure being to promote ſuppuration,
          <lb/>the common cataplaſm of bread and <lb/>milk was applied to the whole inflamed
          <lb/>part, and in about eight days there ap- <lb/>peared a pretty large collection of mat-
          <lb/>ter, with fluctuation, about the middle <lb/>of the <unclear>ſhin</unclear>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Without waiting, therefore, for far- <pb n="13"/>
          <cb n="1"/>
          <lb/>ther ſigns of maturity, I immediately <lb/>opened the tumour in its whole extent,
          <lb/>by an inciſion near four inches long, <lb/>directly over and parallel with the ante-
          <lb/>rior angle of the tibia, and a large <lb/>quantity of thin matter was diſcharged. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Upon inſpecting the inſide of the ab- <lb/>ſceſs, the tibia appeared diveſted of its
          <lb/>perioſteum; and by examining the parts <lb/>above and below the opening with the
          <lb/>probe, and alſo the lateral and hinder <lb/>parts of the bone by bending the probe,
          <lb/>I found it bare on each ſide quite round, <lb/>and above and below, almoſt its whole
          <lb/>length, but not much altered in its co- <lb/>lour, or the ſmoothneſs of its ſurface. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>When the patient firſt complained, <lb/>ſhe did not recollect that ſhe had re-
          <lb/>ceived any hurt; but now, ſhe ſaid, ſhe <lb/>remembered to have received a kick
          <lb/>from another girl as they were at play, <lb/>two or three days before, which gave
          <lb/>her ſome pain for a little while, and <lb/>went off. But whatever was the cauſe
          <lb/>of the diſeaſe, the rapidity of its pro- <lb/>greſs, and the condition of the parts,
          <lb/>were ſufficient proofs that it began ori- <lb/>ginally in, and was really an
          inflamma- <lb/>tion of the perioſteum and bone itſelf. <lb/>As nothing could now be
          expected but <lb/>the loſs of ſo much of the tibia at leaſt, <lb/>as was thus deprived of
          its vital fluids <lb/>and ſenſation, by the loſs of its perioſ- <lb/>teum, there appeared
          but little proſpect <lb/>of ſaving the limb; for whenever the <lb/>loſs of a tranſverſe
          portion of the tibia <lb/>has become neceſſary, it has been the <lb/>common practice to
          amputate the leg <lb/>without delay, rather than wear out the <lb/>patient by deferring
          the operation; and <lb/>the reaſon is plain, for the fibula does <lb/>not only appear too
          ſmall to ſuſtain the <lb/>whole weight of the body, but it has <lb/>no articulation with
          the Os Femoris, <lb/>being only laterally connected with the <lb/>upward and outward part
          of the tibia; <lb/>beſides that the motions of flexture and <lb/>extenſion ariſe from the
          tibia only, in <lb/>which the united tendon of the muſcles <lb/>that extend the leg, and
          all the flexors <lb/>except one terminate. Upon theſe prin- <lb/>ciples, therefore, it
          appears right to <lb/>take away the leg as uſeleſs, when the <lb/>tibia cannot be
          preſerved; and it is <lb/>certainly right to take away ſoon what <lb/>cannot be ſaved at
          laſt. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>However I was inclined to hope, that <lb/>as my patient was very young, nature
          <lb/>might ſupply the defect of the tibia, by <lb/>giving an extraordinary increaſe of
          <lb/>growth and ſtrength to the fibula: And <lb/>that if the diſorder could be prevented
          <lb/>from ſpreading, and the upper extre- <lb/>mity of the tibia preſerved, ſhe might <cb
            n="2"/>
          <lb/>have ſo far the uſe of her leg, as to <lb/>render it much preferable to a wooden
          <lb/>one. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>To preſerve the parts of the bones, <lb/>therefore, which were yet ſound, and <lb/>to
          thicken the diſcharge, I applied lint <lb/>dipt in antiſeptic ſpirituous liquors, to
          <lb/>the bone and internal parts of the ab- <lb/>ſceſs, and cover'd it with a common
          <lb/>pledgit; which method of dreſſing was <lb/>purſued through the whole cure, except
          <lb/>that ſometimes eſcharotics were applied <lb/>to keep down the fungus on the ſides
          <lb/>of the wound, and to prevent, as much <lb/>as poſſible, the aperture from dimi-
          <lb/>niſhing. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>After it was opened the pain ſoon <lb/>ceaſed; but the fever continuing, ſhe
          <lb/>took <hi rend="italic">Tinct. Cort. Peruv.</hi> lightly acidula- <lb/>ted with <hi
            rend="italic">Elix. Vitrioli</hi>; and a diarrhæa <lb/>alſo, which came on as the fever
          began <lb/>to decline, was ſtay'd by the uſe of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fuller</hi>'s
          decoction of <hi rend="italic">Fracaſtorius</hi>; and <lb/>the tincture being continued a
          few days <lb/>longer, at about three weeks end, ſhe <lb/>was quite free from her fever,
          her ap- <lb/>petite returned, ſhe ſlept well, the diſ- <lb/>charge became leſs in
          quantity, and of <lb/>a good colour and conſiſtency, and <lb/>there were no remains of
          preternatural <lb/>colour, heat, or tenſion in the limb <lb/>affected, nor any pain,
          except when ſhe <lb/>was mov'd. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Encourag'd by theſe favourable ap- <lb/>pearances, I continued the ſame exter-
          <lb/>nal applications, I gave her internally <lb/>the decoction of guaiacum; and per-
          <lb/>ſevering in this method, about eleven <lb/>months the bone began to be moveable,
          <lb/>and in leſs than two months more it <lb/>ſeemed quite looſe; and in order to fa-
          <lb/>cilitate its removal, I made an attempt <lb/>to divide it in two, by the trepan ſaw,
          <lb/>but the operation proving more tedious <lb/>and painful than I expected, thro' the
          <lb/>inſtability of the bone, and the attrition <lb/>of its jagged edges againſt the
          inſide of <lb/>the wound; and the diameter of the <lb/>cylindrical ſaw being too ſmall to
          divide <lb/>it intirely, I deſiſted, and with a knife <lb/>and director extended the
          aperture to- <lb/>wards the knee, high enough to ſet the <lb/>upper end of the looſe bone
          at liberty; <lb/>but finding it not yet intirely ſeparated <lb/>at its other extremity, I
          kept the upper <lb/>end of it rais'd as high or higher than <lb/>the level of the ſkin, by
          forcing dreſ- <lb/>ſings of lint under it, which prevented <lb/>its pointed extremity from
          injuring the <lb/>neighbouring parts, and alſo ſecured <lb/>it from being again incloſed
          by the <lb/>healing of the upper part of the wound <lb/>over it. </p>
        <pb n="14"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In about 10 days more, apprehend- <lb/>ing it to be intirely diſengaged, I drew
          <lb/>it with very little violence out of the <lb/>ſinus which ſheathed its lower exre-
          <lb/>mity. It meaſured full five inches and <lb/>a quarter in length, and is the intire
          <lb/>circumference of the tibia, except what <lb/>the diſeaſe has deſtroyed of its
          anterior <lb/>angle and external ſide. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A pretty large hæmorrhage enſued, <lb/>occaſioned by the keen edges of the <lb/>bone
          lacerating the veſſels, which was <lb/>immediately ſuppreſſed by filling the <lb/>cavity
          from whence it iſſued with lint <figure>
            <figDesc>An illustration showing the decayed shinbone from three different sides.
            </figDesc>
          </figure>
          <cb n="2 3"/>
          <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">Tinct. Myrrh. c.</hi> and applying a <lb/>pretty tight bandage. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In a very little time after the extrac- <lb/>tion of the bone, the middle part of
          <lb/>the wound began to cicatrize, and the <lb/>patient walked to my houſe daily to be
          <lb/>dreſſed, with the aſſiſtance of a ſtaff <lb/>only, and which being one day forgot,
          <lb/>ſhe found ſhe had ſo little occaſion for <lb/>it, that ſhe never uſed it afterwards. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The two extremities of the wound <lb/>kept open ſome weeks longer, ſeveral <lb/>ſmall
          portions of bone, at different <lb/>times, working out of them, particu- <cb n="3"/>
          <lb/>larly from the lower part <lb/>one of two inches in <lb/>length, and about the
          <lb/>thickneſ of a ſmall quill, <lb/>after which the cure was <lb/>in a few days completed
          <lb/>with a firm cicatrix; and <lb/>from that time to this, <lb/>which is now upwards
          <lb/>of four years, ſhe has <lb/>continued perfectly ſound<choice>
            <corr>.</corr>
            <sic/>
          </choice>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>She is quite upright, <lb/>has no defect either of <lb/>ſtrength or motion in her
          <lb/>leg, and ſcarcely any <lb/>deformity; if any thing, <lb/>'tis a ſmall matter big-
          <lb/>ger than the other juſt <lb/>above the ankle, occaſi- <lb/>oned by the exuberance
          <lb/>of the callus, by which <lb/>the remains of the tibia <lb/>are conſolidated with the
          <lb/>fibula; and in the mid- <lb/>dle of the leg, inſtead of <lb/>the acute riſing of the
          <lb/>ſkin, there is a remarka- <lb/>ble depreſſion. The <lb/>whole texture of the leg
          <lb/>is much more denſe and <lb/>compact than uſual. The <lb/>cure took up from firſt
          <lb/>to laſt near 16 months. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Scultætus</hi>, in his chi- <lb/>rurgical obſervations, No.
          <lb/>Lxxx1. deſcribes a caſe <lb/>in many particulars re- <lb/>ſembling this, which I
          <lb/>had never ſeen till after <lb/>the cure was completed, <lb/>otherwiſe I ſhould have
          <lb/>been leſs doubtful of the <lb/>event. There are alſo <lb/>two hiſtories of this kind
          <lb/>in the medical eſſays, <lb/>Vol. I. p. 238; but in <lb/>thoſe the patients were
          <lb/>not quite upright. We <lb/>were informed likewiſe <pb n="15"/>
          <cb n="1"/>
          <lb/>by the public papers about 2 years ſince, <lb/>that Mr <hi rend="italic">Le Gat</hi>,
          a ſurgeon in <hi rend="italic">Denmark</hi>, <lb/>had lately ſucceeded in a like attempt,
          <lb/>and had publickly read an account of <lb/>it in the academy of which he is a
          <lb/>member. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Upon the whole, I am of opinion, <lb/>that the ſucceſs of this cure may in ſome
          <lb/>meaſure be attributed to the length of <lb/>time in which it was effected, the de-
          <lb/>cayed bone in the mean while ſerving <lb/>(like a prop to a ruinous edifice) to re-
          <lb/>ſiſt the contractile power of the muſcles, <lb/>and preſerve the extenſion of the
          leg, <lb/>till the other parts had form'd ſuch a <lb/>coalition, and acquired ſuch
          firmneſs <lb/>and calloſity as enabled them to ſupply <lb/>the defect of the tibia. </p>
        <figure>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/><hi rend="sc">Explanation</hi> of the <hi rend="roman">FIGURE</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <list>
              <item rend="indent">
                <lb/><hi rend="italic">a b</hi> That ſide of the tibia which is <lb/>ſituated
                obliquely in the anterior and <lb/>internal part of the leg, where it is co-
                <lb/>vered only with the ſkin and perioſteum<choice>
                  <corr>.</corr>
                  <sic/>
                </choice>
              </item>
              <item rend="indent">
                <lb/><hi rend="italic">a</hi> Its upper end next the knee. The <lb/>circular groove
                in its middle was made <lb/>by the trepan. </item>
              <item rend="indent">
                <lb/><hi rend="italic">c</hi> Is the external ſide.—The angle <lb/>betwixt thoſe two
                ſides, which is very <lb/>much waſted by the diſeaſe, forms the <lb/>keen edge of
                the ſhin. </item>
              <item rend="indent">
                <lb/><hi rend="italic">d</hi> Is its poſterior ſide towards the calf <lb/>of the
                leg. </item>
            </list>
          </p>
        </figure>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
