<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: The Efficacy of Electricity in the Cure of Diseases</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>The Efficacy of Electricity in the Cure of Diseases, determined by a great
              Variety of Experiments made by Appointment of the Royal College of Physicians in
              Sweden.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for D. Henry, and R. Cave, at St John's Gate.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1755</date>
              <biblScope unit="page">313</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1755_GM_0313">
    <body>
      <pb n="313"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/>The Efficacy of Electricity in the Cure of <lb/>Diſeaſes, determined by a great Variety
        <lb/>of Experiments made by Appointment <lb/>of the Royal College of Phyſicians in <lb/><hi
          rend="roman">Sweden</hi>. </head>
      <div>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">D</hi>R <hi rend="italic">Roſen</hi>, the king's firſt phyſician,
          <lb/>and profeſſor <hi rend="italic">Stromer</hi>, having <lb/>made certain trials, from
          whence it <lb/>was judged expedient to examine fur- <pb n="314"/>
          <cb n="1"/>
          <lb/>ther into this new method of cure. <lb/>Dr <hi rend="italic">Zetzell</hi> was
          appointed to purſue it <lb/>every day at certain hours in the pub- <lb/>lick hoſpital of
            <hi rend="italic">Upſal</hi>, on various ſub- <lb/>jects under different diſorders;
          which <lb/>he continued to do for the ſpace of <lb/>two years. The reſult of his expe-
          <lb/>riments is contained in the following <lb/>extract. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>In the Amauroſis, or Gutta Serena. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>In two patients the electrical ſparks <lb/>were drawn from the parts near <lb/>the
          eyes without the leaſt benefit, <lb/>nor was the electrical ſhock from the <lb/>phial
          found to ſucceed better; ſo that <lb/>electricity promiſes little in this diſ- <lb/>order.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>In the Gout. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Pains of the joints were frequently <lb/>obſerved to ceaſe by exciting the e-
          <lb/>lectrical ſparks; but then the gou- <lb/>ty matter ſeemed to be repelled in-
          <lb/>ward, and produced ſymptoms of <lb/>more grievous conſequence: So that <lb/>it was
          often found, that if this ap- <lb/>plication was continued, pains of the <lb/>head,
          vertigo's, ſickneſs at ſtomach, <lb/>and violent gripings would take place, <lb/>which
          again diſappeared as ſoon as <lb/>nature was able to repel the morbid <lb/>matter back to
          the joints. Some un- <lb/>der this treatment urined very plen- <lb/>tifully, and fell into
          copious ſweats in <lb/>the night, which gave hopes that in <lb/>time the obſtinacy of the
          diſeaſe might <lb/>be thus ſubdu'd; but experience prov'd <lb/>the contrary, the
          before-mentioned ill <lb/>ſymptoms all returning in a ſeverer <lb/>degree; ſo that all
          hopes of benefit <lb/>to gouty patients from electricity are <lb/>at an end. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>In an inveterate Head-ach. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>In this chronical caſe drawing out <lb/>the electrical ſparks produced a mi-
          <lb/>tigation, and often a ceſſation of <lb/>the pain; but when it was thought <lb/>that
          an abſolute cure had been effect- <lb/>ed, the diſorder returned with great
          <lb/>aggravation: It is, however, worthy <lb/>note, that where proper internal re-
          <lb/>medies were given at the ſame time, <lb/>the deſired effect was ſpeedily pro-
          <lb/>duced. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>In Contractions. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Electricity has certainly removed ſo <lb/>many complaints of this kind, as to
          <lb/>deſerve being tried wherever the like <lb/>occur. One who had loſt the uſe of
          <lb/>his limbs from cold for ſeveral years, <lb/>was at length quite reſtored by the <cb
            n="2"/>
          <lb/>uſe of Electricity, and another whoſe <lb/>knee joint had been above five years
          <lb/>contracted from a rheumatiſm, was <lb/>able to ſtreighten it after twice elec-
          <lb/>trifying. But in attempting the cure <lb/>of ſuch diſorders by this Method, it
          <lb/>is of great Importance to diſtinguiſh <lb/>carefully which are the Muſcles that
          <lb/>are affected; for it is thoſe alone from <lb/>which ſparks are to be drawn, and
          <lb/>by no means from their antagoniſts, <lb/>which on the other hand ſhould be
          <lb/>relaxed by warm fomentations appli- <lb/>ed for ſome hours together, and after-
          <lb/>wards anointed with ſome emollient <lb/>unguents. At the beginning of this
          <lb/>courſe the ſtomach ought to be forti- <lb/>fied with ſome generous liquor, leſt
          <lb/>the matter removed from the joint <lb/>ſhould be depoſited upon the nobler
          <lb/>parts. The electrical ſhock is not <lb/>near ſo efficacious, as ſimply drawing
          <lb/>out the ſparks. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>In Deafneſs and Singing of the Ears. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>When deafneſs ariſes from indurated <lb/>wax, the drawing of ſparks by an iron
          <lb/>ſtile will help to diſſolve it, or if the <lb/>deafneſs has followed a fever, it will
          <lb/>promote the digeſtion of the metaſta- <lb/>ſis; but in a catarrhal deafneſs, ariſing
          <lb/>originally from a humid air, and in <lb/>ſinging of the ears, all that could <lb/>be
          done by electricity turned to very <lb/>little account. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>In the Epilepſy. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>In ſome epileptics it has certainly <lb/>been ſerviceable, but if the complaint
          <lb/>was hereditary, or owing to a fright, <lb/>it did no ſenſible good or harm. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>In Felons. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The electrical ſparks bring them to <lb/>a ſpeedy digeſtion. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>In Ganglions. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>In the only three caſes of a gan- <lb/>glion on which electricity was tried, <lb/>it
          diſperſed them perfectly. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>In Hyſteric Diſorders. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>In theſe it was never found to be <lb/>attended with the leaſt benefit. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>In the Sciatica. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>In ſome the pains <sic>has</sic> been greatly <lb/>appeaſed by electriſation, but
          return- <lb/>ed again afterwards; in ſome it was <lb/>not at all abated; in others the
          ſuc- <lb/>ceſs appeared extraordinary at firſt, <lb/>but after a few days the force of the
          <lb/>diſorder was turned upon the inteſtines, <lb/>with excruciating torments. </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="315"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>In the Tooth-ach. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Where the anguiſh was owing to <lb/>hollow teeth, or from a catarrhal or
          <lb/>ſcorbutic habit, it ſeldom failed of <lb/>producing a perfect cure, though at
          <lb/>firſt the pain ſeemed to be increaſed, <lb/>and raged for 24 hours, after which
          <lb/>it went off entirely. The ſparks ſhould <lb/>be drawn from the affected tooth by
          <lb/>means of an iron ſtile, for a good <lb/>while together. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>In Coſtiveneſs. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The experiments boaſted of ſo much <lb/>in <hi rend="italic">Italy</hi> of including
          cathartics within <lb/>the electrifying glaſs (<hi rend="italic">ſee Vol. <hi rend="roman"
              >xxii.</hi> p. <hi rend="roman">76.</hi></hi>) <lb/>were very frequently tried, but
          could <lb/>never be made in the leaſt to ſucceed <lb/>in <hi rend="italic">Sweden</hi>.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>In Palſies. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The commotion with the <hi rend="italic">Leyden</hi> phial <lb/>has been made on
          paralytics here <lb/>without any benefit, nor were the <lb/>muſcles irritated by drawing
          ſparks <lb/>from them with any better conſequence; <lb/>yet ſometimes by chance the pain
          has <lb/>been ſo ſevere on an otherwiſe inſen- <lb/>ſible part, as to be hardly tolerable;
          <lb/>and when ſuch parts were once diſ- <lb/>covered, the ſparks were continually
          <lb/>drawn from them alone: This was re- <lb/>peated ſo often on a citizen of <hi
            rend="italic">Upſal</hi>, <lb/>who was a true paralytic, that he was <lb/>perfectly
          cured thereby. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>In Quartans. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>From the few trials that have been <lb/>made in this diſeaſe, nothing can be
          <lb/>concluded for certain. In two caſes <lb/>the fits were leſſened to a kind of pe-
          <lb/>riodical tenſions only, and in a third <lb/>they totally ceaſed. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>In Quotidian Agues. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Electricity has been applied to two <lb/>patients only in this diſorder, in whom
          <lb/>the ſparks were excited all over their <lb/>bodies. One loſt the ague for ſome
          <lb/>time, after which it returned; in the <lb/>other it was not at all put off, but
          <lb/>changed into a tertian. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>In Rheumatiſms. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>What has been ſaid before about <lb/>the ſciatica, may be affirmed of this
          <lb/>diſorder. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Concluſion. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <list>
            <item>
              <lb/>1. In intermittent fevers electrifica- <lb/>tion is inſignificant. </item>
            <item>2. In rheuma- <lb/>tic, arthritic, and ſciatic complaints, it <lb/>iſ very ſeldom
              that any advantage is <lb/>gained without a tranſlation of the <lb/>morbitic matter
              inwards. </item>
            <item>3. There <lb/>is a great agreement between paraly- <lb/>tic and rheumatic
              diſorders. A rheu- <cb n="2"/>
              <lb/>matiſm, with deafneſs, tremors, and <lb/>a difficulty of motion in one entire
              <lb/>ſide, wherein the electrical ſparks oc- <lb/>caſioned a moſt painful ſenſation,
              was <lb/>ſo far conquered, that the patient had <lb/>the uſe of his arm reſtored, and
              then <lb/>was ſeized with an opthalmia, which <lb/>being repelled by cooling
              collyriums, <lb/>the arm became motionleſs again. </item>
            <item>4. <lb/>In a palſy of two of the fingers of one <lb/>hand only, electricity was
              made uſe <lb/>of to no purpoſe. </item>
            <item>5. In all caſes a <lb/>long uſe of electricity brings on a <lb/>coſtiveneſs, and
              an increaſe of appe- <lb/>tite, moſt probably from promoting <lb/>inſenſible
              perſpiration. </item>
            <item>6. A ſaliva- <lb/>tion is excited by drawing ſparks from <lb/>the parotid glands,
              and from the in- <lb/>ſide of the mouth. </item>
            <item>7. In the tooth- <lb/>ach it is good to draw ſparks with an <lb/>iron style, from
              the hard portion of <lb/>the nerves of the ſeventh pair, called <lb/>the bur of the
              ear, though the patient <lb/>complains of an exquiſite pain at that <lb/>inſtant. </item>
            <item>8. Animals of the ſerpent <lb/>kind are killed by the electrical com- <lb/>motion,
              and become exceeding rigid <lb/>when dead. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
      </div>
      <postscript>
        <p rend="indent space size(0.8)">
          <lb/>
          <label>⁂ </label> This paper is of indubitable authority, <lb/>having been publickly read
          before the learned <lb/>body at <hi rend="italic">Upſal</hi>, of which the great <hi
            rend="italic">Linnæus</hi> is <lb/>the head, and communicated to us in <hi rend="italic"
            >Latin</hi>
          <lb/>by a member of the Royal ſociety. </p>
      </postscript>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
