<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: List of Deaths and Preferments - Advertisement</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>List of Deaths and Preferments - Advertisement</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for D. Henry, and R. Cave, at St John's Gate.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1755</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">25</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">43</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1755_GM_0043">
    <body>
      <pb n="43"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <head rend="blackletter align-center">ADVERTISEMENT. </head>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">W</hi><hi rend="sc">Hereas</hi> many noblemen, gentlemen, <lb/>and
        others, who in the polite world <lb/>are diſtinguiſhed by the name of <hi rend="italic">men
          of pleaſure</hi>, <lb/>have, by <hi rend="italic">faſt living</hi>, now commonly called
          <hi rend="italic">ſport- <lb/>ing</hi>, formerly ſtigmatized by the names of <hi
          rend="italic">who- <lb/>ring</hi> and <hi rend="italic">drunkenneſs</hi>, brought upon
        themſelves, <lb/>at the age of 40, all the pains, aches, and in- <lb/>firmities of
        fourſcore; and others, by faſhion- <lb/>ably ſpending their whole fortunes, by contract-
        <lb/>ing debts which they cannot pay, and ruining <lb/>their wives, wards, children, and
        creditors, have <lb/>incurred ſuch reflexions as render life intollera- <lb/>ble. <hi
          rend="sc">And whereas</hi> it has been proved, by <lb/>the late great Ld <hi rend="italic"
          >Bolingbroke</hi> and others, to the <lb/>full ſatisfaction of all gentlemen of <hi
          rend="italic">wit</hi>, <hi rend="italic">hu- <lb/>mour</hi>, men of <hi rend="italic"
          >pleaſure</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">ſporters</hi>, that after <lb/>this life there is
        nothing either to hope or fear; <lb/>ſo that to put an end to it, in ſuch circumſtan-
        <lb/>ces, is greatly for the advantage of themſelves <lb/>and the community. <hi rend="sc"
          >And whereas</hi>, ſuch <lb/>is the prejudice ſtill remaining among the great <lb/>and
        little vulgar, that this neceſſary and heroic <lb/>act reflects indelible diſhonour upon
        ſuch men <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">wit</hi>, <hi rend="italic">humour</hi>, and <hi
          rend="italic">pleaſure</hi>, and their families, <lb/>and makes the expence of bribing a
        coroner's <lb/>jury to perjury abſolutely neceſſary, to prevent <lb/>a forfeiture of their
        perſonal eſtate, if any ſuch <lb/>there be. <hi rend="sc">And whereas</hi>, there is at pre-
        <lb/>ſent no known method, by which this neceſſary <lb/>meaſure may be <hi rend="italic"
          >decently</hi> and <hi rend="italic">privately</hi> executed, <lb/>the razor, ſword, and
        halter having been uni- <lb/>verſally exploded, and the effect of the piſtol, <lb/>as it is
        commonly uſed, being very uncertain, <lb/>ſometimes cauſing a great effuſion of blood,
        <lb/>ſometimes blowing the brains about the room, <lb/>ſpoiling the paintings and other
        furniture, and <lb/>leaving the body bloody and mangled, the coun- <lb/>tenance diſtorted,
        and the features deraced; <lb/>and at the ſame time alarming not only the <lb/>family but
        the neighbourhood, ſo that all at- <lb/>tempts to conceal it by pretending apoplexy or
        <lb/>ſudden death are ineffectual; <hi rend="sc">Notice</hi> is <lb/>hereby given, that a
        gentleman of great ſtudy <lb/>and experience by ſea and land, as well in <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">England</hi> as in foreign parts, has diſcovered and <lb/>obtained the
        king's patent for the following <lb/>remedies againſt life: 1ſt, his <hi rend="italic">white
          powder</hi>, <lb/>which throws a bullet from any fire-arm, with- <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>out noiſe, and yet with the ſame force as that <lb/>commonly uſed; and which, by being
        mixed <lb/>with a certain chymical compound, may be re- <lb/>gulated to any degree of
        ſtrength, according to <lb/>the tickneſs of the ſkull, ſo as to paſs through <lb/>the ear,
        or the roof of the mouth, and lodge in <lb/>the brain, without fracturing any part of the
        <lb/>bone behind, or leaving any appearance of a <lb/>wound. 2dly, His incomparable <hi
          rend="italic">laurel water</hi>, <lb/>which produces its effect even while it is going
        <lb/>down the throat, without noiſe, agony or con- <lb/>vulſions. 3dly, His ineſtimable
        chymical ſpi- <lb/>rit, invidiouſly called, by Dr Mead, the <hi rend="italic">Stygian
          <lb/>ſpirit</hi>, from its ſubtle, imperceptible, and ef- <lb/>fectual influence upon
        life, a ſmall vial of <lb/>which may be ſo held by a perſon in the midſt <lb/>of a large
        circle of gentlemen and ladies, as <lb/>inſtantly to kill him, without affecting any o-
        <lb/>ther of the company. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The author, upon a line poſt-paid, will <lb/>attend and adminiſter theſe remedies
        himſelf, <lb/>to any <hi rend="italic">nobleman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">gentleman</hi>, or
        other man of <lb/><hi rend="italic">wit</hi>, <hi rend="italic">humour</hi>, and <hi
          rend="italic">pleaſure</hi>, who may think fit <lb/>to honour him with his commands,
        provided <lb/>a ſufficient indemnity be given, and the gen- <lb/>tleman has not courage to
        apply them himſelf; <lb/>or they will be delivered, with a printed paper <lb/>of directions,
        to any who ſhall aſk for a <hi rend="italic">doſe of <lb/>the anodyne powder, drops, or
          eſſence</hi>, at the gen- <lb/>tlewoman's, the <hi rend="italic">two blue poſts</hi>, in
          <hi rend="italic">Frith ſtreet, <lb/>Soho</hi>, and no where elſe in <hi rend="italic"
          >England</hi>, at the <lb/>price of <hi rend="italic">one Guinea</hi>, which is nothing to
        the <lb/>value of a cure. </p>
      <postscript>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">P. S.</hi> Upon a proper certificate of the pa- <lb/>tient's life,
          converſation, and circumſtances, <lb/>ſhewing that he is a proper object of charity,
          <lb/>in want of theſe remedies, and unable to buy <lb/>them, they ſhall be delivered <hi
            rend="italic">gratis</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The utmoſt ſecrecy and honour may be de- <lb/>pended on. <figure>
            <figDesc>A small picture of a hand pointing right with its index finger. </figDesc>
          </figure> Beware of Counterfeits. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">N. B.</hi>
          <hi rend="sc">Rock's</hi> medicines will not do; nor <lb/>will thoſe of any other
          advertiſing quack; for <lb/>though they are generally effectual, yet their <lb/>operations
          are ſo ſlow, and the alteration <lb/>which they produce in the patient before death
          <lb/>is ſo very viſible, that the ſecret is always ſuſ- <lb/>pected, and often certainly
          known. </p>
      </postscript>
      <signed rend="italic align-right">
        <lb/>Vivat Rex. </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
