<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Watson: Observations related to the Cicuta, or Hemlock</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Wm Watson</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Observations related to the Cicuta, or Hemlock. By Wm Watson, M. D. F. R. S (See
              Vol. xxx, p.326.)</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for D. Henry at St John's Gate.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1761</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">31</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">157</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1761_GM_0157">
    <body>
      <pb n="157"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/>Obſervations relating to the <hi rend="roman">Cicuta</hi>, or <lb/>Hemlock. By <hi
          rend="roman">Wm Watſon</hi>, M. D. <lb/>F. R. S. (See Vol. <hi rend="roman">xxx</hi>, p.
        326.) </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">D</hi>R. <hi rend="italic">Storke</hi>, who publiſhed at <hi
          rend="italic">Vienna</hi>
        <lb/>laſt year a treatiſe <hi rend="italic">de Cicuta</hi>, has <lb/>lately informed a
        correſpondent in <hi rend="italic">Lon- <lb/>don</hi>, that ſince the publication of that
        <lb/>work he had received letters from al- <lb/>moſt every part of <hi rend="italic"
          >Europe</hi>, confirming <lb/>his good opinion of the virtues of the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Cicuta</hi>; and that he is about to publiſh <lb/>a ſecond treatiſe upon the
        ſame ſubject, <lb/>containing ſtill more extraordinary re- <lb/>lations of cures brought
        about by ad- <lb/>miniſtering that plant. There is no <lb/>doubt therefore but that
        endeavours <lb/>will be made here to confirm the truth <lb/>of the doctor's aſſertions; more
        eſpe- <lb/>cially, as ſome of the diſeaſes, in which <lb/>Dr <hi rend="italic">Storke</hi>
        found the <hi rend="italic">Cicuta</hi> attended with <lb/>great ſucceſs, are ſuch as are of
        all o- <lb/>thers the moſt ſhocking to human nature, <lb/>and have, by too long experience,
        been <lb/>found to give way to no other means. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Hence it is highly important to every <lb/>one, more particularly to phyſicians,
        <lb/>that the very plant directed by Dr <lb/><hi rend="italic">Storke</hi>, be adminiſtered,
        and no other <lb/>in the place of it, either through inat- <lb/>tention or want of
        knowledge; as judg- <lb/>ment in the phyſician is of no real <lb/>ſervice, unleſs his
        preſcriptions are <lb/>faithfully prepared. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>For theſe reaſons it may not be im- <lb/>proper to inform thoſe medical practi-
        <lb/>tioners, who are not converſant in bo- <lb/>tany, and who may, nevertheleſs, be
        <lb/>deſirous of trying the effects of the <hi rend="italic">Ci- <lb/>cuta</hi>, that at
        this time of the year there <lb/>is another plant, growing in the ſame <lb/>places, and
        often mixt with it, ſo much <lb/>reſembling it in appearance as not with- <lb/>out ſome
        attention to be diſtinguiſhed <lb/>from it, which however greatly differs <lb/>from it in
        ſenſible qualities. Great <lb/>care therefore ought to be taken that <lb/>the one of theſe
        ſhould be ſelected from <lb/>the other. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As Dr <hi rend="italic">Storke</hi> has tranſmitted hither a <lb/>ſpecimen of the plant
        he has employed, <lb/>no doubt can remain in aſcertaining its <lb/>ſpecies. It is the <hi
          rend="italic">Cicuta vulgaris</hi> of <lb/>the botaniſts, or common hemlock. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The plant ſo much reſembling hem- <lb/>lock, is the <hi rend="italic">Cicutaria
          vulgaris</hi> of the <lb/>botaniſts, which, in ſome parts of <hi rend="italic">En-
          <lb/>gland</hi>, is called <hi rend="italic">cow-weed</hi>, in others <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">wild-cicely</hi>. Its greateſt reſemblance to <lb/>hemlock is in the ſpring,
        before the <lb/>ſtalks of the leaves of the hemlock are <lb/>interſperſed with purple ſpots,
        and <lb/>therefore at that ſeaſon more eaſily <lb/>miſtaken for it: though even then the <cb
          n="2"/>
        <lb/>leaves of the hemlock ſmell much <lb/>ſtronger, are more minutely divided, <lb/>and of
        a deeper green colour than <lb/>thoſe of the <hi rend="italic">cow-weed</hi>. Afterwards,
        <lb/>indeed, they are more eaſily diſtinguiſh- <lb/>ed, as the <hi rend="italic"
          >cicutaria</hi> flowers at the end <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">April</hi> and beginning of
          <hi rend="italic">May</hi>, and <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">cicuta</hi> not till <hi
          rend="italic">June</hi>, when the other <lb/>is paſt: To ſay nothing of the flower-
        <lb/>ing ſtalk of the cow-weed being fur- <lb/>rowed and ſomewhat downey; and that <lb/>of
        hemlock, ſmooth, even, and al- <lb/>ways ſpotted. Theſe plants differ like- <lb/>wiſe very
        eſſentially in their ſeeds, <lb/>which in the <hi rend="italic">cow-weed</hi> are long,
        ſmooth, <lb/>and black when ripe; whereas thoſe of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Hemlock</hi> are
        ſmall, channelled, and ſwel- <lb/>ling towards their middle. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Beſides the <hi rend="italic">cow-weed</hi>, there is ano- <lb/>ther plant in
        appearance very like the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Hemlock</hi>, altho' widely differing from
        it <lb/>in other reſpects; and, unleſs I am very <lb/>greatly miſinformed, quantities of
        this <lb/>have been collected and ſold in <hi rend="italic">London</hi>
        <lb/>for the <hi rend="italic">Hemlock</hi>. This is more likely <lb/>to be taken for the
        Hemlock in ſummer <lb/>or autumn, as it is an annual plant; <lb/>and is produced and flowers
        late in the <lb/>ſeaſon. The plant here meant is the <lb/><hi rend="italic">cicuta
          minor</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Parkinſon</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">cicutaria
          <lb/>tenuifolia</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Ray</hi>. This however is eaſi- <lb/>ly
        diſtinguiſhed from <hi rend="italic">Hemlcok</hi> by its be- <lb/>ing of the colour and
        ſhape of <hi rend="italic">parſley</hi>, <lb/>its flowering ſtalks having no purple or
        <lb/>other ſpots, and not having the ſtrong <lb/>ſmell peculiar to Hemlock. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To the two plants before-mentioned <lb/>may be added a third, which very fre-
        <lb/>quently, more eſpecially about <hi rend="italic">London</hi>, <lb/>grows along with,
        and is mixed with <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Hemlock</hi>. This plant is called by <lb/>the
        late excellent Mr <hi rend="italic">Ray</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ſmall Hemlock <lb/>Chervill
          with rough ſeeds</hi>; and is deno- <lb/>minated by <hi rend="italic">Caſper Bauhin</hi>
        in his Pinax <lb/><hi rend="italic">Myrrhis ſylveſtris ſeminibus aſperis</hi>. This,
        <lb/>like the Cow-weed before-mentioned, <lb/>can only be miſtaken for Hemlock in <lb/>the
        ſpring. It may be diſtinguiſhed <lb/>then from it, by the leaves of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Myr- <lb/>rhis</hi> being more finely cut, of a paler <lb/>green colour, and though they
        have <lb/>ſomewhat of the Hemlock ſmell, are <lb/>far leſs ſtrong, and have no ſpots. This
        <lb/>plant flowers in <hi rend="italic">April</hi>, and the ſeeds are <lb/>ripe before the
        Hemlock begins to flow- <lb/>er; and theſe ſeeds are cylindrical, <lb/>rough, and terminated
        in an oblong <lb/>point. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The leaves of Hemlock are moſt fit <lb/>for medicinal purpoſes, as being in their
        <lb/>greateſt perfection when collected in <lb/>dry weather from the middle of <hi
          rend="italic">May</hi> to <lb/>the time that their flowering ſtems be- <lb/>gin to ſhoot:
        as by that time the plants <pb n="158"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>will have felt the effects of the warm <lb/>ſun, have acquired an highly viroſe
        <lb/>ſmell, and the ſtems of the leaves are <lb/>covered with purple ſpots, an argu-
        <lb/>ment of the exaltation of their juices. <lb/>And we ſhould be attentive here to give
        <lb/>them all advantages, as three degrees of <lb/>latitude, and other circumſtances of
        <lb/>ſoil and ſituation, may occaſion a very <lb/>ſenſible difference in the qualities of
        the <lb/>ſame plant. An inſtance of which oc- <lb/>curs in the plant under conſideration,
        <lb/>and may be one of the cauſes why the <lb/>effects of the Hemlock have not been
        <lb/>ſuch here, as we are aſſured they are <lb/>at <hi rend="italic">Vienna</hi>, <hi
          rend="italic">viz.</hi> Dr <hi rend="italic">Storke</hi> ſays, that the <lb/>root of the
        Hemlock, when cut into ſli- <lb/>ces, pours forth a milky juice, which <lb/>I have never
        ſeen it do here in <hi rend="italic">England</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There are ſeveral vegetables, which, <lb/>though they thrive here apparently <lb/>well,
        their productions are neverthe- <lb/>leſs not the ſame as in other parts of <lb/>the world,
        where the heat is more in- <lb/>tenſe, and the ſummers are of longer <lb/>continuance. It
        would be extremely dif- <lb/>ficult here, tho' the plants thrive very <lb/>well, to produce
        from the white poppy <lb/>or <hi rend="italic">Ciſtus ladanifera</hi>, either the <hi
          rend="italic">opium</hi> or <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">labdanum</hi>, the known production
        of <lb/>theſe vegetables in other parts of the <lb/>world. No art can make here the <hi
          rend="italic">tra- <lb/>gacantha</hi> pour forth its gum, the <hi rend="italic">lentiſ-
          <lb/>cus</hi> its maſtick, or the candle berry <lb/>myrtle, of <hi rend="italic">North
          America</hi>, its ſebaceous <lb/>concrete: To theſe might be added ma- <lb/>ny others too
        tedious to mention. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In ſuch mild winters as the laſt, the <lb/>leaves of Hemlock may be procured in
        <lb/>any part of them; but they are not to <lb/>be depended upon; as their ſpecific
        <lb/>ſmell is then comparatively weak, their <lb/>juices poor and watry, and they are
        <lb/>wholly without ſpots. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
