<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: The Theory and Cure of the Distemper called a Cold</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>The Theory and Cure of the Distemper called a Cold, from a late Treatise on the
              Subject: Written by John Chandler of London, Apothecary, and F. R. S.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for D. Henry at St John's Gate.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1761</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">31</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">572</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1761_GM_0572">
    <body>
      <pb n="572"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/>The Theory and Cure of the Diſtemper call- <lb/>ed a Cold, from a late Treatiſe on the
        <lb/>Subject: Written by <hi rend="roman">John Chandler</hi> of <lb/><hi rend="roman"
          >London</hi>, Apothecary, and <hi rend="roman">F. R. S.</hi>
      </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>He matter which perſpires from <lb/>the human body is not excre-
        <lb/>mentitious, but is the reſult of the laſt <lb/>and moſt perfect concoction of the ani-
        <lb/>mal juices; it is what remains of the <lb/>alimentary ſubſtances received into the
        <lb/>ſtomach after they have gone through <lb/>the whole courſe of gradual tranſmu-
        <lb/>tation, and are purified from all ex- <lb/>crementitious particles, and it is de-
        <lb/>ſigned for the immediate nouriſhment <lb/>and repair of the body in all its parts. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This juice therefore permeates, or <lb/>paſſes through, every part of the body,
        <lb/>and ſo much of it only as is redundant <lb/>or ſuperfluous, paſſes off through the
        <lb/>pores, and excretory ducts. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But the pores and excretory ducts, <lb/>through which the ſuperfluity of this
        <lb/>juice paſſes, are not thoſe only of the <lb/>ſkin, but of the membranes that co-
        <lb/>ver and line the ſtomach, bowels, and <lb/>every other internal part of the body,
        <lb/>ſo that all the ſurfaces of the body, in- <lb/>ward and outward, are in perpetual
        <lb/>ſtate of perſpiration, by which they <lb/>are kept moiſt and ſupple, and pre-
        <lb/>vented both from adhering, and from <lb/>ſuffering a painful irritation by rub-
        <lb/>bing againſt each other. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This juice, as well as all other juices <lb/>of the body, when it is firſt ſecreted
        <lb/>from the capillary arteries is heated, <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>and therefore in a thin fluid ſtate; but <lb/>afterwards it grows thicker from vari-
        <lb/>ous cauſes, particularly from remain- <lb/>ing at reſt in its ſeveral receptacles, and
        <lb/>from a diſſipation or abſorption of its <lb/>aqueous particles. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This juice may be rendered thick <lb/>and tenacious, by natural and by ſu-
        <lb/>per-natural cauſes; and one ſpecies <lb/>of tenacity will be ſalutary and neceſ-
        <lb/>ſary, the other hurtful and danger- <lb/>ous. It is rendered thick and tena-
        <lb/>cious, and becomes the glandular mu- <lb/>cous of the noſe and mouth, and of <lb/>all
        the canals where ſuch a humour is <lb/>neceſſary to defend their internal ſur- <lb/>face
        againſt acrid and ſtimulating par- <lb/>ticles, by a natural cauſe, and there- <lb/>fore is
        ſalutary and neceſſary. It is <lb/>rendered thick and tenacious alſo by a <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">preter-natural chill</hi>, in its ſecretory or <lb/>excretory ducts; and by
        a corrugation <lb/>or ſpaſmodic conſtriction of the ducts <lb/>themſelves; it then puts a
        ſtop to the <lb/>natural ſecretions and abſorptions, <lb/>conſequently to the free
        circulation of <lb/>the humours through the capillaries, <lb/>which therefore extend and
        load the <lb/>compound organs on which the af- <lb/>fection falls; and, in this caſe, the
        in- <lb/>ſpiſſated perſpirable matter froms the <lb/>tenacious ſubſtance that appears upon
        <lb/>the ſurface of blood, which is taken from <lb/>perſons who are diſordered in conſe-
        <lb/>quence of neglected <hi rend="italic">colds</hi>, and which <lb/>is called <hi
          rend="italic">ſize</hi>; the ſame matter thus <lb/>morbidly inſpiſſated, alſo forms the
        <lb/>tough membranes and adheſions of <lb/>the lungs with the <choice>
          <corr>pleura</corr>
          <sic>pluera</sic>
        </choice> after perip- <lb/>neumonies and pleuriſies, as well as all <lb/>other adheſions
        after inflammatory diſor- <lb/>ders of different parts. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This morbid inſpiſſation of the per- <lb/>ſpirable matter from a <hi rend="italic"
          >chill</hi> in ſome in- <lb/>ternal or external part, therefore pro- <lb/>duces the
        diſeaſe called a <hi rend="italic">cold</hi>, and when <lb/>it falls on the <hi
          rend="italic">pituitary membrane</hi>, which <lb/>is moſt ſubject to this accident, the
        <lb/>moſt immediate and remarkable ſymp- <lb/>toms of the diſeaſe are produced. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">pituitary membrane</hi> is ſo called, <lb/>becauſe it ſecretes
        the pituita or mucus <lb/>of the noſe and mouth; part of it is <lb/>alſo the immediate organ
        of ſmelling; <lb/>it is of great extent, and lines not on- <lb/>ly the noſtrils, but all the
        adjacent ca- <lb/>vities called ſinuſſes: It is full of blood <lb/>veſſels and nerves, and
        the hinder part <lb/>of it contains a great number of glands, <lb/>each of which receives
        into its cavi- <lb/>ty, the thin lymph ſecreted or perſpi- <lb/>red from the minute
        capillaries, which <lb/>by cooling, and by the reſorption of <pb n="573"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>its aqueous parts, becomes the mucus <lb/>already mentioned; the capillary ar-
        <lb/>teries that cover other parts of this <lb/>membrane, alſo ooze out their lymph,
        <lb/>which is thickened by the action of the <lb/>air, and by its being intangled in the
        <lb/>glandular mucus. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When the <hi rend="italic">pituitary membrane</hi> is af- <lb/>fected by a cold, the
        capillary veſſels, <lb/>and ducts of the glands, are ob- <lb/>ſtructed, which produces an
        undue <lb/>fullneſs and diſtention of the veſ- <lb/>ſels, with a conſtriction of the mem-
        <lb/>brane, a ſtimulation of the nerves, and, <lb/>at laſt, an immoderate diſtillation and
        <lb/>eflux of humour; in other words, <lb/>the head is ſtuffed, the party ſneezes, <lb/>and
        the noſe runs: All this is fre- <lb/>quently occaſioned by <hi rend="italic">breathing cold
          air</hi>, <lb/>and forms a diſorder, which was for- <lb/>merly called, a <hi rend="italic"
          >catarrh</hi>, and, errone- <lb/>ouſly ſuppoſed to be derived from the <lb/>brain. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As the blood veſſels which are ſpread <lb/>over this membrane, communicate <lb/>with
        each other, and are derived from <lb/>different trunks, the obſtruction ſome- <lb/>times
        ſhifts from one part to another; <lb/>the diſcharge from the noſtrils will <lb/>ceaſe, and a
        hoarſeneſs or cough come <lb/>on, and <hi rend="italic">vice verſa</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That part of the body on which cold <lb/>is taken, or on which the perſpirable
        <lb/>matter is morbidly thickened by a <hi rend="italic">chill</hi>, <lb/>will firſt ſuffer,
        and ſhew the firſt ſigns <lb/>of the diſorder, which originally is <lb/>local. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is common for perſons coming <lb/>out of a very warm room into the o- <lb/>pen air,
        with the whole body heated <lb/>inſide and out, and the perſpiration <lb/>every where
        encreaſed, to wrap them- <lb/>ſelves up, ſo as to prevent a chill on <lb/>the ſurface of the
        body; but it is alſo <lb/>common to take no precaution for the <lb/>defence of the paſſages
        by which we <lb/>breath; ſuch perſons therefore breath <lb/>a cold damp air, which is
        repeatedly <lb/>drawn up the noſtrils; thus they take <lb/>cold, which immediately affects
        the <lb/><hi rend="italic">pituitary membrane</hi>; in about 12 hours <lb/>the head is
        ſtuffed, with difficulty of <lb/>breathing through the noſe, loſs of <lb/>ſmell, frequent
        ſneezing, a diſtillation <lb/>of a thin humour from the noſe, and a <lb/>heavineſs or pain
        in the forehead: If <lb/>proper care be taken, the humour will <lb/>flow more readily and
        plentifully; in 5 <lb/>or 6 days it will begin to thicken, and <lb/>at laſt become concocted
        mucus; the <lb/>ſneezing, and pain in the forehead go <lb/>off, the diſcharge of thick mucus
        gra- <lb/>dually diminiſhes, and health is per- <lb/>fectly reſtored. This ſpecies of cold
        is <lb/>called, a <hi rend="italic">coryza</hi>, and is a mere local af- <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>fection of that part of the <hi rend="italic">pituitary mem- <lb/>brane</hi>, which is
        ſpread over the noſtrils <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">frontal ſinuſſes</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">coryza</hi>, however, is ſometimes <lb/>produced by a more
        general check of <lb/>the perſpiration, from wet linnen, or <lb/>damp beds; for this check
        will cauſe <lb/>a ſuper-abundance of the perſpirable <lb/>matter, by repelling what ſhould
        have <lb/>been thrown off, and nature will eaſe <lb/>herſelf of the ſuperfluity, where the
        <lb/>readieſt out-let is to be found, which, <lb/>from ſome pre-diſpoſing cauſes, may
        <lb/>happen to be this emunctory. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To facilitate the cure of the <hi rend="italic">coryza</hi>, <lb/>it is often neceſſary
        to take away <lb/>blood, and to empty the bowels by <lb/>gentle aperitives, in order to eaſe
        the <lb/><hi rend="italic">pituitary membrane</hi> of that load and ten- <lb/>ſion, which
        would otherwiſe be too <lb/>great for the elaſticity of the veſſels to <lb/>overcome; and
        which, therefore, might <lb/>multiply the obſtructions, break the <lb/>veſſels, inflame the
        membrane, and <lb/>produce a fever. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If cold damp air received into the <lb/>mouth, affects that part of the <hi
          rend="italic">pituitary <lb/>membrane</hi>, which lines the mouth and <lb/>throat, the
        palate, the uvula, or the <lb/>tonſils, theſe parts will then become <lb/>the ſeat of the
          <hi rend="italic">cold</hi>; the tonſils and u- <lb/>vula will ſwell, a difficulty of
        ſwallow- <lb/>ing and diſcharging the viſcid phlegm, <lb/>with which the parts are loaded,
        will <lb/>come on, and the diſorder is then diſ- <lb/>tinguiſhed by the name of a <hi
          rend="italic">ſore throat</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">ſore throat</hi>, is ſometimes cured like <lb/>the <hi
          rend="italic">coryza</hi> by reſolution, relaxation, or a <lb/>diſcharge of mucus, and
        ſometimes by <lb/>ſuppuration and purulent diſcharges. <lb/>It ſometimes alſo happens, but
        never <lb/>without ill treatment, that the tonſils <lb/>remain enlarged and indurated, which
        <lb/>may produce bad conſequences; and <lb/>if the <hi rend="italic">chill</hi> happens
        between the tonſils, <lb/>and affects the protuberant mouth of <lb/>either of the euſtachian
        tubes, it will <lb/>occaſion an acute pain ſtretching into <lb/>the ear, eſpecially in the
        act of ſwal- <lb/>lowing; a circumſtancet which ought <lb/>always to be attended to, leſt
        the ob- <lb/>ſtruction ſhould extend inward, and in- <lb/>flame the tympanum. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If the <hi rend="italic">chill</hi> attacks the epiglottis, and <lb/>upper part of the
        larynx, a hoarſeneſs <lb/>or loſs of voice follows; if it pene- <lb/>trates deeper into the
        glottis, a diffi- <lb/>culty of breathing will be added; if <lb/>the muſcles of the larynx
        are chilled <lb/>and ſtiffened, this difficulty will en- <lb/>creaſe; and if the circulation
        of the <lb/>blood there ſhould be obſtructed to a <lb/>great degree, through neglect or ill
        <lb/>treatment, a tumour and inflammation <pb n="574"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>will ariſe, and a true inflammatory <lb/>quincy will be produced, one of the <lb/>moſt
        immediately dangerous of all <lb/>diſeaſes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When the <hi rend="italic">chill</hi> happens on the aſ- <lb/>pera arteria, it produces
        and effort to <lb/>pump up and throw off the <choice>
          <corr>viſcid</corr>
          <sic>vicid</sic>
        </choice> ob- <lb/>ſtructing mucus, which effort is called <lb/>a <hi rend="italic"
          >cough</hi>. A cough is cured like other <lb/>ſpecies of cold, by a reſolution of the
        <lb/>obſtructions in the capillaries, by an <lb/>eaſy expectoration, and by a recovery
        <lb/>of ſtrength in the ſolid parts that are af- <lb/>fected, but great care muſt be taken
        <lb/>not to uſe provocative expectorants, <lb/>for they always do harm, and are ſome-
        <lb/>times fatal. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Either of theſe ſpecies of a cold, the <lb/><hi rend="italic">coryza</hi>, the <hi
          rend="italic">ſore throat</hi>, and the <hi rend="italic">cough</hi>, <lb/>may happen
        ſeparately, and all con- <lb/>junctly without affecting the trunk, <lb/>limbs, viſcera, or
        general habit of the <lb/>body; but when they are not ſoon re- <lb/>lieved by nature or art,
        they lay the <lb/>firſt foundation of dangerous local in- <lb/>flammations, particularly in
        the head <lb/>and lungs, and of fevers of the whole <lb/>habit. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A cold ſtream of air received on any <lb/>part of the integuments about the eyes,
        <lb/>produces that ſpecies of a <hi rend="italic">cold</hi> called a <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >blight</hi>. This generally goes off eaſily <lb/>with proper care, but if neglected,
        <lb/>ſometimes degenerates into an eryſi- <lb/>pelas. A cold wind driving upon the
        <lb/>inſide of the eyelid, or the tunica ad- <lb/>nata of the eye itſelf, will ſometimes
        <lb/>cauſe an acute pain, like that occaſio- <lb/>ned by ſand, or grit, getting into the
        <lb/>eye; this generally goes off in a ſhort <lb/>time by keeping the eye ſhut, and fre-
        <lb/>quently applying the warm hand to <lb/>it, but ſometimes will cauſe a ſuffuſion <lb/>of
        red over the whole white of the <lb/>eye with great heat and pain: This <lb/>diſorder ſhould
        be immediately and <lb/>carefully attended to; confinement, <lb/>repoſe, excluſion of light
        and air, <lb/>abſtinence, proper evacuations, and <lb/>lenient applications are neceſſary to
        <lb/>prevent the moſt terrible miſchiefs; <lb/>and all cold ſtyptic collyriums muſt <lb/>be
        avoided, as pernicious in the higheſt <lb/>degree. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If the <hi rend="italic">chill</hi> falls upon the lower part <lb/>of the face, the
        integuments will be <lb/>inflated from ear to ear, and the lips <lb/>and noſtrils become
        ſwelled and hard. <lb/>This diſorder is called a <hi rend="italic">ſwelled face</hi>,
        <lb/>and, if neglected, the ſwelling ſome- <lb/>times ſuppurates, and breaks either
        <lb/>inwardly or outwardly, with very diſ- <lb/>agreeable circumſtances. </p>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When the <hi rend="italic">chill</hi> falls on the neck, <lb/>the glands ſwell and
        harden, and then <lb/>gain the denomination of <hi rend="italic">kernels</hi>;
        <lb/>ſometimes by ſtiffening the muſcles of <lb/>the neck, it produces what is called <lb/>a
          <hi rend="italic">criek</hi>. Sometimes it renders the muſ- <lb/>cles, both of the head
        and arms ri- <lb/>gid; and this rigidity, if it meets with <lb/>any idioſyncraſy of the
        habit, ſome- <lb/>times degenerates into a ſpecies of the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >tetanus</hi>, or irreſoluble rigidity, follow- <lb/>ed by convulſions and death. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If the chilling ſtroke is received on <lb/>the ear, the wax is rendered too thick,
        <lb/>and then, by obſctructing the paſſage, <lb/>it dulls the hearing: If the blood, in
        <lb/>the veſſels of this organ, be chilled, a <lb/>painful tumour will follow, which, if
        <lb/>neglected, or ill managed, by hot a- <lb/>crid ſtimulated applications will pro-
        <lb/>bably terminate in inflammations, im- <lb/>poſthumations, wakefulneſs, dilirium,
        <lb/>convulſions, ſwoonings, and death. <lb/>The ſtructure of the ear is ſo extreme- <lb/>ly
        delicate, its parts ſo numerous, its <lb/>veſſels ſo minute, its inveſting mem- <lb/>branes
        ſo exquiſitely thin, and its <lb/>connexions ſo important, that no raſh <lb/>emperical
        practices ſhould ever be tri- <lb/>ed upon it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If the <hi rend="italic">chill</hi> ſtrikes the whole trunk <lb/>and limbs of the body,
        as is frequent- <lb/>ly the caſe, by going warm on the ri- <lb/>ver, ſitting in damp rooms,
        going too <lb/>thinly clad, or continuing up late at <lb/>night without a fire, the whole
        body <lb/>will be thrown into a <hi rend="italic">ſpaſmodic</hi> ſhiver- <lb/>ing, the firſt
        and moſt uſual ſign of this <lb/>ſpecies of a cold, which, if not <hi rend="italic">imme-
          <lb/>diately</hi> taken care of, is a certain pre- <lb/>lude to a <hi rend="italic"
          >fever</hi>, if it be not a fever al- <lb/>ready begun. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It ſometimes happens, that when a <lb/>cold is taken, a gentle fever ſuper- <lb/>venes,
        attended with no other com- <lb/>plaint than a ſlight pain ſtretching in <lb/>a ſtrait line
        upon the head, in the di- <lb/>rection of the longitudinal <hi rend="italic">ſinus</hi>, the
        <lb/>ſleep is interrupted ſuddenly by unu- <lb/>ſual, though not by confuſed or fright-
        <lb/>ful dreams, and in this ſtate the diſor- <lb/>der will continue for ſeveral days,
        <lb/>without alarming the patient by any <lb/>violent ſymptom. Let it, however, be
        <lb/>remembered, that, in this ſituation, he <lb/>is in the moſt imminent danger, and
        <lb/>that if he is not relieved by the moſt <lb/>ſkilful aſſiſtance, a delirium will ſoon
        <lb/>come on by fits, which, at length, will <lb/>become perpetual, or attended by al-
        <lb/>ternate ſtupors, and end in convulſi- <lb/>ons and death. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is of the utmoſt importance upon <pb n="575"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">firſt</hi> approach of a fever, to take to <lb/>a warm bed, to
        uſe abſtinence, dilu- <lb/>ting liquors, and ſome appropriate e- <lb/>vacuations, which will
        almoſt always <lb/>carry it off in a ſhort time; the dan- <lb/>ger is from delay; for a
        fever, though <lb/>eaſily cured at the beginning, will <lb/>often baffle the moſt powerful
        reme- <lb/>dies, adminiſtered with the greateſt ſa- <lb/>gacity, when it has been ſuffered
        to <lb/>advance without a check. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When the body is preter-naturally <lb/>heated, the air is always of itſelf ſuf-
        <lb/>ficient to produce an obſtucted and <lb/>inſpiſſated perſpiration; for, with reſ-
        <lb/>pect to a body ſo heated, the air is <lb/>always cold. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>We ſhould never therefore expoſe <lb/>ourſelves, in a ſtate of reſt, to the air,
        <lb/>when we are hotter than common <lb/>cloathing, without artificial heat or
        <lb/>exerciſe, will make us. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>We ſhould never accuſtom ourſelves <lb/>to ſit in a room more than temperately
        <lb/>warm, nor to ſit <hi rend="italic">near</hi> a fire, or hover <lb/>over it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>We ſhould never go very warm into <lb/>the cold; but wait till the ſtate of the
        <lb/>body is nearer to that of the air into <lb/>which we are going. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>All currents of air are to be avoided. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When we go out of a playhouſe in <lb/>cold weather, we ſhould always throw <lb/>on ſome
        additional garment, and never <lb/>forget to guard the mouth and noſtrils <lb/>with a
        handkerchief or muff, againſt <lb/>the paſſage of a cold air into them, and <lb/>down the
        throat and windpipe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is dangerous for valitudinary per- <lb/>ſons to go to church in cold weather,
        <lb/>becauſe an abſurd cuſtom univerſally <lb/>prevails, of waſhing the church little
        <lb/>more than 12 hours before the meeting <lb/>of the congregation. In wet or damp
        <lb/>weather, whether hot or cold, it is ad- <lb/>viſeable to have a fire in the rooms
        <lb/>where we ſit or ſleep. Our cloathing <lb/>ſhould always be increaſed in propor-
        <lb/>tion to the coldneſs of the weather. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Luxurious meals are pre-diſpoſing <lb/>cauſes of diſorders ariſing from colds, <lb/>as
        they render perſons more liable to <lb/>take cold, by producing preter-natu- <lb/>ral heat,
        and a plethoric habit. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Upon the firſt ſymptom of a cold go <lb/>Inſtantly to a warm bed in a dry warm
        <lb/>room, practice ſtrict abſtinence, and <lb/>drink warm diluting liquors, ſuch as
        <lb/>may raiſe and continue a <hi rend="italic">moderate</hi>
        <lb/>ſweat till the ſymptoms vaniſh, then <lb/>dreſs in dry warm cloathing, and keep
        <lb/>houſe till 24 hours or more ſhall ſhew <lb/>longer confinement to be unneceſſary. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By this method colds, and the fevers <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>they produce, ſo fatal when fixed by <lb/>delay, will ſcarce ever fail of being
        <lb/>removed: but heating liquors and <lb/>medicines ſo often adminiſtered on <lb/>this
        occaſion, ſhould be carefully a- <lb/>voided. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This little work is written with great <lb/>knowledge of the ſubject, with a mi-
        <lb/>nute attention to all its circumſtances, <lb/>with a benevolent ſolicitude for the
        <lb/>eaſe and health of mankind, with a <lb/>preciſion that may inſtruct the prac-
        <lb/>titioner, and a perſpicuity that will <lb/>render it uſeful and entertaining to all
        <lb/>who are ſufficiently acquainted with <lb/>the technical terms of phyſick and a-
        <lb/>natomy, which in a work of this kind, <lb/>it is impoſſible to avoid. It is alſo re-
        <lb/>markable, for a delicacy extremely <lb/>difficult to be preſerved, and, there-
        <lb/>fore, very rarely found in medical <lb/>treatiſes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It would, however, be injurious to <lb/>cloſe this article, without adding, that
        <lb/>it appears by a caſe which Mr <hi rend="italic">Chandler</hi>
        <lb/>has related of one of his own patients <lb/>in a note, that we owe the knowledge
        <lb/>of the true nature and cure of the pu- <lb/>trid ſore throat, concerning which Dr
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fothergill</hi> publiſhed a treatiſe in the <lb/>year 1748, to the
        learned and ingeni- <lb/>ous Dr <hi rend="italic">Leatherland</hi>, who had made the
        <lb/>diſcovery nine years before, on occa- <lb/>ſion of the death of the two ſons of
        <lb/>the late Rt Hon. <hi rend="italic">Henry Pelham</hi>. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
