<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: On the immoderate Use of Snuff</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>On the immoderate Use of Snuff</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for D. Henry at St John's Gate.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1761</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">31</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">340</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1761_GM_0340">
    <body>
      <pb n="340"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <salute rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr <hi rend="sc">Urban</hi>, </salute>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi> Was much pleaſed to find in your <lb/>title page for <hi
          rend="italic">July</hi> laſt, <hi rend="italic">Cautions a- <lb/>gainſt the immoderate Uſe
          of Snuff</hi>; but <lb/>cannot ſay my expectations were whol- <lb/>ly anſwered in the
        performance. In- <lb/>ſtead of the certain conſequences at- <lb/>tending the immoderate uſe
        of ſnuff, <lb/>we are entertained with an accidental <lb/>caſe or two. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Polypuſſes in the noſe are frequent- <lb/>ly met with; I have ſeen many, but <lb/>not
        one that aroſe by ſnuff-taking. <lb/>The conſtant application of acrimoni- <lb/>ous bodies,
        ſhould ſeem rather tend- <lb/>ing to deſtroy, than excite thoſe fun- <lb/>gous excreſcences,
        tho' an occaſional <lb/>uſe of ſnuff might encourage them in <lb/>habits prone to their
        production, and <lb/>ſooner in the throat than in the noſe; <lb/>becauſe the acrimony of the
        ſnuff muſt <lb/>be ſo ſpent, ere it reach the throat, <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>that it can there act only as a weak <lb/>ſtimulus. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The caſe of the Recruit, was the ef- <lb/>fects of a large doſe of tobacco; and
        <lb/>how many purgatives are there in com- <lb/>mon uſe, an over-doſe whereof be- <lb/>comes
        truly poiſonous? Are not the <lb/>moſt efficacious medicines prepared <lb/>from ſtrong
        poiſons? Is it not known, <lb/>that Hemlock, the moſt poiſonous <lb/>plant in <hi
          rend="italic">England</hi>, has been diſcovered <lb/>lately to cure more than ever it has
        <lb/>killed? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Lady's caſe (tho' immediately <lb/>affected with a poignant ſnuff) muſt <lb/>take
        its original from an ill habit of <lb/>body; for no ulcer is of long continu- <lb/>ance in a
        good one. Nothing but a <lb/>cauſtic can long remain to ſtimulate <lb/>the glands of the
        noſe: The effort of <lb/>ſneezing, attended with rheum, diſ- <lb/>charges all light
        ſubſtances that are not <lb/>cauſtic. Euphorbium is a potential <lb/>cauſtic, which affects
        the glands of the <lb/>noſe with an intolerable burning; and <lb/>upon the wanton abuſe of
        it, as ſnuff, <lb/>I have known it bring on ſtrong con- <lb/>vulſions. Tobacco is a plant,
          <hi rend="italic">ſui ge- <lb/>neris</hi>, there being no other publickly <lb/>known,
        poſſeſſed with the ſame quali- <lb/>ties. 'Tis aromatic, ſtimulant, and <lb/>narcotic; 'tis
        a very warm detergent, <lb/>but not properly corroſive: Uſed as <lb/>ſnuff, 'tis a moſt
        grateful cephalic, re- <lb/>lieving and cheering the brain inſtan- <lb/>taneouſly, and is
        often a cure for the <lb/>head-ach, to thoſe who are not accuſ- <lb/>tomed to it. To ſmoke
        it, produces <lb/>the moſt agreeable, and oft-times the <lb/>moſt uſeful effect, with thoſe
        who can <lb/>bear it. It ſo becomes uſeful in all <lb/>rheumatic caſes, that are not
        attended <lb/>with a fever; and in dropſies, if they <lb/>will forbear drinking after it. A
        pipe <lb/>of it in a morning is very uſeful in <lb/>groſs habits; and the ſupport it af-
        <lb/>fords the ſpirits, longer than any one <lb/>thing elſe, by chewing it, plainly
        <lb/>proves it a very high cordial, which, <lb/>like many other cordials, will intoxi-
        <lb/>cate thoſe who are not accuſtomed to <lb/>them. Its narcotic quality I take to <lb/>be
        accidental, and in habits that can- <lb/>not well bear it; for the ſpirits being
        <lb/>thereby exalted and rarefied to a very <lb/>high degree, fly off, and neceſſarily
        <lb/>leave the body ſluggiſh and ſleepy. <lb/>'Tis very uſeful to old people in ge-
        <lb/>neral, diſſipating and diſcharging that <lb/>rheum wherewith they abound, in
        <lb/>proportion to the decay of natural <lb/>heat. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A phyſician of <hi rend="italic">Newcaſtle under <sic>Line</sic></hi>, <lb/>whoſe lady
        was afflicted with an aſth- <pb n="341"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>ma, prevailed on her to hold a little <lb/>tobacco in her mouth, till ſhe began <lb/>to
        reach, and then put her in bed, to <lb/>encourage ſweating; which, upon a <lb/>few
        repetitions, wholly freed her from <lb/>that diſorder. And I am inclined to <lb/>think, that
        an extract of it would be <lb/>more uſeful than the <hi rend="italic">Gum Ammon.</hi> and
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Squills</hi>, ſo much depended on. The <lb/>Doctor's partial
        declamation againſt <lb/>this plant may have taken riſe from an <lb/>attempt to ſmoke it,
        and becoming <lb/>ſick: However, I very ſeriouſly join <lb/>with him againſt the abuſe of
        it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To young people it can be but very <lb/>rarely uſeful, moſtly prejudicial. To <lb/>the
        young ladies, I offer the following <lb/>obſervations: </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Being once in company, where, a- <lb/>mongſt a number <choice>
          <corr>of</corr>
          <sic>oſ</sic>
        </choice> ladies, the toaſt <lb/>was a ſnuff-taker, who was admired by <lb/>all the
        gentlemen, and, as I obſerved, <lb/>more particularly by a young gentle- <lb/>man of my
        acquaintance; the next <lb/>time I ſaw him, I aſked him about it, <lb/>and he owned he had
        been ſmitten; <lb/>but waiting the opportunity for a kiſs, <lb/>proved his cure, her breath
        ſmelt ſo <lb/>abominably ſtrong of tobacco. There <lb/>is another ill effect of
        ſnuſſ-taking, <lb/>worthy their notice, that it tends to <lb/>disfigure a pretty face with a
        very large <lb/>noſe, which is occaſioned by the fre- <lb/>quent ſqueezing and pulling it
        with <lb/>the handkerchief. Moreover, the <lb/>glands of the noſe, by frequent irrita-
        <lb/>tion, ſoon become diſtended, ſo as to <lb/>render the voice broad and maſculine,
        <lb/>together with a diſagreeable ſnuffling <lb/>in the noſe. Let them alſo obſerve,
        <lb/>that blowing the noſe, hawking, and <lb/>ſpitting, are ever in ſome meaſure of-
        <lb/>fenſive. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A gentlewoman, for whom I had re- <lb/>ſpect, came on a viſit to ſpend a few <lb/>days
        with us; but the continual ſounds <lb/>of her loud coughing, hawking, ſpit- <lb/>ting,
        ſneezing, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> became ſo diſagree- <lb/>able, as cured the whole
        family of ta- <lb/>king ſnuff for a month after. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There yet remains a ſuperior con- <lb/>ſideration, of general importance, that <lb/>by
        irritating the glands to a conſtant <lb/>diſcharge, they anticipate the infirmi- <lb/>ties
        of old age; which, if ever they <lb/>live to ſee, will ſo oppreſs them with <lb/>accumulated
        loads of phlegm, that the <lb/>continuance of their lives will depend <lb/>on the continual
        exerciſes of cough- <lb/>ing, hawking, and ſpitting, which will <lb/>terminate their days
        with miſery to <lb/>themſelves, and all that are about <lb/>them, and probably conclude with
        be- <lb/>ing choaked by phlegm in their ſleep. </p>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I confeſs myſelf too fond of ſnuff, <lb/>and have often ſeriouſly conſidered the
        <lb/>ill conſequences of it. I find that an <lb/>idle amuſement prevails more than any
        <lb/>real occaſion for it; that it gives me <lb/>more pleaſure by the flavour than its
        <lb/>ſtimulus. So I get the richeſt flavour'd <lb/>ſnuff, and to every ounce add half a
        <lb/>drachm of ſaffron, carefully dried and <lb/>powdered, which makes it very rich,
        <lb/>and much leſs of it anſwers my pur- <lb/>poſe. I allow myſelf the free uſe of <lb/>it
        in the morning before breakfaſt, <lb/>which I find uſeful to me; but no <lb/>more afterwards
        the day throughout. </p>
      <signed rend="align-right">
        <lb/>W. </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
