<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Particulars of the Life of Lewis Cornaro</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Particulars of the Life of Lewis Cornaro</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for D. Henry at St John's Gate.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1761</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">31</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">61</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1761_GM_0061">
    <body>
      <pb n="61"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <salute rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr <hi rend="sc">Urban</hi>, </salute>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE precarious ſtate of old peo- <lb/>ple, as repreſented in your
        Mag. <lb/>for <hi rend="italic">October</hi> laſt, by the Bp of <hi rend="italic"
          >Avranches</hi>, <lb/>is indeed a melancholy truth. You ſay <lb/>he was betwixt 80 and 90
        years of age <lb/>when he wrote it. I will, however, <lb/>give you the authority of one at
        his <lb/>age, and older, who undertakes to in- <lb/>form mankind, how to attain extreme
        <lb/>old age, without being ſubject to thoſe <pb n="62"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>gloomy terrors of ſudden death. A <lb/>man who at the age of 70, which 'twas
        <lb/>thought he could not ſurvive three <lb/>days, could ſay to Death, <hi rend="italic"
          >keep thy diſ- <lb/>tance</hi>; and to the phyſician, <hi rend="italic">I have no
          <lb/>need of thee</hi>. The caſe was, he was run <lb/>away with by his coach-horſes, had
        <lb/>one leg and one arm put out of joint, <lb/>and was otherways violently bruiſed.
        <lb/>The phyſician ordered he ſhould loſe <lb/>blood, to prevent a fever: He allowed
        <lb/>the ſurgeons to ſet his bones, but would <lb/>not ſuffer them to bleed him, and ſoon
        <lb/>recovered. At 83 years of age, he <lb/>could mount a horſe without help, was
        <lb/>always merry, always pleaſed, always <lb/>in humour. In ſummer time he tra- <lb/>verſed
        the fields with a ſetting-dog, or <lb/>with tarriers, and viſited the moſt in- <lb/>genious
        men in the neighbouring towns, <lb/>diſcourſing with them on architecture, <lb/>painting,
        ſculpture, mathematics, and <lb/>agriculture, as if inquiſitive after new <lb/>diſcoveries.
        He could ſee and hear as <lb/>well as he ever did in his life, and all <lb/>his ſenſes were
        perfect. The change <lb/>of beds was no hindrance to his re- <lb/>poſe. At that age he
        compoſed a co- <lb/>medy, which was received with ap- <lb/>plauſe. Some affirm, that a man
        after <lb/>he is 70, is but half alive; but in his <lb/>treatiſe on long life, he ſays, he
        would <lb/>not change his age and life for the moſt <lb/>flouriſhing youth which lays no re-
        <lb/>ſtraint upon its ſenſes. And what <lb/>makes moſt to the preſent purpoſe, he <lb/>adds,
        that he is certain he ſhall not fall <lb/>ſick; he is aſſured that he ſhall live ſe-
        <lb/>veral years in health, and that he ſhall <lb/>long enjoy the pleaſure of being in the
        <lb/>world, which is certainly very com- <lb/>fortable, when a man knows how to <lb/>make a
        right uſe of it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the 86th year of his age, his con- <lb/>ſtitution was good, his teeth, his voice,
        <lb/>his memory, his heart, were in as good <lb/>a condition as ever they were in the
        <lb/>briſkeſt days of his youth, nor had his <lb/>judgment loſt any thing of its clear-
        <lb/>neſs or force. Inſtead of drowſineſs <lb/>after meals, he was rather more chear-
        <lb/>ful; and uſed, preſently after riſing from <lb/>table, to write, or ſtudy, without pre-
        <lb/>judice. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>At 91 years of age, he continued <lb/>healthful, briſk, and airy, reliſhed his
        <lb/>food, ſlept quietly, and what is very <lb/>remarkable, his voice grew more tune-
        <lb/>able than ever, and he could chant his <lb/>morning hymn more eaſily than he <lb/>could
        in his youth; which, ſays he, are <lb/>infallible ſigns that I have ſtill a great <lb/>while
        to live. He concludes wiſhing, <lb/>that all like him may live to a happy <lb/>old age<choice>
          <corr>.</corr>
          <sic/>
        </choice>
      </p>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In a letter from his grand-daughter, <lb/>ſubjoined to this work, we are inform-
        <lb/>ed, he was not miſtaken, but lived to <lb/>paſs his 100th year; his mind and eyes
        <lb/>were clear to the laſt moment, and his <lb/><hi rend="italic">exit</hi> was only like a
        little kind of faint- <lb/>ing fit. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I can eaſily apprehend that theſe de- <lb/>clarations of his will appear exceſſively
        <lb/>vain and preſumptuous; but when this <lb/>confidence is found to ariſe from ra-
        <lb/>tional and natural principles, joined to <lb/>the long experience of a virtuous and
        <lb/>religious perſon, ſuch cenſure muſt va- <lb/>niſh. The perſon I have been ſpeaking
        <lb/>of was <hi rend="italic">Lewis Cornaro</hi>, a noble <hi rend="italic">Venetian</hi>,
        <lb/>who has left a ſmall treatiſe, entitled, <lb/><hi rend="italic">The ſure way of
          attaining a long and <lb/>healthful life</hi>. His inſtructions are plain <lb/>and ſimple,
        and for that reaſon, per- <lb/>haps, ſlighted, as was the Prophet's <lb/>preſcription to <hi
          rend="italic">Naaman</hi>; for they whol- <lb/>ly conſiſt in ſtrict temperance. He in-
        <lb/>culcates, with as great judgment as ex- <lb/>perience, what ſeems little known, or
        <lb/>little regarded, that men ſhould abridge <lb/>their quantity of food, in proportion
        <lb/>as they advance in years. In Mr <hi rend="italic">Ad- <lb/>diſon</hi>'s <hi
          rend="italic">Spectator</hi>, on Temperance, he il- <lb/>luſtrates this doctrine, by the
        authority <lb/>of the great example here mentioned; <lb/>and at the ſame time eſtabliſhes
        the au- <lb/>thenticity of this little hiſtory. <hi rend="italic">Cheney</hi>
        <lb/>frequently quotes <hi rend="italic">Cornaro</hi>; but <hi rend="italic">Cheney</hi>
        <lb/>has either groſly miſtaken him, or was <lb/>unable to reduce his enormous bulk
        <lb/>within <hi rend="italic">Cornaro</hi>'s rules: for a belly-full <lb/>of milk, three
        times a day, was incon- <lb/>ſiſtent with <hi rend="italic">Cornaro</hi>'s regimen; nor does
        <lb/>it appear that <hi rend="italic">Cornaro</hi> uſed any milk. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In your Magazine for <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 1759, <lb/>I made ſome obſervations
        on the regi- <lb/>men of old people, and gave ſome ge- <lb/>neral rules, forbidding
        chocolate and <lb/>eggs, not ſuſpecting any of your readers <lb/>living by this rule of <hi
          rend="italic">Cornaro</hi>; for he <lb/>could diſpenſe with yolks of eggs; and <lb/>if any
        one will reduce his quantity of <lb/>food to <hi rend="italic">Cornaro</hi>'s ſtandard, I
        will allow <lb/>him yolks of eggs and chocolate too, if <lb/>he pleaſes; for as you decreaſe
        in quan- <lb/>tity, you muſt enrich in quality. </p>
      <signed rend="italic align-right">
        <lb/>Yours, &amp;c. <hi rend="roman">W.</hi>
      </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
