<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Michell: A remarkable Instance of the Virtues of Hemlock.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Henry Michell</persName>
            </author>
            <title>A remarkable Instance of the Virtues of Hemlock.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for D. Henry at St John's Gate.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1761</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">31</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">435</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1761_GM_0435">
    <body>
      <pb n="435"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <salute rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr <hi rend="sc">Urban</hi>, </salute>
      <p>
        <lb/>
          <figure>
            <figDesc>Decorative frame around the letter "H".</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <hi rend="dc(8)">H</hi>Owever great at <hi rend="italic">Vien- <lb/>na</hi>, and elſewhere the <lb/>ſucceſs
        may have <lb/>been from the uſe of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Hemlock</hi>, it has not, <lb/>as
        I am informed, <lb/>been equal to the ex- <lb/>pectations of practi- <lb/>tioners here. I
        therefore ſend you, <lb/>and if you pleaſe you may lay it before <lb/>the public, thro' the
        means of your <lb/>Magazine, the ſucceſs of its admini- <lb/>ſtration in my own caſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Having for many years been corpu- <lb/>lent, and being obliged to ſit many <lb/>hours
        every day, occaſioned, ſeveral <lb/>years ſince, my legs to ſwell, and fre- <lb/>quently to
        become very hard and pain- <lb/>ful. At times, for theſe four years, <lb/>this has
        encreaſed, and ſeveral ulcers <lb/>have broke out in both my legs, <lb/>which, though they
        ſometimes have <lb/>been healed, they left my legs hard <lb/>and ſwelled, and my tendons
        were ſo <lb/>contracted from the calf to the heel, <lb/>that I could not ſet my feet flat to
        the <lb/>ground without the greateſt pain. I <lb/>was conſtrained therefore to walk upon
        <lb/>my toes, ſupported by ſticks. Since <lb/><hi rend="italic">Chriſtmas</hi> laſt, my
        complaints grew <lb/>worſe, my legs ſwelled more, the ul- <lb/>cers broke out again,
        increaſed in their <lb/>number, extent, and ſoreneſs; and, <lb/>notwithſtanding all the
        means I could <lb/>procure, they would not heal; inſo- <lb/>much, that by the beginning of
          <hi rend="italic">May</hi>
        <lb/>my legs and thighs were very greatly <lb/>diſtended, extremely hard and painful,
        <lb/>of a deep red colour, and numberleſs <lb/>ulcers occupied both my legs from my
        <lb/>knees to my ancles. Many of theſe <lb/>were very large and deep, and ſur- <lb/>rounded
        by high callous lips, and <lb/>gleeted a thin ſharp humour, in ſuch <lb/>a quantity that it
        ran into my ſhoes, <lb/>and upon the floor where I ſtood, and <lb/>wherever it touched my
        fleſh, it bro't <lb/>other ulcers. My feet were likewiſe <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>prodigiouſly ſwelled, and I could ſcarce <lb/>move my ancles, and not in the leaſt
        <lb/>my toes. My ſorrows did not end <lb/>here, for upon lying down in my bed <lb/>the
        warmth thereof made my ulcers <lb/>yet ſorer, and excited ſuch an itching <lb/>all over my
        body, that I was conſtrain- <lb/>ed to leave my bed, and have ſet up- <lb/>right in my chair
        great part of the <lb/>night, not daring to lye down. The <lb/>continuance in this poſture
        made, if <lb/>poſſible, my condition worſe; as my <lb/>legs grew more diſtended, and conſe-
        <lb/>quently my ulcers increaſed in num- <lb/>ber, and the old ones became more <lb/>foul,
        and greatly enlarged. Not on- <lb/>ly me legs and thighs, but my arms <lb/>and head were
        ſwelled and inflamed. <lb/>I was hot and dry, and my ſpittle, <lb/>which had for ſome months
        been <lb/>brackiſh, now became very ſalt. I <lb/>had been in hopes that the diſcharge
        <lb/>from my legs would have drained off <lb/>the humours and relieved me, but I
        <lb/>experienced the reverſe; for the great- <lb/>er my diſcharge was, the more my
        <lb/>complaints encreaſed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In this ſtate I was in the beginning <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">May</hi> laſt, and as I
        had taken a great <lb/>deal of purging phyſic, had tryed va- <lb/>rious applications, and
        had gone thro' <lb/>ſuch other regimen as had been direc- <lb/>ted, and remained,
        nevertheleſs, in <lb/>this lamentable condition, I deſpaired <lb/>of relief, and my life
        became almoſt <lb/>inſupportable. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Under theſe circumſtances, and be- <lb/>lieving myſelf to be in a great degree
        <lb/>dropſical, I conſulted Dr <hi rend="italic">Watſon</hi>, who, <lb/>after having weighed
        all the particu- <lb/>lars, was of a contrary opinion, and <lb/>directed me to loſe 12
        ounces of blood, <lb/>and to take a cooling purge; he alſo <lb/>preſcribed that I ſhould
        have my legs <lb/>fomented every night and morning <lb/>with a decoction of <hi
          rend="italic">hemlock</hi> for half an <lb/>hour, and that a poultice made of the
        <lb/>boyled herb, and beat up with oat- <lb/>meal and lard, ſhould be applied <pb n="436"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>warm after each fomenting, from my <lb/>knees to my ancles, and to be chan- <lb/>ged
        twice a day. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I muſt here obſerve, that as other <lb/>plants are much like, and had in other
        <lb/>inſtances been uſed for <hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi>, the Dr <lb/>was ſo obliging as
        to examine the herb <lb/>I made uſe of, not only to ſatisfy him- <lb/>ſelf of the identity
        of the herb, but <lb/>likewiſe of its condition. I was alſo <lb/>directed to abſtain for the
        preſent from <lb/>animal food, and to drink plentifully <lb/>of milk and water, and of any
        other <lb/>diluting fluid. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The ſecond night after theſe appli- <lb/>cations I ſlept in bed, which I had not
        <lb/>done for a great while; and though I <lb/>was frequently waked by the itching of
        <lb/>my body, as well as by the ſmarting of <lb/>my ulcers, I continued all night in
        <lb/>bed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>At the end of a week, during all <lb/>which time I found myſelf growing <lb/>eaſier, my
        perſpiration in the night <lb/>was reſtored, which had left me a <lb/>conſiderable time. My
        thighs, arms, <lb/>and head changed their deep red co- <lb/>lour for one leſs intenſe, and
        were <lb/>quite reduced to their natural dimen- <lb/>ſions. My itching was leſs, and my
        <lb/>ſkin peeled all over my body; my ſpit- <lb/>tle was leſs ſalt; my legs and feet con-
        <lb/>tinued in the ſame degree of diſtenti- <lb/>on, but were far leſs red and painful,
        <lb/>and their diſcharge was conſiderably <lb/>decreaſed. I could move the toes of <lb/>one
        leg, but not of the other; the <lb/>purge was repeated at intervals, and <lb/>the
        fomentation and poultice continu- <lb/>ed. At the end of the ſecond week, <lb/>the ſkin of
        my thighs, and upper parts <lb/>of my body, was of its natural co- <lb/>lour; my itching
        gone, and my ſpit- <lb/>tle was natural and taſteleſs. The <lb/>ſwelling of my legs and feet
        was much <lb/>leſs, and I could move the toes of the <lb/>other foot. I had likewiſe a much
        <lb/>freer uſe of the joints of my ancles <lb/>than I had for a conſiderable time. <lb/>The
        diſcharge from the large ulcers <lb/>was leſs in quantity and well concoc- <lb/>ted; their
        callous lips were ſoftened <lb/>and of a good colour, and they gave <lb/>me little or no
        pain. Beſides, theſe <lb/>ulcers filled up a-pace, and a vaſt num- <lb/>ber of the ſmall
        ones were entirely <lb/>healed. Under theſe happy appearan- <lb/><choice>
          <corr>ces</corr>
          <sic>ances</sic>
        </choice> the fomentation and poultice <lb/>were chearfully continued, as they <lb/>were
        before directed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Not to be too tedious in my recital, <lb/>I muſt inform you, that at the end of <lb/>a
        month, during which time the diſ- <lb/>charge became leſs and leſs, every ul- <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>cer in both my legs was entirely filled <lb/>up and healed, their callous lips were
        <lb/>diſſolved, and, from the ſubſiding of <lb/>their tumours, my legs were leſs than
        <lb/>they had been for ſome years. I was <lb/>directed, therefore, to diſcontinue the
        <lb/>fomentation, but as there were yet <lb/>conſiderable indurations in the lower
        <lb/>parts of my legs, and upon my ſhin- <lb/>bones, the poultice was continued. <lb/>This I
        wore for a fortnight longer, or <lb/>thereabouts, when all my ulcers being <lb/>firmly
        cicatrized, and the indurations <lb/>ſoftened, it was left off. Though my <lb/>legs were
        quite well and reduced to <lb/>their natural ſize, the ſkin of them, <lb/>from being ſo long
        diſtended, was ſoft <lb/>and flabby; I was therefore directed to <lb/>wear ſtraight
        ſtockings, which was ac- <lb/>cordingly complied with. I could <lb/>now ſet my feet flat
        upon the ground, <lb/>which I had not done for four years, <lb/>could move my ancles and
        toes as well <lb/>as ever, and I could walk with as <lb/>much eaſe and freedom as ever I
        could <lb/>in my life. I then was permitted to <lb/>eat animal food, and to live as I was
        <lb/>accuſtomed to do. However, as I am <lb/>of a corpulent habit, by way of pre-
        <lb/>caution I was directed to drink occaſi- <lb/>onally ſome ſea water, which I have
        <lb/>hitherto continued. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is now three months ſince I left <lb/>off the pultice; my legs continue per-
        <lb/>fectly well, not ſo much as a pimple <lb/>has appeared upon them this autumn, <lb/>and
        I never was in better health in <lb/>my life. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If, during this ſucceſsful treatment, <lb/>I had uſed a great variety of external
        <lb/>and internal medicines, though I had <lb/>been cured, I ſhould not have known <lb/>to
        which to have attributed theſe ſalu- <lb/>tary effects; as poſſibly every one of <lb/>them
        might, in ſome degree, have con- <lb/>ſpired thereto; but as, throughout the <lb/>whole,
        except ſome purges, of which <lb/>I had taken numbers before, I uſed <lb/>nothing but the
        fomentation and poul- <lb/>tice of <hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi>, as before-mentioned.
        <lb/>I cannot but attribute my cure princi- <lb/>pally to the virtues of the <hi
          rend="italic">hemlock</hi>, <lb/>which I think in my caſe were very re- <lb/>markable;
        &amp; as far as one inſtance will <lb/>go, are a ſtrong argument of its ex- <lb/>cellent
        effects. I pretend not to de- <lb/>termine how far it has been uſeful in <lb/>other caſes,
        and under other direction; <lb/>and I cannot here ſuppreſs my grati- <lb/>tude to Dr <hi
          rend="italic">Watſon</hi> for his humanity <lb/>and kind attention to me during the
        <lb/>continuance of my illneſs. </p>
      <signed rend="italic align-right">
        <lb/>Your's, &amp;c. <hi rend="sc">Henry Michell</hi>. </signed>
      <dateline rend="italic align-center">
        <lb/>From my Chambers, New Inn, Oct. 16 </dateline>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
