<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Cautions against the immoderate Use of Snuff.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Cautions against the immoderate Use of Snuff. By Dr. J. Hill.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for D. Henry at St John's Gate.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1761</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">31</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">293</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1761_GM_0293">
    <body>
      <pb n="293"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <head rend="italic align-center">
        <lb/>Cautions againſt the immoderate Uſe of <lb/>Snuff. By Dr <hi rend="roman">J. Hill</hi>. </head>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE Doctor's deſcription of to- <lb/>bacco merits attention. <q
          rend="quotes">To- <lb/>bacco </q>, ſays he, <q rend="quotes"> is a
          narcotick with pe- <lb/>culiar acrimony. 'Tis ſuch a body as <lb/>art might prepare, by
          mixing opium <lb/>with euphorbium. The herb itſelf is <lb/>ſo nearly poiſonous, that no
          phyſician <lb/>gives it inwardly. When by accident <lb/>it has been ſwallowed; or from
          exter- <lb/>nal uſe on any wounded part, has made <lb/>its way into the body, the firſt
          effort <lb/>is that of extreme irritation; and, af- <lb/>ter this, <sic>comes</sic> on the
          worſt effects of <lb/>opium, outragious vomitings, and <lb/>purgings; and afterwards deep
          ſleep, <lb/>but not without convulſions. </q>
      </p>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From theſe the Doctor endeavours to <lb/>prove, that ſnuff, by corroding the
        <lb/>nerves of the noſtrils, impairs, and often <lb/>deſtroys the ſenſe of ſmelling; that
        fall- <lb/>ing into the mouth the ſaliva becomes <lb/>tinctured by it, and the acrimony of
        the <lb/>tobacco ſo much injures the nerves of <lb/>the tongue, that the flavour of fruits
        <lb/>and the more delicate foods cannot be <lb/>perceived; that ſome of the fluid <lb/>which
        the glands of the noſe naturally <lb/>diſcharge, will be drawn, tinctured by <lb/>ſnuff,
        with the ſaliva of the mouth, <lb/>into the ſtomach; and tobacco will <lb/>bring on all the
        miſchiefs that attend <lb/>a bad digeſtion; that the œſophagus, <lb/>the paſſage from the
        mouth to the ſto- <lb/>mach, while it receive the virtues of <lb/>the ſaliva impregnated
        with ſnuff, may <lb/>at ſome time retain a portion of it, <lb/>which by irritating the
        nerves will oc- <lb/>caſion an inflammation that no hand <lb/>can reach. That the acrimony
        of <lb/>ſnuff is able to produce in thoſe parts <lb/>with which it comes in contact dange-
        <lb/>rous ſwellings, and excreſcences; and <lb/>that there is great reaſon to believe
        <lb/>that polypuſſes in the noſe are occa- <lb/>ſioned by ſnuff. The Doctor relates a
        <lb/>caſe of a perſon who took a great deal <lb/>of ſnuff, and died famiſhed, a diſorder
        <lb/>in the throat hindering his ſwallowing. <lb/>On opening his body, there was found
        <lb/>a polypus in his throat which filled up <lb/>the whole paſſage. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Doctor <hi rend="italic">Hill</hi> endeavours further to <lb/>ſhew, that ſnuff, by
        cauſing indigeſtion, <lb/>lays a foundation for the worſt diſor- <lb/>ders; hence
        immediately ariſe wind, <lb/>yawning, belching, and continual <lb/>ſickneſs and vomiting;
        and that if it <lb/>reduce corpulence, it is by ſpoiling <lb/>the digeſtion. He adds, that
        in ſome <lb/>perſons it evidently dulls the appre- <lb/>henſion, and by a long courſe brings
        <lb/>on ſtupidity, and, as it were, a lethar- <lb/>gy of the mind; and that if any ſhould
        <lb/>object that ſnuff aſſiſts, inſtead of im- <lb/>pairing, the imagination, its effects in
        <lb/>quickening the imagination is like <lb/>that of a glaſs of ſpirituous liquors in
        <lb/>giving chearfulneſs, it is a falſe fire in <lb/>both; it is moſt perceived by thoſe
        <lb/>who are leaſt accuſtomed to the thing; <lb/>and uſe wears it off. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Among other inſtances of the bad <lb/>effects of tobacco, the Doctor recites <lb/>the
        following. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">A young recruit who had juſt learnt <lb/>to drink drams and chew
          tobacco, lay <lb/>intoxicated in ſuch a poſture, that his <lb/>ſaliva, tinctured ſtrongly
          with the <lb/>herb, ran for ſome time down his <lb/>throat. He ſoon vomited, and fell in-
            <pb n="294"/>
          <cb n="1"/>
          <lb/>to a purging. After an hour he ſunk <lb/>into a depp ſleep, but was waked by
          <lb/>ſtrong convulſions; he laughed immo- <lb/>derately; and the next moment cried;
          <lb/>his ſight was almoſt loſt; and he knew <lb/>nothing of where he was; but ſeemed
          <lb/>as one mad. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><choice>
          <corr/>
          <sic>'</sic>
        </choice>Another inſtance he remembers of <lb/>a moſt terrible ulcer in the noſe, in a
        <lb/>perſon that took a vaſt quantity of <lb/>ſnuff. <q rend="quotes">The perſon was a lady
          of a ſo- <lb/>ber and virtuous life. She had been <lb/>long accuſtomed to ſnuff, and took
          it <lb/>in very great quantity. After the uſe <lb/>of about a quarter of a pound of ſnuff,
          <lb/>which ſhe perceived to be particularly <lb/>acrid, ſhe felt a ſtrange ſoreneſs in the
          <lb/>upper part of her left noſtril, running, <lb/>as ſhe expreſſed it, toward the griſtle
          <lb/>of the noſe; ſhe left off that particu- <lb/>lar parcel of ſnuff, but continued to
          <lb/>take the uſual kind as much as ever. <lb/>No ſwelling was perceived; but after <lb/>a
          little time came on a diſcharge of a <lb/>very offenſive matter, not in great
          <lb/>quantity, but of an intolerable ſmell, <lb/>and the more ſo to her, as ſhe was na-
          <lb/>turally a perſon of great delicacy. <lb/>The diſcharge encreaſed, and it ſoon
          <lb/>became neceſſary for her to leave off <lb/>ſnuff. A ſurgeon was employed, but <lb/>to
          very little purpoſe; the ſymptoms <lb/>continued; the ulcer encreaſed, and <lb/>from time
          to time, pieces of the bone <lb/>came away. Death, from another diſ- <lb/>eaſe, put an end
          to that miſery, which <lb/>all the art of phyſick and ſurgery ſeem- <lb/>ed very little
          able to relieve. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Many other caſes are produced of <lb/>the bad conſequences attending the <lb/>practice
        of ſnuff-taking, in creating <lb/>diſorders in the noſtrils, throat and <lb/>ſtomach; and he
        concludes with earn- <lb/>eſtly recommending a forbearance from <lb/>this pernicious herb.
      </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
