<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Some Account of a Second Essay on the medicinal Virtues of
          Hemlock</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Some Account of a Second Essay on the medicinal Virtues of Hemlock; by Anthony
              Storck, Physician to the Empress Queen. (For an Account of the first Part, and of the
              Issue of some Experiments made here in Consequence of it, see Vol. xxx. p. 246, and
              this Vol. p. 435-6.) </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for D. Henry at St John's Gate.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1761</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">31</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">624</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1761_GM_0624">
    <body>
      <pb n="624"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/>Some Account of a ſecond Eſſay on the me- <lb/>dicinal Virtues of Hemlock; by <hi
          rend="roman">Anthony <lb/>Storck</hi>, Phyſician to the Empreſs Queen. <lb/>(For an
        Account of the firſt Part, and of <lb/>the Iſſue of ſome Experiments made here <lb/>in
        Conſequence of it, ſee Vol. <hi rend="roman">xxx.</hi> p. <lb/>246, and this Vol. p. 435-6.) </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">D</hi>Octor <hi rend="italic">Storck</hi> obſerves, in his pre-
        <lb/>face, that the oftener he has ad- <lb/>miniſtered the hemlock, the more op-
        <lb/>portunities he has had of admiring the <lb/>virtue of the plant, and this ſecond
        <lb/>eſſay conſiſts chiefly of narratives of <lb/>caſes in which he has uſed it himſelf,
        <lb/>and ſeen the effects of it uſed by others. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It appears from theſe caſes, that the <lb/>Hemlock has perfectly cured diſeaſes <lb/>ſo
        different as the gout, the ſcurvy, <lb/>the rheumatiſm, ſchirrous ſwellings, <lb/>and
        ulcerated cancers, but Dr <hi rend="italic">Storck</hi>
        <lb/>does not therefore conclude that this <lb/>plant will always cure theſe diſeaſes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In different conſtitutions, and un- <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>der different circumſtances, the ſame <lb/>alteration of the ſolids, or the ſame
        <lb/>corruption of the fluids produce very <lb/>different effects, ſo that mercury ſome-
        <lb/>times fails to cure the venereal diſ- <lb/>eaſe, and the bark an intermittent fe-
        <lb/>ver. For cancers, however, Hemlock <lb/>is almoſt a certain and radical cure. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Hemlock uſed by Dr <hi rend="italic">Storck</hi> is <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
          >large, common, ſpotted, ſtinking Hem- <lb/>lock</hi>, called by <hi rend="italic"
          >Linnæus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Conium ſemini- <lb/>bus ſtriatis</hi>, and by <hi
          rend="italic">Cluſius</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Cicutaria ma- <lb/>jor vulgaris</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>For an <hi rend="italic">extract</hi>, this plant is beſt ga- <lb/>thered when its
        flowers are full blown, <lb/>and every part of the plant, <hi rend="italic">except the
          <lb/>root</hi>, may be uſed for this purpoſe, and <lb/>the extract is to be made by
        preſſing <lb/>the juice into a glazed earthen veſſel, <lb/>and placing it over a ſlow fire,
        taking <lb/>care to ſtir it often, till it is boiled to a <lb/>proper conſiſtence. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Dr <hi rend="italic">Storck</hi> obſerves, that, in general, <lb/>apothecaries have
        been too careful in <lb/>depurating this juice, for he prefers <lb/>that extract which is
        thickeſt, and al- <lb/>moſt equal to a pulp. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>An extract may alſo be prepared <lb/>from a decoction of the dried plant, <lb/>when it
        cannot be procured freſh, but <lb/>ſuch extract will be leſs efficacious. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>We are alſo told that ſome hundred <lb/>weight of the extract prepared from <lb/>the
          <hi rend="italic">dry plant</hi>, have been ſent from <hi rend="italic">Vi- <lb/>enna</hi>
        into other countries, without Dr <lb/><hi rend="italic">Storck</hi>'s knowledge, and he
        expreſſes <lb/>great uneaſineſs on that account. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Among a great number of caſes <lb/>which prove the amazing efficacy of <lb/>Hemlock,
        are the following: </p>
      <floatingText type="" subtype="casereport">
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>CASE I. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>A woman about 22, had, from a <lb/>child, been afflicted with ſchirrous
          <lb/>ſwellings of the glands, under the ears <lb/>and about the jaw: About five years
          <lb/>ago a large ſwelling aroſe in her left <lb/>cheek, which extended itſelf down the
          <lb/>ſame ſide of the neck to her collar- <lb/>bone, and in a ſhort time became as
          <lb/>hard as a flint, though without pain. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Within the laſt three years, this <lb/>ſwelling encreaſed to the ſize of a <lb/>man's
          head, the glands of the arm-pits <lb/>became alſo hard, and no leſs than 15 <lb/>ſchirrous
          tumours, the ſmalleſt of <lb/>which was as big as a hen's egg, form- <lb/>ed themſelves on
          the right ſide of the <lb/>neck; both her breaſts alſo became <lb/>ſchirrous. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This woman, hideous as her appear- <lb/>ance muſt be, contracted the venereal
          <lb/>diſeaſe, for which ſhe was brought to <lb/>the hoſpital. </p>
        <pb n="625"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Of the venereal diſeaſe ſhe was cured <lb/>in about five weeks by antivenereal
          <lb/>decoctions, purges mixed with calo- <lb/>mel, and then a ſolution of the cor-
          <lb/>roſſive ſublimate in malt ſpirits, with <lb/>ſtrong and plentiful decoctions of Bur-
          <lb/>dock root. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The ſchirruſes, however, remained <lb/>in the ſame ſtate, and the patient re-
          <lb/>fuſing to continue longer in the hoſpi- <lb/>tal, was diſmiſſed. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>She was, ſoon after, detected in <lb/>ſome crime for which ſhe was thrown <lb/>into
          priſon, and was there ſeized <lb/>again with a fever which brought her <lb/>to the
          hoſpital. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>When ſhe was cured of the fever, <lb/>ſhe choſe rather to continue in the
          <lb/>hoſpital than to go back to priſon, and <lb/>thus a fair opportunity offered to try
          <lb/>what effect the Hemlock would pro- <lb/>duce againſt ſwellings ſo large, and of
          <lb/>ſo long continuance. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Dr <hi rend="italic">Storck</hi> adminiſtered morning and <lb/>evening four pills of
          the extract, each <lb/>weighing two grains, without making <lb/>any external application,
          and in five <lb/>days the glandulous ſwellings became <lb/>moveable, and the large
          ſwelling on <lb/>the left ſide of the neck, ſofter: By <lb/>this it appeared, that
          Hemlock, admi- <lb/><choice>
            <corr>niſtered</corr>
            <sic>miniſtered</sic>
          </choice> only internally, was much <lb/>more efficacious than the ſtrongeſt
          <lb/>preparations of mercury, however ap- <lb/>plied: To haſten the cure, the ſwel-
          <lb/>lings were covered with a hemlock <lb/>plaiſter, and that plaiſter with a cata-
          <lb/>plaſm of the ſame herb, the doſe of <lb/>pills being increaſed at the ſame time. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>On the 10th day, the ſchirrus on <lb/>the left ſide of the neck was not only
          <lb/>ſofter, but reduced in ſize, and the <lb/>ſame happy alteration was alſo produ-
          <lb/>ced in both breaſts. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The reſt of the ſwellings, though <lb/>ſofter, were not diminiſhed, and to-
          <lb/>wards the ſurface they were inflamed <lb/>and painful. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>On the 17th day, the ſchirrus on <lb/>the left ſide of the neck was much more
          <lb/>reduced, both the breaſts were ſoft <lb/>and moveable, and the other ſchirrus
          <lb/>began to tend towards ſuppuration; <lb/>the patient now took ſix pills in the
          <lb/>morning, and ſix in the evening, of <lb/>four grains each. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>On the 24th day, ſome of the ſchir- <lb/>rus's were converted into matter, but
          <lb/>were not opened, as they ſeemed like- <lb/>ly to break; the ſwellings of the neck
          <lb/>and breaſt ſtill gradually diminiſhed, <lb/>and a few days afterwards ſome of the
          <lb/>reſt broke, the plaiſter and <choice>
            <corr>cataplaſm</corr>
            <sic>calaplaſm</sic>
          </choice>
          <lb/>were continued. </p>
        <cb n="2"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>On the 36th day, ſome of the ſwel- <lb/>lings totally diſappeared, the wounds
          <lb/>began to heal, and the ſwellings of the <lb/>neck and breaſt were reduced at leaſt
          <lb/>one third. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Five pills of four grains each were <lb/>now adminiſtered four times a day, <lb/>and
          this quantity was never encreaſed. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In leſs than three months the neck <lb/>and breaſts returned to their natural
          <lb/>ſtate, and from being the moſt hideous <lb/>object imaginable, ſhe became rather
          <lb/>agreeable than otherwiſe. </p>
      </floatingText>
      <floatingText type="" subtype="casereport">
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>CASE II. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A woman about 36 years old was <lb/>brought to the hoſpital with a hard,
          <lb/>painful, immoveable ſwelling in her <lb/>left breaſt, as big as a child's head,
          <lb/>which, towards <choice>
            <corr>the</corr>
            <sic>tne</sic>
          </choice> ſurface, was divi- <lb/>ded into ſeveral ſmaller, ſofter, and <lb/>more painful
          lumps and protuberan- <lb/>ces, the veins were diſtended, and the <lb/>left arm was ſo
          much ſwelled, and ſo <lb/>painful, that it could not be moved. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>To this patient Dr <hi rend="italic">Storck</hi> gave mor- <lb/>ning and evening 12
          grains of the ex- <lb/>tract of Hemlock, and a draught of <lb/>ground-ivy tea. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>On the 4th day the breaſt was ſoft- <lb/>er, but the lumps were bigger, and <lb/>ſome
          ichorous matter iſſued from them. <lb/>The pain was intollerable, and opiates <lb/>became
          neceſſary. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>On the 7th day the doſe was increaſ- <lb/>ed to 18 grains, morning and evening. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>On the 9th, three of the lumps broke <lb/>and diſcharged a great quantity of dark
          <lb/>coloured ſtinking matter, but the breaſt <lb/>became leſs, and the pain decreaſed. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The diſcharge of fœtid ichor con- <lb/>tinued, and on the 14th day a ſcruple <lb/>of
          the Hemlock was given night and <lb/>morning, but the patient was ſeized <lb/><choice>
            <corr>with</corr>
            <sic>was</sic>
          </choice> ſhiverings, her pulſe quickened, <lb/>and ſhe became hot and thirſty: Upon
          <lb/>this the doſe was decreaſed to ten <lb/>grains, and a drachm of the beſt <hi
            rend="italic">Peru- <lb/>vian</hi> bark was adminiſtered every three <lb/>hours in the
          day. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The 16th day the ſhudderings went <lb/>off, pus was diſcharged inſtead of i-
          <lb/>chor, but the patient being ſtill weak <lb/>and thirſty, the ſame remedies were
          <lb/>continued till the 21ſt day, then the <lb/>quantity of Hemlock was again
          <lb/>increaſed to eighteen grains, but a <lb/>drachm of the bark was alſo given <lb/>twice
          a day, a cataplaſm of milk and <lb/>hemlock was applied externally, and <lb/>the holes in
          the breaſt were filled with <lb/>fine lint, moiſtened in an infuſion of <lb/>Hemlock. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>By this treatment ſhe grew gradu- <pb n="626"/>
          <cb n="1"/>
          <lb/>ally better upon the whole, though <lb/>the pain was ſometimes ſo great, that
          <lb/>reſt was ſcarce to be procured, even by <lb/>opiates, and ſometimes the ſhiverings
          <lb/>and heat returned, which made it <lb/>neceſſary for a time, to diminiſh the <lb/>doſe
          of Hemlock, and have recourſe <lb/>more freely to the bark, till theſe <lb/>ſymptoms went
          off. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A great quantity of ſerum came a- <lb/>way from the ulcers, the ſize of the
          <lb/>breaſt diminiſhed, and a drachm of <lb/>the extract was adminiſtered every <lb/>day. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>After ſome time, the lips of the ul- <lb/>cer, which had been thick, callous,
          <lb/>and contracted, began to ſoften and <lb/>reſolve, and partly to be conſumed by
          <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">pus</hi>, ſo that about the 64th day, <lb/>80 grains of the
          Hemlock were admi- <lb/>niſtered every day: Recourſe to the <lb/>bark became again
          neceſſary, and the <lb/>patient was alſo directed to drink <lb/>plentifully of whey, or of
          a ſtrong <lb/>decoction of marſh mallows; the lips <lb/>of the ulcers were covered with a
          <lb/>hemlock plaiſter. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>About the 120th day, hard broad <lb/>cores came away from the ulcers, and <lb/>a
          great quantity of ichor was diſchar- <lb/>ged, in conſequence of which, the <lb/>breaſt
          ſuddenly diminiſhed very great- <lb/>ly; the patient, however, had fre- <lb/>quent
          ſhiverings, and other feveriſh <lb/>ſymptoms, ſo that half an ounce of <lb/>bark and a
          ſcruple of Hemlock were <lb/>given every 24 hours. The ulcers al- <lb/>ſo were filled with
          lint, which had been <lb/>ſteeped in a ſlight infuſion of Hemlock <lb/>and vinegar of
          litharge. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>From this time to the 150th day the <lb/>patient became better upon the whole,
          <lb/>and four ſcruples of the extract were <lb/>adminiſtered every day, and a cata-
          <lb/>plaſm of the Hemlock alone. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>On the 170th day the ulcer was <lb/>quite ſmooth, the ſwelling and hard- <lb/>neſs
          totally diſappeared, and the lips <lb/>of the ulcer waſted quite away. A- <lb/>bout three
          weeks afterwards the cure <lb/>was compleated, and no trace of the <lb/>breaſt remained,
          ſo that all who ſaw <lb/>the patient, thought her breaſt had <lb/>been cut off. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This cure had been performed ſix <lb/>months before the publication of the <lb/>book,
          and the patient remained in <lb/>perfect health. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>From a great variety of caſes, many <lb/>of them moſt deplorable, and with re-
          <lb/>ſpect to all remedies hitherto uſed <lb/>hopeleſs, the Doctor draws the fol-
          <lb/>lowing corollaries: </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>1. Hemlock does not diſſolve the <lb/>blood into a putrid colliquation. </p>
        <cb n="2"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>2. Nor bring on conſumptions. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>3. Nor hurt the ſight. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>4. Nor take away the power of pro- <lb/>creation. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>5. It may be ſafely given in ſchir- <lb/>rus's of the lower belly. </p>
      </floatingText>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The author concludes his work with <lb/>the following cautions: </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>I have related ſeveral caſes in which <lb/>the Hemlock is beneficial; I do not,
        <lb/>however, pretend, that we are to rely <lb/>always on this plant alone. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Other remedies muſt alſo ſometimes <lb/>accompany the Hemlock. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It will be neceſſary for the phyſician <lb/>judiciouſly to follow the reſpective in-
        <lb/>dications. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The ſurgeon muſt alter, add, and <lb/>take away, according as reaſon, foun- <lb/>ded on
        experience, dictates. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That it cureth cancers, is a fact I <lb/>have ſeen, and of which I am convin- <lb/>ced
        by a multitude of experiments; <lb/>but I do not from hence aſſert, that it <lb/>is
        effectual againſt every cancer, nor, <lb/>that from the Hemlock alone is the <lb/>whole cure
        always to be expected. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If there are perſons who, on account <lb/>of their particular conſtitution, or from
        <lb/>a complication of ſymptoms, cannot <lb/>ſupport the Hemlock, let ſuch refrain <lb/>from
        taking it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If the ſymptoms require, alſo, other <lb/>medicines, why may they not be admi-
        <lb/>niſtered together with this plant? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Purgatives are often neceſſary. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Sometimes it may be proper alſo to <lb/>order a bleeding. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In pleuthoric diſpoſitions, hemorrha- <lb/>ges ſhould not ſuddenly be ſtopped; <lb/>for
        with ſuch patients they agree much <lb/>better than artificial bleedings. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In weak conſtitutions, on the con- <lb/>trary, the agaric of the oak muſt im-
        <lb/>mediately and effectually be applied. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The agaric, however, ſhould be on- <lb/>ly fixed to the ſpot from whence the <lb/>blood
        iſſues; extended over the entire <lb/>ulcer, or the wound, it is pernicious, <lb/>and often
        fatal. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In ſome caſes, cooling antiphlogiſtic <lb/>remedies are indicated as well as the
        <lb/>Hemlock. This happens moſt in the <lb/>gout and rheumatiſm. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Sometimes emollients, digeſtives <lb/>ſometimes, and ſometimes aſtringents, <lb/>are
        required. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The knife muſt now and then alſo <lb/>be employed in giving the matter a
        <lb/>diſcharge, which I have often obſerved <lb/>in the <hi rend="italic">ſpina
        ventoſa</hi>; in order that the <lb/>carious and corrupted parts may be ſe- <lb/>parated
        from the ſound. </p>
      <pb n="627"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A fungous cancer muſt alſo be ſome- <lb/>times extracted with the knife. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But leaſt, in ſimilar caſes, a relapſe <lb/>ſhould happen, the Hemlock ought to <lb/>be
        employed, which is ſufficient to pre- <lb/>vent it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It happens, in many inſtances, that <lb/>the callous lips of cancers, or even
        <lb/>fungous cancers themſelves, are con- <lb/>ſumed by the means of the following
        <lb/>remedy alone: </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/>Take of the plant of Hemlock two drams <lb/>and a half; of honey of roſes 3 ounces. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Theſe ingredients are to be ſpread <lb/>on pledgets of lint, and being applied <lb/>to
        the part affected, are to be renewed <lb/>as often as prudence ſuggeſts to be
        <lb/>neceſſary. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When a judicious phyſician joins <lb/>with an expert ſurgeon, in endeavou- <lb/>ring to
        cure deſperate diſorders, they <lb/>frequently make ſurpriſing cures. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But if they diſagree, or are igno- <lb/>rant of the proper treatment, the pa-
        <lb/>tient muſt neceſſarily ſuffer or expire. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If women will but diſcover their <lb/>complaints as ſoon as they perceive <lb/>them,
        and the phyſicians preſcribe the <lb/>Hemlock at a proper time, I make no <lb/>doubt but
        that in ſome years we ſhould <lb/>meet but with very few cancers of the <lb/>breaſt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Hemlock never requires a ſtrict <lb/>regimen to be obſerved. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It allows every thing which the ſto- <lb/>mach eaſily digeſts, and which is capa-
        <lb/>ble of becoming proper nouriſhment. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Nor is wine forbidden, or acids <lb/>hurtful, when taken in a moderate <lb/>quantity.
      </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
