<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Pugh: On the medicinal Nature of Hemlock</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Benjamin Pugh</persName>
            </author>
            <title>On the medicinal Nature of Hemlock</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for D. Henry at St John's Gate.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1761</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">31</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">270</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1761_GM_0270">
    <body>
      <pb n="270"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <salute rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr <hi rend="sc">Urban</hi>, </salute>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi>N <hi rend="italic">Eſſay on the medicinal Nature of
          <lb/>Hemlock</hi>, by Dr <hi rend="italic">Storck</hi>, appeared <lb/>laſt year in your
        Magazine, in which <lb/>its extraordinary virtue and efficacy, <lb/>as well internally as
        externally uſed, <lb/>in the cure of cancers, ſchirrous, and <lb/>œdematous tumours,
        malignant and <pb n="271"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>fiſtulous ulcers, and cataracts, are de- <lb/>monſtrated and explained; the whole
        <lb/>being founded on obſervations made <lb/>in a variety of caſes, where this remedy
        <lb/>was adminiſtered by Dr <hi rend="italic">Storck</hi>, the Ba- <lb/>ron <hi
          rend="italic">Van Swieten</hi>, Dr <hi rend="italic">Kollman</hi>, and o- <lb/>thers of
        the moſt eminent phyſicians <lb/>and ſurgeons at <hi rend="italic">Vienna</hi>. A medicine
        <lb/>ſo ſtrongly recommended by perſons <lb/>of the firſt eminence in their profeſ-
        <lb/>ſions, muſt give every man, concerned <lb/>in medicine, the greateſt pleaſure; to
        <lb/>be able to relieve and cure diſeaſes, <lb/>that have been thought to be incurable
        <lb/>from the beginning of phyſic to this <lb/>time, muſt give every humane ſoul <lb/>that
        joy which can be felt, but cannot <lb/>be deſcribed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Critical Review</hi>, for <hi rend="italic">Auguſt</hi> laſt,
        <lb/>has done due honour to this eſſay, by <lb/>whoſe directions I gathered the herb,
        <lb/>and made the extract, having at that <lb/>time ſeveral patients, proper objects to
        <lb/>try it upon. They punctually obſerv- <lb/>ed my directions, both internally and
        <lb/>externally, for the ſpace of three <lb/>months, without the leaſt benefit in a- <lb/>ny
        reſpect; then, like many others in <lb/>the kingdom, I took it for granted, <lb/>the herb
        had not the ſame virtues in <lb/><hi rend="italic">England</hi> it had at <hi rend="italic"
          >Vienna</hi>; the difference <lb/>might proceed from the different climes, <lb/>but in the
          <hi rend="italic">Gentleman's Magazine</hi> for <hi rend="italic">A- <lb/>pril</hi> laſt,
          <hi rend="italic">p.</hi> 157, the ingenious Dr <hi rend="italic">Wm <lb/>Watſon</hi> has
        made very judicious obſer- <lb/>vations upon the cicuta, or hemlock; <lb/>and has very
        accurately deſcribed three <lb/>ſorts of hemlock, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> the <hi
          rend="italic">cicuta vul- <lb/>garis</hi>, or common hemlock, the <hi rend="italic">cicu-
          <lb/>taria</hi>, cow-weed, or wild cicely, and <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">cicuta
          minor</hi>, or ſmall hemlock. <lb/>This gentleman's obſervations ſoon <lb/>convinced me
        that I had made uſe of <lb/>the cicutaria, or cow-weed, as I be- <lb/>lieve every other
        perſon did who made <lb/>the extract laſt autumn, for I believe <lb/>the leaves of the
        common hemlock <lb/>(which is the true) as ſoon as the ſeeds <lb/>begin to harden and
        advance towards <lb/>ripeneſs, grow dry, and wither away; <lb/>however, Dr <hi rend="italic"
          >Watson</hi> ſays, the leaves of <lb/>the hemlock are moſt fit for medicinal <lb/>purpoſes
        (as being in their greateſt per- <lb/>fection) when collected in dry weather <lb/>from the
        middle of <hi rend="italic">May</hi> to the time <lb/>that their flowering ſtems begin to
        <lb/>ſhoot: as by that time the plants will <lb/>have felt the effects of the warm ſun,
        <lb/>have acquired an highly viroſe ſmell, <lb/>and the ſtems of the leaves are covered
        <lb/>with deep purple ſpots, an argument <lb/>of the exaltation of their juices. Dr <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Watson</hi>'s deſcription of the plant ſet me <lb/>right, for which I beg
        leave to return him <cb n="2 3"/>
        <lb/>my public thanks; and the only mo- <lb/>tive of my writing this letter, is to in-
        <lb/>form others, who might not have ſeen <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Gentleman's
          Magazine</hi>, that the herb <lb/>muſt be gathered immediately, as it <lb/>is now going
        into flower, and the ſuc- <lb/>ceſs I have met with, ſince I had the <lb/>extract made from
        the true hemlock in <lb/><hi rend="italic">May</hi> laſt, (I have ſeveral deplorable ca-
        <lb/>ſes now under my care) and the kind <lb/>aſpect ſome of them have put on this <lb/>laſt
        week, from the application of the <lb/>hemlock, internally and externally, <lb/>makes me
        hope for the ſucceſs Dr <hi rend="italic"><choice>
            <corr>Storck</corr>
            <sic>Stork</sic>
          </choice></hi>
        <lb/>aſſures. Some of my patients now take <lb/>thirty grains of the extract morning
        <lb/>and evening, without any ſenſible ef- <lb/>fect as to ſickneſs or evacuations. In
        <lb/>due time the caſes ſhall be faithfully re- <lb/>lated to the public, by their very hum-
        <lb/>ble ſervant, </p>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <dateline rend="indent italic">
        <lb/>Chelmsford, <lb/>June 17, 1761. </dateline>
      <cb n="3"/>
      <signed rend="sc space">
        <lb/>Benjamin Pugh. </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
