<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Account of the Structure of the Eye</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Account of the Structure of the Eye; with occasional Remarks on some Disorders of
              that Organ, delivered in Lectures at the Theatre of Surgeon's-Hall. By Tho. Gataker,
              Surgeon-Extraordinary to her Royal Highness the Princess of Wales. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for D. Henry at St John's Gate.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1761</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">31</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">218</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1761_GM_0218">
    <body>
      <pb n="218"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/>Account of the Structure of the Eye; with <lb/>occaſional Remarks on ſome Diſorders of
        <lb/>that Organ, delivered in Lectures at the <lb/>Theatre of <hi rend="roman"
          >Surgeon's-Hall</hi>. By <hi rend="roman">Tho. <lb/>Gataker</hi>, Surgeon-Extraordinary to
        her <lb/>Royal Highneſs the Princeſs of <hi rend="roman">Wales</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">M</hi>R <hi rend="italic">Gataker</hi> obſerves in his preface,
        <lb/>that, though there is very little <lb/>known of anatomy that is not to be <lb/>found in
        books, yet the manner in <lb/>which knowledge is communicated in <lb/>books, makes the
        acquiſition of it fre- <lb/>quently difficult, eſpecially upon a <lb/>particular ſubject.
        With reſpect to <lb/>the eye, ſome writers have been ſo con- <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>ciſe and imperfect as to be almoſt un- <lb/>intelligible to thoſe who have not al-
        <lb/>ready a conſiderable knowledge of the <lb/>ſubject; others have been ſo diffuſe
        <lb/>and circumſtantial as to perplex and <lb/>bewilder the reader with tedious cri-
        <lb/>tical diſcuſſions, and an uſeleſs multi- <lb/>plicity of names and diſtinctions; it
        <lb/>alſo frequently happens, that particu- <lb/>lar parts of the eye are deſcribed a-
        <lb/>mong other things that have not any <lb/>immediate connection with it, ſo that <lb/>the
        reader has no clue by which he <lb/>can be directed to them, nor will he, <lb/>if he finds
        theſe ſcattered parts, have a <lb/>regular and comprehenſive view of the <lb/>whole. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr <hi rend="italic">Gataker</hi>'s view, therefore, in theſe <lb/>lectures was, to
        collect and harmo- <lb/>nize into a regular ſyſtem all that has <lb/>hitherto been known
        concerning the <lb/>eye; to give a comprehenſive and me- <lb/>thodical deſcription of the
        eye and eye- <lb/>lids; and occaſionally to add ſome re- <lb/>marks relating to the diſeaſes
        of theſe <lb/>parts, and an explanation of the na- <lb/>ture and uſes of eye-waters,
        ointments, <lb/>and liniments. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The deſcriptive part of this work <lb/>it is impoſſible to abridge, but it may <lb/>be
        of ſome uſe to the public to make <lb/>the knowledge of his remarks as ex- <lb/>tenſive as
        poſſible; the following there- <lb/>fore, is extracted in the words of the <lb/>author. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">Among the variety of medicines <lb/>which are diſtinguiſhed as being <hi
            rend="italic">good</hi>
          <lb/>for particular complaints, there are few <lb/>that have been more celebrated than
          <lb/>certain compoſitions for the diſorders <lb/>affecting the eye and eye-lids. Moſt
          <lb/>of theſe are recommended indiſ- <lb/>criminately for almoſt every com- <lb/>plaint of
          theſe parts; in which kind <lb/>of practice it is not to be ſuppoſed, <lb/>that any juſt
          idea of the medicine di- <lb/>rects the uſe of it. On the other hand, <lb/>the real
          properties of theſe medicines <lb/>are not, I conceive, ſufficiently ex- <lb/>plained,
          where a more intelligent me- <lb/>thod might have been expected. Moſt <lb/>writers upon
          the diſtempers of the eyes, <lb/>recommend applications of this ſort, <lb/>but they either
          ſpeak of them in too <lb/>general terms, without attempting to <lb/>ſhew wherein their
          proper uſe conſiſts, <lb/>or they give a partial and unde- <lb/>ſerved preference to ſome
          particular <lb/>compoſition. In fact, theſe medicines <lb/>are almoſt all capable of doing
          ſervice, <lb/>under certain circumſtances of the <lb/>diſtemper; but as the advantage ari-
          <lb/>ſing from a promiſcuous uſe of them, <lb/>muſt be owing rather to accident than <pb
            n="219"/>
          <cb n="1"/>
          <lb/>judgment, the manner in which they <lb/>may be ſuppoſed to act ought to be at-
          <lb/>tended to. If we examine into the in- <lb/>gredients of theſe compoſitions, we
          <lb/>ſhall find the baſis of them is more or <lb/>leſs of a reſtringent nature, and it is
          <lb/>from this property that they are capa- <lb/>ble of doing ſervice by contracting
          <lb/>and thereby ſtrengthening the veſſels, <lb/>which have been too much diſtended.
          <lb/>In ſome caſes a different form of theſe <lb/>medicines may agree better than o-
          <lb/>thers; a liniment may be preferable to <lb/>a water, or a water to a liniment, ac-
          <lb/>cording to the nature or quantity of <lb/>the diſcharge, with other circumſtan-
          <lb/>ces: Beſides that, there is a peculiarity <lb/>in ſome conſtitutions, which will not
          <lb/>admit of the ſame means of cure, ei- <lb/>ther external or internal, as are effec-
          <lb/>tual in other people, and this is parti- <lb/>cularly true in the preſent caſe, in
          re- <lb/>gard to unctuous applications—So like- <lb/>wiſe the ſtrength of the medicine,
          with <lb/>reſpect to its degree of reſtringency, is <lb/>to be obſerved; and what is ſtill
          of <lb/>great conſequence, the preparing or <lb/>compounding theſe medicines ought to
          <lb/>be done with the utmoſt exactneſs and <lb/>neatneſſ, that no rough particles may
          <lb/>come in contact with the eye, which <lb/>may create any unneceſſary irritation
          <lb/>there. Theſe precautions being at- <lb/>tended to, the applications juſt menti-
          <lb/>oned may be often employed with the <lb/>greateſt advantage; and when the prin-
          <lb/>ciple upon which they are directed is <lb/>properly conſidered, it is eaſy to ſee
          <lb/>that many forms or compoſitions of <lb/>theſe medicines will equally anſwer the
          <lb/>purpoſe, without attributing any ſpe- <lb/>cific property to them. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Upon the whole, this author obſerves <lb/>1ſt, That the eye is placed in that part
        <lb/>of the body which is moſt advantage- <lb/>ous for commanding the view of ob-
        <lb/>jects. 2. That its figure with the con- <lb/>tained humours, is beſt calculated to
        <lb/>receive and refract the rays of light, ſo <lb/>as to form a diſtinct picture of exter-
        <lb/>nal objects upon the bottom of it. <lb/>3. That the eye is connected to the
        <lb/>ſocket, ſo that it is properly retained <lb/>there, and yet is capable occaſional-
        <lb/>ly of a free movement in different di- <lb/>rections without pain or inconveni-
        <lb/>ence. 4. That this organ is furniſhed <lb/>with defence againſt many external ac-
        <lb/>cidents, the greateſt part of it being <lb/>encloſed in a firm bony cavity, or caſe.
        <lb/>5. That it is lodged upon a ſoft yield- <lb/>ing bed of fat, which facilitates the
        <lb/>motions neceſſary to viſion, prevents <lb/>the injuries of preſſure from theſe mo- <cb
          n="2"/>
        <lb/>tions, and keeps the parts in a due ſtate <lb/>of <choice>
          <corr>ſoftneſs</corr>
          <sic>foftneſs</sic>
        </choice> and flexibility. 6. That <lb/>it is capable of various movements by <lb/>means of
        its ſeveral muſcles, accord- <lb/>ing as the different ſituation of the ob- <lb/>ject to be
        viewed requires. 7. That it <lb/>is furniſhed with coats or coverings, <lb/>and the
        ſubſtances called humours con- <lb/>tained in thoſe coats, for the produc- <lb/>tion of the
        neceſſary refractions of the <lb/>rays of light. 8, That is has power by <lb/>the expanſion
        and contraction of the <lb/>pupil to admit a ſufficient quantity of <lb/>light and exclude
        too much, according <lb/>to the diſtance or nearneſs of the ob- <lb/>ject to be viewed, or
        according to the <lb/>degree of light it is ſeen in, which is <lb/>almoſt perpetually
        varying. Laſtly, <lb/>that it has a great number of fine blood <lb/>veſſels and nerves,
        which ſerve for the <lb/>conſtant ſupply of the humours, and <lb/>for the due nouriſhment
        and ſenſation <lb/>of the other parts of the eye. From <lb/>a conſideration of all which,
        ſays he, <lb/>every ſenſible and feeling mind will re- <lb/>flect with pleaſure, admiration,
        and <lb/>reverence, on the infinite art and wiſ- <lb/>dom, which are ſo remarkably diſplay-
        <lb/>ed in the ſtructure and uſes of this ex- <lb/>quiſite organ. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
