<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Lobb: On the Fevers, and Coughs of Infants, and Children</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Theophilus Lobb</persName>
            </author>
            <title>On the Fevers, and Coughs of Infants, and Children</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for D. Henry at St John's Gate.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1761</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">31</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">493</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1761_GM_0493">
    <body>
      <pb n="493"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <head rend="italic align-center">
        <lb/>On the Fevers, and Coughs of Infants, and <lb/>Children. </head>
      <salute rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr <hi rend="sc">Urban</hi>, </salute>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi> Propoſe to communicate to the <lb/>publick, a few papers on the
        moſt <lb/>frequent diſeaſes, with directions for <lb/>managing the ſick, and an account of
        <lb/>ſome of the medicines, which through <lb/>the courſe of a long and large experi-
        <lb/>ence, I have found moſt effectual for <lb/>the cure of them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This ſervice I ſhall endeavour to <lb/>perform for the uſe of the <hi rend="sc"
          >poor</hi>, and <lb/>of ſuch other perſons as cannot have <lb/>better advice: And as with
        a deſire, <lb/>ſo with the hope, that thro' the divine <lb/>bleſſing, they may be the happy
        means <lb/>of preſerving many lives. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I chuſe to put my papers into the <lb/>channel of your Magazine, which has, <lb/>for ſo
        many years, with uncommon re- <lb/>putation, conveyed, not only into mul- <lb/>titudes of
        families, but into many diſ- <lb/>tant cities and countries, things of <lb/>great utility to
        mankind; and thereby <lb/>very much extended their uſefulneſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As to infants, and <choice>
          <corr>children</corr>
          <sic>chrildren</sic>
        </choice>, the <lb/>ſubject of my preſent conſideration, I <lb/>give the following
        directions for the <lb/>general management of them in time <lb/>of health, <hi rend="italic"
          >viz.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>1. That no roller be put round their <lb/>bodies. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>2. Nor any ſort of ſtays uſed; but, <lb/>inſtead of them waiſtcoats under their
        <lb/>frocks, when they are put into ſhort <lb/>petticoats: The human body natu- <lb/>rally
        growing into its beſt ſhape, and <lb/>proportion of its parts, when left to <lb/>itſelf. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>3. That infants have no ſhoes nor <lb/>ſtockings, till they can run about bare-
        <lb/>footed; and then ſhoes without ſtock- <lb/>ings. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>4. That the diet of young children, <lb/>be very plain or ſimple, <hi rend="italic">e.
          g.</hi> milk, <lb/>milk and apples, ſweetened with ſugar <lb/>to a pleaſant taſte, which
        is a proper <lb/>food, not only while they are well, but <lb/>when they have the ſmall pox,
        or mea- <lb/>ſles, or other fevers: Likewiſe water- <lb/>gruel made of oatmeal, with butter
        and <lb/>ſugar, as well as bread, when they are <lb/>coſtive: or water-gruel made of fine
        <lb/>wheat flower inſtead of oatmeal, or <lb/>panada made with white ſea-biſkets, <lb/>and
        ſweetened with loaf ſugar, when <lb/>the ſtools are too many, and very thin. <lb/>For dinner
        they may eat bread pud- <lb/>dings, apple-fritters, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> They may
        <lb/>eat bread and butter, and dry bread <lb/>ſometimes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Their drink may be river water, or <lb/>barley water with milk, or without it. <lb/>But
        feeding young children with ani- <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>mal food, before they are two years of <lb/>age, and giving them fermented, or
        <lb/>ſpirituous liquors, is ſowing the ſeeds <lb/>of diſeaſes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When infants, or young children <lb/>have a fever, whether it be continual <lb/>or
        intermitting, the following general <lb/>directions ſhould be obſerved, <hi rend="italic"
          >viz.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>1. To give them as plentifully as <lb/>they will take it, ſome diluting liquor,
        <lb/>when they are thirſty. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>2. To ſupply them with ſuch nutri- <lb/>tious food, as they will take moſt free-
        <lb/>ly; becauſe it abates the acrimony of <lb/>the blood, repairs the waſte of the bo-
        <lb/>dy, and is one of the beſt cordials; <lb/>and two or three common ſpoonfuls of
        <lb/>ſmall whey, made with canary or moun- <lb/>tain wine, may ſometimes be given <lb/>them.
        I would obſerve (before I de- <lb/>ſcribe the medicines that I ſhall recom- <lb/>mend) that
        an ounce of any liquid <lb/>mixture, contains eight drachms, or a- <lb/>bout two common
        table ſpoonfuls; <lb/>that one ſuch ſpoonful contains four <lb/>drachms: that one drachm, or
        the <lb/>fourth part of ſuch a ſpoonful, is a doſe <lb/>for an infant in the firſt year of
        its <lb/>life: in the ſecond year, the doſe may <lb/>be increaſed to half a ſpoonful: a
        <lb/>child three years old or upwards, may <lb/>take a whole ſpoonful. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The doſes are to be given four times <lb/>a day, at four hours diſtance, and the
        <lb/>child to drink ſome barley-water after <lb/>each; there is no occaſion for its faſt-
        <lb/>ing, but food may be given it as ſoon <lb/>as it has taken its medicine. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The medicines I recommend in the <lb/>diſeaſes mentioned, are the following: </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">A.</hi> Take eight grains of the ſalt of worm- <lb/>wood, four grains
        of cocheneal in fine pow- <lb/>der, fourteen drachms of ſmall alexiteric <lb/>water (or
        common water) and two <lb/>drachms of the balſamic ſyrup, of theſe <lb/>make a <hi rend="sc"
          >mixture</hi> for an infant. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>For a child about two years old, this <lb/>mixture may be prepared in double
        <lb/>quantity: This mixture I have found <lb/>very effectual for the cure of infants,
        <lb/>while they live upon the breaſt, and <lb/>after they are weaned, whether their
        <lb/>fever be continual or intermitting: <lb/>and often of great ſervice againſt <hi
          rend="italic">con- <lb/>vulſions</hi>, and the <hi rend="italic">cough</hi>; and in regard
        <lb/>to theſe laſt ſymptoms, I order the <lb/>belly, the ſides, and breaſt of the child,
        <lb/>to be gently rubbed with warm (not <lb/>hot) oil of olives, for four or five mi-
        <lb/>nutes, and then wiped off again: this <lb/>may be done once or twice a day, or
        <lb/>oftner if there ſhould be occaſion; and <lb/>this is one good remedy againſt con-
        <lb/>vulſion fits. </p>
      <pb n="494"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">B.</hi> Take ſalt of wormwood, ſalt pru- <lb/>nella, and cocheneal, of
        each ten grains, <lb/>ſmall alexiteric water (or common water) <lb/>three ounces and a half,
        balſamic ſyrup, <lb/>half an ounce; of theſe make a <hi rend="sc">mixture</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This mixture is ſomewhat more <lb/>cooling than the former. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If the child is very coſtive, I omit <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">cocheneal</hi>, and
        order the following: </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">C.</hi> Take the calx of antimony, ſalt of <lb/>wormwood, ſalt
        prunella, of each ten <lb/>grains, ſmall alexiteric water (or common <lb/>water) three
        ounces and half, balſamic ſy- <lb/>rup half an ounce; and make a <hi rend="sc">mix-
          <lb/>ture</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">D.</hi> Take compound powder contrayerva, <lb/>calx of antimony, ſalt
        of wormwood, (or <lb/>the ſalt prunella,) of each ten grains, ſmall <lb/>alexiteric water
        three <choice>
          <corr>ounces</corr>
          <sic>onnces</sic>
        </choice>, ſmall <lb/>cinnamon water, balſamic ſyrup, of each <lb/>half an ounce; of theſe
        make a <hi rend="sc">mixture</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The phials, in which the powder <lb/>ſinks to the bottom, muſt be ſhaked be- <lb/>fore
        any is poured out. The mixture <lb/>that is uſed and proves beneficial, muſt <lb/>be
        repeated, and its uſe continued ſo <lb/>long as needful. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When a ſtool ſhall be wanted, a <lb/>glyſter made of milk and ſugar, or of
        <lb/>water-gruel, brown ſugar, and oil of <lb/>olives, may be given to the child. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When a looſeneſs happens, and the <lb/>ſtools are watry, or thin and green, <lb/>then
        the following mixture is pro- <lb/>per, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/>E. Take compound powder of contrayer- <lb/>va, red corall prepared, of each twenty
        <lb/>grains, ſmall cinnamon water, three ounces <lb/>and half, balſamic ſyrup, half an
        ounce; of <lb/>theſe make a <hi rend="sc">mixture</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Sometimes inſtead of the corall, I <lb/>direct the ſame quantity of fine chalk <lb/>in
        fine powder; and order, that half <lb/>a large ſpoonful, or a whole one, accor- <lb/>ding to
        the ſize of the child, be given <lb/>it warm after every thin and griping <lb/>ſtool, firſt
        ſhaking the phial; but ta- <lb/>king a doſe of the mixture marked <hi rend="italic">A</hi>,
        <lb/>every fourth hour, while the fever <lb/>continues. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If the child has a cough, be it hoop- <lb/>ing or not, the mixtures marked <hi
          rend="italic">A.</hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">B.</hi>
        <hi rend="italic">C.</hi> are proper remedies in regard to <lb/>it: and while the cough
        continues, I <lb/>adviſe giving the child two or three <lb/>ſpoonfuls of a tea, made with
        the herb <lb/>called <hi rend="italic">cup-moſs</hi>, ſweetened with a de- <lb/>coction of
        figs; alſo, a tea ſpoonful <lb/>now and then, of a mixture of oil of <lb/>olives, with
        ſugar, to the conſiſtance of <lb/>a thin ſyrup; when the cough conti- <lb/>nues after the
        fever ceaſes, I order two <lb/>or three drops of the <hi rend="italic">balſam</hi> of <hi
          rend="italic">capivi</hi>, <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>to be given night and morning, with <lb/>ſome powder ſugar, to a child about <lb/>four
        years old. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When children have the <hi rend="italic">ſmall pox</hi>, <lb/>if the puſtules are few,
        and continue <lb/>increaſing in bulk, and the ſuppura- <lb/>tion of them proceeds well,
        there is no <lb/>occaſion for medicines; but a ſuitable <lb/>diet, eſpecially milk and
        apples, milk- <lb/>porridge, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> with giving the child now
        <lb/>and then, a little ſack or mountain <lb/>whey, may be ſufficient. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If the puſtules are very numerous, <lb/>and the fever continues, beſides the
        <lb/>ſuitable diet, ſome medicines ſhould be <lb/>given; and the mixture marked <hi
          rend="italic">B</hi>, or <lb/>that marked <hi rend="italic">D</hi>, may be fitly given:
        <lb/>but if the diſeaſe is of the confluent <lb/>kind, and a looſeneſs happens, often
        <lb/>very happily for young children, then <lb/>the mixture marked <hi rend="italic">C</hi>,
        is more proper. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When children have the <hi rend="italic">meaſles</hi>, they <lb/>ſhould be fed with the
        ſame ſorts of di- <lb/>et as in the <hi rend="italic">ſmall pox</hi>; if the fever con-
        <lb/>tinues high, the mixture marked <hi rend="italic">A</hi>, <lb/>may be given, &amp; in
        regard to the cough, <lb/>which often attends this diſtemper, the <lb/>directions
        before-mentioned, about this <lb/>ſymptom, ſhould be obſerved. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The following extracts may ſome- <lb/>what exemplify the advantages ob- <lb/>tainable
        by the foregoing advices. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the latter end of <hi rend="italic">February</hi> laſt, <lb/>I received a letter
        from a gentleman <lb/>near <hi rend="italic">Biddeford</hi> in <hi rend="italic"
          >Devonſhire</hi>, in which <lb/>he writes thus, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="diple quotes">There is a boy of ſix years old in <lb/>this place, that has had the
          hooping <lb/>cough ever ſince <hi rend="italic">September</hi>, he is <lb/>now much
          better, but has prodigi- <lb/>ous wind and belching on his ſto- <lb/>mach, and very ſevere
          fits of cough- <lb/>ing at night, but no hooping. I have <lb/>recommended him to an
          apothecary <lb/>for ſome time, but without effect. <lb/>His father is an induſtrious poor
          <lb/>man. This I mention to you, and <lb/>it would be a very good deed to re- <lb/>commend
          the child to a relief; <lb/>for you muſt know this is a country <lb/>place, where if the
          parents could <lb/>afford adviſing with a phyſician, <lb/>there is none nigher than 25
          miles. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He likewiſe mentions, that the hoop- <lb/>ing cough has been much in that <lb/>country. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">February</hi> 28, I returned an anſwer, <lb/>in which I wrote as
        follows: </p>
      <floatingText>
        <body>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Againſt the Hooping Cough. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>℞. <hi rend="italic">Sal Abſinth.</hi> ℈i. <hi rend="italic">Coccinella</hi> ℈ss. <hi
            rend="italic">Aq. <lb/>Alexiter. ſimple</hi> ℥iii.ss. <hi rend="italic">ſyr.
            balſamic</hi> ℥ss. <lb/><hi rend="italic">et f.</hi>
          <hi rend="sc">mistura</hi>. This mixture may <pb n="495"/>
          <cb n="1"/>
          <lb/>be made in the following manner: </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Take one ſcruple of the ſalt of worm- <lb/>wood, and diſſolve it in a quarter of a
          <lb/>pint of pure water, then add to it ten <lb/>grains of cocheneal in fine powder,
          <lb/>and ſweeten it with white ſugar to a <lb/>pleaſant taſte. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Of this mixture, the fourth part of a <lb/>common or table ſpoonful, may be gi-
          <lb/>ven to a child within the firſt year, four <lb/>times a day, at four hours diſtance,
          <lb/>with a ſpoonful of barley water after <lb/>it. To a child near two years old,
          <lb/>half a ſpoonful may be the doſe: To a <lb/>child above four years old, a common
          <lb/>ſpoonful may be the doſe. As for the <lb/>boy you mentioned of ſix years old, <lb/>he
          may take a large ſpoonful four times <lb/>a day: alſo he may take three or four <lb/>drops
          of the balſam of capivi, with <lb/>powder ſugar night and morning. <lb/>And milk and
          apples are a proper <lb/>food for him, that is apples boiled in <lb/>a pipkin (as if
          intended for ſauce to <lb/>roaſted pork) put into very warm milk, <lb/>and ſweetened to
          his palate with ſugar. </p></body>
      </floatingText>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the latter end of <hi rend="italic">June</hi> laſt, I re- <lb/>ceived another
        letter, dated <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 23, in <lb/>which after an apology for his long
        ſi- <lb/>lence, and ſome other matters, he <lb/>writes thus, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="diple quotes">As to the hooping cough, its now <lb/>out of our neighbourhood. The
          re- <lb/>medy which you preſcribed, had a <lb/>wonderful effect, particularly in the <lb/><choice>
            <corr/>
            <sic>the </sic>
          </choice>caſe of the boy I wrote to you a- <lb/>bout of ſix years old, who was re-
          <lb/>lieved in 24 hours, and I think cured <lb/>in five or ſix days. I recommended <lb/>it
          to ſeveral poor people, and will <lb/>ſay, it always had ſucceſs; therefore, <lb/>in
          behalf of ſeveral poor diſtreſſed <lb/>families, you have my ſincere thanks, <lb/>and may
          the author of all bleſſings, <lb/>reward your humane and charitable <lb/>diſpoſition. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I will only add, that I pray God, in- <lb/>finitely gracious, to direct, and ſuc-
        <lb/>ceed all my endeavours for the good of <lb/>mankind. </p>
      <signed rend="sc align-right">Theophilus Lobb. </signed>
      <dateline rend="italic align-center">
        <lb/>Bagnio-Court, Newgate-ſtreet, Oct. 20. </dateline>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
