<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: New Experiments and Observations in Chemistry.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>New Experiments and Observations in Chemistry.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for D. Henry at St John's Gate.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1761</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">31</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">213</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1761_GM_0213">
    <body>
      <pb n="213"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <head rend="italic align-center">
        <lb/>New Experiments and Obſervations in <lb/><hi rend="sc">Chemistry</hi>. </head>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>T is well known, that many impor- <lb/>tant articles in the <hi
          rend="italic">Materia Medica</hi>
        <lb/>conſiſt of metalic ſubſtances in a ſtate of <lb/>diſſolution; and that, to diſſolve me-
        <lb/>tals, no medium has hitherto been diſ- <lb/>covered but acids, which it is alſo fre-
        <lb/>quently neceſſary to aſſiſt by fire. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But there is great reaſon to believe <lb/>that the violent qualities of acids and
        <lb/>fire, ſometimes impreſs a danger- <lb/>ous character upon the metals which <lb/>they
        diſſolve, foreign to the metals <lb/>themſelves, ſo that their medical qua- <lb/>lities are
        in ſome degree counteracted, <lb/>by the very method which is uſed to <lb/>give them a
        medical form. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This conſideration has engaged M. <lb/><hi rend="italic">de la Garaye</hi>, a gentleman
        of great emi- <lb/>nence, in <hi rend="italic">France</hi>, as well for his ſkill <lb/>as
        his humanity, to attempt the diſ- <lb/>covery of ſome milder agents, by <lb/>which metals
        may be diſſolved into me- <lb/>dicine, without the mixture of dan- <lb/>gerous qualities. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>With this view he began a courſe of <lb/>experiments with the mildeſt neutral
        <lb/>ſalts, aſſiſted only by the warmth of <lb/>the air; and, notwithſtanding, the com-
        <lb/>parative inactivity of theſe diſſolvents, <lb/>he ſucceeded. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>His firſt experiment was made upon <lb/>mercury; he mixed a certain quantity <lb/>of
        this metal with four times its weight <lb/>of ſal ammoniac; and having tritu- <lb/>rated
        them very well together, he left <lb/>the mixture expoſed to the air in a <lb/>glaſs veſſel,
        and grinding it again, from <lb/>time to time, he at length procured a <lb/>ſaline-mercurial
        maſs, which, put into <lb/>a matras, with good ſpirit of wine, <lb/>gave, by means of a
        gentle heat, gra- <lb/>dually increaſed till the ſpirit boiled, <lb/>a light yellowiſh
        tincture, which was <lb/>ſo ſaturated with mercury, that it <lb/>turned copper white, the
        moment it <lb/>touched it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This tincture proved very efficacious <lb/>in the cure of that almoſt endleſs va-
        <lb/>riety of diſorders for which mercury <lb/>is a remedy, and was given in large
        <lb/>doſes, for 15 days together, without <lb/>raiſing a ſalivation. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It produced ſurpriſing effects in ob- <lb/>ſtinate diſorders of the ſkin, and may
        <lb/>be conſidered as one of the beſt reme- <lb/>dies of the kind in the world. It is
        <lb/>however very ſtrange, that the heavieſt <lb/>body in nature, except gold, ſhould be
        <lb/>ſo attenuated, and divided, as to remain <lb/>perfectly ſuſpended in a liquor ſo light
        <lb/>as ſpirits of wine. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A ſolution of mercury was procured <lb/>in the ſame manner, though water <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>was ſubſtituted for ſpirit of wine; but <lb/>this ſhould be adminiſtered only ex-
        <lb/>ternally. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Steel was treated in the ſame manner, <lb/>and with the ſame ſucceſs; being mix-
        <lb/>ed with half its weight of blue vitriol, <lb/>and a little common water, it firſt be-
        <lb/>came hot, and afterwards hardened in- <lb/>to a maſs, which was left to macerate
        <lb/>during 8 days in a cellar: At the end <lb/>of this time it was beaten in a mortar,
        <lb/>and alternately dried and moiſtened <lb/>with water, till it took a fine colour of
        <lb/>ſaffron of ſteel, the whole was then put <lb/>again into a mortar, and, water being
        <lb/>poured to it, it was beaten as long as the <lb/>water drew from it a tincture of ruſt,
        <lb/>and when the water came clear from <lb/>the mixture no more was poured on: <lb/>This
        ruſt-water, when filtered, is a li- <lb/>quor ſo impregnated with ſteel, that <lb/>30 or 40
        drops put into a pint of wa- <lb/>ter makes an excellent chalybeat or <lb/>ferruginous
        draught. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>M. <hi rend="italic">de la Garaye</hi> has alſo uſed ſea ſalt, <lb/>nitre, and ſal
        ammoniac, in this proceſs <lb/>for the ſolution of ſteel; with ſal am- <lb/>moniac he has
        obtained a yellow ſalt, <lb/>from which ſpirit of wine takes away <lb/>the colour to itſelf,
        as well as a ſtiptic <lb/>and better taſte, and a quality of ſtri- <lb/>king a very fine
        deep blue with gall <lb/>nuts. This tincture, and thoſe drawn <lb/>with the other ſalts juſt
        mentioned, are <lb/>very mild and gentle, and may be uſed <lb/>with great ſucceſs in all
        diſeaſes for <lb/>which preparations of ſteel are admi- <lb/>niſtered. M. <hi rend="italic"
          >le Monnier</hi>, the phyſician, <lb/>conſidered it as a ſpecific againſt a con-
        <lb/>vulſive and frightful malady which is <lb/>frequent at St <hi rend="italic"
          >Germains</hi>, and has reſiſt- <lb/>ed almoſt all other remedies. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Copper, treated in this new manner, <lb/>with ſal ammoniac; gives a very fine <lb/>blue
        to water; ſpirit of wine draws <lb/>from it only a ſlight green, but bran- <lb/>dy, which
        contains both water and <lb/>ſpirit, draws from it a very fine <lb/>greeniſh blue. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This tincture, however, cannot be <lb/>adminiſtered internally without danger, <lb/>but
        externally it produces admirable <lb/>effects; the malignant and obſtinate <lb/>ulcers in
        the legs, ſo common in <hi rend="italic">Bri- <lb/>tany</hi>, yield very ſoon to the power
        of <lb/>this remedy. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The chemiſts have hitherto thought <lb/>it impoſſible to reduce the flowers of <lb/>the
        Regulus of <hi rend="italic">Antimony</hi> to their firſt <lb/>ſtate, but it may be done by
        a mixture <lb/>of a coaly (<hi rend="italic">charbonneuſe</hi>) matter, and <lb/>a little
        fixed alcali, which will cauſe <lb/>the flowers to melt with the greateſt <lb/>facility.
      </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
