<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: An Account of a Topical Remedy for the cure of ulcerated
          Cancers.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Account of a Topical Remedy for the cure of ulcerated Cancers. By M. I. C.
              Soultzer , Councellor of the Court and first Physician to his Royal Highness the Duke
              of Saxe Gotha; translated from the French. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed at St John's Gate, for D. Henry; and sold by F. Newbery,
                  the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard, Ludgate Street.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1767</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">37</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">542</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1767_GM_0542">
    <body>
      <pb n="542"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/>An Account of a Topical Remedy for the <lb/>cure of ulcerated Cancers. By <hi
          rend="roman">M. I. <lb/>C. Soultzer</hi>, Councellor of the Court <lb/>and firſt Phyſician
        to his Royal High- <lb/>neſs the Duke of <hi rend="roman">Saxe Gotha</hi>; tranſ- <lb/>lated
        from the <hi rend="roman">French</hi>. </head>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi>N effectual cure for a cancer is ſtill <lb/>among the <hi
          rend="italic">Deſiderata</hi> of phyſic: <lb/>mercury, antimony, and all other alte-
        <lb/>ratives have been long tried, and often <lb/>found to fail: I have alſo tried the <hi
          rend="italic">Bel- <lb/>ladona</hi> or night ſhade, and I find that <lb/>after long
        fatiguing the patient by the <lb/>great dryneſs which it occaſions in the <lb/>throat, it
        does indeed render the ſuppu- <lb/>ration more laudable, and check the <lb/>progreſs of the
        diſeaſe, but it never <lb/>effects the cure, and the ſick though they <lb/>languiſh a little
        longer, certainly periſh <lb/>at laſt. The Cicuta or Hemlock is a <lb/>more powerful remedy;
        but though it <lb/>has been ſucceſsfully adminiſtered in <lb/>cutaneous diſorders, though it
        has re- <lb/>ſolved ſchirrouſes, and, as it were pre- <lb/>pared the body for my topical
        remedy, <pb n="543"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>yet it has but rarely cured an ulcerated <lb/>cancer, being frequently unſucceſsful in
        <lb/>the hands of Mr. <hi rend="italic">Storck</hi> himſelf, as <lb/>appears by his own
        account. The topi- <lb/>cal remedy which I now offer to the <lb/>public is ſimple, harmleſs,
        and eaſily to <lb/>be procured, not only by the rich but <lb/>the poor. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Take carrots freſh gathered, (<hi rend="italic">Daucus <lb/>ſativus</hi>) and reduce
        them to a coarſe <lb/>powder, with a raſp ſuch as bakers uſe <lb/>for their bread; ſqueeze
        out the juice by <lb/>preſſing them in your hand, and then <lb/>warm the pulp either on a
        palate or in an <lb/>earthen pipkin, and apply it in the man- <lb/>ner of a thick poultice;
        if there are holes <lb/>or hollows of any kind, they muſt be <lb/>filled ſo that the
        poultice may touch <lb/>the ulcers in every part, and the whole <lb/>muſt be covered with a
        napkin very well <lb/>dried, and a little warm. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This dreſſing muſt be renewed twice <lb/>in every twenty-four hours, taking a- <lb/>way
        the ſtale poultice and at the ſame <lb/>time waſhing and cleaning the ulcer with <lb/>ſome
        lint faſtened to the end of a probe <lb/>or ſome other proper inſtrument, dipped <lb/>in a
        warm decoction of hemlock, the <lb/><hi rend="italic">cicuta major fœtida</hi>. This
        application <lb/>abates the pain, and in a few days takes <lb/>away the loathſome and almoſt
        inſup- <lb/>portable ſmell, which is the conſtant <lb/>concomitant of cancerous ulcers; the
        <lb/>ſuppuration will gradually diminiſh, and <lb/>inſtead of a ſanies and ichorous matter,
        <lb/>the wound will diſcharge laudable pus. <lb/>The ſtate of the patient will conſequently
        <lb/>become more tollerable, and if the re- <lb/>medy produced no other good effect, it
        <lb/>would be well worth attending to; but <lb/>if the uſe of it is longer continued, the
        <lb/>hard and callous edges of the ulcer will <lb/>become gradually ſoft, the tumour will
        <lb/>diminiſh, and at length totally diſappear; <lb/>new fleſh will be generated, a cicatrix
        <lb/>will be formed, and the cure of the ulcer <lb/>will be compleated. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This is not a vain imagination, but <lb/>an undoubted fact, in which it is impoſ-
        <lb/>ſible that I ſhould be deceived, for I <lb/>have watched the effect of this remedy
        <lb/>with too curious and ſcrupulous an at- <lb/>tention to be impoſed upon by effects of
        <lb/>other cauſes. It is indeed true, that <lb/>ſome of the patients upon whom the
        <lb/>carrot poultice produced this effect, had <lb/>before taken the extract of hemlock:
        <lb/>but in one inſtance it had aggravated <lb/>the ſymptoms, and therefore after a ſhort
        <lb/>time, was wholly laid aſide; in another, <lb/>it appeared to ſtop the progreſs of the
        <lb/>diſeaſe; the pains became violent, the <lb/>ſuppuration ſomewhat more laudible,
        <lb/>but at length the patient took ſuch a <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>diſguſt to the medicine, that it could not <lb/>be got down. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Is it then neceſſary that the patient <lb/>ſhould take extract of hemlock in order
        <lb/>to receive benefit from the carrot poul- <lb/>tice? I think not: but ſuppoſing the
        <lb/>contrary, the extract is a ſafe remedy, <lb/>and eaſily to be procured, and if judici-
        <lb/>ouſly adminiſtered, I know no active <lb/>alterant ſo innocent. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>During the uſe of this poultice, ſuch <lb/>accidents as frequently ſupervene in ul-
        <lb/>cerous cancers, muſt be treated accord- <lb/>ing to their indications; one of my pa-
        <lb/>tients of a lively and cholorick diſpo- <lb/>ſition, who could not be perſuaded to
        <lb/>follow an exact regimen, very frequently <lb/>ſuffered an acceſs of a fever, which oc-
        <lb/>caſioned the pus to be abſorbed, brought <lb/>on diarrhæas, profuſe and colliquative
        <lb/>ſweats, and a ſpitting; a diſcharge from <lb/>the ulcer alſo ſupervened ſo violent as
        to <lb/>wet ſeveral napkins quite through; ſome <lb/>gentle purges, the bark, and leni-
        <lb/>tives were the only remedies I had re- <lb/>courſe to, and they very ſoon ſet all to
        <lb/>rights. There can be no doubt but that <lb/>the cure is greatly facilitated by a proper
        <lb/>regimen. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As this poultice produces an effect ſo <lb/>ſalutary upon ulcers of the moſt malig-
        <lb/>nant kind, it is probable in the higheſt <lb/>degree, that it may be ſucceſsfully ap-
        <lb/>plied to ulcers of another ſpecies. The <lb/>reader will recollect that I have told him
        <lb/>this remedy abates the pain, renders the <lb/>ſuppuration laudible, and takes away
        <lb/>the diſagreeable and infectious ſmell <lb/>which exhales from ulcers of every kind,
        <lb/>eſpecially thoſe of a cancer, very ſoon; <lb/>but the cure is a work of time. I have
        <lb/>applied my poultice more than a year to <lb/>a very large cancer, where the tumour
        <lb/>was extremely hard, before the diſeaſe <lb/>took a turn that promiſed a cure, which
        <lb/>however, was compleated at laſt, what <lb/>effect my remedy would have in the laſt
        <lb/>ſtage of a cancer when the patient is <lb/>conſumed by a hectic fever, I cannot
        <lb/>tell, having never tried it in ſuch a caſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If I had had opportunities to make a <lb/>greater number of experiments, my pre-
        <lb/>ſent to the public might have been more <lb/>conſiderable, but the knowledge which I
        <lb/>have already acquired, I thought it my <lb/>duty to communicate, that other phyſi-
        <lb/>cians might compleat what I have begun; <lb/>as to myſelf, I am ſure I have not been
        <lb/>deceived by appearances, and whatever <lb/>be the fate of my diſcovery, I ſhall think
        <lb/>with <hi rend="italic">M. Storck</hi>, that if among an hun- <lb/>dred ſick, I am the
        means of one reco- <lb/>very, my time will have been employed <lb/>to good purpoſe. </p>
      <pb n="544"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I think that the operation of the poul- <lb/>tice which I recommend will be greatly
        <lb/>facilitated, if the patient at the ſame <lb/>time takes ſmall doſes of the extract of
        <lb/>hemlock, the night ſhade, the bark, or <lb/>ſuch other alterant as appears to be indi-
        <lb/>cated by the temperament and conſtitu- <lb/>tion of the patient, and the nature of the
        <lb/>diſeaſe, for all cancers are not of the <lb/>ſame kind; this, however, I have not
        <lb/>done myſelf, that I might obſerve with <lb/>more accuracy, and confirm with more
        <lb/>certainty, the effects of my poultice. I <lb/>have contented myſelf with giving my
        <lb/>patients carrots boiled in milk. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
