<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: A short, plain, and exact Narrative of all the Proceedings,
          relative to the two Convicts</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>A short, plain, and exact Narrative of all the Proceedings, relative to the two
              Convicts, lately respited by his Majesty, for the Trial of Mr. Thomas Pierce's Styptic
              Medicines, and the true Causes of his Disappointment shewn.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed at St John's Gate, for D. Henry; and sold by F. Newbery,
                  the Corner of St. Paul's Church-Yard Ludgate Street.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1767</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">37</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">460</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1767_GM_0460">
    <body>
      <pb n="460"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">35.</hi> A ſhort, plain, and exact Nar- <lb/>rative of all the
        Proceedings, relative to <lb/>the two Convicts, lately reſpited by his <lb/>Majeſty, for the
        Trial of Mr. <hi rend="roman">Thomas <lb/>Pierce</hi>'s Styptic Medicines, and the true
        <lb/>Cauſes of his Diſappointment ſhewn. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Pierce</hi>, about the year 1761, diſco- <lb/>vered two ſtyptics
        which he had great reaſon <lb/>to believe, would ſtop not only bleedings of <lb/>the ſmaller
        veſſels whether internal or exter- <lb/>nal, but the violent hæmorrhages which pro-
        <lb/>ceed from the larger arteries, that are divi- <lb/><choice>
          <corr>ded</corr>
          <sic>ed</sic>
        </choice> in amputations. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>His opinion of their efficacy was founded <lb/>upon a great variety of experiments,
        which <lb/>had been made upon brutes, in the preſence <lb/>of ſeveral gentlemen of the
        faculty, and be- <lb/>ing deſirous of trying their effect upon the <lb/>larger arteries of a
        human ſubject, he applied <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>to the king for one of the convicts under <lb/>ſentence of death in <hi rend="italic"
          >Newgate</hi>, whoſe leg <lb/>might be cut off, and the ſtyptic only ap- <lb/>plied,
        inſtead of taking up the veſſels the <lb/>uſual way. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He ſet forth in his petition, among other <lb/>things, that his ſtyptic had been
        ſucceſsfully <lb/>applied upon the amputation of the hinder <lb/>leg of a ſtrong dog, and
        the ſame limb of <lb/>a full grown aſs, in the preſence of ſeveral <lb/>gentlemen of the
        faculty, among whom <lb/>were Mr. <hi rend="italic">T. Baker</hi>, ſurgeon of St. <hi
          rend="italic">Thomas</hi>'s <lb/>hoſpital, Mr. <hi rend="italic">George Martin</hi>,
        ſurgeon, in <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fenchurch Buildings</hi>, and Mr. <hi rend="italic"
          >Louttit</hi>, who <lb/>ſubſcribed an atteſtation of the facts in the <lb/>petition. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The petition was recommended by the <lb/>ſheriffs of <hi rend="italic">London</hi>, <hi
          rend="italic">Thomas Challenor</hi>, and <lb/><hi rend="italic">Henry Banks</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A petition was alſo preſented at the ſame <lb/>time by <hi rend="italic">George
          Clippingdale</hi>, then under ſen- <lb/>tence of death in <hi rend="italic">Newgate</hi>,
        ſetting forth that <lb/>he moſt eagerly embraced that opportunity <lb/>of beſeeching his
        majeſty to appoint him <lb/>for the ſubject of the experiment. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In conſequence of theſe teſtimonials and <lb/>petitions, his majeſty was pleaſed to re-
        <lb/>prieve <hi rend="italic">Clippingdale</hi> for the experiment, and <lb/>gave orders to
        lord <hi rend="italic">Egremont</hi>, then ſecretary <lb/>of ſtate to acquaint the ſergeant
        ſurgeons <lb/>therewith, which he did by letter, incloſing <lb/>the petition, and dated <hi
          rend="italic">May</hi> 5, 1763. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After ſtating the principal facts related <lb/>above, the letter, proceeds in theſe
        terms, <lb/>
        <q rend="diple quotes">Before the king declares his further re- <lb/>ſolution on this
          matter, <hi rend="italic">it is his pleaſure <lb/>that you do</hi>, taking to your
          aſſiſtance any <lb/>other gentlemen of the faculty, whom <lb/>you ſhall judge proper, <hi
            rend="italic">call upon the ſaid <lb/>Thomas Pierce</hi>, to ſtate the experiment he
          <lb/>intends to try, and that you do examine <lb/>into the ſame, and report your opinion
          <lb/>as well to the ſaid experiment itſelf, as <lb/>to the utility to be derived
          therefrom, as <lb/>ſoon as poſſible. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This order, according to Mr. <hi rend="italic">Pierce</hi>, the <lb/>ſergeant ſurgeons
        did not condeſcend to o- <lb/>bey, for neither they, nor any perſon from <lb/>them, did ever
        call upon him or ſend to <lb/>him, or make any enquiry concerning the <lb/>experiment to be
        tried. Mr. <hi rend="italic">Pierce</hi> on the <lb/>contrary, waited ſeveral times upon Mr.
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Hawkins</hi>, but even then Mr. <hi rend="italic">Hawkins</hi>
        refuſ- <lb/>ed to enter into converſation with him upon <lb/>the ſubject. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 13th of <hi rend="italic">May</hi>, however, the ſer- <lb/>geant ſurgeons Meſſ.
          <hi rend="italic">Ranby</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Hawkins</hi>, and <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Middleton</hi>, made their reports to lord <hi rend="italic">Egre- <lb/>mont</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The report ſets forth, that Mr. <hi rend="italic">Pierce's</hi>
        <lb/>propoſal, with the declaration of the efficacy <lb/>of the medicine, are founded only
        upon ex- <lb/>periments made upon the blood veſſels of <lb/>brutes; that they know from
        certain expe- <lb/>rience, that this kind of evidence is often <lb/>inconcluſive, there
        being no preciſe analogy <lb/>between the human arteries and the arteries <lb/>of brutes,
        with reſpect to the violence of <pb n="461"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>the bleedings, and the means neceſſary to <lb/>ſtop them, as the hæmorrhages from the
        arte- <lb/>ries of brutes, are in general ſtopped much <lb/>more eaſily, and even frequently
        will ſtop of <lb/>themſelves. That experiments upon brutes <lb/>therefore cannot give
        ſufficient authority for <lb/>the ſergeant ſurgeons to recommend making <lb/>the experiment
        propoſed in Mr. <hi rend="italic">Pierce</hi>'s <lb/>petition; but that if his lordſhip
        would di- <lb/>rect, and Mr. <hi rend="italic">Pierce</hi> would deliver a proper
        <lb/>quantity of his medicine to ſome of the ſur- <lb/>geons of the hoſpitals, they would
        ſoon <lb/>have opportunities of making ſafe and ſuffi- <lb/>cient experiments of its
        efficacy, upon the <lb/>ſmaller arteries of men, and that if from <lb/>ſuch trials the
        medicine appeared to have <lb/>more efficacy than the preſent known ſtyptics, <lb/>there
        would be proper encouragement to <lb/>make further experiments upon the large <lb/>arteries,
        and the convict intended for the ex- <lb/>periment might be reſerved for the making
        <lb/>ſuch trials as ſhould be judged ſatisfactory <lb/>and important. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Upon this report it may be obſerved, that <lb/>the want of preciſe analogy between the
        hu- <lb/>man arteries, and the arteries of brutes, <lb/>which is alledged as a reaſon
        againſt the <lb/>experiment on the convict, is the ſtrongeſt <lb/>reaſon for that
        experiment. On whom ought <lb/>an experiment to be tried, that, for all that <lb/>can
        otherwiſe be known, may be dange- <lb/>rous, but upon one to whom the experiment <lb/>upon
        the whole, notwithſtanding its danger, <lb/>is an advantage? to the criminal it was a
        <lb/>chance of life, and, as the only chance, <lb/>earneſtly ſolicited. Why then ſhould this
        <lb/>benefit to the criminal, which might alſo ter- <lb/>minate in a very important benefit
        to the <lb/>publick be witheld, upon pretence that pre- <lb/>vious experiments ought to be
        made upon <lb/>patients in an hoſpital? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This report, however, having been laid be- <lb/>fore his majeſty, lord <hi
          rend="italic">Egremont</hi> wrote a ſe- <lb/>cond letter to the ſergeant ſurgeons, dated
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">May</hi> 18, to this effect. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That his majeſty approved the procur- <lb/>ing Mr. <hi rend="italic">Pierce</hi>'s
        medicines to be tried in the <lb/>hoſpital, on the ſmaller arteries of men, and <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">deſired</hi> the ſergeant ſurgeons would accord- <lb/>ingly <hi
          rend="italic">apply to Mr. Pierce</hi>, for that purpoſe, <lb/>in caſe he ſhould be
        willing to put into their <lb/>hands ſuch a quantity as they ſhould judge <lb/>ſufficient to
        make the neceſſary experiments <lb/>with. That <hi rend="italic">George Clippingdale</hi>
        being already <lb/>reprieved, his majeſty had determined he <lb/>ſhould not ſuffer, but be
        tranſported for life, <lb/>unleſs it ſhould appear to them that there <lb/>were ſufficient
        grounds to preſerve him here, <lb/>in order to make any important trials of Mr. <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Pierce</hi>'s ſtyptic. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As the ſergeant ſurgeons had not before <lb/>thought fit to comply with his majeſty's
        plea- <lb/>ſure, neither did they now think fit to fulfil <lb/>his <hi rend="italic"
          >deſire</hi>, no application being ever made to <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Pierce</hi> for
        his medicines. Mr. <hi rend="italic">Pierce</hi>
        <lb/>however, waited on the gentlemen of St. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Thomas's</hi>, <hi
          rend="italic">Guy's</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Bartholemew</hi>'s, and Saint <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">George</hi>'s hoſpitals, and told them he was <lb/>willing to let them have
        the medicines to <cb n="2 3"/>
        <lb/>make trial of, provided they would ſuffer <lb/>him to be preſent when they were
        applied, <lb/>but to this they would not conſent, he did <lb/>however, leave ſome at St. <hi
          rend="italic">Thomas</hi>'s hoſpital, <lb/>where, inſtead of being uſed, they were, if
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Pierce</hi> has been truly informed, analyſed <lb/>in order to
        diſcover their compoſition; for <lb/>this reaſon, he ſays, he refuſed to leave any <lb/>with
        Mr. <hi rend="italic">Gataker</hi>, though he candidly aſſured <lb/>him he would give them a
        fair trial. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 7th of <hi rend="italic">June</hi>, the ſergeant ſurgeons <lb/>made their ſecond
        report as follows. </p>
      <floatingText>
        <body>
        <salute rend="indent italic">
          <lb/>My Lord, </salute>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>We are acquainted by Mr. <hi rend="italic">Peirce</hi>, that <lb/>he is willing to
          deliver a quantity of his <lb/>ſtyptic medicines to the ſurgeons of the hoſ- <lb/>pitals,
          in order to have ſuch experiments <lb/>made with them, as to them ſhall ſeem pro-
          <lb/>per; we have likewiſe ſeen and conſulted <lb/>with ſeveral of the ſurgeons of the
          hoſpitals, <lb/>who, we find, have enquired carefully into <lb/>the experiments, upon the
          merit of which <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Peirce</hi>'s petition to his majeſty was
          <lb/>founded, and they ſeem to apprehend thoſe <lb/>experiments of very little force and
          value. <lb/>What effectual and ſafe trials may be made <lb/>with the medicines, they have
          now under <lb/>conſideration. We humbly beg leave to re- <lb/>preſent to your lordſhip,
          that in our own <lb/>opinion, and upon our conſultation with thoſe <lb/>gentlemen, we
          think it will be of no utility <lb/>to the public to preſerve the convict in <hi
            rend="italic">New- <lb/>gate</hi> for any experiment upon the ſubject. </p>
        <signed rend="align-center italic">
          <lb/>We are, My Lord, &amp;c. </signed>
        <cb n="2"/>
        <dateline rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">London</hi>, <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 7, 1763. </dateline>
        <cb n="3"/>
        <signed rend="align-right italic">
          <lb/>John Ranby, <lb/>C. Hawkins, <lb/>D. Middleton. </signed>
          <cb n="2 3"/></body>
      </floatingText>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Upon comparing the two reports of the <lb/>ſergeant ſurgeons together, it will appear
        <lb/>that neither the ſergeant ſurgeons, nor hoſpi- <lb/>tal ſurgeons, except Mr. <hi
          rend="italic">Gataker</hi>, ever in- <lb/>tended that the efficacy of Mr. <hi
          rend="italic">Pierce</hi>'s <lb/>ſtyptic ſhould be determined by experiment. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The ſergeant ſurgeons, in their firſt report <lb/>ſay, that the experiments on brutes
        are not <lb/>a proper foundation for the experiment on <lb/>the convict, but that
        opportunities of <hi rend="italic">ſafe</hi> and <lb/><hi rend="italic">ſufficient</hi>
        experiments would ſoon offer to the <lb/>hoſpital ſurgeons, and that if from ſuch trials
        <lb/>the medicine appeared to be more efficacious <lb/>than others, there would be proper
        encou- <lb/>ragement to make the experiment on the <lb/>convict. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From this part of the report it follows that <lb/>the ſergeant ſurgeons,
        notwithſtanding the <lb/>uncertainty of the experiments on brutes, <lb/>thought that <hi
          rend="italic">ſafe</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ſufficient</hi> experiments <lb/>might be
        made on patients in an hoſpital; <lb/>and that <hi rend="italic">upon the iſſue</hi> of ſuch
        experiments, the <lb/>experiment on the criminal ſhould de- <lb/>pend. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By the ſecond report it appears, that the <lb/>hoſpital ſurgeons declined to try
        experiments, <lb/>which the ſergeant ſurgeons were of opinion, <lb/>might be tried ſafely,
        for the very reaſon <lb/>which in the opinion of the ſergeant ſurgeons <lb/>made them
        neceſſary, the uncertainty of the <lb/>experiments on brutes; and that the ſergeant
        <lb/>ſurgeons who had before certified that the <pb n="462"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>experiment on the criminal ought to depend <lb/>on the experiments in the hoſpital, now
        cer- <lb/>tified that it would be to no purpoſe to pre- <lb/>ſerve the convict, though no
        experiment in <lb/>the hoſpital had been made. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After this report Mr. <hi rend="italic">Pierce</hi> applied again <lb/>to the hoſpital
        ſurgeons, earneſtly preſſing a <lb/>trial of his medicine, but they ſaid they would
        <lb/>make no trial, except the ſergeant ſurgeons <lb/>would ſet them the example. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Thus the experiment on the convict was <lb/>evaded, upon pretence that previous experi-
        <lb/>ments in the hoſpital were neceſſary, and <lb/>theſe previous experiments were evaded,
        up- <lb/>on pretence that they were not properly au- <lb/>thorized. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After this diſappointment Mr. <hi rend="italic">Pierce</hi> de- <lb/>ſiſted from other
        ſolicitations, till he read a <lb/>letter from a friend, giving an account that <lb/>his
        ſtyptic medicines had been ſucceſsfully <lb/>applied upon a young negro ſlave, about 19
        <lb/>years old, whoſe leg had been bitten off by <lb/>a ſhark, as he was bathing in a river. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As this event, properly atteſted, ſeemed <lb/>to obviate the principal objection
        againſt the <lb/>experiment on a criminal made in the firſt <lb/>report, <q
          rend="diple quotes">that it was not authorized by any <lb/>experiments on brutes, there
          being no pre- <lb/>ciſe analogy between their arteries and <lb/>thoſe of men. </q> Mr. <hi
          rend="italic">Pierce</hi> thought him- <lb/>ſelf ſufficiently authorized to ſolicit
        another <lb/>trial on a convict. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He therefore drew up a memorial, to <lb/>which the letter he had received was annexed,
        <lb/>repreſenting his former application and diſ- <lb/>appointment, the ſerjeant-ſurgeons
        declaring <lb/>that experiments on brutes did not authorize <lb/>an experiment on a convict;
        and the hoſpital- <lb/>ſurgeons declaring that they would not make <lb/>the experiment which
        the ſerjeant-ſurgeons <lb/>ſuppoſed might be made ſafely, except the <lb/>ſerjeant ſurgeons
        would firſt warrant them by <lb/>their example; and alledging the fact related <lb/>in the
        letter as obviating the firſt and great ob- <lb/>jection, he prayed that his majeſty would
        or- <lb/>der an experiment to be made on the limb of <lb/>ſome perſon already condemned to
        death; <lb/>and that the operation might be publickly per- <lb/>formed by a perſon to be
        appointed by the <lb/>memorialiſt, every gentleman of the faculties <lb/>of phyſick and
        ſurgery being at liberty to be <lb/>preſent at the experiment, and to ſee the firſt
        <lb/>dreſſings. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This memorial was accompanied with a pe- <lb/>tition of four convicts, earneſtly
        beſeeching <lb/>his majeſty to permit them undergo the o- <lb/>peration. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In conſequence of this memorial and peti- <lb/>tions, his majeſty gave orders that Mr.
          <hi rend="italic">Pierce</hi>
        <lb/>ſhould take whichſoever of the petitioners he <lb/>might think fitteſt for his purpoſe,
        and the <lb/>moſt deſerving of mercy; and Mr. <hi rend="italic">Pierce</hi> fix- <lb/>ed
        upon <hi rend="italic">John Benham</hi>, becauſe he was a man <lb/>of better character than
        the others, had three <lb/>children, and a wife pregnant with a fourth; <lb/>and becauſe
        being a white-ſmith, the <lb/>loſs of a leg would not prevent him from <lb/>ſupporting his
        family honeſtly by his trade. <lb/>When all things were in readineſs, Mr. <hi rend="italic"
          >Pierce</hi>
        <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>applied to two gentlemen of eminence in the <lb/>profeſſion, who firſt conſented, but
        afterwards <lb/>declined to perform the operation; he then <lb/>applied to two other
        gentlemen, with no bet- <lb/>ter ſucceſs, for after they had conſented upon, <lb/>condition
        they had an authority under his ma- <lb/>jeſt's hand, they excuſed themſelves to Mr.
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Hume</hi>, who had been applied to for ſuch au- <lb/>thority, upon
        account of ſuppoſed danger to <lb/>their perſons and characters. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Hume</hi> then aſked Mr. <hi rend="italic">Pierce</hi>, if he
        <lb/>choſe to have the ſerjeant ſurgeons appointed <lb/>to perform the operation? Mr. <hi
          rend="italic">Pierce</hi> took <lb/>two days to anſwer this queſtion, what he
        <lb/>determined he has not told us, but when the <lb/>two days were expired, he went to Mr.
        Se- <lb/>cretary <hi rend="italic">Conway</hi>'s, according to appointment, <lb/>where he
        was received by Mr. <hi rend="italic">Hume</hi>, who in- <lb/>formed him that the ſerjeant
        ſurgeons attended <lb/>in the next room, by the king's order, but <lb/>that they had
        repreſented the buſineſs in ſo un- <lb/>favourable a light, as greatly to have provok-
        <lb/>ed Mr. <hi rend="italic">Conway</hi> at his preſumption in troub- <lb/>ling him with a
        ſecond application, after he <lb/>had made one of the ſame kind when Lord <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Egremont</hi> was ſecretary of ſtate, and which <lb/>had been dropped in
        conſequence of the rea- <lb/>ſons alledged againſt it by the ſerjeant ſurge- <lb/><choice>
          <corr>ons</corr>
          <sic>geons</sic>
        </choice> in their reports. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>What thoſe reaſons were the reader has juſt <lb/>ſeen; if he does not think them
        ſatisfactory <lb/>he will certainly be ſorry that the influence of <lb/>the ſerjeant
        ſurgeons was ſufficient totally to <lb/>diſappoint this ſecond application. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The effect of their influence is certainly <lb/>pernicious to the publick: The medicine
        is <lb/>either efficacious or not; if efficacious, many <lb/>will be deprived of its
        benefit, by fearing to <lb/>uſe what is not eſtabliſhed by experiment; if <lb/>not
        efficacious, many will truſt it to their hurt <lb/>upon ſuch evidence as has been often
        brought <lb/>in favour of noſtrums that are not only in- <lb/>effectual, but pernicious. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A method of ſecuring large veſſels, with- <lb/>out the painful operation of taking them
        up, <lb/>would certainly prevent infinite miſery, and <lb/>preſerve many lives; but if ſuch
        a method <lb/>was actually diſcovered, it is impoſſible that <lb/>the publick ſhould be
        benefited by it, if <lb/>the ſame methods are taken to prevent its be- <lb/>ing brought to
        the teſt of experiment that <lb/>were taken with this, which, for ought that <lb/>appears,
        may be all that is pretended or de- <lb/>ſired. Nothing but a demonſtration <hi
          rend="italic">a priori</hi>
        <lb/>that no ſuch medicine can exiſt, ought to pre- <lb/>clude ſuch experiments as can alone
        demon- <lb/>ſtrate whether it exiſts or not. If nothing can <lb/>be inferred from trials
        upon brutes, and this <lb/>is made a reaſon againſt trials upon men, all <lb/>improvement in
        this important article of ſur- <lb/>gery is precluded for ever. </p>
      <signed rend="align-right">X. </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
