<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Concerning the present peculiar method of treating persons
          inoculated for the small-pox</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Thoughts arising from experience concerning the present peculiar method of
              treating persons inoculated for the small-pox. By W. Bromfield , surgeon to her Royal
              Highness the princess dowager of Wales . Dodsley Price 2 s. 6 d. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed at St John's Gate, for D. Henry; and sold by F. Newbery,
                  the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard, Ludgate Street.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1767</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">37</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">413</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1767_GM_0413">
    <body>
      <pb n="413"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">30.</hi> Thoughts ariſing from experience concern- <lb/>ing the
        preſent peculiar method of treating per- <lb/>ſons inoculated for the ſmall-pox. By <hi
          rend="roman">W. <lb/>Bromfield</hi>, ſurgeon to her <hi rend="roman">Royal Highneſs the
          <lb/>princeſs dowager of <hi rend="italic">Wales</hi></hi>. <hi rend="roman">Dodſley
          Price</hi>
        <lb/>2 s. 6 d. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr Bromfield has ranged his thoughts un- <lb/>der the following heads: <list>
          <item rend="indent">
            <lb/>1. The preparation of the patient. </item>
          <item rend="indent">
            <lb/>2. The manner of operation. </item>
          <item rend="indent">
            <lb/>3. The nature of the diſeaſe. </item>
          <item rend="indent">
            <lb/>4. The uſe of cold air. </item>
          <item rend="indent">
            <lb/>5. The effect of retarding and leſſening <lb/>the eruption. </item>
        </list>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>1. Preparation. Mr. <hi rend="italic">Bromfield</hi> thinks mer- <lb/>curial purges not
        elegible as a general prac- <lb/>tiſe, and has known inſtances of great miſ- <lb/>chief to
        the conſtitution reſulting from ino- <lb/>culation, when the patient has been reduced
        <lb/>too low. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Under this head no inſtance is given of <lb/>miſchief reſulting from what he calls <hi
          rend="italic">the pre- <lb/>ſent peculiar method</hi>. He obſerves, contrary <lb/>to the
        opinion of Dr. <hi rend="italic">Langton</hi>, that the <lb/><hi rend="italic">whole</hi>
        depends upon the <hi rend="italic">habit of body of the <lb/>
          <q rend="quotes">perſon inoculated, </q></hi> and that inoculation <lb/>from the matter of
        an inoculated ſmall-pox, <lb/>is equally efficacious as from that of the na- <lb/><choice>
          <corr>tural</corr>
          <sic>aural</sic>
        </choice> ſort, for that twenty children having <lb/>been inoculated with variolous matter,
        taken <lb/>from a perſon who was the fourteenth in <lb/>deſcent from the natural ſort, all
        of them <lb/>took the infection, ſome had the diſeaſe fa- <lb/>vourably, in others it was
        rather ſevere. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>2. The manner of operation. Mr. <hi rend="italic">Brom- <lb/>field</hi> does not under
        this head object to the <lb/>performance of inoculation, from matter in <lb/>a crude ſtate,
        but thinks the introduction of <lb/>matter between the cutis and cuticle, not ſo <lb/>good a
        method as that uſually practiſed: he <lb/>is alſo of opinion, that inoculation in an
        <lb/>hoſpital is not elegible, becauſe there is <lb/>danger of receiving the infection by
        the <lb/>mouth and noſtrils: but he gives no inſtance <lb/>of injury thus received by any
        patient of thoſe <lb/>who inoculate in the <hi rend="italic">preſent peculiar method</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>3. Of the nature of the diſeaſe. Under <lb/>this head there is not even an inſinuation
        <lb/>that the diſeaſe produced by the preſent pe- <lb/>culiar method of inoculation, is not
        the true <lb/>ſmall-pox. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>4. Of retarding the eruption. There is <lb/>nothing under this head but what is greatly
        <lb/>in favour of the <hi rend="italic">new method</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>5. Of the effect of cold air. Mr. <hi rend="italic">Brom- <lb/>field</hi> does not
        approve the preſent method of <lb/>expoſing variolous patients to the cold air <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">after the eruption is perfect</hi>, he recommends <lb/>his patients, he
        ſays, to be then kept in <lb/>bed, becauſe the ſpecies of the diſeaſe can- <lb/>not be then
        altered, and becauſe the be<unclear>d</unclear>
        <pb n="414"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>muſt, like a general pultiſe, forward the <lb/>maturation. But it does not appear from
        <lb/>any thing Mr. <hi rend="italic">Bromfield</hi> has ſaid, that ex- <lb/>perience has in
        any inſtance ſhewn his me- <lb/>thod to be better than that which he con- <lb/>demns. He
        ſays indeed, that all who have <lb/>attended the deſeaſe in the uſual method, <lb/>muſt have
        experienced, that when the pa- <lb/>tient has been taken up to make his bed, <lb/>he has
        ſometimes become ſick with a pain <lb/>in the ſtomach and reaching, in conſequence <lb/>of
        checked perſpiration by cold air, and <lb/>that ſuch threatening ſymptoms have not
        <lb/>diſappeared till he has been again put <lb/>to bed and a neceſſary cordial
        adminiſtered. <lb/>But he has not produced one inſtance in <lb/>which it became neceſſary to
        put a patient <lb/>to bed, who had been under the care of any <lb/>perſon who inoculates in
        the <hi rend="italic">preſent method</hi>
        <lb/>and who had, as Mr. <hi rend="italic">Bromfield</hi> expreſſes it, <lb/>been <hi
          rend="italic">turned into the ſtreet</hi> as ſoon as the <lb/>eruption was perfect. It
        follows then, for <lb/>ought that appears in this book, that what <lb/>cannot be ſafely done
        by thoſe who do not <lb/>practiſe, or perhaps know, the preſent pe- <lb/>culiar method, may
        be ſafely, and even ad- <lb/>vantageouſly done by thoſe that do. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>5. Of the time of purging. Nothing is <lb/>advanced under this head againſt the me-
        <lb/>thod in queſtion, founded either upon argu- <lb/>ment or experience. Mr. <hi
          rend="italic">Bromfield</hi> obſerves <lb/>that the operators in this method, although
        <lb/>the patient has no more than 15 puſtules <lb/><hi rend="italic">except he chuſes
          it</hi>, do yet purge, as they ſay <lb/>to prevent boils, and if the ferment is raiſ-
        <lb/>ed, ſays he, and the blood not depurated <lb/>by the ſkin, the reſidium ought to be
        car- <lb/>ried off by the inteſtines: thus far they are <lb/>agreed, but <hi rend="italic"
          >Mr. Bromfield</hi> then puts the fol- <lb/>lowing queſtion. <q rend="diple">Are there not
          inſtances <lb/>of this <hi rend="italic">ſaid enemy</hi> being <hi rend="italic">only
            down</hi> in the <lb/>battle? and though he may not ever be <lb/>able to ſhew his face
          as he intended, in <lb/>the character of the ſmall-pox; does he not <lb/>ſometimes, after
          a little recruiting, teaze <lb/>and torment in a variety of forms, ſo as <lb/>to deſtroy
          the patients, though he is <lb/>ſomewhat tedious in the execution. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This quere, whether there are <hi rend="italic">not</hi> ſuch <lb/>inſtances may be
        anſwered by another, are <lb/>there ſuch inſtances; if ſo, let the oppoſers <lb/>of the
        peculiar method produce them, and <lb/>their purpoſe will be effectually anſwered,
        <lb/>whether it is to benefit mankind, or to <lb/>recover a gainful branch of practiſe, out
        <lb/>of the hands of thoſe that have taken it from <lb/>them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Bromfield</hi> indeed ſays, that he has <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >heard</hi> of great numbers that have ſuffered <lb/>in their health ever ſince they were
        inocu- <lb/>lated, and treated on this modern plan, but <lb/>as hearſay is no evidence, it
        is earneſtly re- <lb/>commended to thoſe who have thus ſuffered, <lb/>if there are any ſuch,
        to communicate their <lb/>caſes to the public as a moſt important duty, <lb/>having health
        and life for its object, parti- <lb/>cularly, of the riſing generation. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Under this head there is a very remarkable <lb/>paragraph which ſeems to imply,
        contrary <unclear>to</unclear>
        <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Langton</hi>'s opinion, that the true ſmall-pox, <lb/>may be
        inoculated by the application of mat- <lb/>ter in a crude ſtate. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>At what particular period of the ſmall- <lb/>pox the diſeaſe is infectious cannot, I
        be- <lb/>lieve, ſays Mr. <hi rend="italic">Bromfield</hi>, be aſcertained to <lb/>the
        ſatisfaction of contending parties, but <lb/><hi rend="italic">we have known</hi>, that when
        ſervants who at- <lb/>tended children, have ſickened with the <lb/>ſmall-pox, and the
        children have been re- <lb/>moved to a great diſtance of the <hi rend="italic">firſt ſuſpi-
          <lb/>cious ſymptom</hi>, ſuch children have within a <lb/>few days been ſeized with the
        ſame diſ- <lb/>eaſe. In this caſe Mr. <hi rend="italic">Bromfield</hi> ſuppoſes <lb/>the
        diſeaſe to have been communicated by <lb/>the breath. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Upon the whole, it would be ſtrange if ig- <lb/>norant and bold adventurers, who
        practiſe as <lb/>much of the preſent peculiar method of ino- <lb/>culation as they know,
        ſhould not do ſome <lb/>miſchief for want of knowing more, but <lb/>even their miſcarriages
        are few, and if they <lb/>were numerous, would be no objection to <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic"
          >Sutton</hi>'s practiſe. An account of par- <lb/>ticular caſes well atteſted, as well of
        ſuch <lb/>as have been treated by Mr. <hi rend="italic">Sutton</hi>, as by <lb/>thoſe who
        have adopted his method in ge- <lb/>neral, without knowing particularly the <lb/>medicines
        he uſes, would be a moſt uſeful <lb/>work. Till ſuch account appears, the <hi rend="italic"
          >apparent</hi>
        <lb/>ſucceſs of what is called the <hi rend="italic">preſent peculiar <lb/>method</hi> muſt
        weigh more in its favour with <lb/>every diſintereſted diſpaſſionate perſon, than <lb/>any
        reaſoning however ſpecious can weigh <lb/>againſt it. Experience alone is the fountain
        <lb/>of true medical knowledge. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Bromfield</hi> is certainly a good ſurgeon, <lb/>but he appears
        by this little tract to be a very <lb/>bad writer, for there is ſcarce one period in <lb/>it
        that is not rendered defective, obſcure, and <lb/>inconcluſive by falſe concord and ſyntax.
        By <lb/>the following ſpecimen the reader may judge <lb/>of the reſt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="diple">Suppoſing a patient had a malignant fe- <lb/>ver, <hi rend="italic"
            >which</hi>, after many efforts to deſtroy <lb/>the patient, <hi rend="italic">dame
            nature</hi> ſhould kindly in- <lb/>terfere, and produce a critical tumour; <lb/>would
          any ſurgeon of ſkill prevent its <lb/>coming to ſuppuration? To ſay that <hi rend="italic"
            >tum <lb/>mours</hi> are reſolved without ill conſequence <lb/>is not an anſwer, <hi
            rend="italic">it</hi> muſt be the effect of <lb/>a malignant fever, and then I think no
          <lb/>man in his ſenſes would riſk the conſe- <lb/>quences. <hi rend="italic">This</hi> may
          not be ſo evident to <lb/>all, as the following <hi rend="italic">fact</hi>; ſuppoſing the
          <lb/>inguinal glands <hi rend="italic">became</hi> the ſeat of the <gap reason="illegible"/>
          <lb/>
          <gap reason="illegible"/> of venereal virus, and matter in the <lb/>body of <hi
            rend="italic">the tumour</hi>, not to be <hi rend="italic">felt</hi> by <hi
            rend="italic">the <lb/>touch</hi>, the ſwelling had been diſperſed, <lb/>and for a few
          weeks the patient <hi rend="italic">has</hi> thought <lb/>himſelf well; <hi rend="italic"
            >but how much more frequent <lb/>is it</hi>, that he feels violent nocturnal pains
          <lb/>in his head, arms, and ſhins, which be- <lb/>ing taken by the unſkilful for rheumatic
            <gap reason="illegible"/>
          <lb/>the warm bath and ſweating is adviſed; <lb/>the pains are relieved by an eruption,
          that <lb/>ſoon determines under what claſs to rank it. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Every reader will diſcover this paſſage <lb/>to be groſsly inaccurate, becauſe
          <unclear>every rea-</unclear>
        <pb n="415"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>der will find it unintelligible; the particu- <lb/>lar parts in which the inaccuracy
        principally <lb/>conſiſts, are diſtinguiſhed by <hi rend="italic">Italics</hi>, and it
        <lb/>is preſumed that a comment is unneceſſary; <lb/>perhaps the author's meaning may be ex-
        <lb/>preſſed by what follows: </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Suppoſe a tumour, in conſequence of a <lb/>venereal virus depoſited upon the inguinal
        <lb/>glands, and ſuppoſe that the matter not be- <lb/>ing ſenſible to the touch, the tumour
        ſhould <lb/>be diſperſed: the patient might perhaps <lb/>think himſelf well for a few weeks,
        but he <lb/>would ſoon, if not immediately, feel vio- <lb/>lent nocturnal pains in his head,
        arms and <lb/>ſhins, and if an unſkilful phyſician or ſur- <lb/>geon ſhould ſuppoſe his
        pains to be rheuma- <lb/>tic, and order him the warm bath and ſweat- <lb/>ing, he ſoon would
        be releaved by an erup- <lb/>tion, ſufficiently characteriſtic to aſcertain <lb/>its
        ſpecies, </p>
      <signed rend="align-right">X. </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
