<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: An Essay on the Diseases most fatal to Infants</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Essay on the Diseases most fatal to Infants. To which are added, Rules to be
              observed in the Nursing of Children: with a particular View to those who are brought
              up by Hand. By George Armstrong, M. D. Cadell. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed at St John's Gate, for D. Henry; and sold by F. Newbery,
                  the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard, Ludgate Street.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1767</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">37</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">362</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1767_GM_0362">
    <body>
      <pb n="362"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">11.</hi> An Eſſay on the Diſeaſes moſt fatal <lb/>to Infants. To which
        are added, Rules <lb/>to be obſerved in the Nurſing of Children: <lb/>with a particular View
        to thoſe who are <lb/>brought up by Hand. By <hi rend="roman">George Arm- <lb/>ſtrong, M. D.
          Cadell.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The author of this uſeful treatiſe re- <lb/>marks, that though a great part of our
        <lb/>ſpecies dies in infancy, yet the diſeaſes <lb/>peculiar to infants, are neither ſo
        nume- <lb/>rous, nor their nature ſo difficult to diſ- <lb/>cover, as is generally imagined. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the firſt place, infants are not ſub- <lb/>ject to any of the diſeaſes which grown
        <lb/>perſons frequently bring upon themſelves <lb/>by intemperance, or to thoſe which are
        <lb/>often the conſequence of hard labour, <lb/>violent exerciſe, the inclemency of the
        <lb/>weather, heats, colds, damps, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> They <lb/>ſuffer nothing
        from anxiety or ſorrow, <lb/>which kill many thouſands by bringing <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>on fevers, low ſpirits, and all ſorts of <lb/>nervous diſorders: and as to hereditary
        <lb/>diſeaſes, ſuch as the gout, the conſump- <lb/>tion, and the palſy, few of them appear
        <lb/>in infancy, and from the diſeaſes pecu- <lb/>liar to puberty, which in the female ſex
        <lb/>are various and ſometimes mortal, they <lb/>are exempted of courſe. The diſeaſes
        <lb/>of infants therefore are comparatively <lb/>few, for, except what the nurſes call in-
        <lb/>ward fits, teething, and the rickets, chil- <lb/>dren are ſubject to no diſeaſe from
        which <lb/>adults are free. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The diſeaſes of children almoſt all ariſe <lb/>from one common cauſe, their tender
        <lb/>bowels being overloaded with ſlimy ſe- <lb/>cretions from the glands of the mouth,
        <lb/>fauces, gullet, ſtomach, and inteſtines, <lb/>but above all the liver and the pancreas. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Theſe ſecretions are much larger in <lb/>proportion in children than adults, and
        <lb/>as they cannot uſe exerciſe, and the <lb/>nurſes frequently neglect to give it them
        <lb/>and rub them, the contents of the ſto- <lb/>mach and bowels ſtagnate, and by their
        <lb/>viſcidity or acrimony, or both, produce <lb/>various diſeaſes and death. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The firſt complaint that appears in <lb/>children is generally inward fits; theſe,
        <lb/>if not removed, degenerate into an almoſt <lb/>conſtant drowſineſs, which is ſucceeded
        <lb/>by a fever and the truſh; or terminate <lb/>in vomittings, ſour, curdled, or green
        <lb/>ſtools, the watry gripes and convulſions, <lb/>and indeed the thruſh ſometimes termi-
        <lb/>nates in theſe ſymptoms. Theſe all ariſe <lb/>from the cauſe that has been juſt
        aſſigned, <lb/>and may be conſidered as different ſtages <lb/>of the ſame diſeaſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To prevent inward fits, the firſt ſtage, <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Armſtrong</hi>
        adviſes that the child be <lb/>never laid down to ſleep after it has <lb/>ſucked or been
        fed, till it has broke <lb/>wind. To facilitate which the nurſe <lb/>ſhould hold it ſloping
        in her arms, dan- <lb/>dle it, pat its back, and rub the palms of <lb/>its hands pretty
        ſmartly. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If inward fits are not prevented by <lb/>theſe expedients, he recommends a gentle
        <lb/>puke, to be repeated from time to time <lb/>as occaſion requires. The beſt puke, he
        <lb/>ſays, is from 5 to 10 drops of antimonial <lb/>wine. He has given 5 drops to infants
        <lb/>a few days after their birth with ſucceſs, <lb/>and ſeldom gives a larger doſe till
        they <lb/>are about a month old; repeating it with- <lb/>in half an hour, if the firſt does
        not ope- <lb/>rate; after the firſt month he gives 7, 8, <lb/>9, or 10 drops, and at three
        or four <lb/>months old from 10 to 15. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But there is one rule, ſays the doctor, <lb/>which ought conſtantly to be obſerved
        <lb/>in adminiſtring vomits to infants, as well <pb n="363"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>as adults; always firſt to open the body, <lb/>if coſtive, by a gentle purge or
        clyſter. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To cure the thruſh, he adviſes firſt to <lb/>empty the ſtomach and then the inteſ-
        <lb/>tines, and for this purpoſe nothing ſuc- <lb/>ceeds better than the antimonial wine. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The beſt topical application , he ſays, <lb/>is a ſolution of white vitriol in common
        <lb/>water, about half a ſcruple to 8 ounces. <lb/>The ſolution is to be made a little warm,
        <lb/>and a linen rag is to be dipped in it, then <lb/>either with the finger, or laid on a
        bit of <lb/>ſtick, the mouth is to be rubbed with it <lb/>three or four times in four and
        twenty <lb/>hours. If a little is ſwallowed ſo much <lb/>the better. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When a child is ſeized with a purging, <lb/>of whatever kind, it is common to give
        <lb/>ſmall doſes of rhubarb or magneſia, but <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Armſtrong</hi>
        recommends as better <lb/>than either, ſuch a puke as is mentioned <lb/>above, which
        generally operates both <lb/>ways, and which, if the child's ſtrength <lb/>will bear it,
        ſhould be repeated every five <lb/>or ſix hours till the ſtools begin to change <lb/>for the
        better, then every eight or ten <lb/>hours till they return to their natural <lb/>colour and
        conſiſtence. The doctor has <lb/>ſeldom found any other medicine neceſ- <lb/>ſary except a
        gentle paregoric, ſuch as a <lb/>drachm of the <hi rend="italic">ſyr. papav. rheados</hi>,
        in a <lb/>large ſpoonful of weak cinnamon-water; <lb/>after the firſt paſſages have been
        cleanſed, <lb/>if the child is ſtill griped and reſtleſs, <lb/>to be repeated every three or
        four hours <lb/>till reſt and eaſe are procured. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When the ſtools have ſmelt very ſour, <lb/>or have been curdled or green, three or
        <lb/>four drops of the <hi rend="italic">lixivium tartari</hi>, have <lb/>been given with
        the emetic; and after- <lb/>wards between whiles, the ſame quanti- <lb/>ty in a little
        water, ſweetened with ſugar, <lb/>or ſyrup, with very good ſucceſs. This <lb/>medicine is
        particularly uſeful when the <lb/>milk is apt to curdle on the ſtomach. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The convulſions of children are gene- <lb/>rally ſymptomatic, and ariſe from an ir-
        <lb/>ritation in the ſtomach or bowels, or in <lb/>the gums in the time of teething: if the
        <lb/>irritation is in the ſtomach and bowels, <lb/>whatever clears the bowels of thin acid
        <lb/>contents, or renders theſe contents mild <lb/>and inoffenſive, will remove the convul-
        <lb/>ſions: for theſe purpoſes the puke al- <lb/>ready mentioned is recommended, firſt
        <lb/>giving a clyſter if the child is coſtive, <lb/>repeating the puke occaſionally, and
        <lb/>keeping the body open between whiles <lb/>with the magneſia or rhubarb, in ſmall
        <lb/>quantities mixed with abſorbents. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If convulſions proceed from the ſtrik- <lb/>ing in of the raſh, or the ſudden ſtopping
        <lb/>of the ſalutary diſcharge behind the ears, <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>then, beſides the method preſcribed above, <lb/>it will be neceſſary to apply a bliſter
        be- <lb/>tween the ſhoulders, or a couple behind <lb/>the ears: in this caſe too the warm
        bath <lb/>is ſometimes of great ſervice. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When a child is ſeized with convul- <lb/>ſions without any other complaint, and
        <lb/>without the drying up of the diſcharge <lb/>behind the ears, it is reaſonable to con-
        <lb/>clude that they ariſe immediately from <lb/>the brain. As to theſe, Dr <hi
          rend="italic">Armſtrong</hi> ſays, <lb/>perhaps ſharp clyſters, the ſemicupium,
        <lb/>bliſtering the legs or feet, or behind the <lb/>ears, may be of uſe, but he ſays he can
        <lb/>recommend no ſucceſsful way of treating <lb/>this dreadful diſorder from experience. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The danger that attends teething, the <lb/>doctor thinks ariſes wholly from too
        <lb/>great a fullneſs, or from corrupt hu- <lb/>mours, put in agitation by the pain
        <lb/>which the tooth cauſes in breaking its <lb/>way out. And in either caſe evacua-
        <lb/>tions muſt be of great ſervice: the eva- <lb/>cuation recommended is the ſame as be-
        <lb/>fore. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When the fever runs high, and the <lb/>teeth are near cutting, it may be proper <lb/>to
        launch the gum. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When a raſh appears, of whatever <lb/>ſort, if the child is otherwiſe well, it is
        <lb/>beſt not to meddle with it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When the raſh that frequently appears <lb/>upon children ſoon after they are born
        <lb/>is ſtruck in, the warm bath has been of <lb/>ſingular ſervice, in concert with the me-
        <lb/>thod before directed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Armſtrong</hi> ſays, he has tried the <lb/>antimonial ſolution in
        the whooping <lb/>cough, with very good ſucceſs, and is of <lb/>opinion that if it is given
        in time, it will <lb/>render the diſorder leſs violent and te- <lb/>dious. In this diſeaſe,
        he gives the ſolu- <lb/>tion once or twice a day if the child can <lb/>bear it, in a
        ſufficient quantity to bring <lb/>up the phlegm, which children always <lb/>ſwallow inſtead
        of ſpitting out. If the <lb/>cough is worſe at any particular hour of <lb/>the day, he gives
        it about an hour before <lb/>the paroxyſm is expected, and if it is <lb/>worſe in the night,
        about an hour before <lb/>bed-time. When the violence of the <lb/>cough is over, it is
        ſufficient to adminiſter <lb/>the medicine once or twice a week. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the very dry air of <hi rend="italic">Hampſtead</hi>, Dr. <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Armſtrong</hi> had but two patients that were <lb/>troubled with the rickets; with
        reſpect <lb/>to theſe a few gentle doſes of rhubarb, <lb/>keeping the child dry and clean,
        and rub- <lb/>bing it carefully all over two or three <lb/>times a day, together with the
        cold bath, <lb/>generally effected the cure in a ſhort <lb/>time. </p>
      <pb n="364"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Of the rules for nurſing given by this <lb/>author, the following are the chief. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Every mother who can, ought to ſuckle <lb/>her child, for her own ſake, at leaſt for
        <lb/>the firſt few weeks. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If it is neceſſary to bring a child up <lb/>by hand, it is better to feed it with the
        <lb/>boat than the horn. The horn is a po- <lb/>liſh'd cow's horn, which will hold about
        <lb/>a gill and an half: the ſmall end of it <lb/>is perforated, and has a notch round it,
        <lb/>to which are faſtened two ſmall bits of <lb/>parchments, ſhaped like the tip of the
        <lb/>finger of a glove, and ſewed together <lb/>in ſuch a manner as that the food poured
        <lb/>into the horn can be ſucked through be- <lb/>tween the ſtitches. This appears to be
        <lb/>a very ſimple and ingenious contrivance, <lb/>and it might well be conſidered as an
        <lb/>artificial nipple, if we had breaſt milk <lb/>to convey through it; but Dr. <hi
          rend="italic">Arm- <lb/>ſtrong</hi> thinks that cows milk is not a <lb/>good ſuccedaneum,
        and adviſes thicker <lb/>food for the child than can paſs through <lb/>this inſtrument. The
        food he recom- <lb/>mends is crumb of bread boiled in ſoft <lb/>water, to the conſiſtance of
        what is com- <lb/>monly called pap, or thin panada: the <lb/>crumb of a roll baked the
        preceeding <lb/>day is the beſt. The pap ſhould be very <lb/>ſlightly ſweetened with <hi
          rend="italic">Liſbon</hi> ſugar, ex- <lb/>cept the child is of a lean habit of body,
        <lb/>in which caſe the fineſt loaf ſugar ſhould <lb/>be uſed, and ſea biſcuit ſhould be ſub-
        <lb/>ſtituted for roll. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If the infant is bred up by hand from <lb/>the birth, new cow's milk, not boiled,
        <lb/>ſhould be mixed with its victuals as of- <lb/>ten as poſſible, and now and then ſome
        <lb/>milk alone ſhould be given it to drink: <lb/>aſſes milk is ſtill better than cow's. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If the child is troubled with wind, <lb/>boil a few bruiſed juniper berries, or a
        <lb/>little grated ginger, tied up in a rag, in <lb/>its pap, and give it now and then a pap
        <lb/>ſpoonful of weak pepper-mint water, or <lb/>ſweet-fennel water; if it is coſtive, the
        <lb/>body muſt be kept open with a little <lb/>manna, or magneſia, mixed with its <lb/>food
        as occaſion requires. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When the child comes to be uſed to <lb/>thick victuals, it ſhould have now and
        <lb/>then, between the times of feeding, wa- <lb/>ter in which the upper cruſt of bread
        <lb/>has been boiled, mixed with an equal <lb/>quantity of new milk; or when new <lb/>milk
        cannot be had, with boiled milk, <lb/>ſweetened with a very little ſugar. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When the child comes to be about <lb/>three or four months old, if the victuals
        <lb/>turns ſower on the ſtomach, it will be <lb/>right to uſe weak broth, either of chicken,
        <lb/>veal, or mutton, or beef tea, inſtead of <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>milk, in its food, or at leaſt it may be <lb/>fed with this once or twice a day. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When the child is ſix months old, if <lb/>it is cool, and not inclined to be fat, it
        <lb/>may have at noon, once in 2 or 3 days, <lb/>a very little bit of the white of a boiled
        <lb/>chicken minced very ſmall, and mixed <lb/>into a kind of pap with ſome of the li-
        <lb/>quor that the chicken was boiled in, and <lb/>a good deal of crumb of bread. When
        <lb/>it is inclined to be feveriſh, it muſt have <lb/>nothing of this kind. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>At this age it may have a little plain <lb/>light bread pudding now and then for
        <lb/>dinner; and the nurſe ſhould every <lb/>morning give it a piece of the upper <lb/>cruſt
        of a loaf cut in the ſhape and <lb/>about the ſize of a large Savoy biſcuit, <lb/>one end of
        it dipped in its food, or a <lb/>little milk, the other put into its hand. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The victuals ſhould be made freſh <lb/>twice a day in winter, and three times in
        <lb/>ſummer, and the milk, if new cannot be <lb/>had, and it is neceſſary to boil it, ſhould
        <lb/>never be boiled with the pap, but added <lb/>when the child is fed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The child ſhould be fed chiefly in the <lb/>day time, and put into the habit of ſleep-
        <lb/>ing during the night as ſoon as poſſible; <lb/>at firſt it ſhould be fed frequently,
        and <lb/>by a little at a time; but victuals ſhould <lb/>never be forced upon a child when
        it <lb/>refuſes it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It will greatly contribute to a child's <lb/>reſting at night, if the nurſe, the laſt
        <lb/>thing ſhe does, takes up the child, opens <lb/>it before the fire, turns it dry, and
        feeds <lb/>it, <hi rend="italic">even if it is aſleep</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As to cloathing, children ſhould have <lb/>nothing tight about them, and as few
        <lb/>pins as poſſible. They ought to be <lb/>kept rather warm for the firſt four
        <lb/>months; becauſe, during that time, they <lb/>eaſily catch cold; for the ſame reaſon
        <lb/>they ought to be carefully kept dry. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As to ſleep, Dr. <hi rend="italic">Armſtrong</hi> condemns <lb/>opiates, and prefers
        the bed to the cradle. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The child ought not to be jolted on <lb/>the knee or lap, and though it ſhould <lb/>be
        dandled to divert it and keep it awake <lb/>in the day; it ſhould be done gently at
        <lb/>firſt, and never with a jerk: neither <lb/>ſhould they be hoiſted up high in the
        <lb/>air between the hands, for they are very <lb/>early ſuſceptible of fear. The moſt uſe-
        <lb/>ful exerciſe for very young children, is <lb/>rubbing with the hand, which cannot be
        <lb/>too often repeated, nor continued too <lb/>long, except they have a purging, and
        <lb/>then it ſhould be forborne. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The nurſe ſhould alſo every morning, <lb/>after having well rubbed the child, waſh
        <lb/>its back, loins, groin, and between its <pb n=""/>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>An illustration of a woman with a child, the child holding a small goblet,
            filling an entire (unnumbered) page. The caption reads "<hi rend="italic">From a Drawing
              of Haeslen in 1701. Engraved by Baſan.</hi>" </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <pb n="365"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>thighs, alſo its limbs, all over with cold <lb/>water, and afterwards dry them carefully<choice>
          <corr>.</corr>
          <sic>,</sic>
        </choice>
        <lb/>The head, and behind the ears, the <lb/>neck, arms, and hands, ſhould be waſh- <lb/>ed
        in the ſame manner and dried. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If the ſkin is chafed, it ſhould be firſt <lb/>dried with a fine cloth, and ſome com-
        <lb/>mon powder ſhould be applied with a <lb/>ſoft puff. If it is much galled, as ſome-
        <lb/>times happens by the heat and ſharpneſs <lb/>of the urine, ſome fuller's earth muſt be
        <lb/>diſſolved in a ſufficient quantity of hot <lb/>water, and when it has ſtood till it is
        cold, <lb/>the galled parts muſt be gently rubbed <lb/>with it once or twice a day. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The doctor condemns the uſe of ceruſs <lb/>for this purpoſe, as pernicious to the
        <lb/>nerves. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The book is in general well written; <lb/>there is therefore the greater reaſon to
        <lb/>obſerve, that in more places than one, it <lb/>gives countenance to a barbariſm that
        <lb/>ſeems unaccountably to be gaining <lb/>ground in our language; the ſubſtitu- <lb/>tion
        of <hi rend="italic">lay</hi> for <hi rend="italic">lie</hi>, the preterit for the
        <lb/>preſent. This author ſays, <q rend="diple quotes">the child <lb/>will <hi rend="italic"
            >lay</hi> and divert itſelf. </q> So in the <lb/>participle, <q rend="diple quotes"
          >every body knows the <lb/>pernicious effects of <hi rend="italic">laying</hi> in
          ill-aired <lb/>ſheets. </q>
      </p>
      <signed rend="align-right">X. </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
