<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - A. M.: Observations on the general Practice of Inoculation</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>A. M. </persName>
            </author>
            <title>Observations on the general Practice of Inoculation</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed at St John's Gate, for D. Henry; and sold by F. Newbery,
                  the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard, Ludgate Street.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1767</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">37</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">634</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1767_GM_0634">
    <body>
      <pb n="634"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <salute rend="indent">
        <lb/>SIR, </salute>
      <dateline rend="align-right"><hi rend="italic">Threadneedle-ſtr.</hi>
        <hi rend="italic">Dec.</hi> 26, 1767. </dateline>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE letters of the ſenſible and <lb/>humane Mr. <hi rend="italic"
          >Hanway</hi>, which <lb/>have lately been publiſhed, in regard <lb/>to the practice of
        inoculation for the <lb/><hi rend="italic">ſmall pox</hi>, remind me of ſome con-
        <lb/>verſation which paſſed in a public <lb/>company, where I was preſent, about <lb/>two
        years ſince, on the ſame ſubject; <lb/>the purport of which was, as near as <lb/>my memory
        retains it, as follows. <lb/>The great ſucceſs attending the prac- <lb/>tice; not <hi
          rend="italic">one</hi> in many hundreds dying <lb/>under the operation, the eaſe and
        <lb/>pleaſure it gave to thoſe who were <lb/>inoculated, and their families and re-
        <lb/>lations, and the happineſs they enjoy <lb/>in being able to go without fear of
        <lb/>contracting that dangerous and diſ- <lb/>agreeable diſtemper, into all places <lb/>and
        on all occaſions, and the many <lb/>valuable lives which are thereby pre- <pb n="635"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>ſerved to the community, were all <lb/>urged in its favour. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To all which a gentleman preſent <lb/>replied, that, although the <hi rend="italic"
          >apparent</hi>
        <lb/>ſucceſs is very great, it might be <lb/>doubted, if much of it was not <hi
          rend="italic">ima- <lb/>ginary</hi>, ſeeing that although the num- <lb/>ber of deaths
        under inoculation are <lb/>very inconſiderable, yet within his <lb/>knowledge, they were
        more than was <lb/>generally allowed, ſeveral valuable <lb/>lives, of which he gave ſome
        inſtances, <lb/>having been loſt thereby, and thoſe <lb/>of ſuch who otherwiſe might never
        <lb/>have had the diſtemper, and been pre- <lb/>ſerved many years to the community;
        <lb/>that ſome he feared, and thoſe not a <lb/>few, of which he alſo gave ſome in-
        <lb/>ſtances, were left in a ſtate of health <lb/>worſe than death, by the operation
        <lb/>having been performed on improper <lb/>ſubjects, or by unſkilful hands; in <lb/>ſhort,
        it appeared to him, that how- <lb/>ever beneficial inoculation might be <lb/>to <hi
          rend="italic">particulars</hi>, yet on the whole, it <lb/>is the moſt pernicious
        contrivance as <lb/>ever was found out to deſtroy man- <lb/>kind; and what confirmed him in
        his <lb/>opinion, and was more to be depend- <lb/>ed on than any reaſoning from obſer-
        <lb/>vations, however impartially and care- <lb/>fully made, he ſaid, was a fact col-
        <lb/>lected from the bills of mortality in <lb/><hi rend="italic">London</hi>, from which it
        appears, that, <lb/>taking an average of the thirty- <lb/>eight years next before, and the
        <lb/>thirty-eight years next after the prac- <lb/>tice was introduced, and comparing
        <lb/>them together, where <hi rend="italic">three</hi> died of that <lb/>diſtemper before,
          <hi rend="italic">four</hi> had died ſince; <lb/>and he ſaid it could not be doubted
        <lb/>that, if the number of deaths by that <lb/>diſtemper were increaſed to that de-
        <lb/>gree in <hi rend="italic">London</hi>, the increaſe muſt have <lb/>been much greater,
        and the miſchief <lb/>more fatal in the country at large, <lb/>many conſiderable diſtricts
        of which, <lb/>formerly knew little of the ſmall pox, <lb/>but its name, and it ſeldom
        became <lb/><hi rend="italic">rife</hi>, except in large towns, and in <lb/>them not above
        once in fifteen or <lb/>twenty years, and then by due care <lb/>it was generally confined to
        thoſe pla- <lb/>ces. He ſaid it muſt be confeſſed that <lb/>the miſchiefs he had mentioned,
        might <lb/>happen chiefly, if not wholly, for want <lb/>of a law to oblige thoſe who are
        ino- <lb/>culated, to keep themſelves ſhut up <lb/>for a proper time, as they and the
        <lb/>inoculators are continually mixing <lb/>indiſcriminately in all companies, and
        <lb/>thereby ſpread the infection to a great <lb/>degree, and communicate the diſorder
        <lb/>to many, who would not in all pro- <lb/>bability, otherwiſe ever have the diſ- <cb
          n="2"/>
        <lb/>eaſe. And he concluded with ſay- <lb/>ing, that he was fully perſuaded, that <lb/>no
        war, ſickneſs, or emigration, had <lb/>ever been ſo deſtructive to the popu- <lb/>lation of
        this kingdom, as inoculation <lb/>for the ſmall pox had already been, <lb/>and would
        continue to be, if the <lb/>legiſlature ſhould not think fit to in- <lb/>terfere and
        preſcribe, at leaſt, how <lb/>long the patient ſhould be ſecluded <lb/>from the uninfected;
        if not alſo at <lb/>what time of the year <hi rend="italic">only</hi> the practice
        <lb/>ſhould be allowed. To this it was <lb/>anſwered, that allowing the fact of <lb/>the
        increaſe of deaths to be as he <lb/>aſſerted, it did not, by his own con- <lb/>feſſion, hold
        againſt the practice in <lb/>general, but only againſt the preſent <lb/>method of
        proceeding; but it was <lb/>hoped he was miſtaken as to the fact <lb/>itſelf; if not, it
        muſt be allowed to <lb/>be a matter deſerving a very ſerious <lb/>conſideration; he admitted
        his argu- <lb/>ment lay, and was meant by him on- <lb/>ly againſt the preſent method: ſaying
        <lb/>he was fully convinced that <hi rend="italic">inoculation</hi>, <lb/>which, in his
        opinion, under the <hi rend="italic">pre- <lb/>ſent</hi> management was ſo great an evil,
        <lb/>would under a <hi rend="italic">due</hi> regulation, be the <lb/>greateſt good: but as
        to his fact, he <lb/>ſaid he had no doubt about it, and pro- <lb/>duced a card whereon the
        births and <lb/>deaths diſtinguiſhing the deaths by the <lb/>ſmall pox, were ſtated from the
        bills of <lb/>mortality from 1683 to 1720, when <lb/>inoculation began to be uſed; and
        <lb/>from 1721 to 1758, the thirty-eight <lb/>years next after the introduction there-
        <lb/>of; and by the compariſon, it ap- <lb/>peared to be as he inferred. On the <lb/>card
        was a reference to your Maga- <lb/>zine of <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 1764 p. 332, from
        whence <lb/>I find the calculations are taken.— <lb/>You need not doubt, Sir, how much
        <lb/>many of us were aſtoniſhed at what <lb/>was ſaid, but another gentleman pre- <lb/>ſent
        aſſuring us, that ſince the preſent <lb/><hi rend="sc">Operators</hi> had appeared, the caſe
        <lb/>was quite altered, he having been <lb/>aſſured by the moſt eminent of them <lb/>all,
        that the infection under his me- <lb/>thod could not be communicated ei- <lb/>ther by his
        patients or himſelf and <lb/>remarked, that the compariſon ended <lb/>in the year 1758, then
        ſeven years <lb/>ago; this made me continue the ac- <lb/>count down to this time in the ſame
        <lb/>manner, and am ſorry to find the e- <lb/>vil goes on increaſing, and could wiſh
        <lb/>that ſome remedy were applied. Be <lb/>pleaſed therefore to lay this matter <lb/>before
        thoſe in power, by publiſhing <lb/>theſe papers in your Supplement for <lb/>1767, and you
        will oblige, </p>
      <signed rend="italic align-right">
        <lb/>Yours, &amp;c. <hi rend="sc">A. M. </hi>
      </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
