<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Jean Baptiste Gaber: New Experiments concerning the Putrefaction of the Juices and
          Humours of Animal Bodies.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Jean Baptiste Gaber</persName>
            </author>
            <title>New Experiments concerning the Putrefaction of the Juices and Humours of Animal
              Bodies. By M. Jean Baptiste Gaber, Translated from the Memoirs of the Academy of
              Turin.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed at St John's Gate, for D. Henry; and sold by F. Newbery,
                  the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard, Ludgate Street.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1767</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">37</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">9</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1767_GM_0009">
    <body>
      <pb n="9"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/>New Experiments concerning the Putre- <lb/>faction of the Juices and Humours of
        <lb/>Animal Bodies. By M <hi rend="roman">Jean Baptiſte <lb/>Gaber</hi>, Tranſlated from the
        Memoirs <lb/>of the Academy of <hi rend="roman">Turin</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE great Lord Chancellor <hi rend="italic">Bacon</hi>, <lb/>who
        may be conſidered as the re- <lb/>ſtorer of Philoſophy, was well appri- <lb/>zed of the
        great advantages which <lb/>medical and natural knowledge would <lb/>derive from a judicious
        hiſtory of pu- <lb/>trefaction founded upon experiment. <lb/>I ſhall not, however, attempt
        ſuch a <lb/>work in its utmoſt extent, nor even <lb/>to furniſh materials for ſuch a work,
        <lb/>with reſpect to all ſubjects, for fear my <lb/>attention ſhould be too much divided
        <lb/>among a great variety of facts to be <lb/>properly employed upon any. I ſhall
        <lb/>confine myſelf to the animal juices; <lb/>and, indeed, my experiments have <lb/>been
        made only on the moſt conſi- <lb/>derable of them, or ſuch, at leaſt, as <lb/>appeared to me
        to be the moſt proper <lb/>to throw light upon the internal <lb/>cauſes of many diſeaſes,
        upon their <lb/>effects or ſymptoms, and the indica- <lb/>tions of cure. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>1. A man aged about fifty years <lb/>died of an inveterate jaundice with- <lb/>out a
        fever; and his body having lain <lb/>about 24 hours in a cold place in win- <lb/>ter, was
        then opened. The large in- <lb/>teſtines were found infarcted with aſh- <lb/>coloured
        excrements; and the ſmall <lb/>ones contained here and there a kind <lb/>of yellow mucus;
        the gall-bladder <lb/>was diſtended with a great exceſs of <lb/>bile, nearly black. Some of
        this bile <lb/>I received in a glaſs, from an aper- <lb/>ture which I made in the veſicle,
        and <lb/>found it not very fœtid, but ſome- <lb/>thing glewy and tenacious. I put a
        <lb/>ſmall part of it into another veſſel, <lb/>and poured upon it a drop or two of
        <lb/>aqua-fortis; the mixture immediately <lb/>efferveſced, and ſeveral air bubbles
        <lb/>roſe to the ſurface, with a hiſſing <lb/>which was audible when I brought <lb/>my ear
        cloſe to the veſſel, and the <lb/>mixture became ſenſibly warm. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>2. I divided the remainder of the <lb/>bile into three parts, which I placed <lb/>in
        open glaſſes, where they were ex- <lb/>poſed to different degrees of heat, <lb/>which
        anſwered to the 35th, 25th, and <lb/>10th degrees of <hi rend="italic">Reaumur</hi>'s
        thermome- <lb/>ter. At the end of twenty-four hours <lb/>I mixed them with acids: the bile
        <lb/>which had been placed in a degree of <lb/>heat anſwering to 35, was moſt di-
        <lb/>luted, and gave very ſlight indica- <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>tions of efferveſcence; that which had <lb/>ſtood in 25, was alſo diluted, and the
        <lb/>acid produced a more ſenſible effer- <lb/>veſcence, but ſtill very ſlight; and the
        <lb/>bile which having been expoſed only <lb/>to the temperament of the air, which
        <lb/>might perhaps vary from ſeven to <lb/>ten, preſerved its tenacity, and fer- <lb/>mented
        as forcibly as in Experim. 1. <lb/>This experiment was repeated a few <lb/>hours afterwards,
        in the preſence of <lb/>ſeveral eminent perſons, and the effect <lb/>was the ſame. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>3. Some blood which was taken <lb/>from a vein of the dead body at the <lb/>ſame time,
        appeared to be of a yel- <lb/>lowiſh red. Some of this blood being <lb/>immediately mixed
        with ſpirit of ni- <lb/>tre, efferveſced, but much leſs than <lb/>the bile. This mixture
        being left to <lb/>digeſt for ſome hours, a yellow ſerum <lb/>ſeparated from the blood, and
        covered <lb/>its whole ſurface; this blood being <lb/>ſubjected to the ſame heat as the
        bile, <lb/>and for the ſame time in the ſtove, <lb/>appeared more diſpoſed to efferveſ-
        <lb/>cence than the bile; but this diſpoſi- <lb/>tion afterwards gradually diminiſhed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>4. From theſe experiments the fol- <lb/>lowing obſervations may be drawn. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>1. That in diſeaſed bodies the hu- <lb/>mours may become ſo alcaleſcent as <lb/>to
        efferveſce with acids; for it is not <lb/>probable, that the humours on which <lb/>theſe
        experiments were made effer- <lb/>veſced in conſequence of any altera- <lb/>tion they had
        ſuffered after the body <lb/>was dead; it having been kept only <lb/>24 hours in a cold
        place, and in cold <lb/>weather, where the ſame humours ta- <lb/>ken from a healthy body
        would ſcarce <lb/>have acquired ſuch a degree of alka- <lb/>leſcence in many days. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>2. That a very ſlight degree of <lb/>putrefaction and fœtor, which is not
        <lb/>ſufficient to produce alcaleſcene out <lb/>of the body, as appears by experi-
        <lb/>ments related in the ſequel, will pro- <lb/>duce alcaleſcence in the body. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>3. That alcali formed in the body, <lb/>and contained in the bile, is extreme- <lb/>ly
        volatile, ſince a heat of 25 degrees <lb/>made the greateſt part of it evaporate; <lb/>and
        that the ſame alcali contained in <lb/>the blood, being a little more en- <lb/>tangled with
        other elements, is, con- <lb/>ſequently leſs volatile; ſince the ſame <lb/>degree of heat,
        continued for the ſame <lb/>time, diſſipated but a very inconſider- <lb/>able part of it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>4. This obſervation inclines me to <lb/>ſuſpect, that, in other experiments up- <lb/>on
        putrefaction, in which ſome ope- <pb n="10"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>rators affirm, that they have ſeen in- <lb/>dubitable proofs of the preſence of <lb/>an
        alcali; and others ſay, they have <lb/>ſcarce diſcovered any indications at <lb/>all; the
        difference is the effect of dif- <lb/>ferent degrees of heat, the ſtaleneſs of <lb/>the
        ſubſtance expoſed to the heat, or <lb/>the different volatility of the alcali <lb/>ariſing
        from its coheſion with other <lb/>principles. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>5. The ſame experiments that I <lb/>made upon morbid bile, I made alſo <lb/>upon
        healthy bile, upon blood, and <lb/>upon ſerum. I divided each of theſe <lb/>liquors into
        three parts, which I ſe- <lb/>perately expoſed to the three diffe- <lb/><choice>
          <corr>rent</corr>
          <sic>eent</sic>
        </choice> degrees of heat mentioned a- <lb/>bove; and having ſubmitted them ſe- <lb/>verally
        to the action of mineral acids, <lb/>I found the bile moſt diſpoſed to ef- <lb/>ferveſce;
        and <hi rend="italic">Baglivi</hi> has obſerved, <lb/>that it corrupts ſooner than any other
        <lb/>humour. I found that human bile <lb/>was more diſpoſed to efferveſce than <lb/>the bile
        of an ox; that corrupt blood <lb/>ferments with acids ſtill ſlower, and <lb/>that ſerum
        ferments ſlower than blood. <lb/>In all theſe experiments, the effer- <lb/>veſcence was
        attended with the ſame <lb/>phænomena that are related, (<hi rend="italic">Par</hi> 1.)
        <lb/>Putreſcent humours not only effer- <lb/>veſce with mineral acids, but with <lb/>very
        weak diſtilled vinegar. The ſe- <lb/>veral portions of theſe humours that <lb/>have been
        expoſed to artificial heat, <lb/>become fœtid, and efferveſce ſooneſt, <lb/>and ſooneſt
        arrive at the laſt ſtage of <lb/>fermentation. When this happens, <lb/>the fermentation
        ceaſes <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.7)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* It has ſometimes happened, that ſerum <lb/>expoſed to an heat equal to 35, has
            not effer- <lb/>veſced; which gives cauſe to ſuſpect that the <lb/>alcali contained in
            it diſſipates in proportion <lb/>to the force and continuance of the heat. </p>
        </note>, though the <lb/>heat is continued; and the ſmell, <lb/>which till then is
        intolerably fœtid, <lb/>becomes herbaceous, and is not diſ- <lb/>agreeable <note n="†"
          place="bottom" rend="size(0.7)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>† This always happens in the proceſs of <lb/>vegetation. All putreſcent humours
            depoſited <lb/>in a warm place ſoon become rancid, and <lb/>contract a ſtrong ſmell,
            which, after a long <lb/>time, reſembles that of amber. </p>
        </note>. The fœtor manifeſts it- <lb/>ſelf ſooner, and laſts longer than the
        <lb/>alcaleſcence. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>6. To put the efferveſcence of pu- <lb/>treſcent humours with mineral acids <lb/>beyond
        a doubt, I muſt now obſerve, <lb/>that the aqua-fortis which I uſed in <lb/>my experiments
        was very weak, and <lb/>ſuch as produced no motion in com- <lb/>com water; and this
        efferveſcence is <lb/>ſo far from being the effect of con- <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>centering the acids <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.7)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Which is the caſe with bile not in a <lb/>putreſcent ſtate. </p>
        </note>, that, in my o- <lb/>pinion, the acids may be ſo concen- <lb/>tered as to render the
        efferveſcence <lb/>leſs, principally becauſe the animal <lb/>humours reſiſt efferveſcence,
        in pro- <lb/>portion as they unite with acids ſpee- <lb/>dily and intimately: for when I
        <lb/>made uſe of diſtilled vinegar, not <lb/>ſtrong enough to coagulate the pu-
        <lb/>treſcent humours, I obſerved that the <lb/>efferveſcence was equally violent, and
        <lb/>I have ſeen diſtilled vinegar operate <lb/>ſo powerfully upon a putrid ſerum, <lb/>as
        wholly to convert it into froth. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>7. When I was reading Dr <hi rend="italic">Pringle</hi>'s <lb/>experiments upon this
        ſubject, I ob- <lb/>ſerved that he ſometimes expoſed pu- <lb/>treſcent ſubſtances to an heat
        equal <lb/>to the 100th degree of <hi rend="italic">Farenheit</hi>'s ther- <lb/>mometer
          <note n="†" place="bottom" rend="size(0.7)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>† The freezing point in <hi rend="italic">Farenheit</hi>'s is 32, <lb/>the boiling
            212. On <hi rend="italic"><choice>
                <corr>Reaumur</corr>
                <sic>Reaumer</sic>
              </choice></hi>'s the firſt is <lb/>marked 0, the latter 80. </p>
        </note>, which is nearly the ſame <lb/>with the 30th degree of <hi rend="italic"
          >Reaumur</hi>'s.— <lb/>Now, it is certain, that at this degree <lb/>of heat, animal
        humours very ſoon <lb/>become putrid; but then they loſe as <lb/>ſoon the alcaleſcence which
        they de- <lb/>rive from putrefaction, if this degree <lb/>of heat is continued; ſo that as
        the <lb/>corrupting humours manifeſt their al- <lb/>caleſcent quality for a very ſhort time
        <lb/>only, it might eaſily happen that no <lb/>ſign of alcaleſcence appeared in his
        <lb/>experiment, if it was not made in the <lb/>critical moment: I mean, if he ex-
        <lb/>amined the putreſcent humours a lit- <lb/>tle before the alcali was formed, or <lb/>a
        little after it had evaporated. And <lb/>ſuppoſing the experiment to have been
        <lb/>critically made, ſtill, as the ambient <lb/>heat would have cauſed the alcali to
        <lb/>evaporate almoſt entirely as ſoon as it <lb/>was formed, Dr <hi rend="italic"
          >Pringle</hi> would have <lb/>perceived very ſlight tokens of effer- <lb/>veſcence, though
        with a leſs degree <lb/>of heat they would have been conſi- <lb/>derable: conſequently, if
        that inge- <lb/>nious and accurate obſerver had made <lb/>his experiments with a degree of
        heat <lb/>juſt equal to that with which I made <lb/>mine, the reſult, <hi rend="italic"
          >cæteris paribus</hi>, would <lb/>have been the ſame. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>8. I received ſome blood as it iſſued <lb/>from the arm in a vial; and having
        <lb/>diſſolved it, or broken its texture, by <lb/>continual agitation, I left it to pu-
        <lb/>trify. I obſerved that its fine florid <lb/>red colour inſenſibly faded to a black-
        <lb/>iſh brown; but this change did not <lb/>take place in the whole maſs at the <pb n="11"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>ſame time; it began at the ſurface, <lb/>and gradually deſcended. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>9. Blood in this ſtate does not pu- <lb/>trify ſo ſoon, nor ſo ſoon give ſigns <lb/>of
        alcaleſcence, as the red part ſepe- <lb/>rated from the ſerum, becauſe the ſe- <lb/>rum
        putrifies more ſlowly than any o- <lb/>ther animal humour. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>10. After having diſcovered, by the <lb/>foregoing experiments, that the alcali
        <lb/>flies off with a ſlight degree of heat, I <lb/>was deſirous to try if I could recover
        <lb/>and retain it. I therefore put into an <lb/>alembic of glaſs ſome ſerum which <lb/>had
        ſeparated from blood taken a few <lb/>hours before from a feveriſh patient, <lb/>and I
        placed it in a degree of heat be- <lb/>tween 25 and 28 of <hi rend="italic">Reaumur</hi>'s
        ſcale: <lb/>I paſſed the neck of the alembic thro' <lb/>a hole which was made for that pur-
        <lb/>poſe, in the wooden covering of the <lb/>ſtove, that the head of it might be in
        <lb/>the ſame temperament with the air of <lb/>the chamber, which was equal to a- <lb/>bout
        the 10th degree of the ſame <lb/>ſcale, and that the exhaling vapour <lb/>might condenſe
        there into liquor; to <lb/>the ſpout of the head of the alembic, I <lb/>luted a bottle as a
        receiver, and at the <lb/>end of every two days I had about two <lb/>drachms of this
        diſtilled liquor, upon <lb/>which I poured acids, with different <lb/>effects. That part
        which came over <lb/>firſt, had the ſmell and taſte of ſerum, <lb/>it was clear and
        tranſparent, and did <lb/>not efferveſce either with acids or <lb/>alcali's. The next
        portion was ſlight- <lb/>ly fœtid, but nearly of the ſame taſte <lb/>and tranſparency as the
        firſt; the third <lb/>differed little from the ſecond; but <lb/>the fourth was extremely <choice>
          <corr>fœtid</corr>
          <sic>fætid</sic>
        </choice>, foul, <lb/>opake, and of a pale colour; it did <lb/>not, however, efferveſce, but
        acids <lb/>ſlightly tinged it with red; the fifth, <lb/>which came over after the tenth day,
        <lb/>and was clear, efferveſced with acids, <lb/>and produced a hiſſing which became
        <lb/>ſenſible when the ear was brought <lb/>cloſe to the veſſel: it alſo produced
        <lb/>bubbles and froth; the ſixth portion <lb/>was equally limpid, but efferveſced <lb/>more
        ſlightly, and when I perceived <lb/>that nothing more would come over <lb/>with this degree
        of heat, I broke the <lb/>alembic to examine the reſiduum: I <lb/>found it a viſcous cruſt,
        reſembling <lb/>wax, of a reddiſh colour, and ex- <lb/>tremely fœtid, but the affuſion of
        acids <lb/>produced not the leaſt ſigns of effer- <lb/>veſcence. This experiment, I tho't,
        <lb/>proved to demonſtration, that alcali <lb/>evaporates with a degree of heat from <lb/>25
        to 28; that being collected in a re- <lb/>ceiver, it will efferveſce, and that the <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>reſiduum is a maſs extremely fœtid, <lb/>wholly deſtitute of alcali, and, conſe-
        <lb/>quently, no efferveſcence is to be ex- <lb/>pected by pouring acids upon it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>11. Some blood which I kept in a <lb/>glaſs veſſel cloſe ſtopped, retained its
        <lb/>alcaleſcence a long time, though it <lb/>was expoſed to a degree of heat equal <lb/>to
        25; but upon unſtopping the veſ- <lb/>ſel, it flew off with great violence, in <lb/>a vapour
        extremely fœtid. The ex- <lb/>ploſion was probably cauſed by the ex- <lb/>panſion of the
        air, in conſequence of <lb/>the putrefection, and this experiment <lb/>ſhews why the humours
        that are con- <lb/>tained in the veſſels of a human body, <lb/>become alcaleſcent while they
        are yet <lb/>ſcarce fœtid, at the ſame time that <lb/>drawn from the body, and kept in o-
        <lb/>pen veſſels, they become fœtid before <lb/>they give ſigns of alcaleſcence. As
        <lb/>ſoon as they begin to form alcali in <lb/>the veſſels, the alcali is retained, but
        <lb/>as it exhales from a veſſel expoſed to <lb/>the air, a greater quantity muſt be
        <lb/>formed than exhales before it can be- <lb/>come ſenſible. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>12. As ſerum ſubjected to the expe- <lb/>riment in a ſound ſtate did not give up
        <lb/>its alcali in leſs than ten days, it may <lb/>be fairly inferred that it does not in
        <lb/>leſs time become corrupt, it being cer- <lb/>tain, in the firſt place, that humours
        <lb/>corrupt ſlowly in a cloſed veſſel; and, <lb/>in the ſecond place, that of all hu-
        <lb/>mours, the ſerum continues longeſt <lb/>uncorrupt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I did not doubt, but that ſerum, al- <lb/>ready corrupt, would, in diſtillation,
        <lb/>give up its alcali immediately, I there- <lb/>fore made the ſame experiments upon
        <lb/>corrupt ſerum, that I had made upon <lb/>ſound: My principal view was to de-
        <lb/>termine, exactly, the time when the <lb/>alcali would being to fly off, and after
        <lb/>having collected the diſtilled liquor, <lb/>to try whether it would change the
        <lb/>blue vegetable colour of violets to a <lb/>green, which the ſlowneſs of the pre-
        <lb/>ceding experiment had prevented me <lb/>from attempting. I took for this pur- <lb/>poſe
        ſome blood in ſuch a ſtate of pu- <lb/>treſcence as to efferveſce with acids, <lb/>and
        having put it into a glaſs alembic, <lb/>I expoſed it to the ſame degree of heat <lb/>with
        the ſame precautions and appa- <lb/>ratus as in the preceding experiments. <lb/>The firſt
        day I collected two drachms <lb/>of the diſtilled liquor, which I expo- <lb/>ſed to the
        action of various acids, and <lb/>a violent efferveſcence enſued: I then <lb/>poured ſome of
        the ſame liquor upon <lb/>ſyrup of violets, and it produced as <pb n="12"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>fine a green as ſpirit of hartſhorn; <lb/>this tincture having been changed to <lb/>a
        red, by the affuſion of a few drops <lb/>of aqua fortis, became again blue, up- <lb/>on
        pouring into it ſome more of the <lb/>diſtilled liquor. The liquor that di- <lb/>ſtilled the
        five following days, gave the <lb/>ſame indications of an alcali. As the <lb/>diſtillation
        entirely ceaſed after this <lb/>time, I broke the alembic, and found <lb/>juſt ſuch a
        reſiduum as before, but un- <lb/>der it there was a ſmall portion of li- <lb/>quor, reduced
        to the conſiſtence of ſy- <lb/>rup, which retained ſomewhat of an <lb/>alcaline quality, but
        ſo weak that ha- <lb/>ving expoſed it about twelve hours in <lb/>a window where the heat of
        the air <lb/>was equal to about ten degrees of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Reaumur</hi>'s ſcale,
        the alcali totally diſ- <lb/>appeared. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>13. This efferveſcence and power of <lb/>changing ſyrup of violets green, proves
        <lb/>that putreſcent humours form a true <lb/>alcali, which exhales with a very ſlight
        <lb/>heat. I would have made the expe- <lb/>riment upon the ſyrup of violets with <lb/>the
        putrid humours themſelves, but <lb/>the opacity of the ſerum, the red co- <lb/>lour of the
        blood, and the yellowneſs <lb/>of the bile, would have rendered it <lb/>doubtful. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>14. As the reſiduum left in the alem- <lb/>bic after diſtillation, though not alca-
        <lb/>leſcent, is extremely fœtid, it is evi- <lb/>dent that though the alcali may diſen-
        <lb/>gage and exalt this fœtor, and render <lb/>it more penetrating, it is not the pro-
        <lb/>ductive cauſe of it, becauſe the fœtor <lb/>remains when the alcali is departed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>15. But as both the alcaleſcence and <lb/>fœtor diſappear in the ſame degree of
        <lb/>heat, if long continued <hi rend="italic">(Par. 5.)</hi> it <lb/>appears that this
        fœtor is produced by <lb/>the effluvia of parts extremely vola- <lb/>tile, but different
        from volatile alcali, <lb/>which, though ſooner produced, are <lb/>more ſlowly diſſipated,
        ſince the fœtor <lb/>generally continues longer than the <lb/>alcaleſcence. Alcaleſcence
        may, how- <lb/>ever, be ſometimes connected with a <lb/>ſlight fœtor; and, on the contrary,
        <lb/>extreme fœtor may ſubſiſt without al- <lb/>caleſcence. This is a confirmation of
        <lb/>the difference between the fœtid and <lb/>alcaline particles, which the ingenious
        <lb/>Dr <hi rend="italic">Pringle</hi> has demonſtrated by ano- <lb/>ther argument; he
        obſerves, that the <lb/>exhalations of freſh urine are not per- <lb/>nicious, though they
        contain more al- <lb/>cali than any ſubſtance in a ſtate of <lb/>putrefaction, the odour of
        which is <lb/>pernicious in the higheſt degree. Pu- <lb/>trid effluvia, therefore, are of a
        dif- <lb/>ferent nature from alcaline ſalt. </p>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>16. This being the fact, it follows <lb/>that a volatile alcali is not a neceſſary
        <lb/>product of putrefaction, and that the <lb/>degree of alcaleſcence is not equal to
        <lb/>that of putrefaction; but that, with <lb/>reſpect to vegetable ſubſtances, neu-
        <lb/>tral ſalts, if mixed with oil, become <lb/>volatile by means of putreſcence, tho'
        <lb/>in animal bodies alcali commences by <lb/>the action of the bowels, where en-
        <lb/>veloped with other principles, it be- <lb/>comes perfect, or manifeſts itſelf by
        <lb/>putrefaction; and that for this reaſon <lb/>putrefaction engenders a quantity of
        <lb/>alcali more conſiderable in proportion <lb/>as it finds in putreſcent bodies more
        <lb/>ſalts and other elements capable, by <lb/>mixing with ſalts, of communicating <lb/>to
        them an alcaleſcent volatility. Up- <lb/>on the whole, if it is conſidered, <list>
          <item>1<hi rend="italic">ſt</hi>, <lb/>That aceſcent plants, plants that yield <lb/>an
            acid in diſtillation, yield very little <lb/>of it when they are converted into
            <lb/>blood or humours by the action of <lb/>the ſolids in an animal body; that <lb/>they
            putrify almoſt immediately, and <lb/>yield in diſtillation inſtead of an acid, <lb/>an
            alkali in a great quantity; </item>
          <item>2<hi rend="italic">dly</hi>, <lb/>tha an alcali is ſooner brought off by
            <lb/>diſtillation from putrified ſubſtances <lb/>than others. </item>
          <item>3<hi rend="italic">dly</hi>, That almoſt all <lb/>ſalts are deſtroyed by the action
            of the <lb/>bowels, and putreſcence, and that no <lb/>alcali is found in the aſhes of
            bodies <lb/>conſumed by fire; and, </item>
          <item>4thly, that <lb/>the humours which abound with ſalts <lb/>particularly the urine,
            afford the <lb/>greateſt quantity of alcali after putre- <lb/>faction, I ſhall be
            juſtified in adopt- <lb/>ing the opinion of the chemiſts, who <lb/>ſuppoſe that volatile
            ſalts owe their <lb/>origin to other ſalts which are thus <lb/>changed by the action of
            the bowels <lb/>in animal bodies, by putrefaction and <lb/>by fire, and that totally
            loſing their o- <lb/>riginal form, they become alcalies. </item>
        </list>
        <lb/>Upon this ſuppoſition it will be eaſy <lb/>to conceive how volatile ſalts reſiſt
        <lb/>putrefaction, as well as ſalts of other <lb/>kinds, although putrefaction produces
        <lb/>them. The quantity of alcaline ſalts <lb/>produced by putrefaction, is indeed <lb/>in
        proportion to the quantity of natu- <lb/>ral ſalts pre exiſting in the putrifying
        <lb/>ſubſtances; but as theſe ſalts are not <lb/>ſufficient to prevent putrefaction, it is
        <lb/>not ſurpriſing that the alcali which <lb/>reſults, cannot arreſt its progreſs. If
        <lb/>the natural ſalts had been ſtill more <lb/>abundant, there is reaſon to think <lb/>that
        they might have retarded its <lb/>effects, for urine, which contains the <lb/>greateſt
        quantity of ſalts, is leaſt ſub- <pb n="13"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>ject to putrefaction, and when it is <lb/>become putrid, it effluvia is leſs hurt-
        <lb/>ful than the effluvia of any other hu- <lb/>mour, which can be attributed only <lb/>to
        the abundance of the pre exiſting <lb/>ſalts, and the ſtrength of the alcali that <lb/>is
        formed out of them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>17. The urine of a perſon in health <lb/>will not become putrid in leſs than <lb/>three
        days, ſo as to efferveſce with a- <lb/>cids; but the urine of a perſon ſick of <lb/>a putrid
        fever, will become ſo putrid <lb/>as to produce that effect in four and <lb/>twenty hours.
        The blood of a per- <lb/>ſon ſo diſeaſed will alſo ſhew ſigns of <lb/>alcaleſcence much
        ſooner than the <lb/>blood of a perſon in a pleuriſy. Theſe <lb/>particulars, however,
        belong to ano- <lb/>ther claſs of experiments, which I re- <lb/>ſerve till a future
        opportunity, and <lb/>in which, after an examination of the <lb/>morbific humours, and a
        compariſon <lb/>of the phœnomena which they exhi- <lb/>bit, with each other, I ſhall endea-
        <lb/>vour to deduce ſuch conſequences as <lb/>may facilitate the diſcovery of the
        <lb/>cauſes of diſeaſes, explain their na- <lb/>tures, and direct the method of cure. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Of this intereſting work, when it <lb/>appears, ſome account ſhall be given. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
