<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Inoculation hurtful</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Inoculation hurtful</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed at St John's Gate, for D. Henry; and sold by F. Newbery,
                  the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard, Ludgate Street.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1767</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">37</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">254</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1767_GM_0254">
    <body>
      <pb n="254"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <salute rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr <hi rend="sc">Urban</hi>, </salute>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">E</hi>VERY lover of mankind muſt <lb/>rejoice that a method has been
        <lb/>diſcovered of preſerving multitudes <lb/>from the fatal effects of a moſt loath-
        <lb/>ſome diſtemper by inoculation. It <lb/>muſt, with all thankfulneſs, be ac-
        <lb/>knowledged, that the inventors and <lb/>improvers of it deſerve to be ranked <lb/>among
        the firſt benefactors of their <lb/>fellow creatures. But, whilſt we glad- <lb/>ly pay them
        this tribute of gratitude, <lb/>we cannot but lament that this prac- <lb/>tice hath been
        abuſed and perverted <lb/>to the deſtruction of many lives, <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>which might have been preſerved. <lb/>Inſpect the yearly bills, and you will <lb/>find,
        that for an equal number of <lb/>years, more have died of the ſmall- <lb/>pox within the
        bills of mortality, <hi rend="italic">ſince</hi>
        <lb/>the practice of inoculation, than did <lb/><hi rend="italic">before</hi>. <q
          rend="quotes">How is this to be accounted <lb/>for? </q> The inoculated live: But num-
        <lb/>bers who receive the infection from <lb/>them, in the natural way, die. Hi-
        <lb/>therto, therefore, inoculation ſeems <lb/>not to have been ſo beneficial to this
        <lb/>great city as might reaſonably be ex- <lb/>pected. If it has ſaved, it has alſo
        <lb/>deſtroyed multitudes. It is impoſſible <lb/>to determine preciſely what have been
        <lb/>its effects in the country, ſince no bills <lb/>of mortality are there open to our in-
        <lb/>ſpection. But we may venture to pro- <lb/>nounce, that the methods at preſent
        <lb/>practiſed, if they are not hurtful to <lb/>mankind in general, are not ſo ſer-
        <lb/>viceable to them as they might be <lb/>made. Inoculation introduces the <lb/>ſmall-pox
        into cities and towns which <lb/>otherwiſe might be entirely free from <lb/>that diſtemper.
        Not only private fa- <lb/>milies are inoculated, but hoſpitals are <lb/>provided, in places
        full of people, for <lb/>the reception of all who have money <lb/>in their purſes, and
        chooſe rather to <lb/>have the ſmall pox abroad than at <lb/>home. Hither are patients bro't
        from <lb/>all parts. The conſequences are, the <lb/>ſtagnation of trade, an extraordinary
        <lb/>dearneſs of proviſions, even in this <lb/>dear time, the diſtreſſing of the poor,
        <lb/>and the communicating to multitudes <lb/>this dreadful diſtemper. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">Would you then put a ſtop to i- <lb/>noculation? </q> I am not ſo much the
        <lb/>enemy of my country. For the good <lb/>of mankind may it generally prevail! <lb/>But
        till this time ſhall come, let it be <lb/>put under proper regulations. What <lb/>theſe are,
        ſuperior wiſdom muſt deter- <lb/>mine. I only beg leave humbly to <lb/>propoſe one, <hi
          rend="italic">viz.</hi> that inoculation be <lb/>prohibited within a certain diſtance
        <lb/>of cities, and other populous places, <lb/>where the ſmall-pox is not. If this
        <lb/>were done, we ſhould reap all the be- <lb/>nefits of inoculation, without the in-
        <lb/>conveniences and miſeries with which <lb/>it is at preſent too frequently attend-
        <lb/>ed. Had this been done long ago, <lb/>there would have been fewer orphans
        <lb/>lamenting the loſs of their parents, <lb/>and fewer parents weeping over the
        <lb/>graves of their children. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Many worthy magiſtrates (I know) <lb/>grieve that they cannot prevent the e- <lb/>vil
        of which I have been ſpeaking. <pb n="255"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>But can they only grieve? Yes, <lb/>(thank Heaven!) they can do more; <lb/>they can
        petition the legiſlature; and <lb/>let them petition, or never complain <lb/>of grievances,
        which only want to be <lb/>properly repreſented, in order to be <lb/>redreſſed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Could inoculation be practiſed no <lb/>where but in cities, <hi rend="italic"
          >&amp;c.</hi> the preſent <lb/>faſhion would not only admit of a de- <lb/>fence, but it
        would deſerve praiſe. As <lb/>this is not the caſe, what, I beſeech <lb/>you, is <hi
          rend="italic">their</hi> guilt, who deſtroy multi- <lb/>tudes for their own advantage, and
        <lb/>only becauſe they can do it with im- <lb/>punity? And what can be more un-
        <lb/>reaſonable than that the trade of a <lb/>town ſhould lie at any man's mercy? <lb/>The
        trade of a town did I ſay? If I <lb/>am rightly informed, as the law now <lb/>ſtands, the
        moſt flouriſhing city in the <lb/>kingdom may be made, and continue <lb/>a ſmall-pox
        infirmary, ſo long as any <lb/>inoculator pleaſes. </p>
      <signed rend="italic align-center">
        <lb/>I am, &amp;c. <hi rend="sc align-right">Variolanus. </hi>
      </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
