<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: An Address to the Public on the present Method of
          Inoculation</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Address to the Public on the present Method of Inoculation, proving that the
              matter communicated, is not the Small-Pox, because numbers have been inoculated a
              second, third, and fourth time; that therefore it is no security against a future
              infection; with observations on the preparatory medicines, and a remarkable case of an
              eminent personage, who had the natural Small-Pox in two years and an half after
              inoculation. To which is added, an inquiry into the nature of the confluent-pox and
              its cure. By William Langton M. D. Horsefield . Price 1 s. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed at St John's Gate, for D. Henry; and sold by F. Newbery,
                  the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard, Ludgate Street.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1767</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">37</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">411</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1767_GM_0411">
    <body>
      <pb n="411"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">23.</hi> An Addreſs to the Public on the pre- <lb/>ſent Method of
        Inoculation, proving that <lb/>the matter communicated, is not the Small- <lb/>Pox, becauſe
        numbers have been inoculat- <lb/>ed a ſecond, third, and fourth time; that <lb/>therefore it
        is no ſecurity againſt a future <lb/>infection; with obſervations on the pre- <lb/>paratory
        medicines, and a remarkable caſe <lb/>of an eminent perſonage, who had the na- <lb/>tural
        Small-Pox in two years and an half <lb/>after inoculation. To which is added, an
        <lb/>inquiry into the nature of the confluent-pox <lb/>and its cure. By <hi rend="roman"
          >William Langton M. D. <lb/>Horſefield</hi>. <hi rend="roman">Price 1 s.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The remarkable caſe of one eminent per- <lb/>ſonage, is that of the dutcheſs of <hi
          rend="italic">Boufflers</hi>, <lb/>which the reader will find at large in the
        <lb/>Magazine vol. XXXVI. p. 117. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Langton</hi> ſays, that a diſeaſe is to be <lb/>eſtimated as the
        ſame when it preſents the <lb/><choice>
          <corr>ſame</corr>
          <sic>ſome</sic>
        </choice> appearances, and <hi rend="italic">vice verſa</hi>; and that <lb/>any deflections
        from theſe appearances muſt <lb/>bring it under a different denomination, and <lb/>have
        different indications of cure. To prove <lb/>that the diſeaſe produced by the modern
        <lb/>method of inoculation is not the true <lb/>ſmall pox, he enumerates the differences
        <lb/>of their appearances; and when he has ſo <lb/>done, he ſays that their appearances are
        dif- <lb/>ferent <hi rend="italic">becauſe</hi> both are not the true ſmall-pox, <lb/>(<hi
          rend="italic">i. e.</hi>) the diſeaſe now inoculated is not the <lb/>ſmall-pox, <hi
          rend="italic">becauſe</hi> its appearances are dif- <lb/>ferent; and its appearances are
        different <hi rend="italic">be- <lb/>cauſe</hi> it is not the ſmall-pox. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>His words are theſe; </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="diple">Patients ſeized with the ſmall-pox, <lb/>ſoon have a chillneſs ſucceeded by
          a fe- <lb/>veriſh heat; a pain in the head, back, <lb/>and ſtomach, a nauſea and
          reſtleſſneſs; <lb/>the puſtules are prominent, and filled <lb/>with well concocted pus,
          inclining to <lb/>yellow; there is a conſiderable fever, <cb n="2"/>
          <lb/>and the patient (is) often light-headed. <lb/>Theſe ſymptoms ever attend, in a
          greater <lb/>or leſs degree, the benign ſmall-pox, <lb/>and infallibly preclude all future
          infec- <lb/>tion, on the other hand, the inoculated <lb/>ſmall-pox, if it deſerves that
          name, has <lb/>not one of the preceeding ſymptoms, <hi rend="italic">be- <lb/>cauſe the
            inoculated matter is not the true <lb/>ſmall-pox</hi>. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Langton</hi> however proceeds to obſerve <lb/>that the preſent
        practiſe is to take the mat- <lb/>ter from the inciſion the fourth day after it <lb/>is
        made; and he aſſerts, that by this means, <lb/>a contagious cauſtic water only is procured
        <lb/>inſtead of laudable pus; and that a ſlight <lb/>ferment is raiſed in the lymph,
        producing <lb/>only a few watry blotches, inſtead of a per- <lb/>fect extruſion of variolous
        matter: that in <lb/>the true ſmall-pox, a re-percuſſion of the <lb/>matter inwardly
        produces the moſt dangerous <lb/>conſequences, but no ill effects follow the re-
        <lb/>percuſſion of what is <choice>
          <corr>contained</corr>
          <sic>conttained</sic>
        </choice> in the puſ- <lb/>tules produced by this inoculation; he con- <lb/>cludes
        therefore, that what theſe puſtules <lb/>contain is not variolous; he ſays that the ino-
        <lb/>culated are ſafely expoſed to the cold air in a <lb/>rigorous ſeaſon, whereas the
        practiſe would <lb/>be fatal in the real ſmall-pox. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Perhaps it will not be generally thought, <lb/>that his concluſions follow from his
        premiſes, <lb/>and it is certain that ſome of his facts are <lb/>contrary to experience. It
        appears by in- <lb/>numerable experiments, that patients in the <lb/>real ſmall-pox, taken
        naturally, have been <lb/>expoſed to cold air, with great benefit. Dr. <lb/>Baker in
        particular, (ſee Vol. XXXVI. p. <lb/>382.) mentions the removal of ſome patients <lb/>from
        the infirmary into the fields, and even <lb/>under the arches of a bridge, in ſome of
        <lb/>whom very threatening ſymptoms immedi- <lb/>ately took a favourable turn. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Langton</hi> alſo affirms, that if the diſ- <lb/>eaſe now given
        by the inoculation of matter <lb/>not concocted was the ſmall-pox, it would <lb/>be
        dangerous, <hi rend="italic">becauſe an infection would be <lb/>communicated before it could
          be known of what <lb/>kind it would be</hi>. But it is generally ack- <lb/>nowledged that
        the goodneſs or badneſs of <lb/>the ſmall-pox communicated by inoculation, <lb/>does not
        depend upon the kind from which <lb/>the matter is taken, but wholly upon the ha- <lb/>bit
        and ſtate of the patient receiving the in- <lb/>fection; and all experience proves that ino-
        <lb/>culation with unripe matter is at leaſt nor <lb/>dangerous, whether the diſeaſe
        produced is <lb/>the ſmall-pox or not. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But Dr. <hi rend="italic">Langton</hi> in his zeal againſt inocu- <lb/>lation,
        ſometimes decries it as producing <lb/>the ſmall-pox, and ſometimes as not pro- <lb/>ducing
        it. When danger from a ſecond in- <lb/>fection is to be dreaded, he affirms it is not
        <lb/>the ſmall-pox; when danger from repelling <lb/>medicines, he ſuppoſes it is the
        ſmall-pox. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>An account of the paſſages in which he <lb/>ſuppoſes the ſmall-pox not to be inoculated
        <lb/>by the new method has been given already; <lb/>the paſſages in which, that he may
        condemn <lb/>the treatment before and after the inoculation, <pb n="412"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>he ſuppoſes the ſmall-pox to be inoculated <lb/>follow. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="diple quotes">In <hi rend="italic">this way</hi> there is a <hi rend="italic"
            >probability</hi> of <lb/>having the ſmall-pox, and great danger <lb/>by thwarting
          nature in her <hi rend="italic">operations</hi>, by <lb/>adminiſtering ſuch violent
          medicines as mer- <lb/>cury, tartar emetic, and draſtick purges: <lb/>the humour muſt be
          diſturbed in the ſto- <lb/>mach, and from thence precipitated into <lb/>the maſs of
          fluids, and through the emunc- <lb/>tories. By irritating the nervous parts <lb/>they
          throw the whole ſyſtem into convul- <lb/>ſions, and to the hypochondriacal and hy-
          <lb/>ſteric are certain death. In a word, the <lb/>weak and tender are ſure of ruining
          their <lb/>conſtitutions, and of being ſtill liable to <lb/>the diſeaſe. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But if theſe dreadful evils are <hi rend="italic">probable</hi>, <lb/>how comes it that
        they never happen? What <lb/>perſons have thus ſuffered by the new me- <lb/>thod of
        inoculation? Whom have theſe vio- <lb/>lent medicines deſtroyed? or, among all the <lb/>weak
        and tender who have been patients <lb/>to <hi rend="italic">Sutton</hi>, whoſe conſtitution
        have they ruined? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is indeed difficult to fix this writer ſuf- <lb/>ficiently to examine his
        principles; for tho' <lb/>in the paſſage above, he ſays, that in this <lb/>way (<hi
          rend="italic">Sutton</hi>'s) there is a <hi rend="italic">probability of having <lb/>the
          true ſmall-pox</hi>, yet in the paragraph im- <lb/>mediately preceeding it, he ſays,
        though <lb/>ſcarce <hi rend="italic">one</hi> of the patients (of <hi rend="italic"
          >Sutton</hi>) will <lb/>have the real ſmall-pox, yet by the exhibit- <lb/>ing mercurials
        he effectually prevents it. <lb/>The plain <hi rend="italic">Engliſh</hi> of which (ſetting
        aſide its <lb/>inconſiſtency with what follows) is, that <hi rend="italic">Sut-
          <lb/>ton</hi>, by the exhibition of mercurials, effec- <lb/>tually <hi rend="italic"
          >prevents</hi> what would <hi rend="italic">never happen</hi>, <lb/>for that may be well
        ſuppoſed never to hap- <lb/>pen, which he affirms would ſcarce happen <lb/>to <hi
          rend="italic">one</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Upon the whole, the advantage or diſad- <lb/>vantage of the preſent method of inocula-
        <lb/>tion, muſt be determined by experience, and <lb/>not by the haſty and injudicious
        reaſonings of <lb/>perſons not able to write their native lan- <lb/>guage, without groſs
        violations of grammar <lb/>and common ſenſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The following extracts will juſtify this <lb/>cenſure. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="diple quotes">The ſecret of treating this diſorder, <lb/>muſt be confined to a
          ſingle family, and <lb/>to men (who if they have any modeſty <lb/>will confeſs themſelves
          to be) very inferior <lb/>in <hi rend="italic">natural</hi> and <hi rend="italic">required
            attainments</hi> to many <lb/>of the ſame profeſſion. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>We have here an elegant and accurate di- <lb/>viſion of attainments into two kinds, <hi
          rend="italic">attain- <lb/>ments</hi> that are <hi rend="italic">attained</hi>, and <hi
          rend="italic">attainments</hi> that <lb/>are <hi rend="italic">not</hi> attained; every
        attainment is acquired, <lb/>no attainment is natural. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The author ſays, <q rend="diple quotes">Dr. <hi rend="italic">Baker</hi> in a <hi
            rend="italic">neat</hi>
          <lb/>tract printed laſt year, enquires into the <lb/>ſuperiority of the <hi rend="italic"
            >preſent method of inocu- <lb/>lation</hi> above the beſt <hi rend="italic">practiſe in
            the natural <lb/>way</hi>. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In this paſſage <hi rend="italic">method of inoculation</hi> ſtands <lb/>for <hi
          rend="italic">method of treating the diſeaſe that inoculation <lb/>produces</hi>: and <hi
          rend="italic">practiſe in the <hi rend="sc">natural</hi> way</hi>, <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>for practiſe according to <hi rend="sc">regular art</hi>
        <lb/>on a <hi rend="sc">disease</hi>
        <hi rend="italic">taken in the natural way</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He makes Dr. <hi rend="italic">Woodward</hi> ſay of <hi rend="italic">drinks</hi>,
        <lb/>that <hi rend="italic">it</hi> muſt be temperate. He ſays of the <lb/>preſent method of
        inoculation that <q rend="diple quotes">In re- <lb/>ality it is one of the compleateſt
          bubbles <lb/>that ever was ſo univerſally run into. </q>
        <lb/>The image of <hi rend="italic">running into a compleat bubble</hi>
        <lb/>is an ornament that may atone for the uſe <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">univerſally</hi>,
        an abſolute term in a com- <lb/>parative ſenſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The ſenſe of the following paſſage is juſt <lb/>oppoſite to what was intended. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="diple">Oyſterſhells, crabs claws and eyes, <lb/>pearl, and the reſt, will not
          diſſolve in <lb/>water, for if triturateth therewith, and <lb/>that filtered it <hi
            rend="italic">leaves nothing</hi>. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The truth is, that it (the water) carrying <lb/>nothing away <hi rend="italic">leaves
          all</hi>, and how otherwiſe <lb/>could the experiment prove theſe ſubſtances <lb/>not to
        be ſoluble in water. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Other inſtances of fallacious argument <lb/>and inaccurate compoſition might be given
        <lb/>but the taſk is too unpleaſing to be longer con- <lb/>tinued. </p>
      <signed rend="align-right">X. </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
