<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: A Review of the Venereal Disease and its Remedies</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title> A Review of the Venereal Disease and its Remedies. By William Fordyce, Surgeon.
              2s. Spilsbury</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed at St John's Gate, for D. Henry; and sold by F. Newbery,
                  the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard, Ludgate Street.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1767</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">37</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">595</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1767_GM_0595">
    <body>
      <pb n="595"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">59.</hi> A Review of the Venereal Diſeaſe, <lb/>and its Remedies. By
          <hi rend="roman">William For- <lb/>dyce</hi>, Surgeon. <hi rend="roman">2 s.</hi>
        <hi rend="roman">Spilſbury</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Among miſtakes in former writers on this <lb/>ſubject, Mr. <hi rend="italic"
          >Fordyce</hi> reckons the following: </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>1. That any purgative long uſed will ef- <lb/>fectually cure a clap. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>2. That the patient ſhould not be blooded <lb/>till after a month's purging, even in
        ſanguine <lb/>temperaments, and where the complaint is <lb/>obſtinate. <hi
          rend="italic align-right">Sydenham. </hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>3. That mercurials are never neceſſary in <lb/>the firſt ſpecies of gonorrhea. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>4. That in the gonorrhea which affects <lb/><hi rend="italic">Morgagni</hi>'s <choice>
          <corr>glands</corr>
          <sic>glauds</sic>
        </choice>, and the ſeminal veſicles, <lb/>the cure may be reſted on plaiſters, oint-
        <lb/>ments, fomentations, pultices, the knife, the <lb/>ſweating-box, diet-drinks,
        abſtinence, and <lb/>ſalivation. <hi rend="italic align-right">Boerhaave. </hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>5. That in a confirmed pox, the cure con- <lb/>ſiſts in drawing off all the fat of the
        body, e- <lb/>ven to the laſt particle. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>6. That a gonorrhea never terminates in a <lb/>pox, provided the matter loaded with the
        ve- <lb/>nereal infection is freely and copiouſly diſ- <lb/>charged. <hi
          rend="italic align-right">Aſtruc. </hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Fordyce</hi>, in the courſe of his tract, lays <lb/>down the
        following poſitions, which he ſays <lb/>his own experience has proved to be true. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>1. When mercurial unctions are neceſſary, <lb/>the ſalutary effect does not ariſe from
        the ſa- <lb/>livation ſo much as from the quantity of <lb/>quickſilver neceſſary to
        extinguiſh the ſymp- <lb/>toms. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>2. Swellings in the teſticles which do not <lb/>yield to the hydrargyroſis, diſtortions
        of the <lb/>penis, nodes, gaglions, tubercles, exoſtoſei, <lb/>gummata, cancerous
        appearances, old vene- <lb/>real ſores, and ulcers in the womb, which <hi rend="italic">A-
          <lb/>ſtruc</hi> pronounces to be incurable, do frequent- <lb/>ly yield to ſome kinds of
        mineral water, <lb/>ſtrong decoctions of ſarſaparilla, and <hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi>
        <lb/>outwardly and inwardly applied. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>3. The ſolution of corroſive ſublimate, re- <lb/>commended by <hi rend="italic"
          >Vanſweiten</hi>, and diſpenſed un- <lb/>der as many quackiſh names as there are
        <lb/>advertiſements in the news-papers, cannot be <lb/>depended upon for the cure of the
        venereal <lb/>diſeaſe in any ſtage. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>4. A bad clap will frequently become a <lb/>pox by truſting to the running. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>5. Aſtringents, injections, and balſamics, <lb/>are pernicious. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>6. The purges uſed in this diſeaſe ſhould be <lb/>gentle, and by no means adminiſtered
        daily. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>7. Cancerous buboes, that reſiſted all other <lb/>remedies, have yielded to <hi
          rend="italic">Storck</hi>'s hemlock. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>8. Pocky ſymptoms, <hi rend="italic">when the body is other- <lb/>wiſe in perfect
          health</hi>, <choice>
          <corr>yield</corr>
          <sic>yeild</sic>
        </choice> to a proper quan- <lb/>tity of mercurial ointment. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>9. Guaiacum is of little uſe in this diſeaſe; <lb/>ſo, for ought that appears to this
        author, are <lb/>decoctions of bardana and mezerion, ſapona- <lb/>ria, lobelia, and many
        others that have been <lb/>much cried up. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>10. A cure in a virulent gonorrhea is never <lb/>effected, but a pox generally brought
        on by <lb/>mercurial injections. </p>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>11. Genuine mercury is to be preferred to <lb/>its ores; the native and factitious
        cinnabar, <lb/>and the antimonial kinds inwardly and out- <lb/>wardly applied, have produced
        bad effects, <lb/>both in the hands of this writer and Dr. <hi rend="italic">Aſtruc</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>12. Mercury diſſolved with acids is perni- <lb/>cious, eſpecially the turpeths,
        corroſive ſub- <lb/>limate, or ſublimate dulcified by repeated ſub- <lb/>limations<choice>
          <corr>,</corr>
          <sic>.</sic>
        </choice> and mercurials precipitated. Of <lb/>ſome of theſe half a grain, a fourth part, or
        e- <lb/>ven leſs, and that diluted too, will produce <lb/>anxieties, tremblings, vomitings,
        hyperca- <lb/>tharſes, convulſions, <choice>
          <corr>and</corr>
          <sic>aud</sic>
        </choice> ſometimes death. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>13. All mercurial applications to a vene- <lb/>real ſore of any kind, before the
        infection is <lb/>wholly conquered are pernicious. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>14. If the habit be ſcrophulous or ſcorbu- <lb/>tic, a ſmall quantity of mercurial
        ointment <lb/>rubbed on any part of the body, will often <lb/>produce a violent ſalivation
        of ſeveral weeks, <lb/>and, after all, the venereal taint will remain; <lb/>ſcorbutic and
        ſcrophulous diſpoſitions, there- <lb/>fore, muſt be corrected before a cure can be
        <lb/>effected by mercury. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The author's method of curing a virulent <lb/>gonorrhea is this. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Procure from two to four ſtools every other <lb/>day, for the firſt fourteen days, and
        the ſame <lb/>number every third day for the ſecond fourteen <lb/>days, by half an ounce of
        ſalts and manna. <lb/>If, after this time, the running is not conſide- <lb/>rably
        diminiſhed, or become of a better co- <lb/>lour or conſiſtence, the thighs, particularly
        <lb/>the inſide of them, ſhould be rubbed with an <lb/>ointment conſiſting of equal parts of
        crude <lb/>mercury and hog's lard, to the quantity of an <lb/>ounce or more, at due
        intervals, purging me- <lb/>dicines being intermixed at proper diſtances, <lb/>even though
        the chordee and heat of urine <lb/>ſhould ſtill ſubſiſt; or take <hi rend="italic"
            ><unclear>B</unclear>elloſt</hi>'s pill, <lb/>called alſo the blue pill, ten grains to
        an <lb/>doſe. Fermented liquors, rich food, and ex- <lb/>erciſe ſhould be avoided. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Upon this part of the author's work it may <lb/>be obſerved, that whether it is
        indended <lb/>for the practitioner or patient, it is de- <lb/>fective; for although he
        condemns <hi rend="italic">Boer- <lb/>haave</hi>'s principle, <q rend="diple quotes">that
          mercurials are never <lb/>neceſſary in the firſt ſpecies of gonorrhea, </q>
        <lb/>yet in this direction for its cure, he does not <lb/>adviſe mercurials, either
        internally or exter- <lb/>nally, <hi rend="italic">except</hi> untoward ſymptoms remain
        after <lb/>purging with manna and ſalts a month. Ei- <lb/>ther mercurials ſhould be
        adminiſtered if ſuch <lb/>ſymptoms do not remain, which is not here <lb/>directed, or the
        cure is to be depended upon <lb/>without mercurials, according to a principle <lb/>which is
        condemned; and when the eaſe <lb/>happens in which the author recommends <lb/>mercury, he is
        not explicit with reſpect to the <lb/>friction, though he is with reſpect to the pill.
        <lb/>He ſays an ounce, <hi rend="italic">or more</hi>, ſhould be rubbed <lb/>in <hi
          rend="italic">at due intervals</hi> and that purging medicines <lb/>ſhould be intermixed
        at <hi rend="italic">proper diſtances</hi>; but <lb/>what thoſe intervals and diſtances are,
        or how <lb/>much more than an ounce may be applied, he <lb/>has left undetermined. </p>
      <pb n="596"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The book is, however, written with in- <lb/>telligence and candour; the author
        confeſſes <lb/>his miſtakes, and ſeems to found his princi- <lb/>ples wholly upon
        experience. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He mentions one characteriſtic of the ve- <lb/>nereal diſeaſe, the knowledge of which
        may <lb/>free many perſons, conſcious to practices that <lb/>may have contracted it, from
        the moſt tor- <lb/>menting anxiety upon trifling diſorders that <lb/>reſemble ſome ſymptoms
        of that malady. It <lb/>is, ſays Mr. <hi rend="italic">Fordyce</hi>, always in a <hi
          rend="italic">progreſſive <lb/>ſtate, growing worſe every hour</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He alſo confeſſes that a virulent gonorrhea <lb/>cannot be ſpeedily cured, if it be
        cured effec- <lb/>tually; that it will often run out to two or <lb/>three months and in ſome
        caſes to five or ſix, <lb/>if the ſevereſt regimen is not obſerved: It is <lb/>to be hoped,
        therefore, that quacks and no- <lb/>ſtrum-mongers, who impudently pretend to <lb/>cure it in
        a few days, without confinement, or <lb/>alteration of diet, will be no longer believed,
        <lb/>to the deſtruction of the miſerable and delu- <lb/>ded patient, &amp; perhaps of a wife
        and family. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In his laſt ſection, the author has conſider- <lb/>ed the preſent ſtate of the venereal
        diſeaſe <lb/>among us, and is of opinion, that ſo far <lb/>from being on the decline, it is
        gaining <lb/>ground, which, indeed, from ſome particu- <lb/>lars in this account is very
        probable, for the <lb/>author tells us of one man who got a clap by <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >dining upon turtle</hi>, and of another who in- <lb/>curred the ſame misfortune, by <hi
          rend="italic">carrying ſome <lb/>Cayan pepper about him</hi> in an handkerchief. </p>
      <signed rend="align-right">
        <lb/>X. </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
