<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: The present method of inoculating for the small pox</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>The present method of inoculating for the small pox; to which are added, some
              experiments, instituted with a view to discover the effects of a similar treatment in
              the natural small pox. By Thomas Dimsdale, M. D. 2s. 6d. Owen. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed at St John's Gate, for D. Henry; and sold by F. Newbery,
                  the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard, Ludgate Street.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1767</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">37</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">313</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1767_GM_0313">
    <body>
      <pb n="313"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">2.</hi> The preſent method of inoculating for <lb/>the ſmall pox; to
        which are added, ſome <lb/>experiments, inſtituted with a view to <lb/>diſcover the effects
        of a ſimilar treatment <lb/>in the natural ſmall-pox. By <hi rend="roman">Thomas
          <lb/>Dimſdale</hi>, M. D. <hi rend="roman">2s. 6d. Owen.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>All ages above two years, all ſea- <lb/>ſons and all habits are proper for ino-
        <lb/>culation; critical diſeaſes only, or <lb/>their effects, corroſive acrimonious
        <lb/>humours, and manifeſt debility of the <lb/>whole frame, render the patient unfit
        <lb/>for the operation. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The method of preparing the pati- <lb/>ent, and of performing the operation, <lb/>is
        the ſame as directed by Dr <hi rend="italic">Baker</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">(ſee Vol.
            <hi rend="roman"><hi rend="sc">xxxvi.</hi></hi> p.</hi> 383.) The medi- <lb/>cines
        adminiſtered during preparation <lb/>are a powder conſiſting of 8 grains of <lb/>calomel, 8
        grains of compound pow- <lb/>der of crabs claws, and one-eighth <lb/>part of a grain of
        emetic tartar, or in- <lb/>ſtead of it, two grains of precipitated <lb/>ſulphur of antimony. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This doſe is ſufficient for the moſt <lb/>robuſt conſtitution; for women, chil-
        <lb/>dren, and old or weakly people it muſt <lb/>be proportionably leſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This medicine is to be adminiſtered <lb/>as directed by Dr <hi rend="italic"
        >Baker</hi>, and the next <lb/>morning a doſe of purging ſalts. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But if the conſtitution of the patient <lb/>is very tender and delicate, the medi-
        <lb/>cines ought rather to be alterative <lb/>than purging; and the utmoſt atten- <lb/>tion
        muſt be given ſo to manage the <lb/>mercurial medicine as that it may not <lb/>ſalivate,
        which has ſometimes hap- <lb/>pened, to the irreparable injury of the <lb/>patient. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the ſecond day after inoculation, <lb/>Dr <hi rend="italic">Dimſdale</hi> gives 3
        grains of the crabs <lb/>claws, 3 grains of calomel, and 1-10th <lb/>of emetic tartar, going
        to bed. On <lb/>the next morning a laxative draught, <lb/>conſiſting of two ounces of
        infuſion of <lb/>ſenna, half an ounce of manna, and <lb/>two drams of tincture of jalap. </p>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Theſe medicines are repeated as <lb/>ſoon as the eruptive ſymptoms appear, <lb/>if they
        indicate any unuſual vehe- <lb/>mence. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When the eruption comes on, the <lb/>patient is directed to keep in the open <lb/>air,
        however cold, as much as he can <lb/>bear, but not to ſtand ſtill, and to <lb/>drink cold
        water, if thirſty. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After the eruption is compleated, <lb/>and not before, the patient, is allowed
        <lb/>animal food, boiled meat of the light- <lb/>eſt kind, chicken, veal, or mutton, in
        <lb/>a ſmall quantity. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After maturation, the diet may <lb/>gradually be more generous, but the <lb/>patient is
        urgently preſſed to return <lb/>to his ordinary diet with much cauti- <lb/>on, and to
        reſtrain his appetite as well <lb/>with reſpect to food as fermented li- <lb/>quors. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A raſh ſometimes appears with the <lb/>ſmall-pox, covers the whole ſkin, and <lb/>has
        the appearance of a malignant <lb/>confluent kind. It may be diſtin- <lb/>guiſhed from the
        confluent ſmall-pox <lb/>by the fever, reſtleſsneſs, pain, and <lb/>weakneſs being leſs, and
        a few diſtinct <lb/>puſtules, larger than the reſt, may, <lb/>upon a very critical
        examination, be <lb/>diſtinguiſhed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When this raſh happens, the patient <lb/>muſt neither go into the cold air, nor
        <lb/>drink cold water, for theſe, though ſa- <lb/>lutary to the ſmall-pox, may repel the
        <lb/>raſh, and do miſchief. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Sometimes eruptive ſymptoms hap- <lb/>pen, and no eruption follows. Doctor <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Dimſdale</hi>, in theſe caſes, ſuppoſes the <lb/>patient to have no more to
        fear from <lb/>the diſtemper than if the eruption had <lb/>covered him from head to foot.
        The <lb/>reader, however, may read an account <lb/>of the caſe of the Ducheſs <hi
          rend="italic">de Boufflers</hi>, <lb/>which ſeems to prove the contrary in <lb/>our
        Magazine, Volume <hi rend="sc">xxxvi.</hi>
        <hi rend="italic">p.</hi>
        <lb/>117. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>This method of inoculation has ne- <lb/>ver been known to have bad effects <lb/>upon
        the conſtitution. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Dr <hi rend="italic">Dimſdale</hi> has directed the ſame <lb/>management to patients
        under the na- <lb/>tural ſmall-pox, and his ſucceſs has <lb/>exceeded his expectation. When
        he <lb/>has not been called till the eruption <lb/>has appeared, he has endeavoured to
        <lb/>get the ſick into the open air, and ge- <lb/>nerally given the mercurial and anti-
        <lb/>nomial pill, directing a laxative ſome <lb/>hours after it, to procure three or four
        <lb/>ſtools: This method he has more par- <lb/>ticularly enjoined, and ſometimes re- <pb
          n="314"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>peated, where the ſmall-pox has been <lb/>of a bad kind, with ſymptoms of great
        <lb/>danger. He has followed the ſame <lb/>method during the whole progreſs of <lb/>the
        eruptive fever, with a view to a- <lb/>bate its violence, to check the erupti- <lb/>on, and
        to prevent the conflux. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Doctor has been ſo fortunate as <lb/>not to loſe one patient treated in this
        <lb/>way, though the number amounts to <lb/>forty, and ſome have been ſo weak <lb/>when
        carried into the air, that they <lb/>could not ſtand without ſupport: <lb/>They ſhould,
        however, be kept mov- <lb/>ing about between two. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The following extracts ſeem to ſhew <lb/>a remarkable difference between the
        <lb/>inoculated and natural ſmall-pox with <lb/>reſpect to the time of their appearance
        <lb/>as a prognoſtic. </p>
      <floatingText type="" subtype="extract">
        <head rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>
          <q part="i">Inoculated Small Pox. </q>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>p. 34. <q part="f">If the eruptive appearances <lb/>are obſerved <hi rend="italic"
              >early</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">favourable</hi> event <lb/>is implied; but if the
            alteration on <lb/>the fifth or ſixth day is ſo inconſidera- <lb/>ble as to make it
            doubtful whether the <lb/>infection has taken place, the appear- <lb/>ance is <hi
              rend="italic">unfavourable</hi>, and implies a <lb/><hi rend="italic">late</hi> and
            more <hi rend="italic">untoward</hi> diſeaſe, to pre- <lb/>vent which, I order the
            powder to be <lb/>taken every night, and an ounce of <lb/>ſalts in the morning, which
              <hi rend="italic">forwards</hi>
            <lb/>the inflammation; I have conſtantly <lb/>obſerved that an <hi rend="italic"
              >early</hi> commencement <lb/>of eruptive complaints portends that <lb/>the diſtemper
            will be <hi rend="italic">mild</hi> and <hi rend="italic">favour- <lb/>able</hi>; when
            they are <hi rend="italic">late</hi>, the ſymp- <lb/>toms are <hi rend="italic"
              >irregular and untoward</hi>. </q>
        </p>
      </floatingText>
      <floatingText type="" subtype="extract">
        <head rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>
          <q part="i">Natural Small-Pox. </q>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>p. 67. <q rend="quotes" part="f">The mercurial powder, and <lb/>ſubſequent purge, <hi
              rend="italic">mitigate</hi> the fever <lb/>preceding eruption; and I will add,
            <lb/>that the eruption is moſt certainly <hi rend="italic">re- <lb/>tarded</hi>; that
            is, it does <hi rend="italic">not appear ſo <lb/>ſoon</hi> after the attack of the
            diſeaſe, nor <lb/>come out <hi rend="italic">ſo precipitately</hi> when it has be-
            <lb/>gun to appear as it ſeemed likely to <lb/>have done, if the natural progreſs had
            <lb/>not been interrupted, which ſhews the <lb/>utility of the practice, for it is
            evident <lb/>from experience, that the <hi rend="italic">later</hi> the e- <lb/>ruption
            ſhews itſelf, after the begin- <lb/>ning of the diſeaſe, and the <hi rend="italic"
              >ſlower</hi> it <lb/>comes out, the more <hi rend="italic">mild</hi> and <hi
              rend="italic">favoura- <lb/>ble</hi> is the ſubſequent diſorder. </q>
        </p>
      </floatingText>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By theſe extracts it appears that the <lb/>mercurial powders and ſalts <hi
          rend="italic">forward</hi>
        <lb/>the inflammation in the inoculated <lb/>ſmall-pox, and <hi rend="italic">mitigate</hi>
        the <hi rend="italic">fever</hi> in the <lb/>natural; that in the inoculated an <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">early</hi> commencement of eruptive com- <lb/>plaints portends that the
        diſtemper <lb/>will be <hi rend="italic">favourable</hi>: and that in the na- <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>tural the eruption is <hi rend="italic">favourable</hi> in pro- <lb/>portion as it is
          <hi rend="italic">late and ſlow</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the commonly neglected interval <lb/>between the completion of the erupti- <lb/>on,
        and the fever of maturation, Dr <lb/><hi rend="italic">Dimſdale</hi> recommends the ſame
        mer- <lb/>curial antimonial medicine as in the <lb/>eruptive fever, to be repeated at pro-
        <lb/>per intervals till the maturation ad- <lb/>vances, and then to be diſcontinued<choice>
          <corr>.</corr>
          <sic>,</sic>
        </choice>
        <lb/>He directs alſo a cupful of the follow- <lb/>ing apozem to be taken, if neceſſary,
        <lb/>after the mercurial medicine, often e- <lb/>nough to procure two or three ſtools <lb/>a
        day. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Cream of tartar two drachms, man- <lb/>na one ounce, diſſolved in a quart of
        <lb/>barley-water. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the moſt dangerous ſtage of the <lb/>diſeaſe, that of maturation, Dr <hi
          rend="italic">Dimſdale</hi>
        <lb/>recommends no medicine but the fol- <lb/>lowing: </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">Mix together one part of weak <lb/>ſpirit of vitriol, and two parts of
          ſweet <lb/>ſpirit of vitriol; put half an ounce of <lb/>this mixture to a quart or three
          pints <lb/>of barley-water, &amp; drink it at pleaſure. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Doctor thinks that in the natu- <lb/>ral confluent ſmall-pox, even when <lb/>the
        eruption is compleated, the altera- <lb/>tive and purging medicines may be <lb/>given, and
        the patient permitted to <lb/>go into the open air in cold weather; <lb/>even while the
        mercurial purge is o- <lb/>perating; but in the bleeding or pur- <lb/>ple ſmall-pox, he
        ſays, the mercurial <lb/>evacuating courſe ſeems to be impro- <lb/>per, though very cold
        repellent me- <lb/>thods may be tried. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To this account of treating the diſ- <lb/>eaſe, whether inoculated or natural,
        <lb/>ſeveral caſes are added, of perſons <lb/>who, having been inoculated, had e-
        <lb/>ruptive ſymptoms, but no eruption; <lb/>ſome of theſe were inoculated a ſe- <lb/>cond
        time without any effect, and one <lb/>of them, whoſe breath was tainted, <lb/>and arm
        inflamed, is ſaid to have in- <lb/>fected his wife, who attended him as <lb/>nurſe, and was
        ſuppoſed to have had <lb/>the diſtemper before. </p>
      <signed rend="align-right">X. </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
