<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Schmidius: Observations on some extraordinary symptoms, occasioned by
          Nutmeg</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Jacob Schmidius</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Observations on some extraordinary symptoms, occasioned by Nutmeg taken in too
              great a quantity. By Dr Jacob Schmidius.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed at St John's Gate, for D. Henry; and sold by F. Newbery,
                  the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard, Ludgate Street.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1767</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">37</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">72</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1767_GM_0072">
    <body>
      <pb n="72"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/>Obſervations on ſome extraordinary ſymp- <lb/>toms, occaſioned by <hi rend="roman"
          >Nutmeg</hi> taken in <lb/>too great a quantity. By Dr <hi rend="sc">Jacob
          <lb/>Schmidius</hi>. </head>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Gentleman of <hi rend="italic">Lower Sileſia</hi>, about
        <lb/>thirty-ſix years old, of a good <lb/>conſtitution, and who enjoyed a good <lb/>ſtate of
        health, having felt, during <lb/>ſome days, ſome cholic pains, took it <lb/>in his head, by
        way of remedy, to eat <lb/>four nutmegs, which weighed all to- <lb/>gether two ounces, and
        he drank, in <lb/>eating them, ſome glaſſes of beer; <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>which he had no ſooner done, but was <lb/>ſeized with a great heat, a violent pain
        <lb/>in the head, a vertigo and delirium, <lb/>and <sic>we</sic> inſtantly deprived of the
        uſe of <lb/>ſight, ſpeech, and all his ſenſes. He <lb/>was put to bed, where he remained
        <lb/>two days and two nights; his body <lb/>was oppreſſed with laſſitude, always
        <lb/>drowſy, yet without being able to ſleep. <lb/>The third day he was in that lethargic
        <lb/>ſtate which is called a <hi rend="italic">coma vigil</hi>, with <lb/>a weak and
        intermitting pulſe. Cepha- <lb/>lic remedies, cordials, and among o- <lb/>thers, the ſpirit
        of cephalic vitriol, <lb/>and the eſſence of caſtoreum, were ad- <lb/>miniſter'd in good
        ſpirit of ſal ammo- <lb/>niac. The fourth day he recovered a <lb/>little, but had abſolutely
        loſt his me- <lb/>mory; ſo as not to remember the leaſt <lb/>thing he had done in his life.
        A con- <lb/>tinued fever then came on, accompa- <lb/>nied by an obſtinate watchfulneſs; a
        <lb/>palpitation of the heart ſeemed to be <lb/>the fore-runner of other ſymptoms, <lb/>and
        he was finally ſtruck with a palſy <lb/>in all his limbs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>At the expiration of eight days, he <lb/>recovered the uſe of reaſon, and ſaid,
        <lb/>that during the firſt four days of his <lb/>illneſs, he ſeemed to himſelf to have
        <lb/>conſtantly a thick veil before his eyes, <lb/>and that a great number of ſparks and
        <lb/>flaſhes continually iſſued from it. All <lb/>the bad ſymptoms of this malady
        <lb/>yielded at laſt ſucceſſively to the conti- <lb/>nued uſe of remedies ſuited to his con-
        <lb/>dition; and in three months time he <lb/>was perfectly recovered, but he was
        <lb/>particularly indebted, for his cure, to <lb/>mercurial and ammoniacal remedies. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>According to chemical principles, it <lb/>might, perhaps, be ſaid, that the aro-
        <lb/>matic and oily ſalt contained in nut- <lb/>meg, of which this patient had taken
        <lb/>too large a doſe, had immediately ex- <lb/>cited ſo great an agitation in the hu-
        <lb/>mours, and ſo rapid a motion in the <lb/>animal ſpirits, as in ſome meaſure to
        <lb/>partake of the nature of fire, and that <lb/>a viſcid and narcotic ſulphur, which
        <lb/>reſides likewiſe in the nutmeg, tho' in <lb/>a leſs ſenſible manner, being carried,
        <lb/>at the ſame time, into the maſs of <lb/>blood, by ſuddenly fixing the animal
        <lb/>ſpirits, and intercepting their courſe <lb/>in the nerves, had afterwards cauſed
        <lb/>the ſtupor in the limbs, the aphony, <lb/>and the palſy. But I leave others to ex-
        <lb/>plain theſe phænomena, my only view, <lb/>by communicating this obſervation, <lb/>being
        to ſhew that the immoderate uſe <lb/>of nutmeg may be attended with very <lb/>great danger.
      </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
