<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: The Case of a Lady who died of a Tympany.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>The Case of a Lady who died of a Tympany.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed at St John's Gate, for D. Henry; and sold by F. Newbery,
                  the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard, Ludgate Street.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1767</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">37</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">360</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1767_GM_0360">
    <body>
      <pb n="360"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <head rend="italic align-center">
        <lb/>The Caſe of a Lady who died of a <lb/><hi rend="roman">Tympany</hi>. </head>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">L</hi>ADY <hi rend="italic">Haſtings</hi>, daughter of the <lb/>late
        Rev. Dr. <hi rend="italic">Moſes Terry</hi>, of <hi rend="italic">Lin- <lb/>coln</hi>, was,
        in the prime of life, ſubject <lb/>to the dropſy, without any very ma- <lb/>terial decay of
        her health and ſpirits, <lb/>which ſhe enjoyed to an uncommon de- <lb/>gree, notwithſtanding
        the increaſe of the <lb/>diſorder. After having procured the <lb/>advice of the beſt
        phyſicians, who con- <lb/>ſulted together upon her caſe, the diſor- <lb/>der was left to
        take its courſe. Her <lb/>belly was ſwelled to an enormous ſize <lb/>by the water collected
        between the ſkin <lb/>and the fleſh, and which, if ſtruck, <lb/>ſounded like a drum. Indeed
        her ſkin <lb/>by the ſwelling, was not unlike the <lb/>parchment on the head of a drum, and
        <lb/>was ſtretched and braced nearly as <lb/>tight. When the diſorder was about <lb/>ten
        years ſtanding, it began to bear very <lb/>hard upon her ſtrength (though ſhe had <lb/>ſtill
        no complaint of ſickneſs, or any <lb/>thing but the cumberſomeneſs of her <lb/>own weight)
        and ſhe had therefore no <lb/>power to walk, or hardly to ſtand. A <lb/>chair of a
        convenient make and ſize, con- <lb/>trived ſo that ſhe might wheel herſelf <lb/>about
        therein, was accordingly prepared <lb/>for her, as was alſo a coach of uncom- <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>mon dimenſions, for her to ride out <lb/>in. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Whenever ſhe rode in her coach ſhe <lb/>had always another perſon that uſed to <lb/>ſit
        exactly oppoſite to her, with her knees <lb/>cloſely fixed againſt hers, leſt any vio-
        <lb/>lent motion ſhould throw her forwards. <lb/>Though her ſtrength was much impaired
        <lb/>under ſuch an amazing preſſure, yet ſhe <lb/>was very lively, and ſaw a great deal of
        <lb/>company, and uſed to bear a part in con- <lb/>verſation with extraordinary chearful-
        <lb/>neſs. She lived very abſtemiouſly, and <lb/>this kept her up for many years longer,
        <lb/>probably, than otherwiſe ſhe would have <lb/>ſuſtained herſelf. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>During the laſt year of her life ſhe <lb/>was ſwelled ſo much that ſhe was unable
        <lb/>to move or help herſelf, and would <lb/>have thought death a happy deliverance
        <lb/>from a life now rendered inſupportable. <lb/>Her bulk, at the time I am now ſpeak-
        <lb/>ing of, exceeded that of large ſugar <lb/>hogſhead; and, however amazing this <lb/>may
        ſeem, there are ſeveral now living <lb/>at <hi rend="italic">Lincoln</hi> that well knew
        her, and ſaw <lb/>her when ſhe was in this condition, that <lb/>can vouch for the truth of
        it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>One day, as ſhe was ſitting with com- <lb/>pany, ſhe felt herſelf on a ſudden ſo
        <lb/>much eaſier and lighter, that ſhe could <lb/>not help ſignifying it by her countenance
        <lb/>to thoſe ſhe was with, which ſhe had <lb/>hardly done before the cauſe of it was
        <lb/>plainly diſcovered, by a prodigious quan- <lb/>tity of water running upon the floor in
        a <lb/>plentiful ſtream. She was delighted be- <lb/>yond expreſſion at this diſcharge of her
        <lb/>load, and looked upon it as a favourable <lb/>ſymptom that would precede a cure.---
        <lb/>But neither ſhe, nor her friends, who <lb/>gladly took part in her joy, obtained
        <lb/>their wiſhes; for the fleſh mortified, <lb/>and ſhe died the fourth day after this
        <lb/>happened, a ſhocking ſpectacle indeed! <lb/>Her belly, after this rupture, was as
        <lb/>black as ink, and the <choice>
          <corr>ſkin</corr>
          <sic>fkin</sic>
        </choice> hung down <lb/>over her knees upon the floor. Such an <lb/>inſtance of magnitude
        had not been <lb/>known by any body then living; and <lb/>how ſhe could carry upwards of 40
        gal- <lb/>lons of water within her will be amaz- <lb/>ing, no doubt, to thoſe who never
        before <lb/>heard of her caſe; but this aſtoniſhing <lb/>quantity abſolutely came from her
        when <lb/>ſhe burſt. From the time this happened <lb/>to the day on which ſhe died, ſhe felt
        no <lb/>pain or uneaſineſs, and was thorough- <lb/>ly ſenſible when ſhe fetched her laſt
        <lb/>breath. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>She lies buried in <hi rend="italic">Lincoln</hi> cathedral, <lb/>with ſome
        notifications of the ſingularity <lb/>of the diſtemper which ended her life. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
