<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Of Soap and Lixiviums in the Cure of the Stone</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Of Soap and Lixiviums in the Cure of the Stone</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed at St John's Gate, for D. Henry; and sold by F. Newbery,
                  the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard, Ludgate Street.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1767</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">37</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">502</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1767_GM_0502">
    <body>
      <pb n="502"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <salute rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="sc">Urban</hi>, </salute>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(1.5)">T</hi>HE extraordinary anſwer to my let- <lb/>ter on the ill effects
        ariſing from the <lb/>imprudent and long continued uſe of <lb/>lixiviums, and ſoap-lyes,
          <sic>demand</sic> from <pb n="503"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>me a return. Why ſhould Mr. <hi rend="italic">Alex- <lb/>ander Blackrie</hi> be ſo very
        angry on the <lb/>occaſion? for, had he read that letter <lb/>calmly, he would not have
        declared it <lb/>replete either with miſrepreſentations, <lb/>inconſiſtencies, or
        abſurdities. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He unfortunately miſconceives the <lb/>whole affair, when he thinks that letter
        <lb/>calculated for lucrative views. Why <lb/>does he allow the propriety of my argu-
        <lb/>ment, and at the ſame time abuſe it? <lb/>I advanced, that lixiviums and ſoap-
        <lb/>lyes, indiſcriminately uſed, were often- <lb/>times injurious to the conſtitution, and
        <lb/>enumerated the various ills ariſing there- <lb/>from. This, I ſay, he allows, and de-
        <lb/>nies, in the ſame ſentence, by the help <lb/>of the proviſo (judiciouſly adminiſtered)
        <lb/>which <choice>
          <corr>proviſo</corr>
          <sic>proviſio</sic>
        </choice> is here out of place, and <lb/>his reference to <hi rend="italic">Boerhaave</hi>'s
          <hi rend="italic">Elementa <lb/>Chemica</hi>, where the proceſs and hiſtory of
        <lb/>alkaline ſalts are given, yields little ſa- <lb/>tisfaction on this head. He ſays, that
        <lb/>it is an highly corroſive production, and <lb/>particularly deſtructive to all animal
        ſub- <lb/>ſtances with which it comes in contact, <lb/>(eſpecially when joined with quick
        lime, <lb/>by which the ſtrongeſt cauſtics are pro- <lb/>duced) as ſuch he recommends it to
        be <lb/>taken, but in very ſmall doſes, and <lb/>chiefly when an acid is predominant in
        <lb/>the body. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To ſuppoſe that the caſe of Dr. <hi rend="italic">Jurin</hi>
        <lb/>is a miſrepreſentation, becauſe not to be <lb/>found in his publication, is a compleat
        <lb/>blunder, for how could the doctor write <lb/>the hiſtory of his own caſe after his
        <lb/>death? and if the doctor's killing him- <lb/>ſelf with his own lixivium may be ſome-
        <lb/>what doubtful, I muſt remind Mr. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Blackrie</hi> of the fatal
        effects which the <lb/>doctor's lixivium produced on Lord <lb/><hi rend="italic"
        >Orford</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If Mr. <hi rend="italic">Blackrie</hi> has read Dr. <hi rend="italic">Whytt</hi>
        <lb/>on Lyme-Water attentively, he will <lb/>there find that ſoap is preferred to lixi-
        <lb/>viums. He ſays, indeed, that lixiviums <lb/>may be taken in ſmall doſes with lime-
        <lb/>water, to advantage, in ſome caſes, and <lb/>he ſays as much of <hi rend="italic"
          >Spiritus Nitri dulcis</hi>, <lb/>which you know, Sir, to be an acid, <lb/>conſequently
        diametrically oppoſite to <lb/>lixiviums. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The next ſentence is tortured out of <lb/>its true meaning, merely for the ſake of
        <lb/>contradiction; for, in my firſt letter, <lb/>inſerted in the Magazine of <hi
          rend="italic">July</hi>, (to <lb/>which I refer the reader) I mention that <lb/>the uſe of
        lixiviums were brought into <lb/>practice again, in conſequence of Dr. <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Hales</hi>'s experiments on erroneous prin- <lb/>ciples; for, by the
        addition of an unc- <lb/>tuous body, this corroſive medicine is <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>rendered mild, and by the union, not <lb/>leſs, but more effectual, in moſt caſes
        <lb/>where deobſtruents can be ſerviceable; <lb/>here I refer the reader to the proceſs of
        <lb/>ſoap in <hi rend="italic">Boerhaave</hi>'s chymiſtry, and ob- <lb/>ſervations on it as
        a medicine, which, I <lb/>flatter myſelf, will be found more ſatis- <lb/>factory on this
        head, than Mr. <hi rend="italic">Black- <lb/>rie</hi>'s reference to the ſame author's pro-
        <lb/>ceſs on alkaline ſalts. Can it be proved <lb/>that lixiviums are better ſolvents of the
        <lb/>human ſtone, than ſoaps? I anſwer, <lb/>No. And for this I refer to Dr. <hi
          rend="italic">Deſ- <lb/>cherney</hi>'s experiments on the urine of <lb/>ſuch patients as
        took his ſoap medicines. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Reſpecting punch being a ſolvent of <lb/>human calculi, it was ſpoken figurative-
        <lb/>ly; but, taken ſeriouſly, punch is a ſol- <lb/>vent of ſoft calculi, and lixiviums are
        no <lb/>more, if ſo much ſo, when diluted for <lb/>internal uſe; for this I refer the reader
        <lb/>to Dr. <hi rend="italic">Lobb</hi>'s experiments on calculi, as <lb/>read before the
        Royal-Society in 1738. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Before Mr. <hi rend="italic">Blackrie</hi> takes upon him- <lb/>ſelf to give advice to
        the author of that <lb/>letter, let him remember, that ſcurrility <lb/>is inconſiſtent with
        the Gentleman and <lb/>Scholar. If he has prepared a lixivium <lb/>which he thinks better
        than ſuch as are <lb/>uſed by others, far be it from me to find <lb/>fault with his
        endeavours at improve- <lb/>ment, I congratulate him thereupon. </p>
      <signed rend="italic align-center">I am you humble ſervant. </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
