<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: An Account of the Manner of inoculating for the
          Small-Pox in the East-Indies</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Account of the Manner of inoculating for the Small-Pox in the East-Indies.
              With some Observations on the Practice and Mode of treating that Disease in those
              Parts. Inscribed to the learned the President and Members of the College of Physicians
              in London. By J. Z. Holwell. F. R. S. Becket. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed at St John's Gate, for D. Henry; and sold by F. Newbery,
                  the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard, Ludgate Street.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1767</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">37</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">554</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1767_GM_0554">
    <body>
      <pb n="554"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">49.</hi> An Account of the Manner of ino- <lb/>culating for the
        Small-Pox in the <hi rend="roman">Eaſt- <lb/>Indies</hi>. With ſome Obſervations on the
        <lb/>Practice and Mode of treating that Diſ- <lb/>eaſe in thoſe Parts. Inſcribed to the
        lear- <lb/>ned the Preſident and Members of the Col- <lb/>lege of Phyſicians in <hi
          rend="roman">London</hi>. By <hi rend="roman">J. Z. <lb/>Holwell. F. R. S.</hi>
        <hi rend="roman">Becket</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The method of inoculation uſed by the <hi rend="italic">Bra- <lb/>mins</hi> of <hi
          rend="italic">Indoſtan</hi>, time out of mind, remark- <lb/>ably tends to ſupport the
        practice now gene- <lb/>rally followed with ſuch marvellous ſucceſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In that country the ſmall-pox is epidemi- <pb n="555"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>cal every ſeventh year. During the months of <lb/><hi rend="italic">March</hi>, <hi
          rend="italic">April</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">May</hi>, it is then, (though at <lb/>all
        other times ſo mild, as ſcarcely to be not- <lb/>ed,) confluent, malignant, and fatal to
        nearly <lb/>all that take it naturally, whether <hi rend="italic">European</hi> or
        <lb/>native. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Inoculation is performed in <hi rend="italic">Indoſtan</hi> by a <lb/>particular tribe
        of <hi rend="italic">Bramins</hi>, who are delegated <lb/>annually for the ſervice: They
        divide them- <lb/>ſelves into ſmall parties, and plan their cir- <lb/>cuits, ſo as to arrive
        at their deſtination ſome <lb/>weeks before the uſual return of the diſeaſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The inhabitants of <hi rend="italic">Bengal</hi>, knowing when <lb/>the inoculating <hi
          rend="italic">Bramins</hi> annually return, ob- <lb/>ſerve the regimen enjoined,
        abſtaining for a <lb/>month, from fiſh, milk, and ghee, (a kind of <lb/>butter made
        generally of buffalo's milk) the <lb/>prohibition of fiſh reſpects only the native <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Portugueſe</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Mahometans</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Bramine</hi> paſs from houſe to houſe, and <lb/>operate at the
        door, refuſing to inoculate any <lb/>who have not duly obſerved the preparatory <lb/>courſe.
        It is no uncommon thing for them to <lb/>aſk the parents how many pocks they chuſe
        <lb/>their children ſhould have; and, ſtrange as it <lb/>is, they hardly ever exceed or are
        deficient, <lb/>in the number required. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>They inoculate indifferently on any part, <lb/>but prefer the outſide of the arm,
        mid-way be- <lb/>tween the wri<unclear>ſt</unclear> and the elbow for the males; <lb/>and
        the ſame between the elbow and the ſhoul- <lb/>der for the females. Previous to the opera-
        <lb/>tion, the operator takes a piece of cloth in his <lb/>hand, and with it gives a dry
        friction upon the <lb/>part intended for inoculation, for the ſpace of <lb/>eight or ten
        minutes, then with a ſmall inſtru- <lb/>ment he wounds, by many ſlight touches, a- <lb/>bout
        the compaſs of a ſilver groat, juſt making <lb/>the ſmalleſt appearance of blood, then
        opening <lb/>a linen double rag, takes from thence a ſmall <lb/>pledgit of cotton charged
        with the variolous <lb/>matter, which he moiſtens with two or three <lb/>drops of water, and
        applies it to the wound, <lb/>fixing it on with a ſlight bandage, and ordering <lb/>it to
        remain on for ſix hours, without being <lb/>moved, then the bandage to be taken off, and
        <lb/>the pledget to remain <choice>
          <corr>until</corr>
          <sic>untill</sic>
        </choice> it falls off itſelf; <lb/>ſometimes (but rarely) he ſqueezes a drop from <lb/>the
        pledget, upon the part, before he applies <lb/>it. The cotton is ſaturated with matter from
        <lb/>the inoculated puſtules of the preceding year, <lb/>for they never inoculate with freſh
        matter, <lb/>nor with matter from the diſeaſe caught in the <lb/>natural way, however
        diſtinct and mild the ſpe- <lb/>cies. He then proceeds to give inſtructions <lb/>for the
        treatment of the patient through the <lb/>courſe of the proceſs, which are moſt religi-
        <lb/>ouſly obſerved, and are as follow: </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He extends the prohibition of fiſh, milk, <lb/>and ghee, for one month, from the day of
        i- <lb/>noculation; early on the morning ſucceeding <lb/>the operation, about two gallons of
        cold water <lb/>are ordered to be thrown over the patient, from <lb/>the head downwards, and
        to be repeated every <lb/>morning and evening until the fever comes on, <lb/>(which uſually
        is about the cloſe of the ſixth <lb/>day from the inoculation) then to deſiſt until <lb/>the
        appearance of the eruption (which com- <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>monly happens at the cloſe of the third com- <lb/>pleat day from the commencement of
        the fe- <lb/>ver) and then to purſue the cold bathing as <lb/>before, through the courſe of
        the diſeaſe, and <lb/>until the ſcabs of the puſtules drop off. <lb/>They are ordered to
        open all the puſtules <lb/>with a fine ſharp pointed thorn, as ſoon as <lb/>they begin to
        change their colour, and whilſt <lb/>the matter continues in a fluid ſtate. Con-
        <lb/>finement to the houſe is abſolutely forbidden, <lb/>and the inoculated are ordered to
        be expoſed <lb/>to every air that blows; and the utmoſt indul- <lb/>gence they are allowed
        when the fever comes <lb/>on, is to be laid on a mat at the door; but, the <lb/>eruptive
        fever is generally ſo trifling, as ſel- <lb/>dom to require this indulgence. Their regi-
        <lb/>men is ordered to conſiſt of all the refrigerat- <lb/>ing things the climate and ſeaſon
        produce, as <lb/>plantains, ſugar-canes, water-melons, rice, <lb/>gruel made of white
        poppy-ſeeds, and cold <lb/>water, or thin rice-gruel, for their ordinary <lb/>drink. The
        regimen they order when they <lb/>are called to attend the diſeaſe taken in the <lb/>natural
        way is uniformly the ſame. There <lb/>uſually begins to be a diſcharge from the ſca-
        <lb/>rification, a day before the eruption, which <lb/>continues through the diſeaſe, and
        ſometimes <lb/>after the ſcabs of the pock fall off, and a few <lb/>puſtules generally
        appear round the edge of <lb/>the wound; when theſe two circumſtances <lb/>appear only,
        without a ſingle eruption on any <lb/>other part of the body, the patient is deemed <lb/>as
        ſecure from future infection, as if the erup- <lb/>tion had been general. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When the treatment preſcribed is ſtrictly <lb/>followed, ſcarce one in a million fails
        of re- <lb/>ceiving the infection, or miſcarries under it; <lb/>of the multitudes I have
        ſeen, ſays Mr. <hi rend="italic">H.</hi>
        <lb/>the number of puſtules have been ſeldom leſs <lb/>than fifty, &amp; hardly ever
        exceeded two hundred. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The ſucceſs of this practice may well be <lb/>thought to preclude any reaſoning to ſhew
        its <lb/>propriety; yet Mr. <hi rend="italic">Holwell</hi> has added the rea- <lb/>ſons upon
        which the <hi rend="italic">Bramins</hi> found the ſeve- <lb/>ral particulars of their
        practice, as follows: </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>They forbid fiſh, becauſe they ſuppoſe it to <lb/>be a viſcid and inflammatory diet,
        tending to <lb/>produce a tough ſlimy phlegm in the firſt paſſa- <lb/>ges. Milk, becauſe by
        its quick aſſimilation <lb/>with the blood, it has a remote tendency to in- <lb/>flammation,
        when the blood is thrown into any <lb/>preternatural ferment; and butter, becauſe in
        <lb/>common with all oily fat ſubſtances, it fouls <lb/>the firſt paſſages more than any
        other aliment, <lb/>and in the courſe of digeſtion acquires an acri- <lb/>mony which it
        conveys into the blood. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>They uſe friction on the part where inocu- <lb/>lation is to be made, that the
        circulation in the <lb/>ſmaller blood-veſſels may be accelerated, <lb/>and they dilute the
        matter with water, that, <lb/>concurring with ſuch acceleration, it may be <lb/>more readily
        and eagerly received. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>They direct the inoculated to be ſluiced <lb/>with cold water, morning and evening,
        till the <lb/>fever comes on, which produces a much <lb/>greater effect than bathing by
        immerſion, in <lb/>all caſes that require the cold-bath, becauſe <lb/>they ſay the ſudden
        ſhock increaſing the mo- <pb n="556"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>tion of the blood, drives all offenſive princi- <lb/>ples from the heart, brain, and
        other interior <lb/>parts, to the ſurface, and ſpeedily and cer- <lb/>tainly promotes the
        fermentation. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When the fever appears, they deſiſt from <lb/>this uſe of cold water, becauſe they ſay
        that <lb/>when the fermentation is once begun, the <lb/>blood ſhould not receive any
        additional com- <lb/>motion till the eruption appears; then the aſ- <lb/>perſion is to be
        continued to the end of the <lb/>diſeaſe, that by the freſh impetus it gives to <lb/>the
        blood, it may enable it utterly to expel <lb/>the remainder of the immediate cauſe of the
        <lb/>diſeaſe into the puſtules. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Holwell</hi> ſays, he has himſelf been an <lb/>eye-witneſs, that
        when the puſtules have ſunk, <lb/>and the patient been in the moſt imminent dan- <lb/>ger,
        he has been inſtantly reſtored by the ex- <lb/>ternal application of about two gallons of
        cold <lb/>water, which has never failed to fill the pock, <lb/>as if by enchantment. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>They open the puſtules with a thorn while <lb/>the <choice>
          <corr>matter</corr>
          <sic>mater</sic>
        </choice> is in a fluid ſtate, even when the <lb/>puſtules are moſt diſtinct, from a notion
        that <lb/>it effectually prevents inflammation and weak- <lb/>neſs of the eyes, boils, and
        other eruptions <lb/>and diſorders: In this, ſays Mr. <hi rend="italic">Holwell</hi>,
        <lb/>they are countenanced by the opinion of <hi rend="italic">Tyſ- <lb/>ſot</hi>, and other
        able and ingenious writers. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>They utterly condemn bleedings and purging <lb/>in the ſmall-pox, which are frequently
        prac- <lb/>tiſed in <hi rend="italic">Europe</hi>, inſiſting that bleeding leſſens <lb/>the
        natural powers, and purging counteracts <lb/>the regular courſe of nature, which, in this
        <lb/>diſeaſe, invariably tends to throw out the of- <lb/>fending cauſe upon the ſkin. </p>
      <signed rend="align-right">
        <lb/>X. </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
