<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Medical Transactions, published by the College of
          Physicians</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Medical Transactions, published by the College of Physicians, in London,
              concluded from p. 479. Vol. LXII.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed at St. John's Gate, for D. Henry, and sold by F. Newbery,
                  the Corner of St. Paul's Church-Yard Ludgate-Street.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1773</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">43</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">32</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1773_GM_0032">
    <body>
      <pb n="32"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">2.</hi>
        <hi rend="sc">Medical Transactions</hi>, <lb/>publiſhed by the College of Phyſicians,
        <lb/>in <hi rend="roman">London</hi>, concluded from <hi rend="roman">p. 479. <lb/>Vol.
          LXII.</hi>
      </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">Art. XXV.</hi> (by miſtake called <hi rend="roman">XXIII.</hi>)
        <lb/>Queries, by Dr. <hi rend="roman">W. Heberden</hi>. </head>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Query</hi> I. <hi rend="dc(1.5)">I</hi>S the ſizey covering of the
        <lb/>blood of any uſe in direct- <lb/>ing the method of cure? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This query is followed by ſeveral <lb/>very judicious remarks, tending to <lb/>ſhew,
        that this covering is not of any <lb/>uſe in directing the cure; and they are <lb/>concluded
        by the following paragraph: <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">The more we know of the human <lb/>body, the more reaſon we find to be- <cb
            n="2"/>
          <lb/>lieve, that the ſeat of diſeaſes is not to <lb/>be ſought for in the blood, to the
          ſen- <lb/>ſible qualities of which they ſeem to <lb/>have little relation; and, though it
          be <lb/>ſuppoſed to hold in all maladies, yet, <lb/>in reality, it is in but very few that
          the <lb/>blood, and, I might add, the urine, <lb/>affords a practitioner much informa-
          <lb/>tion. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Q.</hi> II. Are the dangerous ſymptoms, <lb/>which attend what is
        called the incar- <lb/>cerated hernia, occaſioned by any pre- <lb/>ternatural and
        extraordinary ſtructure <lb/>of the tendinous opening in external <lb/>oblique muſcles? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This query, like the former, the <lb/>Doctor determines in the negative, with
        <lb/>apparently good reaſon. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Q.</hi> III. In England, few make any <lb/>doubt of the great damage
        attending <lb/>wet rooms, and damp cloaths or beds; <lb/>is this opinion founded upon
        experi- <lb/>ence, or is it a prejudice which has been <lb/>ſuffered to grow up and get
        ſtrength, <lb/>merely for want of being examined? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Dr. Heberden ſeems to be of opi- <lb/>nion, that the notion of damage re- <lb/>ceived
        from wet rooms, and damp <lb/>cloaths and beds, is a prejudice un- <lb/>ſupported by facts;
        and, in ſupport of <lb/>this opinion, makes ſeveral remarks, <lb/>to the following effect: </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The air is often as fully ſaturated <lb/>with moiſture, as it could be by va-
        <lb/>pours riſing from a chamber covered <lb/>with water. The air from rivers and <lb/>the
        ſea is alſo probably copiouſly re- <lb/>pleniſhed with vapours, yet theſe va- <lb/>pours are
        not known or pretended to <lb/>produce any ill effect: on the contra- <lb/>ry, the moſt
        celebrated of the ancient <lb/>phyſicians recommended the banks of <lb/>a running ſtream for
        the ſituation of a <lb/>houſe, as more healthy than any other; <lb/>and modern phyſicians
        ſend patients to <lb/>the ſea ſide, merely for the benefit of <lb/>the ſea-air. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Venice, where all the houſes, as it <lb/>were, ſtand in water, is not obſerved to
        <lb/>be leſs healthy than London. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Perſons who are much diſpoſed to <lb/>ſweat lie many hours every night, for
        <lb/>months, in bed-cloaths, which are im- <lb/>pregnated with a moiſture that is pro-
        <lb/>bably leſs wholeſome than that which <lb/>would have been left in ſheets half dri-
        <lb/>ed after waſhing, yet they receive no <lb/>injury, except the evacuation is too
        <lb/>copious. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Children, and perſons troubled with <lb/>the ſtone, conſtantly wet their beds <lb/>with
        urine, yet do not appear to ſuffer <lb/>in their health. </p>
      <pb n="33"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is common, in certain diſorders, <lb/>to go to bed with the legs or arms
        <lb/>wrapped in linen cloths, thoroughly <lb/>ſoaked in Malvern water, ſo that the
        <lb/>ſheets will, in many places, be as wet <lb/>as they can be, yet neither theſe pa-
        <lb/>tients, nor their bed-fellows, receive <lb/>any harm from a continuance of this
        <lb/>practice for many months; yet Mal- <lb/>vern water has no peculiarity but being
        <lb/>purer than any other known in Eng- <lb/>land. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The greateſt valetudinarians do not <lb/>ſcruple to ſprinkle lavender water upon
        <lb/>their ſheets, and yet, when the ſpirit is <lb/>flown off, there is left what is as
        truly <lb/>water, as if it had been taken from the <lb/>river. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Is it the coldneſs of wet linen which <lb/>is feared? how, then, are ſhirts and
        <lb/>ſheets, colder than any unfrozen wa- <lb/>ter, ſafely worn and lain in, by many
        <lb/>perſons, who, during a hard froſt, ne- <lb/>ver warm either? Does the danger lie
        <lb/>in the dampneſs? how happens it, <lb/>then, that a warm or cold bath, and <lb/>long
        continued fomentations, can be <lb/>uſed with impunity? Is it the cold and <lb/>dampneſs
        together? how happens it, <lb/>then, that the thick, cold, and long- <lb/>continued fogs, in
        the north-weſt of <lb/>England, produce no ill effects upon <lb/>thoſe who live in them? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The writer of this epitome does not <lb/>pretend to anſwer theſe queries; but <lb/>he
        takes the liberty to ſubjoin the fol- <lb/>lowing: </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Is there any ſuch diſorder as a cold? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If there is, and it is not produced <lb/>by cold or damp ſeparately, nor by cold
        <lb/>and damp together, how is it produ- <lb/>ced? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Are not fevers of various kinds the <lb/>effects of the diſorder called a cold? <lb/>Is
        not a cough one of the effects which <lb/>it ſeldom fails to produce? and, does <lb/>not a
        cough, in young perſons, very <lb/>frequently bring on inflammations of <lb/>the lungs, from
        irritation, with ulcera- <lb/>tion, and death, from a true phthiſis? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Have not thoſe, who, after wearing <lb/>damp linen, and ſleeping upon a damp <lb/>bed,
        have always been ſeized with a <lb/>ſore throat, a flux at the noſe, feveriſh <lb/>ſymptoms,
        or, at length, a tormenting <lb/>cough, which has laſted many weeks, <lb/>perhaps ſome
        months, as good reaſon <lb/>to ſuppoſe, that the damp linen produ- <lb/>ced the diſorder, as
        the phyſicians have, <lb/>when they ſee an intermitting fever <lb/>diſappear, after the
        patient has taken <lb/>the bark, to conclude that the bark <lb/>was the cauſe of the cure. </p>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Q.</hi> IV. It has been the practice of <lb/>phyſicians, to take away
        blood from <lb/>the arm, or foot, in order to ſtop vio- <lb/>lent <sic>hœmorrhages</sic>
        from ſome other <lb/>parts which do not admit of a topical <lb/>application: If it be
        intended, by this <lb/>practice, to weaken the power of the <lb/>heart, and to give the
        lips, or ends, of <lb/>the broken blood-veſſel a chance of <lb/><choice>
          <corr>collapſing</corr>
          <sic>collapfing</sic>
        </choice>, or of being plugged up, by <lb/>means of a more languid circulation, <lb/>would
        not all this be as likely to hap- <lb/>pen, after the patient had been equally
        <lb/>weakened, by loſing the ſame quantity <lb/>of blood from the original rupture;
        <lb/>and, in the mean time, might he not <lb/>ſtand a chance of its ſtopping ſpontane-
        <lb/>ouſly, before he was reduced to that <lb/>degree of weakneſs? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Theſe queries the Doctor anſwers in <lb/>the affirmative, with apparently good
        <lb/>reaſons; for which the reader is re- <lb/>ferred to the book. </p>
      <signed rend="align-right">X. </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
