<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Case, exemplifying the effects of fixed air</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Case, exemplifying the effects of fixed air, applied by way of clyster, in the
              cure of a putrid fever. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed at St. John's Gate, for D. Henry, and sold by F. Newbery,
                  the Corner of St. Paul's Church-Yard Ludgate-Street.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1773</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">43</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">553</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1773_GM_0553">
    <body>
      <pb n="553"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/>Caſe, exemplifying the effects of fixed <lb/>air, applied by way of clyſter, in
        <lb/>the cure of a putrid fever. </head>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">J</hi>AN. 8, 1772, Mr. Lightbowne, a <lb/>young gentleman, was ſeized
        with <lb/>a fever, which, after ten days, began <lb/>to be attended with thoſe ſymptoms
        <lb/>that indicate a putreſcent ſtate of the <lb/>fluids. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>18th. His tongue was black, but the <lb/>blackneſs went off upon drinking: <lb/>he now
        took little notice of thoſe that <lb/>were about him: his belly was looſe, <lb/>his pulſe
        beat 110 ſtrokes in a minute, <lb/>and was rather low: he was ordered, <lb/>by Mr. Hey, to
        take 25 grains of Pe- <lb/>ruvian bark, with five of tormentill <lb/>root in powder, every
        four hours, and <lb/>to uſe red wine and water cold as his <lb/>common drink. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>19th. Mr. Hey viſited him early, on <lb/>account of a bleeding at the noſe: <lb/>the
        hæmorrhage was ſuppreſſed by <lb/>tents made of ſoft lint, dipped in cold <lb/>water
        ſtrongly impregnated with tinc- <lb/>ture of iron, which were introduced <lb/>within the
        noſtrils, quite thro' to their <lb/>poſterior apertures; a method which has <lb/>never yet
        failed Mr. Hey in like <unclear>caſes</unclear>. <lb/>His tongue was now covered with a
        <lb/>thick black pellicle, his teeth were fur- <lb/>red with the ſame kind of ſordid mat-
        <lb/>ter, and even the roof of his mouth <lb/>and fauces were not free from it: <lb/>his
        looſeneſs and ſtupor continued, and <pb n="554"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>he was almoſt unceſſantly muttering to <lb/>himſelf: he took the Peruvian bark
        <lb/>with tormentill every two or three <lb/>hours: a ſtarch clyſter, containing a
        <lb/>drachm of the compound powder of <lb/>bole, without opium, was given <lb/>morning and
        evening: a window was <lb/>ſet open in the room, though it was a <lb/>ſevere froſt, and the
        floor was frequent- <lb/>ly ſprinkled with vinegar. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As he now nauſeated the bark in <lb/>ſubſtance, it was exchanged for Hux<choice>
          <corr>- </corr>
          <sic> </sic>
        </choice>
        <lb/>ham's tincture of which he took a <lb/>table ſpoonful every two-hours in a <lb/>cup
        full of cold water. His looſeneſs <lb/>rather increaſed, and the ſtools were <lb/>watery,
        black, and fœtid: it was judged <lb/>neceſſary to moderate this diſcharge, <lb/>by mixing a
        drachm of the <hi rend="italic">theriaca <lb/>Andromachi</hi> with each clyſter. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>21ſt. The ſame putrid ſymptoms re- <lb/>mained, and a <hi rend="italic">ſubſultus
          tendinum</hi> came <lb/>on: his ſtools were more fœtid; and <lb/>ſo hot, that the nurſe
        could not apply <lb/>her hand to the bed-pan, without feel- <lb/>ing pain on this account. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Conſidering, therefore, that, if this <lb/>putrid ferment could be more imme-
        <lb/>diately corrected, a ſtop would proba- <lb/>bly be put to the flux, and the <hi
          rend="italic">fomes</hi>
        <lb/>of the diſeaſe likewiſe removed, Mr. <lb/>Hey thought nothing was ſo likely to
        <lb/>effect this, as the introduction of fixed <lb/>air into the alimentary canal, which,
        <lb/>from the experiments of Dr. Macbride, <lb/>and Dr. Prieſtley, appears to be the
        <lb/>moſt powerful corrector of putrefac- <lb/>tion hitherto known <note n="*"
          place="bottom" rend="size(0.8)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Since this was written, Dr. Prieſtley <lb/>has diſcovered the aſtoniſhing
            antiſeptic <lb/>properties of Nitrous air, which Dr. Hey <lb/>thinks may likewiſe be
            applied with ad- <lb/>vantage medicinally. </p>
        </note>, and, therefore, <lb/>tried the injection of this kind of air <lb/>by way of
        clyſter. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The next morning Dr. Hird and <lb/>Dr. Crowther, attended the operation, <lb/>and
        propoſed the following method of <lb/>treatment: they firſt gave him five <lb/>grains of
        ipecacoanha, to evacuate in <lb/>the moſt eaſy manner part of the pu- <lb/>trid <hi
          rend="italic">colluvies</hi>: he was then allowed to <lb/>drink freely of briſk orange
        wine, <lb/>which contained a good deal of fixed <lb/>air, yet had not loſt its ſweetneſs:
        the <lb/>tincture of bark was continued as be- <lb/>fore; and the water, which he drank
        <lb/>along with it, was impregnated with <lb/>fixed air from the atmoſphere of a <lb/>large
        vat of fermenting wort: inſtead <lb/>of the aſtringent, air alone was injected,
        <lb/>collected from a fermenting mixture of <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>chalk and oil of vitriol: he drank a <lb/>bottle of orange-wine in the courſe of
        <lb/>this day, but refuſed any other liquor <lb/>except water and his medicine: two
        <lb/>bladders full of air were thrown up <lb/>in the afternoon. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>23d. His ſtools were leſs frequent; <lb/>their heat, likewiſe, and peculiar <hi
          rend="italic">fœtor</hi>
        <lb/>were conſiderably diminiſhed; his mut- <lb/>tering was much abated, and the <hi
          rend="italic">ſub- <lb/>ſultus tendinum</hi> had left him. Find- <lb/>ing that part of the
        air was rejected <lb/>when given with a bladder in the uſual <lb/>way, Mr. Hey took the
        flexible <lb/>tube of that inſtrument which is uſed <lb/>for throwing up the fume of
        tobacco, <lb/>and tied a ſmall bladder to the end of <lb/>it that is connected with the box
        made <lb/>for receiving the tobacco, which he <lb/>had previouſly taken off from the
        <lb/>tube: he then put ſome bits of chalk <lb/>into a ſix ounce phial, until it was
        <lb/>half filled; upon theſe he poured ſuch <lb/>a quantity of oil of vitriol as he
        <lb/>thought capable of ſaturating the <lb/>chalk, and immediately tied the blad- <lb/>der,
        which he had fixed to the tube, <lb/>round the neck of the phial: the cly- <lb/>ſter pipe,
        which was faſtened to the <lb/>other end of the tube, was introduced <lb/>into the <hi
          rend="italic">anus</hi> before the oil of vitriol <lb/>was poured upon the chalk. By this
        <lb/>method the air paſſed gradually into <lb/>the inteſtines as it was generated; the
        <lb/>rejection of it was in a great meaſure <lb/>prevented; and the inconvenience of
        <lb/>keeping the patient uncovered during <lb/>the operation was avoided. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>24th. He was ſo much better, that <lb/>there ſeemed to be no neceſſity for re-
        <lb/>peating the clyſters; the other means <lb/>were continued. The window of his <lb/>room
        was now kept ſhut. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>25th. All the ſymptoms of putreſ- <lb/>cency had left him. He took nouriſh- <lb/>ment
        to day, with pleaſure; and, in <lb/>the afternoon, ſat up an hour in his <lb/>chair. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>His fever, however, did not imme- <lb/>diately leave him; but this we attribut- <lb/>ed
        to his having taken cold from be- <lb/>ing incautiouſly uncovered when the <lb/>window was
        open, and the weather ex- <lb/>tremely ſevere; for a cough, which had <lb/>troubled him in
        ſome degree from the <lb/>beginning, increaſed, and he became <lb/>likewiſe very hoarſe for
        ſeveral days, <lb/>his pulſe, at the ſame time, growing <lb/>quicker: but theſe complaints
        alſo <lb/>went off, and he recovered, without <lb/>any return of the bad ſymptoms above-
        <lb/>mentioned. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
