<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Proposals for Establishing more Accurate and Comprehensive
          Bills of Mortality</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Proposals for Establishing more Accurate and Comprehensive Bills of Mortality.
              From the Second Volume of Essays Medical and Experimental , lately published by Tho-
              mas Percival. M. D. F. R. S. and S. A.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed at St. John's Gate, for D. Henry, and sold by F. Newbery,
                  the Corner of St. Paul's Church-Yard Ludgate-Street.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1773</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">43</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">117</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1773_GM_0117">
    <body>
      <pb n="117"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Proposals</hi> for Eſtabliſhing more Ac- <lb/>curate and Comprehenſive
          <hi rend="sc">Bills</hi> of <lb/><hi rend="sc">Mortality</hi>. From the Second <lb/>Volume
        of <hi rend="roman">Eſſays Medical and Ex- <lb/>perimental</hi>, lately publiſhed by <hi
          rend="roman">Tho- <lb/>mas Percival. M. D. F. R. S. and <lb/>S. A.</hi>
      </head>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(1.5)">T</hi>HE eſtabliſhment of a judicious <lb/>and accurate regiſter of
        the births <lb/>and burials, in every town and pariſh, <lb/>would be attended with the moſt
        impor- <lb/>tant advantages, medical, political, and <lb/>moral. By ſuch an inſtitution, the
        in- <lb/>creaſe or decreaſe of certain diſeaſes; <lb/>the comparative healthineſs of
        different <lb/>ſituations, climates, and ſeaſons; the <lb/>influence of particular trades
        and ma- <pb n="118"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>nufactures on longevity; with many o- <lb/>ther curious circumſtances, not more
        <lb/>intereſting to Phyſicians, than beneficial <lb/>to mankind; would be aſcertained with
        <lb/>tolerable preciſion. In a political view, <lb/>exact regiſters of human mortality are
        <lb/>of ſtill greater conſequence, as the <lb/>number of people, and the progreſs of
        <lb/>population in the kingdom, may in the <lb/>moſt eaſy and unexceptionable manner <lb/>be
        deduced from them. They are the <lb/>foundation, likewiſe, of all calculations
        <lb/>concerning the values of aſſurances on <lb/>lives, reverſionary payments, and of
        <lb/>every ſcheme for providing annuities <lb/>for widows, and perſons in old age. <lb/>In a
        moral light, alſo, ſuch <hi rend="italic">tables</hi> are of <lb/>evident utility, as the
        increaſe of vice <lb/>or virtue may be determined, by ob- <lb/>ſerving the proportion which
        the diſ- <lb/>eaſes ariſing from luxury, intempe- <lb/>rance, and other ſimilar cauſes, bear
        to <lb/>the reſt; and in what particular places <lb/>diſtempers of this claſs are found to
        be <lb/>moſt fatal. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A few examples may, perhaps, con- <lb/>firm and illuſtrate theſe obſervations. <lb/>In
        the Pais de Vaud, a diſtrict of the <lb/>province of Bern, in Switzerland, and <lb/>in a
        country pariſh in Brandenburg, <lb/>1 in 45 of the inhabitants die annually; <lb/>and at
        Stoke Damarell, in Devonſhire, <lb/>1 in 54; whereas in Vienna, and <lb/>Edinburgh, the
        yearly mortality ap- <lb/>pears to be 1 in 20; in London 1 in <lb/>21; in Amſterdam and Rome
        1 in 22; <lb/>in Northampton 1 in 26; and in the <lb/>pariſh of Holy Croſs, near Shrewſbu-
        <lb/>ry, 1 in 33. In the Pais de Vaud, the <lb/>proportion of inhabitants who attain
        <lb/>the age of eighty, is 1 in 21½; in <lb/>Brandenburgh 1 in 22<unclear>½</unclear>; in
        Norwich <lb/>1 in 27; in Mancheſter 1 in 30; in <lb/>London 1 in 40; and in Edinburgh 1
        <lb/>in 42. Theſe facts afford a ſtriking, <lb/>but melancholy proof, of the unfavour-
        <lb/>able influence of large towns on the <lb/>duration of life.—From the moſt ac-
        <lb/>curate computation, London is found <lb/>to contain 601,750 inhabitants; and <lb/>from
        1759 to 1768, the burials have <lb/>exceeded the chriſtenings every year up- <lb/>wards of
        7000; which is the recruit <lb/>the metropolis requires annually from <lb/>the country, to
        ſupport the preſent <lb/>number of its people. In 1757, a ſur- <lb/>vey was made of
        Mancheſter and Sal- <lb/>ford. The number ot inhabitants then <lb/>amounted to 19,839; and
        the burials, <lb/>excluſive of thoſe amongſt Diſſenters, <lb/>were 778. But ſince that time
        the <lb/>populouſneſs of Mancheſter has con- <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>ſiderably increaſed. Half of all that <lb/>are born in this town die under five
        <lb/>years old. The iſland of Madeira is <lb/>ſo remarkably healthy, that two thirds <lb/>of
        all who are born in it live to be mar- <lb/>ried. Autumn is the moſt healthy, <lb/>and
        ſummer the moſt ſickly ſeaſon <lb/>there. The mortality of ſpring and <lb/>ſummer, is to
        that of autumn and win- <lb/>ter, as 115 to 100. In Mancheſter, <lb/>diſeaſes are moſt
        frequent and fatal in <lb/>the months of January, February, and <lb/>March; and leaſt ſo in
        July, Auguſt, <lb/>and September. The mortality of <lb/>theſe two ſeaſons is as 11 to 8; and
        of <lb/>the firſt fix months of the year, com- <lb/>pared with the laſt ſix months, as 7 to
        <lb/>6. Mr. Muret, Secretary to the Oeco- <lb/>nomical Society of Bern, informs us,
        <lb/>that he had the curioſity to examine the <lb/>regiſter of mortality in one town, and
        <lb/>to mark thoſe whoſe deaths might be <lb/>imputed to intemperance. And he found <lb/>the
        number ſo great, as to incline him <lb/>to believe that drunkenneſs is more de-
        <lb/>ſtructive to mankind than pleuriſies, <lb/>fevers, or the moſt malignant diſtem-
        <lb/>pers <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.8)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Vid. a very valuable Treatiſe on Re- <lb/>verſionary Payments, by the Rev. Dr.
            <lb/>Price; the Bern Obſervations for the year <lb/>1766; Philoſophical Tranſactions,
            vol. <lb/>57 and 59; and Dr. Short's new Obſerva- <lb/>tions. </p>
        </note>. Such are the important uſes to <lb/>which Tables of Human Mortality <lb/>have been
        applied. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The following plan of a more exact <lb/>and comprehenſive regiſter, than has
        <lb/>hitherto been kept, is ſubmitted to the <lb/>conſideration and correction of thoſe
        <lb/>who undertake the charge of the Bills <lb/>of Mortality in Mancheſter. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>1. Let a table of <hi rend="italic">chriſtenings</hi>, <hi rend="italic">mar-
          <lb/>riages</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">burials</hi>, be kept in every <lb/>church,
        chapel, and place of religious <lb/>worſhip in the town, and delivered at <lb/>certain
        ſtated times, to the clerk of the <lb/>pariſh-church, to be formed into one <lb/>general
        bill, and quarterly or annually <lb/>publiſhed. It is of importance that <lb/>the <hi
          rend="italic">ſtill-born</hi> children, and thoſe who <lb/>die before <hi rend="italic"
          >baptiſm</hi>, ſhould alſo be re- <lb/>giſtered; and the midwives ſhould be <lb/>deſired
        to deliver an account of <lb/>them. Perhaps, the ſextons may aſſiſt <lb/>in aſcertaining
        their number, as they <lb/>are uſually interred in church-yards, or <lb/>other public
        burial-grounds. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>2. Let the table of <hi rend="italic">chriſtenings</hi> ſpe- <lb/>cify the <hi
          rend="italic">males</hi> and <hi rend="italic">females</hi> who are <lb/>baptized; and the
        table of <hi rend="italic">deaths</hi> ex- <pb n="119"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>preſs the <hi rend="italic">males</hi> who die, under the <lb/>ſeveral denominations of
        children, <lb/>batchelors, married-men, and widow- <lb/>ers; the <hi rend="italic"
          >females</hi> who die under the <lb/>correſponding denominations of chil- <lb/>dren,
        maidens, married women, and <lb/>widows. An obſervance of theſe <lb/>diſtinctions will
        determine the compa- <lb/>rative number of <hi rend="italic">males</hi> and <hi
          rend="italic">females</hi>
        <lb/>who are born; the difference between <lb/>the ſexes in the expectation of life;
        <lb/>and the proportion which the annual <lb/>births, deaths, and marriages, bear to
        <lb/>each other. Thus by the Bills of <lb/>Mortality which have been kept at <lb/>Vienna,
        Breſlaw, Dreſden, Leipſic, <lb/>Ratiſbon, and other towns in Germany, <lb/>it appears that
        the proportion of <hi rend="italic">males</hi>
        <lb/>to the <hi rend="italic">females</hi> who are born is as 19 to <lb/>18: but the
        proportion of <hi rend="italic">boys</hi> to <lb/><hi rend="italic">girls</hi> who die under
        ten years of age, <lb/>is as 7 to 6; and of <hi rend="italic">married men</hi> to <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">married women</hi> in Breſlaw as 5 to 3; <lb/>in Dreſden as 4 to 1. At
        Vevey, in <lb/>Switzerland, for 20 years, ending in <lb/>1764, there died in the firſt month
        135 <lb/><hi rend="italic">males</hi> to 89 <hi rend="italic">females</hi>; and in the firſt
        <lb/>year 225, to 162. The ſame accounts <lb/>ſhew likewiſe that, both at Vevey and
        <lb/>Berlin, the <hi rend="italic">ſtill-born males</hi> are to the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >ſtill-born females</hi> as 30 to 21. In the <lb/>pariſh of Holy Croſs, Salop, an ac-
        <lb/>count was taken by the Vicar, A. D. <lb/>1760, of the number of <hi rend="italic"
          >males</hi> and <lb/><hi rend="italic">females</hi> of the age of ſeventy and up-
        <lb/>wards: The latter amounted to <hi rend="italic">thirty- <lb/>five</hi>, the former only
        to <hi rend="italic">eight</hi>. At <lb/>Paris, and in Sweden, it has been ob- <lb/>ſerved,
        that <hi rend="italic">women</hi> not only live <lb/>longer than <hi rend="italic">men</hi>,
        but that <hi rend="italic">married <lb/>women</hi> live longer than <hi rend="italic">ſingle
          women</hi>: <lb/>and in Switzerland it appears particu- <lb/>larly, from the calculations
        of M. <lb/>Muret, that of equal numbers of <hi rend="italic">ſingle</hi>
        <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">married women</hi>, between the age <lb/>of 15 and 25, more of
        the former died <lb/>than of the latter, in the proportion of <lb/>2 to 1 <note
          place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.8)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>† Vid. Dr. Price's Obſervations on Re- <lb/>verſionary Payments. </p>
        </note>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>3. Let the ages of the dead under <lb/><hi rend="italic">five</hi>, be ſpecified by
        ſingle years; and <lb/>afterwards, by periods of five or ten <lb/>years. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>4. Let the Bills of Mortality con- <lb/>tain not only a liſt of the diſeaſes of
        <lb/>which all die, but alſo expreſs particu- <lb/>larly the number dying of each diſeaſe,
        <lb/>in the ſeveral diviſions of life and diffe- <lb/>rent ſeaſons of the year. To accom-
        <lb/>pliſh this, it will be neceſſary for the <lb/>Phyſicians of the town, to conſider the
          <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>preſent liſt of diſtempers; to reject all <lb/>ſynonymous and obſolete terms; and
        <lb/>to give a ſhort and eaſy explanation of <lb/>thoſe which are retained: and when-
        <lb/>ever a perſon dies, who has been at- <lb/>tended by any of the Faculty, the Phy-
        <lb/>ſician, Surgeon, or Apothecary, ſhould <lb/>be deſired to certify in writing the age
        <lb/>and diſtemper of the deceaſed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The following <hi rend="sc">Tables</hi> are con- <lb/>ſtructed upon this <hi rend="sc"
          >plan</hi>; and if the <lb/>ſcale be enlarged, will ſerve for the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Church Regiſter</hi>, as well as for quarter- <lb/>ly or annual publication. It appears
        <lb/>to be unneceſſary, and in many inſtan- <lb/>ces would be exceptionable, to inſert
        <lb/>the names of the deceaſed: Their <lb/><hi rend="italic">denomination</hi> and <hi
          rend="italic">diſeaſe</hi>, the refore, may <lb/>be expreſſed, in the columns allotted
        <lb/>to each, by dots or units, which are to <lb/>be ſummed up at the end of every three
        <lb/>months, and ſet down in figures. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">list</hi> of <hi rend="italic">marriages</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
          >chriſten- <lb/>ings</hi> may be kept in the common me- <lb/>thod. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The additional trouble which this <lb/>more comprehenſive and accurate <hi rend="sc"
          >re- <lb/>gister</hi> will occaſion to the clerks of <lb/>the ſeveral churches, &amp;c.
        may be com- <lb/>penſated by diſtributing amongſt them, <lb/>at the diſcretion of any
        judicious clergy- <lb/>man, the money which ariſes from the <lb/>ſale of the quarterly
        Bills. If a hun- <lb/>dred of theſe be ſubſcribed for, or ſold <lb/>at the price of one
        ſhilling each, the <lb/>ſum of twenty pounds per annum will <lb/>thus be raiſed, without
        impoſing any <lb/>new burthens on the town. Every <lb/>ſecond, third, fourth, or fifth year,
        the <lb/>bills may be collected into a volume, <lb/>and publiſhed, under the direction of
        <lb/>two or more Phyſicians, with obſerva- <lb/>tions on the ſtate of the weather, the
        <lb/>prevalence of epidemic diſeaſes, their <lb/>ſymptoms and method of cure, and the
        <lb/>increaſe or decreaſe of population du- <lb/>ring that period. Such a work will
        <lb/>afford the moſt important inſtruction to <lb/>the public; and from the profits of it,
        <lb/>a fund may be eſtabliſhed for the bene- <lb/>fit of the clerks, and the ſupport of the
        <lb/>inſtitution. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>N. B. It is obvious that the plan <lb/>here propoſed is not local, and that it <lb/>may
        be executed with equal facility and <lb/>advantage every town and pariſh in the
        <lb/>kingdom.—Bills of Mortality might be <lb/>rendered more uſeful in a political view,
        <lb/>by taking ſometimes the number of <lb/>houſes and inhabitants, under and <lb/>above
        particular ages, wherever ſuch <lb/>regiſters are eſtabliſhed. </p>
      <pb n="120"/>
      <table rend="boxed" rows="10" cols="10">
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>I. <lb/>TABLE <hi rend="sc">of</hi> DEATHS. <lb/>January, February, March. </head>
        <row role="label" rend="size(0.7)">
          <cell>Ages. </cell>
          <cell>Males. </cell>
          <cell>Females. </cell>
          <cell>Ages. </cell>
          <cell rend="hanging">Batche- <lb/>lors. </cell>
          <cell rend="hanging">Married <lb/>Men. </cell>
          <cell rend="hanging">Widow- <lb/>ers. </cell>
          <cell rend="hanging">Maid- <lb/>ens. </cell>
          <cell>Married <lb/>Women </cell>
          <cell>Widows. </cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell rend="size(0.7)">1 </cell>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell rend="size(0.7)">20 </cell>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell rend="size(0.7)">2 </cell>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell rend="size(0.7)">25 </cell>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell rend="size(0.7)">3 </cell>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell rend="size(0.7)">30 </cell>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell rend="size(0.7)">4 </cell>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell rend="size(0.7)">35 </cell>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell rend="size(0.7)">5 </cell>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell rend="size(0.7)">40 </cell>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell rend="size(0.7)">10 </cell>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell rend="size(0.7)">45 </cell>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell rend="size(0.7)">15 </cell>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell rend="size(0.7)">50 </cell>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell rend="size(0.7) align-center">Total <lb/>under 15 </cell>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell rend="size(0.7)">60 </cell>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell rend="size(0.7)">&amp;c. </cell>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
        </row>
      </table>
      <table rend="boxed" rows="10" cols="16">
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>II. <lb/>TABLE <hi rend="sc">of</hi> DISEASES. <lb/>January, February, March. </head>
        <row role="label" rend="size(0.7) align-center">
          <cell>Diſeaſes. </cell>
          <cell>1 </cell>
          <cell>2 </cell>
          <cell>3 </cell>
          <cell>4 </cell>
          <cell>5 </cell>
          <cell>10 </cell>
          <cell>20 </cell>
          <cell>30 </cell>
          <cell>40 </cell>
          <cell>50 </cell>
          <cell>60 </cell>
          <cell>70 </cell>
          <cell>80 </cell>
          <cell>90 </cell>
          <cell>100 </cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell rend="size(0.7)">Caſualties </cell>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell rend="size(0.7)">Apoplexy </cell>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell rend="size(0.7)">Aſthma </cell>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell rend="size(0.7)">Cancer </cell>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell rend="size(0.7)">Chincough </cell>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell rend="size(0.7)">Cholic </cell>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell rend="size(0.7) hanging">Conſump- <lb/>tion </cell>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell rend="size(0.7) hanging">Convul- <lb/>ſions </cell>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell rend="size(0.7)">&amp;c, &amp;c. </cell>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
        </row>
      </table>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
