<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Experiments upon Vegetables, discovering their great Power of purifying the
          common Air </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Experiments upon Vegetables, discovering their great Power of purifying the
              common Air in the Sun-Shine, and of injuring it in the Shade and at Night. To which is
              joined, A new Method of examining the accurate Degree of Salubrity of the Atmosphere.
              By John Ingen- housz , Counsellor of the Court, and Body-Physician to their Imperial
              and Royal Majestities, F. R. S. &amp;c. &amp;c. 8vo. Elmsly. 6s. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed at St. John's Gate, for D. Henry; and sold by F. Newbery,
                  the Corner of St. Paul's Church-Yard, Ludgate-Street.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1780</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">50</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">481</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1780_GM_0481">
    <body>
      <pb n="481"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">72.</hi> Experiments upon Vegetables, diſco- <lb/>vering their great
        Power of purifying the <lb/>common Air in the Sun-Shine, and of in- <lb/>juring it in the
        Shade and at Night. To <lb/>which is joined, A new Method of exa- <lb/>mining the accurate
        Degree of Salubrity <lb/>of the Atmoſphere. By <hi rend="roman">John Ingen- <lb/>houſz</hi>,
        Counſellor of the Court, and Body- <lb/>Phyſician to their Imperial and Royal Ma-
        <lb/>jeſtities, F. R. S. &amp;c. &amp;c. 8vo. <hi rend="roman">Elmſly</hi>. <hi rend="roman"
          >6s</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>THIS learned Hollander, he tells <lb/>us, in his dedication, was recommended <lb/>by
        Sir John Pringle to inoculate ſuch <lb/>of the Imperial Family of Auſtria as <lb/>had
        eſcaped the ſmall-pox, ſo deſtruc- <lb/>tive to many of them. The time which <lb/>his <q
          rend="quotes">auguſt Sovereign </q> allowed him <lb/>to ſpend laſt ſummer in this iſland,
        he <lb/>has employed, theſe pages will evince, <lb/>to very uſeful and ſalutary purpoſes.
        <lb/>Dr. Prieſtley's new diviſion of air into <lb/>nitrous, inflammable, phlogiſticated,
        <lb/>dephlogiſticated, and fixed, is the ori- <lb/>gin of theſe experiments, which are a
        <lb/>part of the reſult of above 500, all made <lb/>in leſs than three months. By theſe
        <lb/>(among other things) it appears that <lb/>the leaves of trees or plants which ab-
        <lb/>ſorb moiſture from the air, from rain, <lb/>and from dew, and expoſe their upper
        <lb/>and varniſhed ſurface to the ſun, yield <lb/>dephlogiſticated <note n="*"
          place="bottom" rend="size(0.8)">
          <cb n="1 2" type="footnote"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* <q rend="quotes">That pure, etherial, permanent, and elaſtic <unclear><choice>
                  <corr>fluid</corr>
                  <sic>flaid</sic>
                </choice></unclear>, which was firſt diſcovered and <lb/>ſo named by Dr. Prieſtley.
              It is reſpirable air deſtitute of its phlogiſtic or inflamma- <lb/>ble principle, or
              really common air of the higheſt purity, ſuch as never exiſts in the <lb/>common
              atmoſphere. </q>
          </p>
        </note> air by day, owing to <lb/>the warmth of the ſun, but chiefly, <lb/>if not only, to
        the light, and poiſonous <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>air in the night, and in the ſhade: this <lb/>miſchievous effect is checked by cold
        <lb/>weather: they alſo yield poiſonous air <lb/>by the warmth of a fire. Dead leaves
        <lb/>yield no dephlogiſticated air; and <lb/>beans, peaches, or any fruits, kept in
        <lb/>cloſe rooms, are ſo extremely noxious, <lb/>that they would eaſily poiſon an un-
        <lb/>wary perſon ſleeping. Flowers too <lb/>are very dangerous, as they ooze out <lb/>both
        by day and night an unwholeſome <lb/>air, and contaminate common air <lb/>equally in every
        ſituation. <q rend="quotes">But the <lb/>miſchief which trees do by night to <lb/>the
          ſurrounding air cannot do any ob- <lb/>ſervable harm to animals; for thoſe
          <lb/>miſchievous exhalations being, very <lb/>providentially, ſpecifically lighter than
          <lb/>the common air, riſe at the ſame time <lb/>up: and thus the lower region, in
          <lb/>which we breathe, is freed from them <lb/>almoſt as ſoon as they are produced;
          <lb/>whereas the dephlogiſticated air iſſuing <lb/>out of the plants in great abundance
          <lb/>in the day-time is ſpecifically heavier <lb/>than common air, and is therefore in-
          <lb/>clined to remain longer among us, and <lb/>to afford us all the benefit for which
          <lb/>the Supreme Wiſdom has originally <lb/>deſtined it. </q> Roots left out of the
        <lb/>ground have the ſame deleterious <lb/>power. A law of nature hitherto un- <lb/>known,
        or involved in darkneſs, Dr. <lb/>Ingen<choice>
          <corr>-</corr>
          <sic> </sic>
        </choice>houſz has thus diſcovered and <lb/>brought to light; and he has alſo put <lb/>it
        beyond a doubt, that <q rend="quotes">vegetables <lb/>have a remarkable ſhare in keeping the
          <lb/>ſalubrity of our atmoſphere, by im- <lb/>bibing thoſe ſeptic, noxious, and phlo-
          <lb/>giſtic particles which were communi- <lb/>cated to it by the breathing of ani-
          <lb/>mals, &amp;c. as well as by pouring down <lb/>a moſt beneficial ſhower of purified or
          <lb/>dephlogiſticated air. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>For inaccuracies of language the au- <lb/>thor, though a foreigner, has no occa-
        <lb/>ſion to apologiſe, as we have ſcarce diſ- <lb/>covered any but 'ſhook' for 'ſhaken,'
        <lb/>and 'without' for 'unleſs;' ſoleciſms <lb/>too common to our natives. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
