<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Curious and authentic Instance of Longevity</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Curious and authentic Instance of Longevity</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed at St. John's Gate, for D. Henry; and sold by F. Newbery,
                  the Corner of St. Paul's Church-Yard, Ludgate-Street.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1780</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">50</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">280</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1780_GM_0280">
    <body>
      <pb n="280"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <div>
        <salute rend="indent">
          <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="sc">Urban</hi>, </salute>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(1.5)">T</hi>HE following authentic inſtance of <lb/>longevity ſhews the
          happy effects <lb/>of a temperate, well-ordered, and vir- <lb/>tuous life. I do not
          remember ſeeing <lb/>it any-where quoted, and it ſeems to <lb/>have eſcaped notice, though
          recorded <lb/><unclear>by ſo eminent a man as Bartholin</unclear>
          <pb n="281"/>
          <cb n="1"/>
          <lb/>concerning his own grandfather by <lb/>the mother's ſide <note place="bottom" n="*">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Vide Tho. Bartholini Hiſtoriarum <lb/>Anatom. Cent. quint. </p>
          </note>. That one, who was <lb/>a bookiſh man and an author, whoſe <lb/>conſtitution was
          naturally very weak <lb/>and delicate, and who had been poſi- <lb/>tively doomed to an
          early death by his <lb/>phyſician, ſhould elude the prognoſtic <lb/>for no leſs a term
          than ninety-five <lb/>years, is an encouraging circumſtance <lb/>to literary men and
          valetudinarians. <lb/>For their benefit I ſend it. </p>
        <signed rend="sc align-right">
          <lb/>J. Boerhadem. </signed>
      </div>
      <div>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>
          <q rend="paradiple">Quantum huc [ſcil. ad longævi- <lb/>tatem] conferat animus ſemper ſibi
            <lb/>ſimilis, nulliſque paſſionibus in tranſ- <lb/>vorſum raptus, effari nequeo. </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>
          <q rend="quotes">Avus meus maternus D. Thomas <lb/>Finckius (priori ſeculo libris, geome-
            <lb/>tria rotundi, horoſcopia, &amp;c. hoc ſe- <lb/>culo liberis clarus; numeravit enim
            <lb/>liberos, nepotes, pronepotes, abnepo- <lb/>tes 97.) annum ingreſtus erat nona-
            <lb/>geſimum-ſextum hâc animi conſtantiâ, <lb/>&amp; diutius vitam in ſenio vegetam pro-
            <lb/>traxiſſet, niſi febris filum abrupiſſet. <lb/>Per totum vitæ curſum a ſe pompam
            <lb/>removit, &amp; uſu rerum ornamenta me- <lb/>tiebatur. Teneram ætatem ægritu-
            <lb/>dinibus habuit obnoxiam, ut Medicus <lb/>curae illius præfectus ſpoponderit pa-
            <lb/>rentibus, omnes itinerum vias quas <lb/>emenſurus eſſet, auro ſe obducturum.
            <lb/>Cæterum a longâ peregrinatione re- <lb/>dux, prognoſticum eluſit temperantiâ
            <lb/>&amp; morum facilitate. Coercuit luxu- <lb/>riam, gulam temperavit, cui tamen
            <lb/>neceſſaria ſuggeſſit etiam durioris ſub- <lb/>ſtantiæ, quæ libentius avidiuſque ap-
            <lb/>petebat, quam cupedias; divitias <lb/>æquis oculis aſpexit, frugalitatem co-
            <lb/>luit, &amp; animum metu vel gaudio af- <lb/>fectum ſub vinculis habuit, iracun-
            <lb/>diam lenivit, adverſitates ſprevit, &amp; <lb/>quanquam liberorum, generum, ne-
            <lb/>potum, abnepotum, affinium, ami- <lb/>corumque ſæpius funera audiverit, &amp;
            <lb/>inter tot vitæ grandævæ moleſtias ver- <lb/>ſaretur, conſtanti tamen animo omnia
            <lb/>perpeſſus nunquam lachrymas fudit <lb/>niſi defunctæ uxoris &amp; bibliothecæ
            <lb/>vulcano conſumptæ memoriâ re- <lb/>currente. </q>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>For the benefit of the <hi rend="roman">Engliſh</hi> reader, <lb/>the above account
          is thus tranſlated: </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>
          <q rend="quotes">It is inexpreſſible how much equa- <lb/>bility of temper unruffled by
            paſſion <lb/>contributes to long life. My maternal <lb/>grandfather, Thomas Fink, (who
            in <lb/>the preceding century was as diſtin- <lb/>guiſhed by his learning, his ſkill in
            <lb/>geometry, the horoſcope, &amp;c. as in the <cb n="2"/>
            <lb/>preſent by the number of his de- <lb/>ſcendents, for he had children, grand-
            <lb/>children, great grand-children, and <lb/>great great grand-children, to the num-
            <lb/>ber of 97,) had by this uniformity <lb/>of temper attained to his 96th year,
            <lb/>and might have reached to a vigorous <lb/>old age, had not a fever ſhortened his
            <lb/>days. He ſtudiouſly through life <lb/>avoided ſhow, meaſuring ornament by <lb/>uſe.
            His tender age was ſubject to <lb/>illneſs, ſo that the phyſician who had <lb/>the care
            of his health promiſed his <lb/>parents that he would engage to cover <lb/>every road he
            travelled with gold: <lb/>he returned, however, from a long <lb/>journey, having by
            temperance <lb/>and eaſineſs of temper eluded the prog- <lb/>noſtication. He checked all
            tendency <lb/>to luxury, and reſtrained his appetite, <lb/>frequently eating coarſer
            food, and <lb/>that too with greater eagerneſs than <lb/>dainties. He looked on wealth
            with- <lb/>out coveting it; for he ſtudied fru- <lb/>gality, and kept under due controul
            <lb/>every motion of joy or fear; maſter of <lb/>his anger, ſuperior to diſappointment;
            <lb/>and, though he loſt by death many <lb/>of his children, grand-children, great
            <lb/>grand-children, relations and friends, <lb/>and in ſo long a life muſt be preſumed
            <lb/>to have met with many troubles, he bore <lb/>them all with great conſtancy, and ne-
            <lb/>ver was known to ſhed a tear, except <lb/>when he recollected the death of his
            wife, <lb/>and the loſs of his library by fire. </q>
        </p>
      </div>
      <postscript>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>
          <label>⁂ </label> In our account of Mr. Thick- <lb/>neſſe's <hi rend="italic"
            >Valetudinarian's Bath Guide</hi>, <lb/>p. 136, we omitted to obſerve, that his
          <lb/>method of prolonging health and life by <lb/>the breath of young women is no new
          <lb/>diſcovery, but ſeems borrowed from <lb/>the practice of the Jewiſh phyſicians in
          <lb/>the laſt illneſs of King David, and has <lb/>been of late years detailed with much
          <lb/>ſerious humour by Dr. Campbell, in <lb/>his <hi rend="italic">Hermippus
            Redivivus</hi>: 1746, 8vo. <lb/>enlarged 1749, 8vo. tranſlated into Ita- <lb/>lian, and
          printed at Leghorn, 1756, 4to. </p>
      </postscript>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
