<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Valetudinarian's Bath Guide</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Valetudinarian's Bath Guide: or, the Means of obtaining long life and health.
              Dedicated to the Earl of Shelburne. By Philip Thicknesse, Esq. Dodsley. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed at St. John's Gate, for D. Henry; and sold by F. Newbery,
                  the Corner of St. Paul's Church-Yard, Ludgate-Street.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1780</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">50</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">136</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1780_GM_0136">
    <body>
      <pb n="136"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">16</hi> Valetudinarian's Bath Guide: or, the <lb/>Means of obtaining
        long life and health. <lb/>Dedicated to the Earl of <hi rend="roman">Shelburne</hi>. By
          <lb/><hi rend="roman">Philip Thickneſſe</hi>, Eſq. <hi rend="roman">Dodſley</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>THE facetious writer of this treatiſe <lb/>has brought together in a ſmall com-
        <lb/>paſs a great variety of miſcellaneous <lb/>matter for the entertainment of his
        <lb/>readers. He has embelliſhed his per- <lb/>formance with a frontiſpiece, which he
        <lb/>calls <hi rend="italic">The Genius of Nature in Contemp- <lb/>lation of the
          Univerſe</hi>; and has dedi- <lb/>cated it to Lord Shelburne, with a wiſh, <lb/>that <q
          rend="quotes">the King, for his own honour, <lb/>and the ſafety amd proſperity of his peo-
          <lb/>ple, may ſoon call upon his Lordſhip <lb/>to exerciſe thoſe rare talents which
          <lb/>God has given him for recovering <lb/>the glory and welfare of this empire. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In his Preface he ſeems to lament, <lb/>that, notwithſtanding the aſtoniſhing
        <lb/>effects of the Bath Waters, thoſe who <lb/>preſcribe them are ſtill ignorant of their
        <lb/>contents; and propoſes a ſubſcription <lb/>to bring down ſome able Chemiſt to
        <lb/>analyſe them, in order to put that mat- <lb/>ter beyond a doubt. This, he thinks,
        <lb/>would be a charity that would extend <lb/>to future generation. Were it certain-
        <lb/>ly known what their impregnations <lb/>are, an artificial water might be pre- <pb
          n="137"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>pared, from which, thoſe whoſe neceſ- <lb/>ſities or bodily infirmities keep at a diſ-
        <lb/>tance, might derive almoſt an equal <lb/>benefit with thoſe who enjoy them at <lb/>the
        fountain-head. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The treatiſe is divided into XIII. <lb/>Chapters. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Chap. I. Of the Bath Waters. In <lb/>this chapter, the writer is both jocoſe <lb/>and
        ſerious, he pays no great reſpect <lb/>to the memory of King Bladud, becauſe <lb/>he was a
        king; but thinks his hogs <lb/>were to be commemorated for the diſ- <lb/>covery of the
        waters in preference to <lb/>his Majeſty. He advances as a cer- <lb/>tainty, that drinking
        them is never of <lb/>any ſervice, (on the contrary, is often <lb/>dangerous,) but when they
        act either <lb/>laxatively by the bowels or kidneys, or <lb/>are accompanied with medicines
        that do. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Chap. II. Of Apothecaries. In this <lb/>chapter, he treats Dr. Graham and <lb/>Mrs.
        Macaulay with ſome pleaſantry. <lb/>He ſpeaks of Phyſicians, whoſe patients <lb/>are too far
        gone to receive any relief <lb/>themſelves, who preſcribe merely for <lb/>the benefit of the
        Apothecaries; and <lb/>of Apothecaries, who, truſting to the <lb/>ſkill of their
        apprentices, have ſent pa- <lb/>tients to the grave, not from the <hi rend="italic">diſ-
          <lb/>orders</hi> they laboured under, but from <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">diſorder</hi> in
        which their medicines <lb/>have been prepared. He, therefore, cau- <lb/>tions all who come
        to Bath to be care- <lb/>ful to employ a phyſician who is above <lb/>preſcribing for an
        apothecary, and an <lb/>apothecary, who is not above ſuperin- <lb/>tending his medicines
        himſelf. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Chap. III. Of Phyſicians. The <lb/>greateſt excellence of a phyſician, he <lb/>ſays, is
        to know when he can do no- <lb/>thing, and to have honſeſty enough <lb/>to ſay ſo. He does
        not pay any great <lb/>compliment to the Bath Phyſicians; <lb/>but, as he takes upon himſelf
        the of- <lb/>fice of a guide, he adviſes thoſe, who <lb/>come to Bath to drink the waters,
        to <lb/>proceed with caution. He had, he ſays, <lb/>the misfortune to loſe a beloved bro-
        <lb/>ther in the prime of life, by haſtily <lb/>drinking as much in three weeks, as
        <lb/>formerly had relieved him by drinking <lb/>moderately of them in ſix. He dropt
        <lb/>down dead, after drinking plentifully <lb/>of Bath waters, and eating a hearty
        <lb/>breakfaſt of ſpongy rolls. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Chap. IV. Of Bathing. He joins <lb/>with Dr. Oliver in opinion, that bath- <lb/>ing is
        the moſt general ſolvent of all ob- <lb/>ſtructions in the human body, whether <lb/>natural
        or acquired; and, therefore, <lb/>thinks it highly beneficial in all gouty <lb/>and
        rheumatic complaints; but cau- <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>tions againſt bathing early in the morn- <lb/>ing, and taking the full force of the
        <lb/>heat, which, inſtead of opening the <lb/>pores, often ſhuts them up. In this
        <lb/>chapter the writer indulges a kind of <lb/>humour (which ſeems natural to
          him)<unclear>,</unclear>
        <lb/>of ſporting with his readers, which <lb/>thoſe of a graver turn will think might
        <lb/>have been ſpared. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Chap. V. Of Long Life and Health. <lb/>He is in this chapter what ſome people <lb/>may
        think no leſs <hi rend="italic">waggiſh</hi>. He men- <lb/>tions an ancient inſcription, the
        pur- <lb/>port of which is, that Marcus Claudius <lb/>Hermippus lived to 115 years and five
        <lb/>days, by the ſalutary breath of young <lb/>virgins; and, as a proof of the reality
        <lb/>of the recipe, the writer confirms it <lb/>by his own experience. <q rend="quotes"
          part="i">I am, my- <lb/>ſelf, </q>ſays he, <q rend="quotes" part="f">now turned of ſixty,
          and, <lb/>in general, though I have lived in va- <lb/>rious climates, and ſuffered
          ſeverely <lb/>both in body and mind, yet, having al- <lb/>ways partaken of the breath of
          young <lb/>women, whenever they lay in my way, <lb/>I feel none of thoſe infirmities which
          ſo <lb/>often ſtrike my eyes and ears in this <lb/>great city, by men much younger than
          <lb/>myſelf. </q> In this chapter he quotes <lb/>many inſtances of longevity, and makes
        <lb/>no doubt but that every man who has <lb/>attained the age of 40, has it in his
        <lb/>power to double that period. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Chap. VI. Of Surgeons. The writ- <lb/>er expreſſes the higheſt reſpect for men <lb/>of
        this profeſſion, and mentions ſeve- <lb/>ral at Bath who are and may be of in- <lb/>finite
        ſervice to the community. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Chap. VII. Of Bilious Diſorders. <lb/>The Bath waters, the writer ſays, are
        <lb/>conſidered as particularly ſerviceable in <lb/>all bilious complaints; and adds, that
        <lb/>he is as well qualified to give his advice <lb/>in that particular caſe as any man
        <lb/>living; for which he aſſigns his rea- <lb/>ſons, having, he ſays, for more than
        <lb/>twenty years, ſuffered at times the <lb/>moſt excruciating pains, by voiding
        <lb/>innumerable gall-ſtones. Though <lb/>the duct from the gall-bladder is no <lb/>bigger
        than a crow quill, he voided <unclear>one</unclear>
        <lb/>6-8ths of an inch one way, by 5-8ths <lb/>the other. This chapter is full of ſo-
        <lb/>lid reaſoning and valuable inſtruction, <lb/>and is of more worth than whole trea-
        <lb/>tiſes on the ſubject founded on theory <lb/>without experiment. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Chap. VIII. Remarks on Dr. Oli- <lb/>ver's Eſſay on the Uſe and Abuſe of <lb/>Warm
        Bathing in Gouty Caſes. In <lb/>this chapter the writer detects a prac- <lb/>tice, which it
        is ſurely of the utmoſt <lb/>conſequence to diſcountenance, viz. <pb n="138"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>that by <hi rend="italic">feeling the pulſe</hi> of a ſerjeant, <lb/>a guide, or a
        ſomebody about the <lb/>King's Bath, or any of the public <lb/>baths, the patient can
        procure a vio- <lb/>lent hot one, a moderately hot one, or <lb/>a warm one, and all his
        fellow-bath- <lb/>ers muſt take it according to his mind. <lb/>This certainly demands
        regulation. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Chap. <sic>VIII.</sic> Of the Antiquity and <lb/>ancient Baths of the City. This chap-
        <lb/>ter is rather curious than uſeful. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Chap. IX. Of Wine, and drinking <lb/>to exceſs. Good wine, of a proper age, <lb/>the
        writer aſſerts, is not only an excel- <lb/>lent cordial, but to men of a certain <lb/>age,
        it tends to the prolonging of life. <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">A man, </q> ſays he, <q rend="quotes">who loves his <lb/>bottle in
          Switzerland, is highly eſteem- <lb/>ed: At Naples, or Madrid, he is dread- <lb/>ed; but I
          hardly ever knew one in <lb/>England who loved it, who was not at <lb/>bottom a generous,
          honeſt, and well- <lb/>meaning, if not a brilliant man. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Chap. X. Remarks on Dr. Charle- <lb/>ton's Analyſis of Bath Waters. The <lb/>writer
        does not ſeem to have much <lb/>faith in the Doctors Analyſis, as it <lb/>differs from that
        of the late Dr. Lucas, <lb/>who was the author's intimate friend. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Chap. XI. Of the promiſcuous <lb/>Bathing of both Sexes. Here the <lb/>writer takes
        occaſion to correct himſelf <lb/>for holding forth, in his IVth Chap- <lb/>ter, the picture
        of a country dame, <lb/>who found herſelf uncommonly agi- <lb/>tated by treading on a
        particular ſpot. <lb/>He tells alſo the well-known ſtory of <lb/>Naſh's toſſing a little
        gentleman into <lb/>the bath to his own wife, who looked, <lb/>he ſaid, ſo much like an
        angel in <lb/>the watery element that he wiſhed to <lb/>be there with her; which he had no
        <lb/>ſooner ſaid, than ſouſe he came in, and <lb/>both fell a flouncing together, to the no
        <lb/>ſmall diverſion of the numerous ſpec- <lb/>tators. This chapter is cloſed with <lb/>a
        ſerious remark, that the promiſcuous <lb/>bathing of the ſexes did not prevail in <lb/>Rome,
        till effeminacy, the forerunner <lb/>of the downfal of all empires, had be- <lb/>come
        general; and it has been obſerv- <lb/>ed alſo, that the profligacy of women <lb/>has been
        another ſtrong mark of the <lb/>approaching diſſolution of kingdoms. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Chap. XII. Of Muſic. To the <lb/>power of muſic Mr. Thickneſſe aſcribes <lb/>many
        exhilarating virtues. He ob- <lb/>ſerves its effects on the youthful and <lb/>gay, and ſees
        no reaſon why it ſhould <lb/>not have a ſimilar influence on the hy- <lb/>pochondriac and
        valetudinarian. It is <lb/>a cordial to the troubled breaſt, and is <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>to the fibres of the body what tuneing <lb/>is to the harp. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Chap. XIII. Of the cure of the <lb/>Dropſy, by Dr. Bacher. Mr. Thick- <lb/>neſſe
        concludes his miſcellaneous per- <lb/>formance with ſtrongly recommending <lb/>Dr. Bacher's
        recipe, which was pur- <lb/>chaſed by the French King, and pub- <lb/>liſhed for the benefit
        of his ſubjects. <lb/>The recipe is as follows: </p>
      <p rend="indentall hanging">
        <lb/>℞ Extract. noſtr. hellebor. <lb/>Myrrhæ ſolutæ, a a ℥j. <lb/>Card. Benedict.
        pulveriſat. ʒ iij. ℈j. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>M. F. S. A. Maſſa aere ſicco exſic- <lb/>canda donec formandis pillulis apta ſit
        <lb/>ſignal ad gran. ſemiſſ. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Of theſe pills ten are to be taken at <lb/>once, and the doſe repeated three times,
        <lb/>an hour between each. They firſt <lb/>open the belly, and then carry off the
        <lb/>diſorder by urine. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Theſe chapters are followed by an <lb/>appendix, containing a compariſon of <lb/>ſome
        experiments made by different <lb/>phyſicians to aſcertain the contents of <lb/>Bath waters. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Upon the whole, whoever viſits Bath <lb/>will find this performance worth the
        <lb/>purchaſe. There are, indeed, ſome <lb/>things in it that might have been ſpar- <lb/>ed;
        but thoſe are atoned for by others <lb/>of a very uſeful kind. The valetudi- <lb/>narian
        will find in it the means point- <lb/>ed out to recover health; the gouty <lb/>patient to
        get eaſe; and thoſe who la- <lb/>bour under bilious complaints cannot <lb/>adviſe with a
        better Doctor. To young <lb/>perſons who reſort to Bath, it will be <lb/>a monitor; to the
        ſtranger, a guide; <lb/>and to thoſe who love play, a leſſon. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
