<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Rules necessary to be observed by the Gouty</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Rules necessary to be observed by the Gouty</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed at St. John's Gate, for D. Henry; and sold by F. Newbery,
                  the Corner of St. Paul's Church-Yard, Ludgate-Street.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1780</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">50</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">276</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1780_GM_0276">
    <body>
      <pb n="276"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(1.5)">D</hi>R. Grant, in his Obſervations on <lb/>the Origin, Progreſs,
        and Method <lb/>of treating the Abrabilious Tempera- <lb/>ment and Gout, lays down the
        follow- <lb/>ing rules to thoſe who mean to be cured <lb/>of the gout radically: </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>1. He muſt quit the flat fertile cul- <lb/>tivated plains during the ſummer ſea-
        <lb/>ſon every year, and remove to the high- <lb/>eſt parts of the country were the air is
        <lb/>thin, pure, and piercing. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>2. Learn to amuſe himſelf with con- <lb/>trary diverſions ſo as to fatigue himſelf
        <lb/>every day. Of theſe, fiſhing and wa- <lb/>ding in the clear ſtream is the beſt;
        <lb/>walking is next; riding is only a ſuc- <lb/>cedaneum, and a carriage is not equal
        <lb/>to the intention. </p>
      <pb n="277"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>3. Avoid populous towns and great <lb/>cities, ſhun all occaſions of anxiety,
        <lb/>debilitating paſſions, noxious diſſipa- <lb/>tions, exhauſting pleaſures, and heavy
        <lb/>mental concerns, or intenſe thinking, <lb/>even on agreeable ſubjects. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>4. Keep to regular hours of exer- <lb/>ciſe, eating, and ſleeping; ſhort ſleep is
        <lb/>beſt, on hard beds, in the early part of <lb/>the night. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>5. Let his apartments be large, lofty, <lb/>ill finiſhed, and well warmed by ſtrong
        <lb/>fires. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>6. He will ſoon feel the advantages <lb/>of frequent bathing, much friction, <lb/>and
        warm clothing. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>7. His diet muſt be in proportion to <lb/>his exerciſe, both in quality and quan-
        <lb/>tity; but he muſt never quite ſatisfy <lb/>his hunger at any time; in general it is
        <lb/>proper to abſtain from butter, fat, high- <lb/>ſeaſoned, ſalted and ſmoaked meats;
        <lb/>ſome forbid black fleſh and pork, but <lb/>I do not find much difference, ſo that
        <lb/>the fat and ſkin are taken away; wild <lb/>fowl and game of all kinds are proper,
        <lb/>and ſo is fiſh without butter. Animal <lb/>food muſt not be uſed above once a day;
        <lb/>four days in the week he may eat meat, <lb/>but never mix fiſh and fleſh in the ſame
        <lb/>day, far leſs in the ſame meal. Butter- <lb/>milk, whey, fruit, greens, roots, ſeeds,
        <lb/>bread, and diſhes prepared from them, <lb/>ought to conſtitute the greater part of
        <lb/>his nouriſhment, eſpecially during the <lb/>ſummer and harveſt; tea and coffee,
        <lb/>thin chocolate, and cocoa, agree with <lb/>moſt people, mixed with milk, provided
        <lb/>they eat no butter along with them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>8. The beſt common drink is cold <lb/>water, but when he takes animal food <lb/>he may
        drink ſmall-beer, cyder, wine, <lb/>or ſpirits very much diluted. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>9. When he eats heartily at dinner <lb/>he ought to eat no ſupper, but ſuffer <lb/>the
        ſtomach to be quite empty once in <lb/>twenty-four hours. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>10. He muſt be well rubbed all over <lb/>every night and morning; and altho' <lb/>I
        wiſh him to be warmly clothed, yet <lb/>I think he ought to walk out in the <lb/>air as much
        as may be. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>11. When he is quite free from all <lb/>complaint, ſea-bathing, or even cold
        <lb/>bathing, will agree with moſt people, to <lb/>reſtore the ſtrength. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>12. But in all ſituations he muſt take <lb/>care to keep his body regular by taking
        <lb/>ſulpher at night, when he is coſtive; <lb/>and if he ſhould be tormented with
        <lb/>wandering pains, the aron-root and <lb/>ſcurvy-graſs will be of ſervice to him. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By ſuch means as theſe, properly <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>conducted, and ſteadily proſecuted for <lb/>a length of time, a man of obſervation,
        <lb/>by only attending to the juvantia and <lb/>laetanda in his own conſtitution, will
        <lb/>in general radically cure any recent <lb/>gout, always moderate it, never injure
        <lb/>his natural <choice>
          <corr>ſtate</corr>
          <sic>ſtaie</sic>
        </choice> of health, or ſhorten <lb/>his life. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I do not expect that it can be in the <lb/>power of every one of my friends to
        <lb/>obſerve all my directions literally; but <lb/>it is my province to draw the line, and
        <lb/>them to follow it as near as circum- <lb/>ſtances may permit, carefully obſerving
        <lb/>what does and what does not agree. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
