<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - A. Z.: Human Body uncommonly preserved</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>A. Z.</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Human Body uncommonly preserved</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed by John Nichols, for David Henry, late of Saint John's
                  Gate; and sold Eliz. Newbery, the Corner of St. Paul's Church-Yard,
                  Ludgate-Street. 1786.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1786</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">56</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">1007</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1786_GM_1007">
    <body>
      <pb n="1007"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <salute rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="sc">Urban</hi>, </salute>
      <dateline rend="align-right"><hi rend="italic">Nov.</hi> 20. </dateline>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">H</hi>EARING by chance of a human <lb/>body in a very curious and
        uncom- <lb/>mon ſtate of preſervation, in the poſſeſ- <lb/>ſion of a gentleman of fortune in
        Weſt- <lb/>minſter, I procured, through the inte- <lb/>reſt of a friend, a ſight of it,
        which <lb/>perfectly anſwered the deſcription that <lb/>had been given me, and gratified my
        <lb/>curioſity in the fulleſt manner poſſible. <lb/>Incloſed is a very exact repreſentation
          <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.8)">
          <cb n="1 2" type="footnote"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* We thank our correſpondent for the communication; but ſhall content ourſelves
            with <lb/>copying the inſcription: <q rend="quotes">This print is an exact
              repreſentation of a boy about twelve years <lb/>old, who was found erect, with his
              cloaths on, in a vault under St. Botolph's Aldgate old <lb/>church, in the year 1742,
              and is ſuppoſed to have been ſhut in at the time of the plague in
                <lb/>166<unclear>6</unclear>, as the vault had not been opened from that period till
              the time abovementioned, when <lb/>the church was pulled down. The extraordinary
              circumſtance of this boy is this, that his <lb/>ſkin, fibres, and inteſtines, are all
              dried, and very little of his bones appears, and weighs <lb/>about 18 pounds. Now in
              the poſſeſſion of John Symmons, eſq. of Groſvenor-houſe, <lb/>Weſtminſter. </q>
          </p>
        </note>
        <lb/>of it from a copper-plate of the propri- <lb/>etor's, to which is annexed a ſhort de-
        <lb/>ſcription of the circumſtances attending <lb/>its diſcovery, &amp;c. than which nothing
        <lb/>can be more conſiſtent with probability. <lb/>In addition to what is there deſcribed,
        <lb/>and to throw further light on ſo ſtrange <lb/>a phænomenon, it may not be amiſs to <pb
          n="1008"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>ſay, that the extreme length is about <lb/>four feet, the ſex very clearly marked,
        <lb/>and the bones every where completely <lb/>covered but in thoſe places where exter-
        <lb/>nal violence ſeems to have been uſed <lb/>for the purpoſe of laying them open. <lb/>Of
        the teeth, all the inciſores are want- <lb/>ing, and but ſix of the grinders left,
        <lb/>three in each jaw. The viſcera are <lb/>cloſely inveſted by the outer integu-
        <lb/>ments, and of courſe dried up in the <lb/>ſame manner as the other more ſolid
        <lb/>parts, the cartilages of the ears quite <lb/>perfect, and the ſhape moſt accurately
        <lb/>preſerved; the back part of the ſcalp is <lb/>thinly covered with ſhort hairs of a red-
        <lb/>diſh caſt. That no putrefaction, even <lb/>in the ſmalleſt degree, ever took place,
        <lb/>is evident from the medullary ſubſtance <lb/>of the eyes, which is dried like the reſt,
        <lb/>and ſtill perceptible in that ſtate. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I underſtand that many human bodies, <lb/>under the ſame predicament, have been
        <lb/>found in a conventual vault at Toulouſe, <lb/>but do not recollect to have heard of
        <lb/>any thing preciſely ſimilar within the <lb/>limits of this iſland; the humidity of
        <lb/>our climate, perhaps, tending in gene- <lb/>ral to the prevention of that eſſect,
        <lb/>which can only be produced by the ex- <lb/>treme of a contrary principle. The <lb/>body
        of Humphrey Duke of Glou- <lb/>ceſter, when diſcovered entire at St. <lb/>Alban's, was in a
        ſort of pickle, upon <lb/>the conſumption of which it preſently <lb/>mouldered to duſt; as
        was, I believe, <lb/>that of Robert Earl of Eſſex, found <lb/>ſome years ago at Carmarthen.
        Many o- <lb/>ther bodies, that were ſaid to have been <lb/>entire at the time of their
        diſcovery, on <lb/>being expoſed to the air, ſome immedi- <lb/>ately, and all the others at
        no very diſ- <lb/>tant interval of time, fell to nothing, ſome <lb/>even eluding the graſp
        of the firſt diſco- <lb/>verers on the ſpot; whereas this is not on- <lb/>ly perfectly
        ſolid, but of the conſiſtency <lb/>and toughneſs of ſtrong leather through- <lb/>out, ſo
        that the whole body, weighing <lb/>18lb, can be ſuſpended, and even held at <lb/>full
        length, by one foot, without the ſmall- <lb/>eſt injury. The preſent poſſeſſor of <lb/>this
        valuable curioſity is Mr. Symmons, <lb/>of Groſvenor-houſe, Weſtminſter, who <lb/>behaved to
        me with very great polite- <lb/>neſs, and very liberally expreſſed a wil- <lb/>lingneſs that
        it ſhould be ſeen by any <lb/>perſon curious in the purſuit of natural <lb/>hiſtory. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As your entertaining and inſtructive <lb/>Miſcellany is the propereſt vehicle for
        <lb/>ſuch information to the public, I have <lb/>taken the liberty of troubling you with <cb
          n="2"/>
        <lb/>the above, preferably to the publiſher <lb/>of any other periodical publication. </p>
      <signed rend="align-center">
        <lb/>Yours, &amp;c. <hi rend="align-right">A. Z. </hi>
      </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
