<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: The Present Practice of Surgery</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>The Present Practice of Surgery. Containing the Description,Causes, and Treatment
              of each Complaint; together with the most approved Methods of Operating. By Robert
              White, M. D. and Practitioner in Surgery. 8vo. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed by John Nichols, for David Henry, late of Saint John's
                  Gate; and sold Eliz. Newbery, the Corner of St. Paul's Church-Yard,
                  Ludgate-Street. 1786.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1786</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">56</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">688</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1786_GM_0688">
    <body>
      <pb n="688"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">106.</hi> The Preſent Practice of Surgery. Con- <lb/>taining the
        Deſcription,Cauſes, and Treat- <lb/>ment of each Complaint; together with the <lb/>moſt
        approved Methods of Operating. By <lb/><hi rend="roman">Robert White</hi>, M. D. and
        Practitioner in <lb/>Surgery. 8vo. </head>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>HAVING every reaſon to believe <lb/>that this volume will be both accept- <lb/>able and
        uſeful to ſtudents and young <lb/>practitioners, we ſhall let the author in- <lb/>troduce
        himſelf. </p>
      <p rend="indent space size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">The great improvements, </q> he ſays, <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple"> made in the art, within the laſt thirty <lb/>or forty years,
          have rendered the practical <lb/>part ſo widely different from what it is <cb n="2"/>
          <lb/>handed down in the writings of former <lb/>practitioners, as to give ample room for
          fur- <lb/>ther explanations and remarks.—Much, it <lb/>is confeſſed, has been publiſhed
          upon the <lb/>ſubject within that term; but ſome of thoſe <lb/>publications are too
          voluminous and expen- <lb/>ſive; ſome treat only on particular ſubjects; <lb/>and others
          are rather confined to the im- <lb/>provement of operations, and to hypothetical
          <lb/>invention, that made ſubſervient to general <lb/>practice. Experience, however, and
          obſerva- <lb/>tion, together with a competent knowledge <lb/>of anatomy, are the leading
          principles upon <lb/>which this noble art is founded, and upon <lb/>which it ought to be
          ſupported.—In this re- <lb/>fined age, theory has too much the aſcend- <lb/>ency. New
          ſyſtems are daily creating;— <lb/>no ſooner is one become faſhionable and ad- <lb/>mired,
          than another ſprings up, and induſ- <lb/>triouſly controverts it, if it does not overturn
          <lb/>it. Education is, in fact, wrought up be- <lb/>yond the limits of uſeful knowledge;
          and <lb/>the moſt ingenious men are too often divert- <lb/>ed by fanciful ſchemes, founded
          upon falſe <lb/>principles. Hence the ſtudent is unwarily <lb/>led into vain purſuits, and
          is too apt to neg- <lb/>lect ſound practical knowledge. But, allow- <lb/>ing ſuch attempts
          to be ingenious, at the <lb/>ſame time there is little need of argument <lb/>to prove
          their fallibility; and although they <lb/>may be laudable, and even uſeful, yet it is
          <lb/>likely they would be much more ſo, were <lb/>they entered upon with greater caution,
          and <lb/>managed with more temperate zeal. The <lb/>ſurgical art has very little need of
          ſuch aids, <q rend="italic indentall">
            <lb/>Non tali auxilio — <lb/>— eget — </q>
          <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">modus operandi</hi> is of little ſignification, <lb/>provided
          ſucceſs attends the means employed <lb/>towards relief. Human reaſon is evidently <lb/>too
          weak to inveſtigate the myſterious courſe <lb/>of nature with any degree of certainty; and
          <lb/>in ſurgery, as in every other branch of the <lb/>medical art, thoſe applications
          which will <lb/>moſt aſſiſt, and leaſt interrupt, her efforts, <lb/>are beſt entitled to
          preference. Common <lb/>ſenſe will in general be found equal to the <lb/>taſk of
          ſuggeſting the means, and obſerva- <lb/>tion and practice will readily aſcertain the
          <lb/>propriety of uſing them. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">For the more immediate benefit, then, <lb/>of young practitioners,
          a general ſyſtem, as <lb/>compendious as its nature would admit of, <lb/>formed from the
          general practice, in its preſent <lb/>cultivated ſtate, and founded upon poſitive
          <lb/>facts, cannot ſurely be thought an uſeleſs per- <lb/>formance. In the proſecution of
          which, the <lb/>reader will readily imagine the neceſſary <lb/>obligations which the
          author muſt lay under <lb/>to the ingenious and uſeful works of ſeveral <lb/>eminent
          writers upon the different ſubjects. <lb/>—Upon theſe premiſes the author introduces
          <lb/>a plain, conciſe, intelligible ſtate of the <lb/>moſt rational practice; and he has
          therefore <lb/>drawn up his account of it, in what he <lb/>deems the moſt ready and
          eligible plan, by <lb/>dividing in into general heads, and giving a <pb n="689"/>
          <cb n="1"/>
          <lb/>regular deſcription of each diſorder, its <lb/>cauſes, and mode of cure. He has alſo
          ſpe- <lb/>cified a few inſtances of ſucceſs in his own <lb/>practice, wherein he has
          ventured to deviate <lb/>from the moſt reſpectable authorities. And, <lb/>in order to
          render the work more complete, <lb/>he has added a lift of ſuch topical and other
          <lb/>remedies as are moſt applicable to ſurgical <lb/>caſes. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>As a ſpecimen of the whole perform- <lb/>ance, we ſhall ſelect his obſervations on
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Venomous Wounds</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent space size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">The moſt formidable wound of this <lb/>kind, which we have to
          guard againſt in <lb/>this climate, is cauſed by the bite of <hi rend="italic">Mad
            <lb/>Animals</hi>; <hi rend="italic">Dogs</hi> particularly. Its deſcription <lb/>and
          ſymptoms are as follow: </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">No ſudden effect upon the conſtitution <lb/>is obſerved from
          the bite of a mad dog, and <lb/>the wound itſelf is not more difficult to heal <lb/>than
          lacerated wounds in general, of the <lb/>ſame magnitude. The patient has alſo no
          <lb/>particular affliction, except dejection of ſpi- <lb/>rits from a dread of the
          conſequences, till <lb/>about a month or ſix weeks from the acci- <lb/>dent, ſooner or
          later, according to various <lb/>circumſtances; when a redneſs, heat, and <lb/>tenſion
          generally attend the edges of the <lb/>wound, and at the ſame time wandering <lb/>pains
          and ſpaſmodic affections diverge from <lb/>the part; which ſymptoms are accompanied
          <lb/>with nauſea, difficult reſpiration, anxiety about <lb/>the præcordia, vertigo, and
          loſs of muſcular <lb/>ſtrength; great depreſſion of ſpirits and the <lb/>love of ſolitude
          enſue; ſleep is diſturbed by <lb/>twitchings, horrid dreams, and reſtleſſneſs; <lb/>and
          the pulſe is all this time quick, weak, <lb/>and irregular. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">On the firſt or ſecond day the foregoing <lb/>ſymptoms
          gradually increaſing, comes on a <lb/>peculiar affection of the pharynx and gullet,
          <lb/>which, upon an attempt to drink, occaſions <lb/>a ſenſe of ſuffocation, and a
          convulſive af- <lb/>fection of thoſe parts and the organs of re- <lb/>ſpiration; theſe
          ſymptoms even the common <lb/>air in inſpiration will produce, particularly <lb/>if the
          weather is moiſt. This anxiety, and <lb/>not being able to drink without the greateſt
          <lb/>difficulty, gives the diſeaſe the appellation of <lb/>Hydrophobia. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">As the general ſymptoms increaſe, the <lb/>ſaliva is ſwallowed
          in leſs degree; great <lb/>quantities of it are ſpit off in a viſcid and <lb/>frothy
          ſtate, with powerful and repeated ef- <lb/>forts, attended with a ſingular kind of noiſe,
          <lb/>different from common hawking, which per- <lb/>ſons, prepoſſeſſed with the opinion,
          may con- <lb/>clude to be like the barking of a dog: the <lb/>light now begins to grow
          intolerable, and <lb/>the urine flows involuntarily. Thus ends <lb/>the ſecond ſtage of
          this terrible complaint. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">At this awful period follow heat and <lb/>fluſhing, with a
          ſtrangulated appearance in <lb/>the face and neck, together with a quicker <lb/>pulſe, in
          ſome weaker, in others ſtronger; <lb/>with involuntary emiſſions. Convulſive ſpaſms <cb
            n="2"/>
          <lb/>affect moſt parts of the body: ſome are afflicted <lb/>with a fierce delirium, or
          outrageous mad- <lb/>neſs; and others ſhew a fixed melancholy, <lb/>with a moſt pitiable
          countenance, having a <lb/>perfect ſenſe of their miſerable ſtate. At <lb/>length the
          lower limbs become paralytic, <lb/>convulſions increaſe, the pulſe grows lan- <lb/>guid,
          cold ſweats enſue, and death puts an <lb/>end to the general diſtreſs, which commonly
          <lb/>happens on the 3d or 4th day from the attack. <lb/>Such were nearly the progreſſive
          ſymptoms <lb/>of a poor huſbandman, who, within an hour <lb/>of his death, called for
          ſeveral of his ac- <lb/>quaintances, and ſealed his laſt farewell by <lb/>ſhaking hands
          with them, telling them, at <lb/>the ſame time, that they need not be afraid <lb/>of him,
          for he would do them no harm. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">This poor man had been for ſome hours <lb/>deprived of the uſe
          of his lower limbs, which, <lb/>in his reſtleſs ſtate, he dragged after him <lb/>round the
          room, hawking up and ſcattering <lb/>about the ſaliva; at the ſame time he ex-
          <lb/>preſſed as great horror at the mention of a <lb/>bed, as this pitiable claſs of
          patients are ſaid <lb/>to do at the ſight of water; both which <lb/>equally influenced his
          mind with a dread of <lb/>ſuffocation. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">Whilſt he was performing the before- <lb/>mentioned act of
          friendſhip with his fellow- <lb/>ſervant, his mind being particularly agi- <lb/>tated, a
          general convulſion ſeized him, and <lb/>curled him up as it were in a heap, which <lb/>was
          ſucceeded by as ſudden a ſtretch, that <lb/>cloſed the melancholy ſcene. </q>
      </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
