<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Medical Sketches. </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Medical Sketches. In Two Parts. By John Moore, M. D. 8vo.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed by John Nichols, for David Henry, late of Saint John's
                  Gate; and sold Eliz. Newbery, the Corner of St. Paul's Church-Yard,
                  Ludgate-Street. 1786.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1786</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">56</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">507</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1786_GM_0507">
    <body>
      <pb n="507"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <head rend="italic indentall hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">80.</hi> Medical Sketches. In Two Parts. <lb/>By <hi rend="roman">John
          Moore</hi>, M. D. 8vo. </head>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>THIS lively and ingenious writer, <lb/>after remarking the revolutions of ſyſ-
        <lb/>tems in medical hiſtory, and the danger <lb/>of implicitly adopting the faſhionable
        <lb/>doctrines of the day, proceeds to ſhew, <lb/>that phyſical ſkill is only to be acquired
        <lb/>by noting the general properties of <lb/>drugs, by acutely obſerving their parti-
        <lb/>cular operations on the human ſyſtem, <lb/>under various circumſtances, and by
        <lb/>drawing judicious inferences from cau- <lb/>tious experiments.—To follow this line
        <lb/>of conduct with ſucceſs requires a clear <lb/>underſtanding, in a two-fold view—
        <lb/>clear in the exerciſe of vigorous powers, <lb/>and alſo clear from an obſtinate, fond
        <lb/>attachment to pre-conceived theories. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From the introductory part we ſhall <lb/>extract ſome general obſervations that
        <lb/>may afford ſome uſeful hints to our va- <lb/>letudinary readers; though poſſibly our
        <lb/>author, like Dr. Buchan, may be eyed <lb/>aſkance by his brethren as a betrayer of
        <lb/>the myſteries of his profeſſion. </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">What is the buſineſs of a phyſician?— <lb/>Why, to apply his knowledge
          and experi- <lb/>ence to the cure of diſeaſes, in which he <lb/>muſt be directed by that
          degree of under- <lb/>ſtanding he poſſeſſes; and if he is deficient <lb/>in ſenſe, his
          experience will prove a ſource <lb/>from which he will draw falſe inferences; <lb/>and
          learning, if he has it, will make him <lb/>more preſumptuous, and lead him farther
          <lb/>into error. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">How many practitioners do we meet <lb/>with, who are convinced that
          fevers are <lb/>cured by the draughts, impregnated with <lb/>contrayerva root and cardiac
          confection, <lb/>with which they teize the patient every two <lb/>or three hours? And how
          are they con- <lb/>vinced of this? They will anſwer, from <lb/>experience; for the drugs,
          not having actu- <lb/>ally killed the patient, but only retarded his <lb/>cure, he
          recovers at lengthm notwithſtanding <lb/>all the draughts he has been obliged to
          <lb/>ſwallow. The ſagacious doctor imputes the <lb/>cure to his own preſcriptions, and
          proba- <lb/>bly publiſhes the caſe for the benefit of <lb/>poſterity. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">I have known a very well-meaning man <lb/>miſtake a preſcription of
          feeble efficacy for <lb/>one of the moſt powerful febrifuges that <cb n="2"/>
          <lb/>ever was contrived; he had ordered it pro- <lb/>bably at firſt, when the diſeaſe
          began to take <lb/>a favourable turn, or immediately before a <lb/>happy criſis took
          place, and imputed the <lb/>whole effect to the preſcription. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">He gives the ſame medicine in another <lb/>inſtance or two, on the very
          day the fever <lb/>commences; it is an ephemera <note n="*" place="bottom">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* <q rend="quotes">A fever that begins and ends in the <lb/>compaſs of one day.
              </q>
            </p>
          </note>; and he <lb/>is confirmed in his opinion of the power of <lb/>the medicine: he
          proclaims it the happieſt <lb/>combination that ever was invented, which, <lb/>by a kind
          of electric attraction, draws the <lb/>morbific matter to itſelf, and then hurries it
          <lb/>out of the body. After a few inſtances of this <lb/>kind, it is impoſſible to open
          his eyes; he <lb/>imputes the unfortunate termination of other <lb/>caſes to ſome latent
          cauſe, which oppoſed <lb/>the ſalutary effects of his favourite medicine. <lb/>That any
          man, particularly a man of letters, <lb/>and bred to the practice of phyſic, ſhould be
          <lb/>ſo eaſily deceived, could ſcarcely be believed, <lb/>if we did not ſee ſuch examples
          frequently, <lb/>and if we did not know with what partiality <lb/>mankind in general view
          what they conſider <lb/>as their own inventions, and with what com- <lb/>placency they
          embrace opinions which flatter <lb/>their own judgment. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">Another thing which prevents ſome <lb/>practitioners from knowing the
          futility of <lb/>their own preſcriptions, and what Nature, <lb/>left to herſelf, can do,
          is, that they never <lb/>leave Nature to herſelf. The inſtant they <lb/>are called, they
          fall to work with their <lb/>draughts, juleps, and apozems, and perſevere, <lb/>with
          unrelenting aſſiduity, till the diſeaſe <lb/>terminates one way or other. If the patient
          <lb/>recovers, the medicines get the credit; if he <lb/>dies, the diſeaſe is thought to
          have been in- <lb/>curable. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">The being teized to ſwallow drugs is a <lb/>ſpecies of diſtreſs to which
          the rich are more <lb/>expoſed than the poor, provided the lat- <lb/>ter keep out of
          hoſpitals. <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> is allowed <lb/>to cure as many of them as ſhe
          can; and <lb/><hi rend="italic">Art</hi>, being little ſolicitous of ſeducing ſuch
          <lb/>patients out of her ſiſter's hands, they gene- <lb/>rally have <hi rend="italic"
            >real</hi> need of medicines before they <lb/>are preſſed to take them. But a phyſician,
          <lb/>whoſe practice lies among the higheſt ſpheres <lb/>of life, if it amounts to three
          thouſand <lb/>pounds yearly, is ſuppoſed, at a moderate <lb/>computation, to receive two
          thouſand five <lb/>hundred of that ſum for preſcribing for ima- <lb/>ginary complaints, or
          ſuch as would have <lb/>diſappeared fully as ſoon had they been left <lb/>to themſelves.
          But this ought not to be im- <lb/>puted as a crime to the phyſician. If an old <lb/>lady
          cannot dine with comfort till he has <lb/>felt her pulſe, looked at her tongue, and told
          <lb/>her whether her chicken ſhould be roaſted <lb/>or boiled, it is reaſonable he ſhould
          be paid <lb/>for his trouble. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">The difference between a good phyſician <lb/>and a bad one is certainly
          very great; but <pb n="508"/>
          <cb n="1"/>
          <lb/>the difference between a good phyſician and <lb/>no phyſician at all, in many caſes,
          is very <lb/>little. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">If, during the courſe of the common <lb/>epidemic diſeaſes which occur
          in this iſland <lb/>every Spring and Autumn, 200 patients were <lb/>taken promiſcuouſly,
          and one half delivered <lb/>to the care of the faculty, to be treated ac- <lb/>cording to
          art, that is, as private patients<unclear>;</unclear> by <lb/>whom they are fee'd every
          time they pre- <lb/>ſcibe, and the other half delivered to the <lb/>care of nurſes,
          inſtructed to give them no <lb/>phyſic whatever, but merely cooling drinks, <lb/>and ſuch
          light and ſimple food as the patients <lb/>appetites might lead them to wiſh for, I am
          <lb/>convinced the world would be a good deal <lb/>ſurpriſed at the reſult of the
          experiment. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">It is aſtoniſhing how exceedingly apt <lb/>medical practitioners of
          every denomination <lb/>are to impute to drugs that ſalutary effect <lb/>which proceeds
          from the univerſal influence <lb/>of another cauſe, which cauſe is that inhe- <lb/>rent
          bias obſervable in the animal œconomy <lb/>to reſtore health; for, as the ſurface of a
          <lb/>lake, which clearly reflects the ſky and hills, <lb/>and verdant ſcenes around its
          borders, when <lb/>it is diſturbed by the falling of a ſtone, im- <lb/>mediately
          endeavours to recover its ſcattered <lb/>images, and reſtore them to the ſame beau-
          <lb/>teous order in which they are wont to ap- <lb/>pear; in like manner, when the natural
          <lb/>courſe of the animal œconomy is interrupted <lb/>and diſturbed by the diſeaſe, the
          powers of <lb/>the conſtitution are continually endeavouring <lb/>to reſtore its organs to
          the perfect uſe of <lb/>their functions, and to recover its uſual vi- <lb/>gour and
          ſerenity. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">This <hi rend="italic"><unclear>vis</unclear> medicatrix naturæ</hi>,
          this conſtant <lb/>tendency in nature to overcome diſeaſe and <lb/>reſtore health, was
          obſerved by the father of <lb/>medicine; and a ſentiment to the ſame pur- <lb/>poſe is the
          very firſt expreſſed by Sydenham, <lb/>in his ineſtimable work, and is acknowledged
          <lb/>by all candid and diſcerning practitioners to <lb/>have a powerful influence in the
          cure of diſ- <lb/>eaſes. Indeed I am inclined to believe, that <lb/>phyſicians, in
          proportion to their candour <lb/>and diſcernment, acknowledge and rely upon <lb/>this
          power in nature; and, in proportion to <lb/>their ſelfiſhneſs and weakneſs, impute every
          <lb/>recovery to their own preſcriptions. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">A judicious and experienced phyſician <lb/>conſiders himſelf merely as
          an aſſiſtant to <lb/>Nature; when her force ſeems to be ſuffi- <lb/>cient, he leaves her
          to perform the cure; <lb/>when ſhe feels too feeble, he aſſiſts her by <lb/>every means in
          his power. His patients, <lb/>therefore, are ſure, in the firſt place, of all <lb/>the aid
          which Nature can give them; and, <lb/>as often as it is requiſite, if Art has diſcover-
          <lb/>ed or invented any thing to alleviate or re- <lb/>move their complaint, they are ſure
          of that <lb/>alſo. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">Whereas, a phyſician, who has an over- <lb/>weening conceit of his own
          powers and thoſe <lb/>of his art, is apt, by unneceſſary and officious <cb n="2"/>
          <lb/>attempts, to interrupt the ſalutary proceſs of <lb/>Nature, and, like the
          inconſiderate man who <lb/>would plunge his hand into the diſturbed <lb/>lake, in order to
          aſſiſt its efforts to regain its <lb/>loſt tranquillity, he only helps to increaſe
          <lb/>the diſorder and confuſion he means to <lb/>remedy. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">If well-meaning practitioners, who really <lb/>wiſh to do every thing in
          their power for the <lb/>recovery of their patients, and whoſe greateſt <lb/>errors
          proceed from thinking more in their <lb/>power than there is, can do ſo much harm,
          <lb/>how much greater miſchief is to be dreaded <lb/>from the number of cunning,
          unprincipled, <lb/>intereſted practitioners in medicine, who, <lb/>without being deceived
          themſelves, impoſe <lb/>upon the weakneſs and credulity others? <lb/>Thoſe, generally, are
          men of ſuperficial <lb/>knowledge, of a conſiderable degree of na- <lb/>tural ſhrewdneſs,
          and ſuch a portion of im- <lb/>pudence, as ſets them above embarraſſment, <lb/>even when
          their ignorance and fraud are <lb/>made manifeſt. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">Such men ſtudy the foibles of mankind, <lb/>fatten on the fears and
          hopes and caprices of <lb/>the rich valetudinarians, and ſqueeze the laſt <lb/>lingering
          ſhilling out of the weakened hands <lb/>of the poor. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">There is a kind of quackery which <lb/>ſome people ſeem to invite; they
          cannot be <lb/>fully convinced of their phyſician's ſkill and <lb/>attention without it.
          Proofs of this are to <lb/>be met with every where. In a certain city <lb/>on the
          Continent I happened to call upon a <lb/>lady, who, on accout of a pain and ſlight
          <lb/>ſwelling in her ancle, had conſulted a well- <lb/>known phyſician, who, although he
          is ac- <lb/>cuſed by his brethren of much charlatanical <lb/>parade in his practice,
          commands the admi- <lb/>ration of his patients in a more ſupreme de- <lb/>gree than any
          doctor I was ever acquainted <lb/>with. He had juſt left her when I entered. <lb/>She told
          me he had ordered a poultice of bread <lb/>and milk to be applied to the part; and
          <lb/>then, giving her watch to her maid, ſhe de- <lb/>ſired her to take particular care
          that the <lb/>poultice ſhould be boiled exactly <hi rend="italic">four mi- <lb/>nutes and
            a half</hi>, for ſuch were the expreſs <lb/>orders of Monſieur le Docteur. On my ex-
          <lb/>preſſing ſome ſurpriſe at the minuteneſs of <lb/>theſe orders, ſhe exclaimed, <q
            rend="diple quotes">Mon Dieu, <lb/>quelle preciſion! il calcule comme un <lb/>ange! </q>
        </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">The fortunes that have been made, <lb/>and are ſtill making, by men of this
          de- <lb/>ſcription, in the cities of London and Paris, <lb/>and by the venders and
          inventors of noſ- <lb/>trums, or ſecret and infallible cures, is <lb/>quite aſtoniſhing. I
          mention Paris and <lb/>London particularly, becauſe, though other <lb/>towns are in ſome
          degree expoſed to the <lb/>ſame evil, yet the reputation of thoſe pre- <lb/>tended cures
          is always higheſt where the <lb/>field for impoſition is wideſt, and the chance <lb/>of
          detection leaſt. </q>
      </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
