<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Simple Cure for the Itch</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Simple Cure for the Itch</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed by John Nichols, for David Henry, late of Saint John's
                  Gate; and sold Eliz. Newbery, the Corner of St. Paul's Church-Yard,
                  Ludgate-Street. 1786.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1786</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">56</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">130</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1786_GM_0130">
    <body>
      <pb n="130"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <salute rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="sc">Urban</hi>, </salute>
      <dateline rend="align-right"><hi rend="italic">Edinburgh</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Jan.</hi> 14. </dateline>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">Y</hi>OUR correſpondent Humanitas, ſee <lb/>vol. LV. p. 791. 888.
        (with whom <lb/>I heartily agree in reprobating the uſe of <lb/>the ordinary ſulphureous and
        mercurial <lb/>applications) does not ſeem to be in- <lb/>formed of a ſimple remedy,
        entirely <lb/>free from the objections urged againſt <lb/>thoſe abovementioned, which has
        been <lb/>lately employed, with the beſt ſucceſs, <lb/>in the cure of the itch: the remedy I
        <lb/>ſpeak of is the vegetable acid. Of this, <lb/>trial was firſt made in the year 1780,
        <lb/>by Dr. Piſchecow, at that time ſurgeon <lb/>at Livenſk, in Ruſſia. This gentleman,
        <lb/>who came to England not long after- <lb/>wards, has deſcribed his mode of treat-
        <lb/>ment in this diſeaſe in a theſis, printed <lb/>at Edinburgh in 1784 <note n="*"
          place="bottom" rend="size(0.8)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Dr. P. though he publiſhed his theſis at <lb/>Edinburgh, took his degree from
            another <lb/>univerſity. </p>
        </note>, intituled, <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes"><hi rend="italic">Tent<unclear>am</unclear>en Zoologico-practicum de nova
            <lb/>Methodo Pſoram ſanandi.</hi>
        </q> As the diſ- <lb/>tribution of this pamphlet has been con- <lb/>fined to the narrow
        circle of a few <lb/>friends, I ſhould be glad to have an <lb/>opportunity, through the
        medium of <lb/>your uſeful Miſcellany, of making the <lb/>author's practice more generally
        known. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">In the year 1780 </q> (ſays the Dr.) <q rend="quotes">, <lb/>when I was
          ſurgeon at Livenſk, in the <lb/>diſtrict of Woronitz, I found many of <lb/>the poorer ſort
          of people had the itch; <lb/>and, as there were ſeveral diſtilleries in <cb n="2"/>
          <lb/>the place, I applied to all that were in- <lb/>fected, baths made of the reſiduum
          <lb/>(called <hi rend="italic">barda</hi> in the Ruſſian tongue) <lb/>after the
          diſtillation of the ſpirits. I <lb/>ſoon diſcovered, after ſeveral trials, the
          <lb/>efficacy of this application to be ſo great, <lb/>that I did not even think of, much
          leſs <lb/>had occaſion for, any ſulphureous oint- <lb/>ments. If the eruptions did not
          diſap- <lb/>pear on the firſt uſe of the <hi rend="italic">barda bath</hi>, <lb/>they were
          ſure to be removed on the ſe- <lb/>cond. In villages where, on account <lb/>of their
          diſtance from the town, I could <lb/>not procure <hi rend="italic">barda</hi>, I employed
          the <lb/>common Ruſſian drink, called <hi rend="italic">Kuaſs</hi> or <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Quaſs</hi>, with the ſame ſucceſs. Thus <lb/>encouraged, I afterwards made
          trial of <lb/>almoſt every other ſort of vegetable acid: <lb/>and I never found it to
          fail. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">From theſe experiments </q>(adds the <lb/>author) <q rend="quotes"
          >frequently performed with ſuc- <lb/>ceſs on perſons infected with the itch, <lb/>I deduce
          the following practical corol- <lb/>lary, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> that acids, applied
          to the hu- <lb/>man ſkin, prove deſtructive, and, in a <lb/>manner, inſtant poiſon, to
          very ſmall <lb/>inſects, ſuch as the <hi rend="italic">acari ſirones</hi>
          <note n="†" place="bottom" rend="size(0.8)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>† For ſo the animalcula, which cauſe the <lb/>itch, are called by Linnæus. </p>
          </note>. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Such is the ſimplicity of the remedy <lb/>which this author propoſes, that, if it re-
        <lb/>ally poſſeſſes the efficacy which he ſays it <lb/>does, no unprejudiced practitioner
        can <lb/>heſitate a moment to lay aſide the ordi- <lb/>nary unctuous applications for this
        diſ- <lb/>eaſe, and to ſubſtitute, in their place, <lb/>the acidulated bath. In large towns,
        <lb/>where there are many breweries, plenty <lb/>of ſour grains can always be had; and
        <lb/>theſe will anſwer equally well with the <lb/>Ruſſian <hi rend="italic">barda</hi>: on
        the other hand, in <lb/>country places, ſour milk may be em- <lb/>ployed in their ſtead.
        When the erup- <lb/>tion is confined to the hands, would not <lb/>the vapour of boiling
        vinegar be the beſt <lb/>application? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But Dr. P. does not ſeem to have <lb/>been aware that this deleterious pro- <lb/>perty,
        with reſpect to animalcula, is <lb/>not peculiar to vegetable acids, but is <lb/>poſſeſſed
        in common by thoſe alſo of the <lb/>mineral kingdom. The oil of vitriol, <lb/>as it is
        improperly called, has, in ſome <lb/>caſes, applied externally, removed the <lb/>diſeaſe. I
        believe, indeed, that it has <lb/>never been uſed in the form of a bath. <lb/>A few drops of
        this oil will go a far <lb/>greater way than a much larger quan- <lb/>tity of the vegetable
        acid; and, as it is <lb/>cheaper than vinegar, and much more <lb/>commodious than either the
        grains or <pb n="131"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>ſour milk, it will be better to employ <lb/>it, where it can be had, in preference
        <lb/>to any of them. </p>
      <signed rend="align-right">Yours, &amp;c. <hi rend="sc">Medicus</hi>. </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
