<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Review of New Publications. The London Medical Journal. Vol.
          VII. For the Year 1786. Parts I, II, III. 8vo.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Review of New Publications. The London Medical Journal. Vol. VII. For the Year
              1786. Parts I, II, III. 8vo. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed by John Nichols, for David Henry, late of Saint John's
                  Gate; and sold Eliz. Newbery, the Corner of St. Paul's Church-Yard,
                  Ludgate-Street. 1786.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1786</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">56</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">871</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1786_GM_0871">
    <body>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <choice>
          <corr>
            <pb n="879"/></corr>
          <sic>
            <pb n="871"/></sic>
        </choice>
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">122.</hi> The <hi rend="roman">London</hi> Medical Journal. Vol. VII.
        <lb/>For the Year 1786. Parts I, II, III. 8vo. </head>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>THIS valuable collection of medical <lb/>papers (of ſome of the volumes of which
        <lb/>we have occaſionally given an account) <lb/>has been carried on with increaſing re-
        <lb/>putation ſince the year 1780, and has <lb/>now an extenſive circulation on the con-
        <lb/>tinent, being, as ws are informed, re- <lb/>gularly tranſlated, ſoon after its appear-
        <lb/>ance here, into the French and ſome <lb/>other foreign languages. A part of the
        <lb/>work is publiſhed once in three months, <lb/>ſo as to make one volume annually.—
        <lb/>The following are the papers contained <lb/>in the three parts already publiſhed of
        <lb/>the volume for the preſent year. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">I.</hi> Obſervations on the Uſe and Abuſe <lb/>of Mercury in the Cure
        of the Syphilis. <lb/>Communicated, in a Letter to <hi rend="roman">Samuel <lb/>Foart
          Simmons</hi>, M. D. F. R. S. by <hi rend="roman">Tho- <lb/>mas Kirkland</hi>, M. D. Member
        of the <lb/>Royal Medical Society of <hi rend="roman">Edinburgh</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Dr. Kirkland, who has obtained great <lb/>reputation by ſeveral valuable publica-
        <lb/>tions, here points out, from his own <lb/>long and ſucceſsful experience, the great
        <lb/>efficacy of ſmall doſes of mercury in <lb/>venereal caſes. The preparation he re-
        <lb/>commends is, a ſcruple of crude mer- <lb/>cury, rubbed down with a drachm of
        <lb/>ſtarch, and made into twenty pills, two <lb/>of which are to be taken daily, occa-
        <lb/>ſionally interpoſing an opening medi- <lb/>cine —The Doctor highly extols this
        <lb/>mode of practice, and obſerves, that <lb/>large doſes or mercury are not only
        <lb/>unneceſſary, but often violently per- <lb/>nicious. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">II.</hi> Some Experiments made with a <lb/>View to aſcertain the
        Duration of the in- <lb/>ſertious Power of the Variolous Matter. <lb/>By <hi rend="roman"
          >Thomas Houlſton</hi>. M. D. Phyſician <lb/>to the <hi rend="roman">Liverpool</hi>
        Infirmary. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This gentleman kept ſome variolous <lb/>matter in a bottle, ſlightly corked, from
        <lb/>1768 till 1782, when the inoculated two <lb/>patients with it, but without effect;
        <lb/>whence he infers, that the matter of the <lb/>ſmall pox loſes its power of commuicat-
        <lb/>ing infection after a certain number of <lb/>years. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">III.</hi> Caſe of a Retention of Urine re- <lb/>moved by Electricity.
        Communicated, in <lb/>a Letter to Dr. <hi rend="roman">Simmons</hi>, by <hi rend="roman"
          >Samuel <lb/>Snowden</hi>, M. D. Phyſician at <hi rend="roman">Stroud</hi>, in <lb/><hi
          rend="roman">Glouceſterſhire</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The good effects of electricity in this <lb/>caſe were particularly ſtriking, as the
        <lb/>patient, for ſome time, was able to void <lb/>his urine only while he was on the elec-
        <lb/>trical ſtool. </p>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">IV.</hi> Caſe of a Lumbar Abſceſs, with an <lb/>Account of the
        Appearances on Diſſection. <lb/>By Mr. <hi rend="roman">Laurence White Maguire</hi>, Sur-
        <lb/>geon of the Navy. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">V.</hi> Caſe of an Abſceſs of the Liver, oc- <lb/>caſioned by a Blow;
        with an Account of <lb/>the Appearances on Diſſection. Commu- <lb/>nicated, in a Letter to
        Dr. <hi rend="roman">Simmons</hi>, by <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="roman">Iſaac Oliphant</hi>, Surgeon
        in <hi rend="roman">London</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">VI.</hi> An Account of a Suppreſſion of <lb/>Stools and Urine,
        occaſioned by an Accu- <lb/>mulation of hardened Fæces in the Rectum. <lb/>By the ſame. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This caſe is extremely curious; but <lb/>we have not room to inſert the <choice>
          <corr>parti</corr>
          <sic>pari</sic>
        </choice>- <lb/>culars. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">VII.</hi> Two Inſtances of the Effects of <lb/>drinking pure Spirits,
        in repeated and <lb/>large Quantities. Communicated, in a <lb/>Letter to Dr. <hi
          rend="roman">Simmons</hi>, F. R. S. by <hi rend="roman">John <lb/>Rollo</hi>, M. D. late
        Surgeon in the Royal <lb/>Artillery. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A tremendous leſſon for all dram- <lb/>drinkers! </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">VIII.</hi> An Account of a ſucceſsful Me- <lb/>thod of reducing the
        Funis, in Caſes in <lb/>which it comes down before the Head of <lb/>the Fœtus. By Mr.<hi
          rend="roman"> Richard Croft</hi>, Sur- <lb/>geon at <hi rend="roman">Tutbury</hi> in <hi
          rend="roman">Staffordſhire</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The method here recommended is <lb/>new and ingenious. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">IX.</hi> Two ſucceſsful Caſes of Delivery <lb/>by the Crotchet, in
        extreme Deformity of <lb/>the Pelvis. Communicated, in a Letter <lb/>to Dr. <hi rend="roman"
          >Simmons</hi>, by Mr. <hi rend="roman">John Clarke</hi>, <lb/>Surgeon in <hi rend="roman"
          >London</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The author proves, from theſe caſes, <lb/>that it is poſſible to bring a fœtus
        <lb/>through any pelvis, however ſmall its <lb/>dimenſions may be, when the head is
        <lb/>leſſened; and therefore, that the Cæ- <lb/>ſarean ſection can hardly become neceſ-
        <lb/>ſary on account of the diminution of the <lb/>capacity of the pelvis. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/>X. On the Efficacy of Flowers of Zinc <lb/>in the Epilepſy. By <hi rend="roman">J.
          Lind</hi>, M. D. Phy- <lb/>ſician to the Royal Hoſpital at <hi rend="roman">Haſlar</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XI.</hi> An Account of a remarkable Cure <lb/>of a Dropſy, after the
        Patient had been <lb/>tapped Sixteen Times. By Mr. <hi rend="roman">R. Cook</hi>,
        <lb/>Surgeon at <hi rend="roman">Barking</hi> in <hi rend="roman">Eſſex</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This caſe is indeed truly remarkable; <lb/>for what ſixteen tappings and the aſſiſt-
        <lb/>ance of the moſt eminent of the faculty <lb/>had failed to produce, was at length
        <lb/>(after the diſeaſe had continued near <lb/>eight years, and the patient had voided,
        <lb/>in the different tappings, above 82 gal- <lb/>lons of water,) effected by an accidental
        <lb/>motion as the patient (a widow lady <lb/>near Rickmanſworth, Herts,) was mak- <lb/>ing
        her bed, for the ſake of a little ex- <choice>
          <corr>
            <pb n="880"/></corr>
          <sic>
            <pb n="872"/></sic>
        </choice>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>erciſe. She had then a ſudden inclina- <lb/>tion to make water, and in the courſe
        <lb/>of a day or two voided ſeveral gallons. <lb/>The diſeaſe was happily removed in
        <lb/>this manner. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XII.</hi> Obſervations on the Uſe of the <lb/>Globe Peſſary. In a
        Letter to Dr. <hi rend="roman">Sim- <lb/>mons</hi>, by <hi rend="roman">Thomas Denman</hi>,
        M. D. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XIII.</hi> Caſe of a Negro Woman who <lb/>performed the Cæſarean
        Operation on <lb/>herſelf. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The circumſtances of this curious <lb/>and extraordinary narrative are authen-
        <lb/>ticated by Dr. Morton, a reſpectable <lb/>phyſician at Kingſton in Jamaica, who
        <lb/>had the care of the patient, as well as <lb/>by the letters of other medical gentle-
        <lb/>men of eminence, who are acquainted <lb/>with the fact. The poor Negro wo- <lb/>man,
        who is the ſubject of the caſe, be- <lb/>ing impatient of the pains of labour, <lb/>tore
        open the uterus with a blunt knife, <lb/>and let out her inteſtines with the fœ- <lb/>tus.
        The latter died ſoon after its <lb/>birth; but the mother recovered, and <lb/>has ſince been
        delivered of a live child <lb/>at the full term. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XIV.</hi> An Account of a remarkable Fact <lb/>relative to the Small
        Pox. Communicat- <lb/>ed, in a Letter to Dr. <hi rend="roman">Simmons</hi>, F. R. S. <lb/>by
          <hi rend="roman">William Wright</hi>, M. D. F. R. S. <lb/>Phyſician-General in <hi
          rend="roman">Jamaica</hi>, &amp;c. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This gentleman relates a curious fact, <lb/>which proves that, in the cure of the
        <lb/>ſmall pox, a perſon who has already <lb/>gone through the diſeaſe may have a <lb/>local
        affection without the habit in ge- <lb/>neral being tainted with the variolous <lb/>poiſon,
        and yet that ſuch local affection <lb/>is capable of communicating the diſ- <lb/>eaſe.—The
        fact in queſtion is as fol- <lb/>lows: The author, many years alfer he <lb/>had had the
        ſmall pox in the natural <lb/>way, having been attending patients la- <lb/>bouring under
        that diſtemper, had a <lb/>large variolous puſtule on his thumb. <lb/>From this puſtule he
        inoculated ſix ne- <lb/>groes, all of whom paſſed through the <lb/>diſeaſe in the uſual
        manner. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XV.</hi> Remarks on Malignant Fevers; <lb/>and their Cure, by cold
        Water and freſh <lb/>Air. By the ſame. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The author relates two ſtriking in- <lb/>ſtances of the efficacy of cold bathing
        <lb/>(a remedy of which he points out the <lb/>antiquity) in the malignant fevers of
        <lb/>hot climates. One of theſe inſtances is <lb/>his own caſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XVI.</hi> Caſe of a painful Affection of <lb/>the Face cured by
        Electricity. By Mr. <lb/><hi rend="roman">Robert Blunt</hi>, Surgeon at <hi rend="roman"
          >Odiham</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The painful diſeaſe here deſcribed <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>was of the kind firſt pointed out by the <lb/>late eminent Dr. Fothergill, who had
        <lb/>in vain ſought for a remedy of any cer- <lb/>tainty in ſuch caſes. We are therefore
        <lb/>happy to read this account of the im- <lb/>mediate relief obtained from electricity,
        <lb/>in the inſtance here recorded. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XVII.</hi> Hiſtory of a Caſe in which <lb/>Symptoms of Pulmonary
        Conſumption <lb/>were relieved by the Expectoration of <lb/>a Piece of curious bone. By Mr.
          <hi rend="roman">C. <lb/>Holman</hi>, Surgeon at <hi rend="roman">Milverton</hi> in <hi
          rend="roman">So- <lb/>merſetſhire</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The patient was apparently in the <lb/>laſt ſtage of a conſumption, when he
        <lb/>coughed up a great quantity of blood, <lb/>and with it a piece ot carious bone,
        <lb/>ſix eighths of an inch long, and weigh- <lb/>ing ſix grains, which he remembered to
        <lb/>have ſwallowed ſeveral years before.— <lb/>From the time the bone was ſwallowed <lb/>he
        had been ſubject to a cough, and <lb/>other ſymptoms; but all his complaints <lb/>ceaſed on
        its removal. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XVIII.</hi> Obſervations on the Medical <lb/>and Surgical Uſes of cold
        Water. By <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="roman">N. Chavaſſe</hi>, Surgeon at <hi rend="roman"
          >Walſall</hi>
        <lb/>in <hi rend="roman">Staſſordſhire</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Many uſeful remarks occur in this <lb/>paper. The following may be intereſt- <lb/>ing
        to many of our readers: <q rend="diple quotes">The <lb/>ſedative, ſtudious, and
          valetudinary, <lb/>are often afflicted with a violent and <lb/>alarming head-ach. This
          diſeaſe is <lb/>difficult to palliate when preſent, and <lb/>its recurrence not eaſily
          obviated. <lb/>For more than two years I have been <lb/>ſeverely handled, at times, by
          this <lb/>complaint. After trying various re- <lb/>medies without benefit, I have now
          <lb/>learned to mitigate, and finally to re- <lb/>move, it by the application of cold
          <lb/>water to the head. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XIX.</hi> An Account of a Caſe in which <lb/>the Head of the Os
        Femoris, ſhattered by <lb/>a Gun-ſhot, is ſuppoſed to have been re- <lb/>generated. By Mr.
          <hi rend="roman">Joſ. Brandiſh</hi>, Sur- <lb/>geon at <hi rend="roman">Alceſter</hi>, in
          <hi rend="roman">Warwickſhire</hi>. Com- <lb/>municated, with an Account of a curious
        <lb/>Fact relative to the Effects of Opium, in <lb/>a Letter to Dr. <hi rend="roman"
          >Simmons</hi>, by <hi rend="roman">James John- <lb/>ſtone</hi>, M. D. Phyſician at <hi
          rend="roman">Worceſter</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This caſe is an extraordinary inſtance <lb/>of the powers of nature, in re-producing
        <lb/>a part of one of the largeſt bones.—The <lb/>fact relative to opium is alſo very cu-
        <lb/>rious. A patient, who was accuſtomed <lb/>to take a large doſe of it every other
        <lb/>night, for a very painful diſorder (the <lb/>ſtone), got no ſleep the night he took
        <lb/>it, but uſually ſlept well the following <lb/>night. </p>
      <pb n="881"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XX.</hi> Recommendation of Electricity for <lb/>the Cure of a
        Cataract, illuſtrated by a <lb/>Caſe. By Mr. <hi rend="roman">Charles Kite</hi>, Surgeon at
          <lb/><hi rend="roman">Graveſend</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The reader will find in this paper <lb/>ſome judicious obſervations relative to
        <lb/>the application of electricity in caſes of <lb/>cataract. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XXI.</hi> Caſe of a Fracture of the Skull, <lb/>ſucceſsfully treated.
        Communicated, in a <lb/>Letter to Dr. <hi rend="roman">Simmons</hi>, by Mr. <hi rend="roman"
          >J. Cau- <lb/>ſer</hi>, Surgeon at <hi rend="roman">Stourbridge</hi> in <hi rend="roman"
          >Wor- <lb/>ceſterſhire</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XXII.</hi> Experiments and Obſervations <lb/>on the Contents of the
        Medullary Cells in <lb/>Dropſy. Communicated, in a Letter to Dr. <lb/><hi rend="roman"
          >Simmons</hi>, by Mr. <hi rend="roman">John Hall</hi>, Surgeon <lb/>and Teacher of Anatomy
        in <hi rend="roman">London</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XXIII.</hi> Caſe of an Excreſcence in the <lb/>Urethra of a Female
        Patient, ſucceſsfully <lb/>treated. By Mr. <hi rend="roman">J. C. Jenner</hi>, Surgeon
        <lb/>at <hi rend="roman">Painſwick, Glouceſterſhire</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XXIV.</hi> Account of a General Inocula- <lb/>tion at <hi rend="roman"
          >Painſwick</hi>. By the ſame. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XXV.</hi> Obſervations and Queries on <lb/>Animal Heat. By Mr. <hi
          rend="roman">John Pearſon</hi>, <lb/>Surgeon to <hi rend="roman">The Lock Hoſpital</hi>,
        &amp;c. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XXVI.</hi> Obſervations and Facts rela- <lb/>tive to the Practice of
        Inoculation of the <lb/>Small Pox. Communicated, in a Letter <lb/>to Dr. <hi rend="roman"
          >Simmons</hi>, F. R. S. by Mr. <hi rend="roman">John <lb/>Covey</hi>, Apothecary at <hi
          rend="roman">Baſingſtoke</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XXVII.</hi> Caſe of Chorea Sancti Viti <lb/>cured by Cuprum
        Ammoniacum. By <hi rend="roman">R. <lb/>Willan</hi>, M. D. Member of the Royal Col-
        <lb/>lege of Phyſicians, <hi rend="roman">London</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XXVIII.</hi> Singular Termination of <lb/>Dropſy. By the ſame. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XXIX.</hi> Practical Obſervations on Am- <lb/>putation. Communicated,
        in a Letter to <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="roman">Simmons</hi>, F. R. S. by Mr. <hi rend="roman"
          >James <lb/>Lucas</hi>, one of the Surgeons of the General <lb/>Infirmary at <hi
          rend="roman">Leeds</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Theſe obſervations, which ſeem to be <lb/>highly deſerving the attention of ſur-
        <lb/>geons, are accompanied by an engraving <lb/>illuſtrative of a particular mode of am-
        <lb/>putating, recommended by the author. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XXX.</hi> An Account of the good Effects <lb/>of Electricity in Four
        Caſes of a diſeaſed <lb/>Teſticle. By Mr. <hi rend="roman">G. Houndsfield</hi>, Sur-
        <lb/>geon at <hi rend="roman">Sheffield</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XXXI.</hi> Caſe of Worms diſcharged <lb/>through a Wound in the Groin.
        Com- <lb/>municated, in a Letter to Dr. <hi rend="roman">Simmons</hi>, <lb/>F. R. S. by Mr.
          <hi rend="roman">W. Coleman</hi>, Surgeon <lb/>at <hi rend="roman">Sandwich</hi> in <hi
          rend="roman">Kent</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XXXII.</hi> Obſervations on Necroſis. By <lb/>M. <hi rend="roman"
          >Bouſſelin</hi>, Surgeon-Major of the <lb/><hi rend="roman">Poliſh</hi> Army, &amp;c. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This curious diſeaſe does not ſeem <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>to have excited the attention of ſur- <lb/>geons till of late years. In this paper
        <lb/>we have a good account of the ſymp- <lb/>toms and manner of treating it, illuſ-
        <lb/>trated by eight caſes. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XXXIII.</hi> Obſervations on the Effects <lb/>of Magiſtery of Biſmuth,
        given inter- <lb/>nally, as an Antiſpaſmodic. By <hi rend="roman">Lewis <lb/>Odier</hi>, M.
        D. Phyſician at <hi rend="roman">Geneva</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Magiſtery of Biſmuth has hi- <lb/>therto been employed only as a coſme- <lb/>tic;
        but, from this account of it, it <lb/>ſeems to be a remedy of conſiderable <lb/>efficacy in
        certain painful affections of <lb/>the ſtomach, ariſing from too great an <lb/>irritability
        of that organ. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Beſides the articles we have parti- <lb/>cularly noticed, we meet with ſeveral
        <lb/>others, extracted from books. Amongſt <lb/>theſe, are ſeveral papers from the vo-
        <lb/>lume lately publiſhed at Boſton by the <lb/>American Academy of Arts and Sci-
        <lb/>ences; and likewiſe the following cu- <lb/>rious caſe from a work by Dr. Wltezek,
        <lb/>phyſician to the King of Poland. This <lb/>is, <q rend="diple quotes">The caſe of a
          young lady, twenty- <lb/>three years old, who, after ſwallow- <lb/>ing ſeveral keys (one
          of which mea- <lb/>ſured about three inches in length, <lb/>and was with difficulty forced
          down <lb/>by means of a ſcrotary), nails, nee- <lb/>dles, different pieces of gold,
          ſilver, <lb/>and copper coin, glaſs, &amp;c. lingered <lb/>twenty-two weeks; during the
          whole <lb/>time of which ſhe was afflicted with <lb/>an inceſſant nauſea, and with fre-
          <lb/>quent and painful vomiting of a fœ- <lb/>tid, blackiſh fluid. Her fæces were <lb/>in
          general hard, and of a black co- <lb/>lour. On diſſection, the ſtomach was <lb/>found in a
          very diſeaſed ſtate, its in- <lb/>ner ſurface being every where in- <lb/>flamed and
          ulcerated. It contained, <lb/>beſides the articles already enume- <lb/>rated, two
          pen-knives, the blades of <lb/>which were ſeparated from the han- <lb/>dles, the handles
          of ſix table-ſpoons, <lb/>and the bowls of three others, which <lb/>had been bent by the
          patient, to en- <lb/>able them to paſs into the ſtomach. </q>
      </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
