<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Fashion in Physic censured</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Fashion in Physic censured</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine, and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed by John Nichols, for David Henry, late of Saint John's
                  Gate; and sold Eliz. Newbery, the Corner of St. Paul's Church-Yard,
                  Ludgate-Street. 1786.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1786</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">56</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">637</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1786_GM_0637">
    <body>
      <pb n="637"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <salute rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="sc">Urban</hi>, </salute>
      <dateline rend="align-right"><hi rend="italic">June</hi> 2. </dateline>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(1.5)">T</hi>HE continual changes which appear <lb/>in modes of dreſs are
        neither ſur- <lb/>priſing nor blameable; I will even af- <lb/>firm they are praiſe-worthy in
        a commer- <lb/>cial nation like ours. But that phyſic <lb/>ſhould be ſubjected to a kind of
        faſhion <lb/>is a matter of more ſerious conſideration. <lb/>The modern practice is greatly
        changed <lb/>from what prevailed ſome years ago. <lb/>New medicines are ſubſtituted; the eſ-
        <lb/>ſential ones are reduced to a ſmall num- <lb/>ber; and, if we take a retroſpective view
        <lb/>of the ſolemn pharmacopoliſt in his ſhop <lb/>of the laſt century, ſurrounded with
        alli- <lb/>gators, &amp;c. dried and ſtuffed, pillars of <lb/>boxes, drawers, pots, and
        muſty herbs, <lb/>which ſerved either to impoſe upon or <lb/>raiſe the admiration of the
        vulgar, we <lb/>ought to eſteem ourſelves happy that, in <lb/>the preſent enlightened age,
        the whole <lb/><hi rend="italic">materia medica</hi> is capable of being com- <lb/>priſed in
        a ſingle cheſt. Chemicals have <lb/>waged war with Galenicals, and both <lb/>together have
        nearly driven out the old- <lb/>faſhioned ſalutiferous juices of our fields <lb/>and
        gardens. If the ancient practice was <lb/>more tedious in its courſe and operation, <lb/>the
        effects were certainly leſs dangerous. <lb/>I would always prefer a gentle ſanative <lb/>to
        a more active and violent medicine, <lb/>which, in the hands of inexperience, <lb/>might do
        fatal miſchief. I ſpeak here <lb/>only in general line, without pretend- <lb/>ing to
        diſallow that, in acute and certain <lb/>caſes, more ſubtile, and even forcible, <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>medicines are required. At the ſame <lb/>time, we ought to reflect that, inde-
        <lb/>pendent of the known powers and effi- <lb/>cacy of ſuch, we ſhould not loſe ſight of
        <lb/>the various degrees of operation in dif- <lb/>ferent habits and under changeable cir-
        <lb/>cumſtances. I ſhall, for the preſent, con- <lb/>fine my obſervations to the uſe of
        Opium <lb/>only, that faſhionable <hi rend="italic">vade mecum</hi>, that
        <lb/>wonder-working noſtrum. To refuſe it <lb/>the title of 'valuable,' would be doing
        <lb/>an injuſtice to its approved merit. This <lb/>merit is, however, in my opinion, too far
        <lb/>exalted, and that by a kind of medical <lb/>enthuſiaſm. Become familiar in the clo-
        <lb/>ſet of the hypochondriac, it is the cradle <lb/>which rocks life away;—a temporary
        <lb/>friend, with whom too long an acquaint- <lb/>ance is more or leſs dangerous. In ſhort,
        <lb/>it is not to be adminiſtered, in any quan- <lb/>tity, except in the greateſt emergency,
        <lb/>and with the greateſt precaution, as a <lb/>conſcientious and intelligent practitioner
        <lb/>aſſured me he never did without tremb- <lb/>ling. It has been known, ſometimes,
        <lb/>not to anſwer the intended purpoſes; in <lb/>which caſes it frequently acts in oppoſi-
        <lb/>tion, producing an <hi rend="italic">inſomnia</hi>, or, what is <lb/>worſe, <hi
          rend="italic">alienatio mentis</hi>. I ſhall add no <lb/>more, and only beg to be
        underſtood that <lb/>I do not condemn the uſe, but the too <lb/>general abuſe, of this
        appeaſing medicine. <lb/>Perhaps ſome of your medical correſpon- <lb/>dents may join with me
        in theſe ſenti- <lb/>ments. Their learned opinion on this <lb/>ſubject, communicated through
        the chan- <lb/>nel of your Magazine, will be highly ac- <lb/>ceptable to </p>
      <signed rend="sc align-right">Philomathes. </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
