<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: A Guide for Gentlemen studying Medicine at the University of
          Edinburgh</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>A Guide for Gentlemen studying Medicine at the University of Edinburgh. By J.
              Johnson, Esq.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine: and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed by John Nichols, at Cicero's Head, Red Lion Passage,
                  Fleet-Street: And Sold by Eliz. Newbery, the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard,
                  Ludgate-Street. 1792. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1792</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">62</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">1027</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1792_GM_1027">
    <body>
      <pb n="1027"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <head rend="italic align-center">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">258.</hi> A Guide for Gentlemen ſtudying Medicine <lb/>at the
        Univerſity of <hi rend="roman">Edinburgh</hi>. </head>
      <byline rend="italic align-center">
        <lb/>By <hi rend="roman">J. Johnſon</hi>, Eſq. </byline>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>IN whatever light we view this pam- <lb/>phlet, it appears to be a very extraordi-
        <lb/>nary performance. If it be meant to <lb/>ſerve the intereſts of the medical ſchool
        <lb/>of Edinburgh, it is one of the moſt in- <lb/>judicious attempts of the kind that we
        <lb/>have ever ſeen, and ſuch as muſt be re- <lb/>jected with indignation by thoſe to whom
        <lb/>it is <q rend="quotes">with reſpect offered by the author. </q>
        <lb/>If it be Mr. Johnſon's intention to ex- <lb/>poſe the medical profeſſors to contempt
        <lb/>and ridicule, we cannot ſay that his wit <lb/>is keen or his irony delicate. He evi-
        <lb/>dently wants abilities to ſucceed in ſuch <lb/>an enterprize. After briefly mentioning
        <lb/>the celebrity of the univerſity of Edin- <lb/>burgh, he immediately throws out ſome
        <lb/>thing like a cenſure on the diſcipline of <lb/>our univerſities. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">Gentlemen, </q> ſays he, <q rend="quotes">who attend
          <lb/>the college of Edinburgh enjoy <hi rend="italic">advan- <lb/>tages</hi> which are
          denied them in other <lb/>univerſities; they are allowed to reſide <lb/>where they pleaſe,
          are not diſtinguiſhed <lb/>from the other inhabitants of the town <lb/>by any peculiarity
          of dreſs, and are con- <lb/>fined to <hi rend="italic">no particular routine of
          ſtudy</hi>. </q>
        <lb/>And is it indeed any great advantage to <lb/>young men in an univerſity that they are
        <lb/>confined to no particular routine of <lb/>ſtudy? Yes, ſays our author, <q rend="quotes"
          >they <lb/>have thus no opportunity of loitering <lb/>away their time in <hi rend="italic"
            >licenſed idleneſs</hi>, which <lb/>often happens in univerſities where dif- <lb/>ferent
          regulations prevail<unclear>l</unclear>
        </q> This is <lb/>pleaſant; but the joke is ſpoiled by an <lb/>unlucky note, which informs
        us that <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">the candidates for the degree of <hi rend="italic">the</hi>
          <lb/>doctor of <hi rend="italic">medicine</hi> (we quote the <hi rend="italic">ipſiſſima
            <lb/>verba</hi>) are excepted from this rule; they <lb/>muſt attend a certain number of
          claſſes <lb/>before they can be admitted to trial. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Contradictions and inconſiſtency ſeem <lb/>to be favourite figures of ſpeech with
        <lb/>our <hi rend="italic">guide</hi>. After praiſing the univerſity <lb/>of Edinburgh for
        confining its youth to <lb/>no particular routine of ſtudy, he gravely <lb/>tells us, that,
        in conſequence of their <lb/>want of diſcipline and regularity, <q rend="quotes"
          >young <lb/>men are often led aſtray into the enticing <lb/>fields of fancy and
            ſpeculation<unclear>;</unclear> and that <lb/>even the opinions of the <hi rend="italic"
            >teachers</hi>
        </q> (by <lb/>whom the <hi rend="italic">profeſſors</hi> muſt be meant, for <lb/>the Scotch
        colleges have no <hi rend="italic">tutors</hi>) <q rend="quotes">are <cb n="2"/>
          <lb/>generally biaſſed by prejudice or motives <lb/>of intereſt! </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Theſe <hi rend="italic">judicious</hi> obſervations are meant <lb/>as an introduction
        to <q rend="quotes">a conciſe deſcrip- <lb/>tion of all the medical inſtitutions at
          <lb/>Edinburgh, with hints reſpecting the <lb/>proper method of reaping benefits from
          <lb/>them. </q> In the courſe of this deſcription <lb/>he ſometimes inſtructs the
        ſtudents, and <lb/>ſometimes corrects the profeſſor; but <lb/>ſeems never to loſe ſight of
        his main ob- <lb/>ject of vilifying, under the maſk of the <lb/>groſſeſt flattery, thoſe to
        whom he has, <lb/>with matchleſs effrontery, inſcribed his <lb/>pamphlet. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">The plan of Dr. Monro's courſe of <lb/>lectures, </q> he ſays <q
          rend="quotes">is much more ex- <lb/>tenſive than that of any other lecturer on
          <lb/>anatomy, perhaps, in Europe. </q> Having <lb/>laviſhed upon a man of the firſt
        eminence <lb/>in his profeſſion a great deal of hyperbo- <lb/>lical praiſe of this kind,
        which we will <lb/>be bold to ſay the Doctor deſpiſes, Mr. <lb/>Johnſon, true to his cauſe,
        inſtances the <lb/>profeſſor's <q rend="quotes"><hi rend="italic">preparation</hi>, as
          being, that <lb/>in which he particularly <hi rend="italic">excels</hi>! </q>' Were
        <lb/>this a fact, we cannot ſay that it would <lb/>raiſe Dr. Monro in our eſtimation, as his
        <lb/>talents might certainly have been more <lb/>uſefully employed on other objects. But
        <lb/>we have reaſon to believe that it is not a <lb/>fact. The mind of the profeſſor of ana-
        <lb/>tomy is too great to permit him to ſeek <lb/>fame from ſuch mechanical purſuits;
        <lb/>though, in the opinion of our author, <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">every medical practitioner ought to be <lb/>deemed a <hi rend="italic"
            >murderer</hi> who has not conſi- <lb/>dered the <hi rend="italic">appearance</hi> of
          anatomical pre- <lb/>parations. </q> He next regrets that, <q rend="quotes">in
          <lb/>the anatomical courſe of lectures in the <lb/>college of Edinburgh, ſtudents cannot
          <lb/>be accommodated with <hi rend="italic">private diſſections</hi>. <lb/>This </q>(he
        ſays) <q rend="quotes">is <hi rend="italic">a very great defect</hi>, <lb/>but of
            <hi rend="italic">no importance</hi>! </q> From the par- <lb/>ticular prejudices of the
        low people in <lb/>Scotland, he thinks it will never be poſ- <lb/>ſible to eſtabliſh a
        public diſſecting-room <lb/>in Edinburgh; but, in the very next pa- <lb/>ragraph, we are
        given to underſtand, <lb/>that <q rend="quotes">ſome individuals have attempted <lb/>this
          project with ſucceſs. </q> He then <lb/>tells us, that <q rend="quotes">though twenty dead
          bo- <lb/>dies cannot, by the utmoſt exertions of <lb/><hi rend="italic">blameable
            induſtry</hi>, be procured annually <lb/>for diſſection in the capital of Scotland,
          <lb/>yet Dr. Monro is always properly ſup- <lb/>plied with bodies for illuſtrating his re-
          <lb/>marks, and for communicating to his <lb/>pupil a <hi rend="italic">perfect knowledge
            of anatomy</hi>. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Hitherto Mr. Johnſon ſeems to have <lb/>made an aukward attempt at ironical
        <lb/>writing; but he puts off his thin diſ- <pb n="1028"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>guiſe when deſcribing the botanical lec- <lb/>tures of Dr. Rutherford. <q rend="quotes"
         >In ſtudying <lb/>botany, </q> ſays he, <q rend="quotes">the phyſiology
          of <lb/>plants deſerves the principal concern. <lb/>The long time, which Dr. R. needleſsly
          <lb/>employs in explaining the terms of the <lb/>art, renders the ſtudy highly diſguſting
          <lb/>to his pupils, and prevents him from <lb/>doing ſufficient juſtice to the phyſiologi-
          <lb/>cal department of the courſe. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Of Dr. Black and Dr. Duncan, the <lb/>profeſſors of <hi rend="italic">chemiſtry</hi>
        and the <hi rend="italic">inſtitutions <lb/>of medicine</hi>, he writes, upon the whole,
        <lb/>rather favourably; though, after a great <lb/>deal of coarſe and hyperbolical praiſe,
        he <lb/>cenſures the <hi rend="italic">former</hi>, for <q rend="quotes">not allotting
          <lb/>a diſtinct part of his courſe to the late <lb/>important and numerous diſcoveries
          <lb/>which have been made in chemiſtry by <lb/>the French; </q> and ſtrongly inſinuates,
        <lb/>that the firſt part of the courſe given by <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">latter</hi> is
        altogether ſuperfluous. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He ſpeaks reſpectfully, in his way, of <lb/>the lectures given by Dr. Home, on the
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">materia medica</hi>. <q rend="quotes">They are neceſſary, </q>
        <lb/>he ſays, <q rend="quotes">to prevent practitioners from <lb/>the neceſſity of
          confeſſing their ignorance <lb/>to apothecaries' apprentices! </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">All the claſſes already enumerated <lb/>may be conſidered to be ſubſervient
          to <lb/>the practice of medicine. Dr. Gregory, <lb/>whoſe abilities are ſo well known,
          ſuc- <lb/>ceeded the celebrated Dr. Cullen in this <lb/>charge. As he has not yet made out
          a <lb/>perfect plan of lectures, very little can <lb/>be ſaid reſpecting his courſe. </q>
        Enough, <lb/>however, is ſaid of it to ſhew that, in the <lb/>opinion of this <hi
          rend="italic">Guide</hi>, it is a very imper- <lb/>fect courſe. Of this we cannot pretend
        <lb/>to be judges, as we never had the hap- <lb/>pineſs to hear Dr. Gregory lecture, ei-
        <lb/>ther from his preſent or his former chair. <lb/>But, as we have read his works, we
        ſhall <lb/>not heſitate to affirm, in the emphatic <lb/>language of our old friend <hi
          rend="sc">Samuel <lb/>Johnson</hi>, that he has <hi rend="italic">more mind</hi> than
        <lb/>a thouſand ſuch lecturers, as <hi rend="italic">he</hi>, whoſe <lb/>merits, in the
        opinion of this author, <lb/>alone ſupport the fame of the univerſity <lb/>of Edinburgh. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This meritorious lecturer is <hi rend="italic">Dr. Ha- <lb/>milton, profeſſor of
          midwifery</hi>, a man, <lb/>compared with whom our Guide, if ſe- <lb/>rious in his
        encomiums, conſiders your <lb/><hi rend="italic">Gregorys</hi>, and <hi rend="italic"
          >Monros</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Cullens</hi>, and <lb/><hi rend="italic">Blacks</hi>,
        as mere children in medical ſci- <lb/>ence! Midwifery is the moſt important <lb/>of all
        ſtudies, and Dr. Hamilton the <lb/>moſt eminent of all teachers! <q rend="quotes">He
          <lb/>explains the peculiarity of the <hi rend="italic">ſtructure <lb/>of women</hi>, and
          the diſeaſes ariſing from <lb/>that cauſe. He then proceeds to ſhew <cb n="2"/>
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">the effects of pregnancy</hi>, and the diſeaſes <lb/>in
          conſequence, with the proper treat- <lb/>ment. </q> Such is the firſt part of his
        <lb/>courſe. <q rend="quotes">In the ſecond we are told, <lb/>that the management of all the
          variety of <lb/>labours is detailed; and that in this part <lb/>of his courſe Dr. H. is
          particularly emi- <lb/>nent! The treatment of women in <lb/>child-bed forms the third part
          of the <lb/>courſe, and is a ſubject which has never <lb/>been fully explained but by the
          profeſ- <lb/>ſor, who gives a very extenſive view of <lb/>it in his lectures! In the
          fourth part of <lb/>this valuable courſe the nature and treat- <lb/>ment of the diſeaſes
          incident to children <lb/>in early infancy are pointed out, and a <lb/>practice founded on
            <hi rend="italic">philoſophical princi- <lb/>ples</hi> for thte <hi rend="italic">firſt
            time</hi> introduced into this <lb/>branch of the art of healing! </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To ſuppoſe that, by all theſe fulſome <lb/>encomiums, our author really means to
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">ſerve</hi> Dr. Hamilton, is impoſſible; for <lb/>he immediately
        proceeds to level him <lb/>with a London <hi rend="italic">quack</hi>, by advertiſing his
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">lectures</hi> in the very ſtyle uſed by that <lb/>fraternity in the
        wording of their <hi rend="italic">ſpeci- <lb/>ficks</hi>. <q rend="quotes">Dr. Hamilton
          gives three courſes <lb/>of lectures in the year. The fees are <lb/>three guineas for the
          firſt, two guineas <lb/>for the ſecond, and one guinea for the <lb/>third courſe; after
          which, the gentlemen <lb/>are entitled to attend <hi rend="italic">gratis</hi>. The lec-
          <lb/>tures ſhould be attended by <hi rend="italic">every</hi> medi- <lb/>cal ſtudent,
          whatever his future proſpects <lb/>may be; for, without a knowledge of the <lb/>ſubjects
          of them, <hi rend="italic">no practitioner of me- <lb/>dicine can expect to ſucceed in
            buſineſs!</hi>
        </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Our author, having waſted his <hi rend="italic">irony</hi>
        <lb/>upon the <hi rend="italic">profeſſors</hi> in the univerſity, pro- <lb/>ceeds to <hi
          rend="italic">open war</hi> with the <hi rend="italic">private <lb/>teachers</hi> of
        medicine. <q rend="quotes">Theſe men, </q>
        <lb/>he ſays, <q rend="quotes">have not the opportunities for <lb/>acquiring
          knowledge, nor the means for <lb/>conveying inſtruction, which the profeſ- <lb/>ſors
          enjoy. </q> Of courſe, the far-famed <lb/>Dr. Hamilton muſt, a few years ago, <lb/>have
        been very inferior, in the obſtetric <lb/>art, to the late Dr. Young; and it is <lb/>hardly
        to be ſuppoſed that he is equal to <lb/>him yet, as he has not ſo long enjoyed <lb/>the
        advantages of a profeſſorſhip. <q rend="quotes">As <lb/>the profeſſors in the univerſity
          have <hi rend="italic">no <lb/>ſalaries</hi>, they muſt poſſeſs abilities equal <lb/>to
          the important duties of their charge. <lb/>Their lectures muſt <hi rend="italic"
            >therefore</hi> be at leaſt <lb/>equal to thoſe of any private teacher. </q>
        <lb/>There is a profeſſor of <hi rend="italic">logick</hi> in the uni- <lb/>verſity of
        Edinburgh; but he muſt be <lb/>more contemptible in his line than Dr. <lb/>Rutherford is
        ſaid to be in his, if he <lb/>taught Mr. Johnſon to reaſon in this <lb/>manner. Have <hi
          rend="italic">private</hi> teachers ſalaries? <pb n="1029"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>and do ſalaries make thoſe, by whom <lb/>they are enjoyed, dunces? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In his ſtrictures upon private teachers <lb/>it ſeems to be our author's aim to diſ-
        <lb/>countenance that uſeful body of men, <lb/>though, with his uſual conſiſtency, he
        <lb/>confeſſes that <q rend="quotes">thet ſtimulate the pro. <lb/>feſſors to perſorm their
          duty with vi- <lb/>gour. </q> Indeed they have contributed, <lb/>in no ſmall degree, to
        ſpread the cele- <lb/>brity of the medical ſchool of Edin- <lb/>burgh. So thoroughly are the
        profeſ- <lb/>ſors convinced of this truth, that we <lb/>have been credibly informed, of
        what, <lb/>indeed, we ſhould have taken for grant- <lb/>ed, that a very eminent private
        teacher of <lb/><hi rend="italic">anatomy</hi> and <hi rend="italic">midwifery</hi> is
        publicly pa- <lb/>tronized by the Doctors <hi rend="italic">Monro</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
          >Ha- <lb/>milton</hi>, although he has no connexion <lb/>whatever with the unirverſity,
        nor any <lb/>particular relation to the infirmary. <lb/>Thoſe eminent men, far from dreading
        <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">ſeduction</hi>, as this author phraſes it, <lb/>of private
        teachers, well know that the <lb/>greater number of opportunities which <lb/>Edinburgh
        affords for the acquiſition of <lb/>uſeful knowledge, the greater will be <lb/>the concourſe
        of ſtudents to that univer- <lb/>ſity; and every man of common ſenſe <lb/>muſt know, that
        the ſtudents will never <lb/>deſert the ſchools of the public profeſſors <lb/>for thoſe of
        private teachers, unleſs the <lb/>latter be more eminent than the former <lb/>in that
        department of ſcience in which <lb/>they lecture. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From this impotent libel the univerſity <lb/>of Edinburgh has nothing to dread. The
        <lb/>malice of its author is apparent, but his <lb/>power is not great. Who he is we know
        <lb/>not; but it is plain that he is no Eng- <lb/>liſhman, as he uſes ſeveral phraſes with
        <lb/>which our language has no knowledge. <lb/>In Oxford and Cambridge there is no <lb/>ſuch
        degree as that of <hi rend="italic">doctor of medicine</hi>; <lb/>and, notwithſtanding our
        author's pre- <lb/>tended knowledge of the courſe of me- <lb/>dical education in the
        univerſity of <lb/>Edinburgh, we imagine that <hi rend="italic">doctor of <lb/>phyſick</hi>
        is the proper ſtyle, even in Scot- <lb/>land. If, as we ſtrongly ſuſpect, he be <lb/>an <hi
          rend="italic">unſucceſsful private teacher himſelf</hi>, <lb/>his book will probably make
        him known; <lb/>and in that caſe he will doubtleſs incur <lb/>the contempt which he has ſo
        ſtrenuouſly <lb/>laboured to bring upon others. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
