<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: An Address to the Governors of the Bath Hospital</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Address to the Governors of the Bath Hospital, on the Propriety of extending
              the Benefits of that humane and laudable Institution. By several of the Governors.
            </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine: and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed by John Nichols, at Cicero's Head, Red Lion Passage,
                  Fleet-Street: And Sold by Eliz. Newbery, the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard,
                  Ludgate-Street. 1792. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1792</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">62</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">744b</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1792_GM_0744">
    <body>
      <pb n="744"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">169.</hi> An Addreſs to the Governors of the <hi rend="roman"
          >Bath</hi>
        <lb/>Hoſpital, on the Propriety of extending the <lb/>Benefits of that humane and laudable
        Inſtitu- <lb/>tion. By ſeveral of the Governors. </head>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>SOME difference of opinion among <lb/>the governors, relative to the propriety <lb/>and
        expediency of building a new hoſ- <lb/>pital, in a ſituation better adapted to the
        <lb/>original purpoſes of the inſtitution than <lb/>the preſent, has given riſe to this ad-
        <lb/>dreſs, which, from the nature of the <lb/>ſubject, and from the circumſtance of
        <lb/>its being the production of ſeveral of <lb/>the governors, highly reſpectable, as
        <lb/>well in character as number, cannot fail <lb/>to excite the attention of the publick,
        <lb/>and, in ſome degree, to intereſt every <lb/>perſon who has the cauſe of Humanity
        <lb/>at heart, and who wiſhes that the <lb/>medical virtues of the Bath waters, ſo
        <lb/>often and ſo happily experienced by the <lb/>opulent, may, as far as it is practicable,
        <lb/>be felt alſo by the poor. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That the gentlemen who oppoſe the <lb/>meaſures here contended for, are actu- <lb/>ated
        by motives which originate in their <lb/>good wiſhes to the inſtitution itſelf, we
        <lb/>cannot entertain a doubt, but it appears <lb/>very clearly to us, that their
        antagoniſts <pb n="745"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>have infinitely the better in point of ar- <lb/>gument; and that the facts upon which
        <lb/>thoſe arguments are grounded demand <lb/>their moſt ſerious and diſpaſſionate con-
        <lb/>ſideration: nor do we ſee how they can, <lb/>conſiſtently, refuſe to go into <hi
          rend="italic">an inquiry</hi>, <lb/>which, as it can have, on either ſide, no <lb/>other
        object than <q rend="diple quotes">the ſacred cauſe of <lb/>humanity and truth, </q> can
        never be <lb/>ſuppoſed to injure the intereſts of <hi rend="italic">that <lb/>charity</hi>
        for which they are concerned. <lb/>
        <q rend="diple quotes">For the queſtion on which we differ <lb/>(ſay the advocates for ſuch
            <hi rend="italic">inquiry</hi>) <lb/>is not whether the hoſpital <hi rend="italic">ſhall
            be <lb/>removed</hi> or no, <hi rend="italic">but</hi> whether the mat- <lb/>ter ſhall
          be <hi rend="italic">inveſtigated</hi>, for the <hi rend="italic">ſole <lb/>purpoſe</hi>
          of <hi rend="italic">finding out</hi> which of the <lb/>two propoſals would be moſt bene-
          <lb/>ficial. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The proceedings of the General <lb/>Courts, and of the Committees, upon <lb/>this
        buſineſs, are detailed with great <lb/>preciſion and candour. The reader is <lb/>fairly put
        into poſſeſſion of the ſubject. <lb/>The objections raiſed againſt the re- <lb/>moval of the
        hoſpital appear to be given <lb/>in their full force; and they are all, in <lb/>our opinion,
        completely and moſt ſatiſ- <lb/>factorily anſwered. The propoſed ſi- <lb/>tuation for the
        new hoſpital appears to <lb/>be free from all the inconveniences <lb/>which affect the
        preſent, and which (by <lb/>the alterations daily taking place in that <lb/>part of the
        city) are increaſing to an in- <lb/>tolerable degree. It is proved that the <lb/>funds of
        the hoſpital will permit the <lb/>governors to appropriate a portion of <lb/>the capital
        towards extending the bene- <lb/>fits of the charity; and that the public <lb/>wants appear
        to demand ſome ſuch ap- <lb/>propriation; and it is obſerved, with <lb/>equal truth and
        ſhrewdneſs, that <q rend="diple quotes italic">a <lb/>charity ſhould avoid being rich, as
          well <lb/>as poor. </q> That no difficulty, how- <lb/>ever, may remain with thoſe who,
        from <lb/>a too timid and cautious prudence, have <lb/>always a dread of incurring large ex-
        <lb/>pences, whatever be the probable ad- <lb/>vantages to be derived from them, it is
        <lb/>afterwards ſhewn that the actual <hi rend="italic">re- <lb/>moval</hi> of the hoſpital
        will <hi rend="italic">coſt leſs</hi> than <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">enlargement</hi> of it
        (which, if it be <lb/>not removed, ſeems to be agreed on all <lb/>hands to be neceſſary), by
        the ſum of <lb/><unclear>314l</unclear>. The tenure too, in the former <lb/>caſe, may be
        made <hi rend="italic">freebold</hi>; whereas in <lb/>the latter it muſt continue to be held
        by <lb/>ſufferance, as it were, and ſubject to <lb/>very ſerious inconvenience. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A ſummary view of the general ad- <lb/>vantages to be obtained by the removal <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>of the hoſpital is compriſed in the fol- <lb/>lowing extract from the concluſion of
        <lb/>the addreſs: </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">It may not be improper to obſerve, that <lb/>the Annual Reports, publiſhed
          for more than <lb/>twenty years paſt, have conſtantly ſtated, <lb/>
          <q rend="diple quotes">that ſince the year 1766 the governors ad- <lb/>mit as many
            patients as the houſe will con- <lb/>tain; and hope, by the continuance of cha-
            <lb/>ritable benefactions, further to extend this <lb/>uſeful charity. </q> This ſhews
          it to have been <lb/>the uniform intention of the governors to <lb/>provide for the relief
          of a greater number of <lb/>the objects of the inſtitution, whenever its <lb/>finances
          would allow of it, and a proper op- <lb/>portunity offered. The injury which the
          <lb/>preſent hoſpital will ſuſtain, in a few years, <lb/>from the improvement of the Lower
          Town, <lb/>—the benefit which a new ſite will derive <lb/>from the ſame cauſe—a ſite
          originally pre- <lb/>ferable to the old, but which could not be <lb/>eaſily obtained
          before)—the large ſurplus of <lb/>income, which has ariſen in the laſt ſeven
          <lb/>years;—the enhanced value of the ground <lb/>on which the hoſpital ſtands; and the
          great <lb/>improbability of ſo favourable an opportunity <lb/>ever offering again for
          placing it near the ſa- <lb/>lutary ſprings which gave riſe to its eſtab- <lb/>liſhment,
          and from whence it derives its <lb/>importance and uſefulneſs;—form ſuch a
          <lb/>concurrence of accidental, or rather provi- <lb/>dential, circumſtances, connoted
          with the <lb/>intereſt of the charity, as demands the pecu- <lb/>liar and unprejudiced
          attention of the go- <lb/>vernors. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In a well-written appendix to the ad- <lb/>dreſs we are informed, that, at a ſubſe-
        <lb/>quent meeting of the governors, a reſo- <lb/>lution for a committee of inquiry was
        <lb/>again rejected (by a majority of 24 to <lb/>20), and the means of entering into the
        <lb/>merits of the queſtion effectually, for <lb/>the preſent, prevented. Upon this ſub-
        <lb/>ject, the addreſſing governors obſerve, </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">We know not how to account for this <lb/>conduct, otherwiſe than by
          ſuppoſing that <lb/>ſome of the governors, who ſeem to have <lb/>too haſtily formed a
          decided opinion againſt <lb/>the removal of the hoſpital in an early ſtage <lb/>of the
          buſineſs, and, from a limited view of <lb/>the ſubject, are apprehenſive that a free diſ-
          <lb/>cuſſion, and a more enlarged view, would <lb/>prove unfavourable to their
          determination; <lb/>and that, feeling a reluctance (natural to the <lb/>human mind) to
          retract an adopted opinion, <lb/>or to loſe any part of their influence with <lb/>other
          governors, who probably rely on their <lb/>judgement, they neither wiſh to be better
          <lb/>informed themſelves, nor chooſe that their <lb/>friends and the publick ſhould
          acquire a <lb/>ſufficient knowledge of the merits of the <lb/>queſtion to form a competent
          judgement of <lb/>their own. We truſt, however, that the <lb/>importance of the cauſe in
          which we are <pb n="746"/>
          <cb n="1"/>
          <lb/>engaged (the ſacred cauſe of humanity and <lb/>truth), and a regard to the faithful
          diſcharge <lb/>of our duty as truſtees of the charity, will <lb/>juſtify our earneſtneſs
          in its behalf; and we <lb/>ſhall eſteem ourſelves happy if our paſt en- <lb/>deavours, or
          future ſervices, may tend to <lb/>promote its welfare and extenſion. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It appears, that theſe ſpirited and <lb/>benevolent gentlemen have actually
        <lb/>purchaſed the premiſes on which they <lb/>wiſh to erect the new hoſpital, from
        <lb/>motives equally honourable to them- <lb/>ſelves and favourable to the purpoſes of
        <lb/>the charity. With an extract from this <lb/>part of the appendix we muſt conclude
        <lb/>our remarks; but not without recom- <lb/>mending this pamphlet to the candid
        <lb/>attention of the friends of the Bath hoſ- <lb/>pital and heartily wiſhing that ſucceſs
        <lb/>to the generous exertions of their au- <lb/>thors, which their cauſe and their con-
        <lb/>duct ſeem ſo eminently to deſerve. </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">sWe cannot, however, conclude this ap- <lb/>pendix to our
          addreſs without expreſſing <lb/>our concern at being under the neceſſity of <lb/>refuting,
          with the contempt it deſerve<unclear>s</unclear>, an <lb/>inſinuation which has been
          induſtriouſly <lb/>whiſpered into the over-credulous ears of <lb/>the publick, that the
          purchaſe of the Alfred <lb/>hotel, and indeed the whole inquiry, tended <lb/>only to
          promote a mere jobb. The fact is <lb/>ſimply this: ſeveral gentlemen have pur- <lb/>chaſed
          Alfred hotel and premiſes for 1300l. <lb/>for the purpoſes already mentioned. They
          <lb/>mean to keep this purchaſe for two years to <lb/>come, and they have let the Alfred
          houſe <lb/>itſelf to the committee for conducting the <lb/>Bath city infirmary and
          diſpenſary for that <lb/>time. This will afford leiſure for the gen- <lb/>tlemen, who have
          hitherto ſo uniformly en- <lb/>deavoured to ſuppreſs an inquiry, to reflect <lb/>coolly on
          the matter, and to ſee the propo- <lb/>ſal; for the queſtion on which we differ is
          <lb/>not whether the hoſpital ſhall be removed or <lb/>no, but whether the matter ſhall be
          inveſti- <lb/>gated, for the ſole purpoſe of finding out <lb/>which of the two propoſals
          would be moſt <lb/>beneficial. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">If, however, all our endeavours to com- <lb/>plete this
          inquiry, in order to enable the go- <lb/>vernors to form an adequate judgement of <lb/>the
          propriety of the meaſure, ſhould prove <lb/>unſucceſsful, we have only to reflect that we
          <lb/>have done our duty in the moſt impartial <lb/>manner, and with a view only to the
          real <lb/>advantage of the charity: we ſhall, in this <lb/>caſe, part with our property in
          the premiſſes <lb/>which we have purchaſed, and apply the <lb/>ſurplus (which we are
          aſſured will be, two <lb/>years hence, very conſiderable, from the <lb/>improvements
          carrying on in that part of <lb/>the city) towards the ſupport of ſuch of the <lb/>public
          charities in Bath as ſhall then ſeem <lb/>moſt to require aſſiſtance. </q>
      </p>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">With this declaration of our ſentiments <lb/>and intentions we
          take our leave, in perfect <lb/>friendſhip and cordiality with every gover- <lb/>nor,
          however oppoſite to us in opinion; <lb/>and at all times ready and willing to co-ope-
          <lb/>rate in meaſures which, in caſe of the failure <lb/>of our own propoſals, ſhall, by
          the majority <lb/>of governors, after due deliberation, be <lb/>thought neceſſary to the
          welfare and exten- <lb/>ſion of this admirable inſtitution. </q>
      </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
