<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Essay on Pulmonary Consumptions</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Essay on Pulmonary Consumptions, including Histories of several remarkable
              Instances of Recovery from the most alarming Stages of the Disorder, by an improved
              Method of Treatment. By William May, M. D. Member of the Royal College of Physicians,
              London, Fellow of the London Medical Society, late one of the Physicians to the
              Universal Dispensary, London. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine: and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed by John Nichols, at Cicero's Head, Red Lion Passage,
                  Fleet-Street: And Sold by Eliz. Newbery, the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard,
                  Ludgate-Street. 1792. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1792</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">62</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">744a</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1792_GM_0744">
    <body>
      <pb n="744"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">168.</hi> Eſſay on Pulmonary Conſumptions, includ- <lb/>ing Hiſtories
        of ſeveral remarkable Inſtances of <lb/>Recovery from the moſt alarming Stages of the
        <lb/>Diſorder, by an improved Method of Treat- <lb/>ment. By <hi rend="roman">William
          May</hi>, M. D. Member of <lb/>the Royal College of Phyſicians, <hi rend="roman"
          >London</hi>, Fel- <lb/>low of the <hi rend="roman">London</hi> Medical Society, late one
        <lb/>of the Phyſicians to the Univerſal Diſpenſary, <lb/><hi rend="roman">London</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>TO diveſt conſumption of part of its <lb/>horrors, and to ſhew that it is curable
        <lb/>in its worſt ſtage, is the profeſſed inten- <lb/>tion of Dr. May in this little work.
        <lb/>As this is contrary to the generally-re- <lb/>ceived opinion, he begins with reciting
        <lb/>a number of examples, part furniſhed <lb/>by his own practice, and part extracted
        <lb/>from the writings of other phyſicians, <lb/>where the termination of the diſeaſe
        <lb/>was favourable, under the moſt unpro- <lb/>miſing circumſtances. What the doctor
        <lb/>thinks moſt important in theſe obſerva- <lb/>tions is, that the cures were effected by
        <lb/>purſuing a method different from that <lb/>generally recommended; for, inſtead of
        <lb/>repeated evacuations, and cooling and <lb/>antiphlogiſtic medicines, being preſcrib-
        <lb/>ed in theſe caſes, a cordial and nouriſh- <lb/>ing diet, with mild, tonic, and bracing
        <lb/>medicines, were uſed. This leads him <lb/>to a conſideration of the nature and
        <lb/>cauſes of <hi rend="italic">pthiſis pulmonalis</hi>, which has <lb/>not hitherto, he
        thinks, been ſufficiently <lb/>inveſtigated. Scrophula has long been <lb/>conſidered as one
        of the cauſes of this <lb/>diſeaſe: our author conſiders it as of its <lb/>eſſence. To prove
        this, he recurs to <lb/>the deſcription of the two diſeaſes, <lb/>given by noſologiſts, and
        of the habits <lb/>and conſtitutions peculiarly ſubject to <lb/>them. Theſe are, according
        to Cullen, <lb/>
        <q rend="diple quotes">perſons of a ſanguine, or ſanguineo- <lb/>melancholic temperament,
          having <lb/>fine ſkins, roſy complexions, large <lb/>veins, ſoft fleſh, and a thick upper
          <lb/>lip. </q> Having eſtabliſhed, as he ſup- <lb/>poſes, the ſimilarity, or, at the
        leaſt, the <lb/>near connexion of theſe diſeaſes with <lb/>each other, he proceeds to ſhew,
        that <lb/>repeated bleedings, with ſaline and <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>cooling medicines, and a low diet, as <lb/>they tend to weaken the ſtomach, im-
        <lb/>pair digeſtion, and to debilitate the con- <lb/>ſtitution, are injurious in this
        diſeaſe: <lb/>on the contrary, that air and exerciſe, a <lb/>more generous diet, with
        occaſional <lb/>emeticks, opiates, the bark, and other <lb/>bracing medicines, will ſeldom
        fail of <lb/>effecting a cure in the worſt caſes. We <lb/>cannot prevail upon ourſelves to
        be ſo <lb/>ſanguine in our expectations of always, <lb/>or even frequently, effecting a cure
        in <lb/>the worſt ſpecies or ſtages of conſump- <lb/>tion, by any method yet known. Neit-
        <lb/>her has the doctor convinced us that <lb/>ſcrophula always exiſts in pthiſical <note
          n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.8)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* The number of athletic and robuſt per- <lb/>ſons, who become conſumptive in
            conſe- <lb/>quence of repeated colds, or after pleuritic or <lb/>peripneumonic
            affections, ſufficiently evince <lb/>that there are other cauſes, beſides ſcrophula,
            <lb/>capable of producing the diſeaſe; and, con- <lb/>ſequently, that no one method of
            cure can be <lb/>adapted to all caſes. </p>
        </note>
        <lb/>caſes; but that the method recommend- <lb/>ed by him has been ſucceſsfully em-
        <lb/>ployed, after the phlogiſtic ſymptoms <lb/>were removed, we have had opportuni-
        <lb/>ties of ſeeing in our own practice; and <lb/>we believe it to be the method adopted
        <lb/>by the moſt experienced phyſicians. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
