<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: A Treatise on the Management of Female Breasts during
          Childbed</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>A Treatise on the Management of Female Breasts during Childbed; and several new
              Observations on Cancerous Diseases, with Prescriptions. To which are added, Remarks on
              Pretenders to the Cure of Cancers, &amp;c. By William Rowley, M. D. &amp;c. &amp;c.
              The Second Edition, with Additions, &amp;c. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine: and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed by John Nichols, at Cicero's Head, Red Lion Passage,
                  Fleet-Street: And Sold by Eliz. Newbery, the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard,
                  Ludgate-Street. 1792. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1792</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">62</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">937</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1792_GM_0937">
    <body>
      <pb n="937"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">225.</hi> A Treatiſe on the Management of Female <lb/>Breaſts during
        Childbed; and ſeveral new <lb/>Obſervations on Cancerous Diſeaſes, with Pre-
        <lb/>ſcriptions. To which are added, Remarks on <lb/>Pretenders to the Cure of Cancers,
        &amp;c. By <lb/><hi rend="roman">William Rowley</hi>, M. D. &amp;c. &amp;c. The <lb/>Second
        Edition, with Additions, &amp;c. </head>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>THIS experienced author has here <lb/>given the publick a freſh teſtimony of <lb/>his
        profeſſional zeal, by a work in which <lb/>he ſeems to have dedicated his labours <lb/>to
        aſcertain the reaſons why the cancer <lb/>is <hi rend="italic">curable</hi> under certain
        circumſtances, <lb/>and why, in other inſtances, it muſt <lb/>remain <hi rend="italic"
          >incurable</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Nothing, certainly, can add greater <lb/>dignity to the art of medicine than to
        <lb/>declare, with preciſion, from facts, what <lb/>may be rationally expected; it prevents
        <lb/>deluſion of falſe hopes, which ever <lb/>ends in painful diſappointment. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The treatiſe conſiders, in the firſt <lb/>part, the moſt rational methods of pre-
        <lb/>venting or curing all the accidents that <lb/>happen to the breaſts in childbed, and
        <lb/>particularly in preventing future can- <lb/>cers. The directions are ſhort, rational,
        <lb/>and eaſily practicable. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Dr. Rowley proceeds to examine the <lb/>cauſe and cure of <hi rend="italic">cancerous
          indurations</hi>. <lb/>The principal views on theſe ſubjects <lb/>are intended to prove,
        that cancers hap- <lb/>pen between the age of 36 and 60; at <lb/>earlier periods cancers
        ſcarcely ever ap- <lb/>pear. The firſt ſpecies, for they are <pb n="938"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>divided into three, are <hi rend="italic">varices</hi> of the <lb/>veins. This ſpecies
        is conſidered <hi rend="italic">cura- <lb/>ble</hi>. The ſecond ſpecies is the former
        <lb/>joined with diſeaſed lymphaticks. This <lb/>is ſaid to be more <hi rend="italic"
          >difficult of cure</hi>. The <lb/>third ſpecies is a <hi rend="italic">ſtony
        hardneſs</hi>, and, <lb/>when painful, is conſidered the <hi rend="italic">true oc-
          <lb/>cult cancer</hi>, and ariſes from the other <lb/>two affections, joined with an
        induration <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">adeps</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">fat</hi>. This is
        ſaid, in <lb/>general, to be, in its nature, <hi rend="italic">incurable</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The treatment of all theſe ſpecies is <lb/>conſidered, both radical and palliative.
        <lb/>Preſcriptions are delivered. <hi rend="italic">Mercury, <lb/>given alone</hi>, or uſed
        without <hi rend="italic">ſulphureous <lb/>antimonials</hi>, is condemned as injurious.
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Opium</hi>, <hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi>, and all <hi
          rend="italic">poiſonous drugs</hi>, <lb/>now ſo much in vogue, are conſidered <lb/>highly
        improper, if a radical cure be at- <lb/>tempted. The author has been at Vi- <lb/>enna, and
        expoſes the fallacy of the <lb/>pretended cures by hemlock with a free- <lb/>dom that does
        him honour. All the <lb/>ſuperſtitious and other remedies are <lb/>next examined; and their
        abſurdity or <lb/>cruelty appear obvious. <q rend="quotes">The unfor- <lb/>tunate patients,
        </q> ſays the author, <q rend="quotes">like <lb/>drowning men, catch at a ſtraw, and
          <lb/>often haſten death by their weakneſs <lb/>and faith. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The next chapter is on the <hi rend="italic">confirmed <lb/>cancer</hi>, in which
        anatomical ſkill and <lb/>much obſervation are diſplayed; but it <lb/>plainly appears, that
        practitioners have <lb/>ſought for, and had faith in, remedies <lb/>in caſes where no
        remedies could poſſi- <lb/>bly act without a regeneration of thoſe <lb/>parts that were
        actually obliterated by <lb/>the diſeaſe; which regeneration, after <lb/>deſtruction, was
        next to impoſſible. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the <hi rend="italic">operation</hi> for cancerous tu- <lb/>mours the author gives
        his reaſons <hi rend="italic">for <lb/>and againſt cutting</hi>, and concludes, that <lb/>in
          <hi rend="italic">very few</hi> caſes the knife is neceſſary: <lb/>and it is aſſerted,
        that cutting off the <lb/>breaſt often cauſes a premature or lin- <lb/>gering and miſerable
        death. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To purſue the Doctor through his <lb/>work would be more than our limits <lb/>could
        permit; but in our next the heads <lb/>ſhall be recited. </p>
      <trailer rend="italic align-right">(To be continued). </trailer>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
