<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: An easy Cure for the Scurvy</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An easy Cure for the Scurvy</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine: and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed by John Nichols, at Cicero's Head, Red Lion Passage,
                  Fleet-Street: And Sold by Eliz. Newbery, the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard,
                  Ludgate-Street. 1792. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1792</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">62</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">603</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1792_GM_0603">
    <body>
      <pb n="603"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <salute rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="sc">Urban</hi>, </salute>
      <dateline rend="align-right"><hi rend="italic">Lincoln</hi>, <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 23. </dateline>
      <div>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> GENTLEMAN of this town, diſ- <lb/>tinguiſhed for his humane
          and be- <lb/>nevolent diſpoſition, has juſt been at the <lb/>expence of printing and
          diſtributing the <lb/>letter here ſubjoined. The motive ap- <lb/>pears to me to be ſo
          praiſe-worthy, that <lb/>I have no doubt but you will give it <lb/>fuller effect by an
          inſertion in your <lb/>widely-circulated Miſcellany. </p>
        <signed rend="align-right">J. C. </signed>
      </div>
      <div rend="size(0.8)">
        <salute rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Dear Sir, </salute>
        <dateline rend="align-right"><hi rend="italic">—</hi>, <hi rend="italic">2d July</hi>, 1777. </dateline>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>About a fortnight ago I went to ſee Tom, <lb/>at Bow, where he is very happy, and
          hath <lb/>made great improvement, eſpecially in the <lb/>uſe of his pen. This I know will
          give you <lb/>pleaſure; but it will give you more to read <lb/>the following narrative of
          cures performed <lb/>by a deſpiſed weed that grows on every ditch, <lb/>and is a nuiſance
          in every garden, which I <lb/>ſend with a requeſt that you will make it as <lb/>public as
          poſſible, and as ſpeedily as you can, <lb/>becauſe, the plant being now in bloom, I ap-
          <lb/>prehend its juices will neither be ſo copious <lb/>nor efficacious after its ſeeds
          are formed; <lb/>and I am very deſirous that as many more <lb/>proofs may be made of its
          virtues as poſſible <lb/>during the remains of the reaſon. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Tom's maſter, Mr. Emblin, informed me, <lb/>that he was perfectly cured of a violent
          ſcor- <lb/>butic complaint, which had afflicted him <lb/>many years, notwithſtanding he
          had taken <lb/>Maredant's drops, other noſtrums, and ſea- <lb/>water, by drinking a
          tea-cup-full of the <lb/>freſh-expreſſed juice of Clivers, or Cleavers, <lb/>commonly
          called Hariff, or Gooſe-graſs, ten <lb/>ſucceſſive mornings. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>That, being agreeably ſurpriſed at his own <lb/>extraordinary cure, he adminiſtered
          the ſame <lb/>medicine to ſeveral of his boys, who were <lb/>affected with ſcorbutic
          humours, one of them <lb/>remarkably and ſeverely; and they were <lb/>cured every one. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>That a perſon in Bow had been afflicted <lb/>ſeveral months with a violent pain in
          the <lb/>tendons of his heels, which communicated <lb/>all up the hind part of his legs,
          and was at- <lb/>tended with a great depreſſion of ſpirits; he <lb/>was under the care of
          an eminent apotheca- <lb/>ry, who treated his complaint as rheumatic, <lb/>without giving
          him any relief. Early laſt <lb/>ſpring, having heard of the cures Mr. Em- <lb/>blin had
          made of himſelf and his ſcholars, by <lb/>taking the juice of Hariff, or Gooſe-graſs, he
          <lb/>had the young plants gathered, and uſed <lb/>them as tea; but ſo ſoon as they were
          big <lb/>enough to furniſh a proper quantity of juice, <lb/>he took a tea-cup-full ten
          mornings, and is <lb/>ſo far recovered that he feels nothing of his <lb/>complaint, unleſs
          after ſevere or long exer- <pb n="604"/>
          <cb n="1"/>
          <lb/>ciſe. It is preſumed this perſon, for ſo ob- <lb/>ſtinate a complaint, ſhould have
          continued <lb/>the medicine longer. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A child in Bow, a girl about two years <lb/>old, appeared to be ſinking under a
          compli- <lb/>cation of diſeaſes. She had a ſevere wheezing <lb/>and ſhortneſs of breath, a
          ruſtling in her <lb/>breaſt, vomited a great quantity of phlegm, <lb/>had loſt her
          appetite, and got very little <lb/>ſleep; conſequently was very weak, and <lb/>judged to
          be in a dangerous way. The <lb/>child's nurſe informed its mother that ſhe <lb/>ſerved in
          a family where a young lady, ſup- <lb/>poſed to be far gone in a conſumption, was
          <lb/>perfectly cured by taking, by the direction of <lb/>a great phyſician, a tea-cup-full
          of the juice <lb/>of Hariff, or Gooſe-graſs, ſeveral times a <lb/>day, after it had been
          boiled and ſcummed <lb/>till no more ſcum would ariſe, and then cloſe <lb/>bottled. In
          conſequence of this intelligence, <lb/>the child's mother prepared and adminiſtered
          <lb/>this medicine, and in leſs than a fortnight all <lb/>the forementioned ſymptoms
          diſappeared, <lb/>the child recovered its appetite and ſleep, <lb/>and became quite
          lively. Its overjoyed pa- <lb/>rent boaſted of the recovery of her child to <lb/>an
          acquaintance, who had borne and brought <lb/>up a great number of her own, who would
          <lb/>allow no merit to the medicine, but inſiſted <lb/>the cure was owing to the return of
          warm <lb/>weather, and the child's natural ſtrength. <lb/>The medicine was left off; and,
          behold! all <lb/>the ſymptoms returned. The medicine was <lb/>adminiſtered as before; the
          child recovered <lb/>in the ſame aſtoniſhing manner, and is now <lb/>very well. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This invaluable medicine was firſt intro- <lb/>duced in the neighbourhood of Bow by a
          <lb/>maid-ſervant in a gentleman's family, the <lb/>palms of whoſe hands broke out ſo full
          of <lb/>ſores that ſhe could not uſe them. She told <lb/>her miſtreſs that ſhe muſt have
          recourſe to <lb/>her old medicine, and that would ſet her to <lb/>rights<choice>
            <corr>.</corr>
            <sic/>
          </choice> Being aſked what it was, ſhe ſaid, <lb/>that ſhe had loſt much of her time in
          ſervice <lb/>by the ſores which uſed to break out, as thoſe <lb/>ſhe had then on her
          hands, in the ſpring of <lb/>the year; that ſhe had tried abundance of <lb/>things, but
          found benefit from none; that at <lb/>laſt ſhe was ſent to an hoſpital, from which
          <lb/>ſhe was diſcharged as incurable; but was af- <lb/>terwards told of the juices of
          Hariff, or Gooſe- <lb/>graſs, which ſhe took as above, and was <lb/>perfectly cured. This
          medicine was pro- <lb/>vided; ſhe took it ten mornings, and, to the <lb/>ſurprize of her
          miſtreſs and all the family, <lb/>was perfectly cured. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A little while after this, a lad, who work- <lb/>ed in the linen-ground near Bow,
          broke out <lb/>in ſores all over his body, ſo dreadfully, that <lb/>he was reduced to uſe
          crutches for his ſup- <lb/>port. Somebody, who had heard of the cure <lb/>laſt related,
          recommended the ſame medicine <lb/>to the lad, who took it, and got ſo well as to
          <lb/>return to his work, but left the place pre- <lb/>ſently after, and hath not ſince
          been heard of. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Theſe two laſt-recited caſes coming to the <cb n="2"/>
          <lb/>knowledge of Mr. Emblin, induced him to <lb/>try the medicine; and he having related
          his <lb/>own and the forementioned cures to me, <lb/>whoſe face at that time was very
          ſore, I took <lb/>this ſimple eaſy draught ten mornings, and, <lb/>I praiſe God! am
          perfectly well recovered. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Thoſe proofs of the extraordinary powers <lb/>of this innocent taſteleſs herb, I
          think, are <lb/>ſufficient to awaken the attention of every <lb/>perſon who ſhall hear of
          them; wherefore, <lb/>I repeat my requeſt, that you will make <lb/>them public as ſoon as
          poſſible. Perhaps <lb/>ſome gentleman, whoſe province it is to care <lb/>for the health of
          Britiſh ſeamen, may take <lb/>notice of it, and recommend its trial to the <lb/>faculty;
          and if it ſhall be found to retain its <lb/>ſanative quality, when boiled and preſerved
          <lb/>in bottles, what a valuable acquiſition will it <lb/>prove! </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The idea of making the above facts known <lb/>did not occur to me ſooner, or I would
          have <lb/>attempted to have done it myſelf; but being <lb/>obliged to ſet out on my
          journey, and know- <lb/>ing the benevolence of your mind, I make no <lb/>apology for
          devolving the taſk upon you. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Remember me to, &amp;c. &amp;c. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It may be eaten with or without other ve- <lb/>getables, as a ſallad, with oil and
          vinegar. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Clivers have lately been recommended in <lb/>cancers; the juice ſhould be drunk twice
          a <lb/>day in ſuch quantities as the ſtomach will <lb/>bear, and an ointment, made by
          boiling equal <lb/>parts of hogs-lard and the juice of the Clivers, <lb/>may be applied to
          the affected part. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
