<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: An Essay on the Nerves, Digestion, Nutrition, &amp;c.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Essay on the Nerves, Digestion, Nutrition, &amp;c.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine: and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed by John Nichols, at Cicero's Head, Red Lion Passage,
                  Fleet-Street: And Sold by Eliz. Newbery, the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard,
                  Ludgate-Street. 1792. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1792</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">62</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">886</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1792_GM_0886">
    <body>
      <pb n="886"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <salute rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="sc">Urban</hi>, </salute>
      <dateline rend="align-right"><hi rend="italic">July</hi> 1. </dateline>
      <div>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi> HAVE always thought the duty of <lb/>every one to be as
          uſeful to ſociety as <lb/>he can; on that opinion I ſent you my <lb/>Diſſertation on the
          Gout, which you <lb/>were ſo obliging to publiſh in your in- <lb/>ſtructive Magazine, p.
          102, I now ſend <lb/>you a phyſiological Eſſay on the vital <lb/>powers of the human
          frame, wherein <lb/>digeſtion, nutrition, the action of the <lb/>nerves, and the
          circulation of the blood, <lb/>are deſcribed in a plain and ſimple man- <lb/>ner, and
          perhaps more agreeable to Na- <lb/>ture, than has hitherto been done; <lb/>which I hope
          you will be kind enough <lb/>to inſert as early as you poſſibly can. <lb/>I have an Eſſay
          on Vegetation, which <lb/>I alſo propoſe to ſend you ſoon. </p>
        <signed rend="align-center">
          <lb/>Yours, &amp;c. <hi rend="align-right">P—. </hi>
        </signed>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>An Eſſay on the Nerves, on Digeſtion, Nu- <lb/>trition, Circulation of the Blood. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>THE heart has always been conſi- <lb/>dered as a principal part in the circula-
          <lb/>tion of the blood. The heart is a <cb n="2"/>
          <lb/>muſcle. The motion of the muſcles is <lb/>contraction; and this contraction, let it
          <lb/>be voluntary or involuntary, is perfor- <lb/>med by the nerves; therefore, the ac-
          <lb/>tion of the nerves appears to be our firſt <lb/>enquiry. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The nerves are ſolid, fibrous veſſels, <lb/>proceeding from the brain and ſpinal
          <lb/>marrow. Theſe veſſels differ from the <lb/>blood-veſſels, which proceed from the
          <lb/>heart, in theſe things: the blood veſſels <lb/>are hollow, and contain a very percei-
          <lb/>vable fluid, the blood; they alſo pro- <lb/>ceed from the heart by a large trunk,
          <lb/>and branch out into leſs and leſs <lb/>branches, until they come to the extre-
          <lb/>mities in ſmall capillary tubes. On the <lb/>contrary, the nerves proceed from the
          <lb/>brain or ſpinal marrow in one ſmall <lb/>branch or bundle, and generally pro-
          <lb/>ceed in that manner to the muſcle to <lb/>which they belong, or to the extremi-
          <lb/>ties. This nervous bundle conſiſts of a <lb/>number of ſmall capillary fibres without
          <lb/>the leaſt perceivable cavity for contain- <lb/>ing or admitting any fluid. This has
          <lb/>occaſioned its having been diſputed, <lb/>whether the nerves act by a kind of vi-
          <lb/>bration, or by a very ſubtile fluid paſſ- <lb/>ing through them. The nerves, when
          <lb/>they proceed from the brain or ſpinal <lb/>marrow, are of a ſoft medullary ſub-
          <lb/>ſtance; and they are ſpread and become <lb/>ſoft again at their extremities. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The nerves are always filled with the <lb/>nervous fluid, which fluid, it is proba-
          <lb/>ble, is a modification of light, or per- <lb/>haps light itſelf. As light is one of
          the <lb/>firſt agents in this material ſyſtem, it is <lb/>not to be wondered at that we
          cannot <lb/>perceive it but by its actions. But, not <lb/>being able to perceive the
          nervous fluid <lb/>or light in the nerves, many have been <lb/>led to imagine that they
          contained no <lb/>fluid at all. The experiments on light <lb/>in electricity ſeem to
          explain the action <lb/>of the nervous fluid in the human frame <lb/>better than any
          other. I ſhall, there- <lb/>fore, make ſome obſervations thereon, <lb/>in order to explain
          myſelf the more <lb/>fully. It muſt be remembered that the <lb/>wires, which act as
          conductors of the <lb/>electrical light, are filled with it from <lb/>end to end, let
          their length be ever ſo <lb/>great. Thus the light is one continued <lb/>body through
          their whole length, in the <lb/>ſame manner as a leaden pipe may be <lb/>filled with
          water: thus, when more wa- <lb/>ter is forced in at one end, the ſame <lb/>quantity is
          forced out at the other at the <lb/>ſame inſtant of time. Light is the ſame <lb/>in
          electricity: as ſoon as the machine is <pb n="887"/>
          <cb n="1"/>
          <lb/>ſet in motion, the wires which commu- <lb/>nicate with it, already full from end to
          <lb/>end, inſtantaneouſly receive the puſh of <lb/>light at their farther end, let the
          diſtance <lb/>be what it will. If you cut or deſtroy <lb/>the wire in any part, the power
          of con- <lb/>ducting light is then deſtroyed; yet it is <lb/>found by the <hi
            rend="italic">Leyden vial</hi>, that this <lb/>vial, being filled with the electrical
          <lb/>fluid, may be taken and carried any diſ- <lb/>tance from the machine, and it will re-
          <lb/>tain the light therein contained if it is <lb/>not made to touch any proper body to
          <lb/>diſcharge it. Having obſerved thus <lb/>much, in order to explain myſelf the
          <lb/>better, I ſhall return to give a deſcrip- <lb/>tion of the nerves and their method of
          <lb/>acting. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The nerves derive their origin from <lb/>the medullary ſubſtance of the brain and
          <lb/>ſpinal marrow. Here the <hi rend="italic">ſoul</hi> ſeems to <lb/>be united to the
          body; here all ideas <lb/>obſerved by the different ſenſations of <lb/>the nerves are
          impreſſed, are remarked, <lb/>and laid up for the <hi rend="italic">ſoul</hi> to reaſon on
          <lb/>and compare. Here the excited mo- <lb/>tions of the nervous ſyſtem give occa-
          <lb/>ſion to thought, to reaſon; and here the <lb/><hi rend="sc">will</hi> gives new
          motions to the nervous <lb/>ſyſtem. This mutual communication or <lb/>influence we aſſume
          as a fact. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The nerves are white fibrous cords. <lb/>
          <q rend="quotes">Within the ſcull we perceive the <lb/>nerves to be the medullary
            ſubſtance <lb/>continued, and the ſpinal marrow is all <lb/>employed in forming nerves.
            Their <lb/>fibrous texture is evident at the origin <lb/>of moſt of the nerves within
            the ſcull, <lb/>and in the ſpinal marrow; they may be <lb/>divided into ſuch ſmall
            threads that a <lb/>very good eye can ſcarcely perceive <lb/>them; but theſe threads,
            when viewed <lb/>with a microſcope, appear each to be <lb/>compoſed of a great number of
            ſmaller <lb/>threads. </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Having given a deſcription of the <lb/>make and form of the nerves, and <lb/>whence
          they proceed, I ſhall now en- <lb/>deavour to ſhew their uſe and method <lb/>of acting. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The uſe of the brain ſeems to be de- <lb/>ſigned for ſeparating the nervous fluid
          <lb/>from the blood, and the receptaculum <lb/>or place for retaining it, till it be found
          <lb/>neceſſary for uſe. The nerves appear <lb/>to be adapted for containing and diſ-
          <lb/>tributing it as it is wanted! It ſeems to <lb/>appear that the nerves remain always
          <lb/>filled with this fluid, which is ſent out <lb/>from the brains, and never returns,
          but <lb/>is waſted by the voluntary and the in- <lb/>voluntary actions of the body; the
            <cb n="2"/>
          <lb/>nerves of every muſcle are filled with it, <lb/>which is continually waſted by their
          <lb/>action. Thus, by labour or any actions <lb/>of the muſcles, the nervous fluid is con-
          <lb/>tinually ſpent and waſted, which waſte <lb/>is continually reſtored from the general
          <lb/>receptacle, the brain; till, by the great <lb/>diminution, the ſtrength and vigour of
          <lb/>the body is loſt, and the perſon becomes <lb/>inſenſible about any farther action,
          but <lb/>ſinks under it and becomes ſenſeleſs and <lb/>falls aſleep. During the night's
          ſleep, <lb/>the brain continues to ſeparate and lay <lb/>up in ſtore a quantity of the
          nervous fluid, <lb/>ſo that when the perſon awakes in the <lb/>morning he finds himſelf
          capable of <lb/>performing the actions ſimilar to the day <lb/>before. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The nerves being always filled with <lb/>the nervous fluid; all muſcles, as the
          <lb/>heart, &amp;c. will have a ſpaſmodic action <lb/>after it is ſeparated from the body,
          and <lb/>this action will continue till the ner- <lb/>vous fluid is diſcharged; this power
          of <lb/>the nervous fluid is called by anatomiſts <lb/><hi rend="italic">vis inſita</hi>,
          or the inherent power; and <lb/>this power with the method of action <lb/>may be
          underſtood by obſerving the ex- <lb/>periments on the Leyden vial, which <lb/>will act
          till the electrical fluid is diſ- <lb/>charged; but the nerves which give <lb/>ſenſations,
          and act with the power of <lb/>will, muſt have a communication with <lb/>the brain; for,
          if they are cut or tied <lb/>tight with a ligature, they become inſen- <lb/>ſible, and
          loſe their power of action: <lb/>thus, <q rend="quotes">when the nerves are compreſſed,
            <lb/>cut, or in any other way deſtroyed, the <lb/>parts ſupplied with ſuch nerves,
            farther <lb/>from the head or ſpine than where the <lb/>injuring cauſe has been applied,
            have <lb/>their ſenſations, motions, and nouriſh- <lb/>ment, weakened or loſt; while no
            ſuch <lb/>defects are ſeen on the parts nearer to <lb/>the origin of the nerves; and in
            ſuch <lb/>experiments where the cauſe impeding <lb/>the nerves to exert themſelves could
            be <lb/>removed, and the ſtructure of the nerves <lb/>was not injured, as for example
            when a <lb/>ligature upon a nerve, ſtopping its in- <lb/>fluence, has been taken away,
            the mo- <lb/>tion and ſenſation of the parts were ſoon <lb/>reſtored. From which it
            appears that <lb/>the nerves are the principal inſtruments <lb/>in our ſenſations,
            motions, and that this <lb/>influence juſt now deſcribed may be <lb/>called <hi
              rend="italic">vis nervea</hi>, is not inherent in <lb/>them, unleſs the communication
            between <lb/>theſe cords and their origin is pre- <lb/>ſerved. </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>
          <q rend="quotes">From what has been obſerved, it ap- <lb/>pears that muſcular motion
            depends on <pb n="888"/>
            <cb n="1"/>
            <lb/>the influx of the nervous fluid and the <lb/>inſtantaneous conſtruction of the
            muſcle, <lb/>when the mind wills to make it act, will <lb/>be eaſily underſtood <hi
              rend="italic">from the nerves being</hi>
            <lb/>always full. </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Having explained the different opera- <lb/>tions of the nerves, and ſhewn that the
          <lb/>nervous fluid is the cauſe of the actions <lb/>of the muſcles, I ſhall deſcribe the
          other <lb/>vital powers, as digeſtion, nutrition, <lb/>the circulation of the blood,
          &amp;c. and <lb/>ſhall begin as ſoon as life commences, <lb/>or as ſoon as a child becomes
          a perfect <lb/>living animal. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>On the Life, Motions, and Actions, of the <lb/>Animal or Human Frame. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>WHILST the child is contained in <lb/>the mother's womb, it is no other than <lb/>an
          adventitious maſs or appendage of <lb/>the mother; but, as ſoon as the head is
          <lb/>projected into the world, the atmoſphere, <lb/>together with the <hi rend="italic"
            >vivifying ether</hi>, enters <lb/>its lungs, gives life to the child, and
          <lb/>henceforward it becomes a perfect liv- <lb/>ing animal; after this period, life can-
          <lb/>not be ſuſtained one minute without the <lb/>conſtant ſupply of this vivifying ether.
          <lb/>Hence, prevent air, by ſtopping the <lb/>windpipe or otherwiſe, from entering the
          <lb/>lungs, and death enſues. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Having pointed out when animal life <lb/>begins, I ſhall now endeavour to explain
          <lb/>the method made uſe of for its growth, <lb/>nouriſhment, and ſupport. Hencefor-
          <lb/>ward we find that the animal frame is <lb/>nouriſhed and ſupported by meat and
          <lb/>drink taken in by the mouth, and <lb/>thence into the ſtomach. I ſhall here
          <lb/>begin my inquiry. Before I do this, it <lb/>will be neceſſary to deſcribe the method
          <lb/>nature makes uſe of to aſſimilate the <lb/>food taken in there, for the uſes of the
          <lb/>different parts of the body. The un- <lb/>derſtanding the method nature makes
          <lb/>uſe of to digeſt the food has greatly per- <lb/>plexed phyſicians; the following de-
          <lb/>ſcription of it, perhaps, may be the <lb/>beſt: it has been obſerved that the ſto-
          <lb/>mach of animals is ſupplied with a li- <lb/>quid called the <hi rend="italic">gaſtric
            juice</hi>; this liquid <lb/>is of a very ſolvent nature, but different <lb/>in
          different animals. It is probable that <lb/>hunger proceeds from the effect this
          <lb/>juice has on an empty ſtomach! It is of <lb/>a different quality in different
          animals, <lb/>being deſigned by nature to be the ge- <lb/>neral ſolvent for the ſtomach of
          each <lb/>animal; thus this <hi rend="italic">gaſtric</hi> juice in dogs <lb/>and other
          carnivorous animals will diſ- <lb/>ſolve even bones or ivory, but will have <lb/>little
          effect on vegetables, whilſt on the <cb n="2"/>
          <lb/>contrary this gaſtric juice in ruminating <lb/>animals, as the ox, ſheep, &amp;c.
          will ea- <lb/>ſily diſſolve vegetables, but has no effect <lb/>on fleſh; but the gaſtric
          juice of the hu- <lb/>man ſtomach is capable of diſſolving, <lb/>nearly with equal eaſe,
          both animals <lb/>and vegetables. Thus the food being <lb/>admitted into the ſtomach, it
          is mixed <lb/>with the gaſtric juice, which opens and <lb/>diſſolves its parts, and by a
          kind of tri- <lb/>turation, joined to the heat and cloſe- <lb/>neſs of the ſtomach,
          diſſolves its contents, <lb/>and brings it to a thin pulp, which it <lb/>diſcharges into
          the duodenum; where <lb/>it is again mixed with the gall and pan- <lb/>creatic juice, and
          becomes a kind of <lb/>froth, and by the periſtaltic motion of <lb/>the guts is forced
          into the <hi rend="italic">dejunum</hi> and <lb/><hi rend="italic">ileum</hi>. The
          greateſt part of the lacteals <lb/>enters theſe two guts, which penetrate <lb/>through the
          whole coats of theſe guts <lb/>with their roots or ſmaller parts, through <lb/>which the
          chyle enters, and is thence <lb/>carried to the <hi rend="italic">receptaculum chyli</hi>,
          and <lb/>hence into the <hi rend="italic">vena cava</hi>. The aliment <lb/>paſſes through
          theſe guts being diſtended <lb/>with ſteam, the chyle-veſſels are open- <lb/>ed thereby,
          and the chyle forced into <lb/>them, and thence into the blood. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Thus digeſtion and nutrition appear <lb/>to be performed; but then it ſeems won-
          <lb/>derful that the ſtomach ſhould be able <lb/>to digeſt and diſſolve ſubſtances more
          <lb/>difficult to be diſſolved than the ſtomach <lb/>itſelf; but this difficulty is
          cleared up by <lb/>the ſagacious inquirer Mr. Hunter, who <lb/>has obſerved, <q
            rend="quotes">that animals of various <lb/>kinds, living in the ſtomach, are even
            <lb/>hatched and bred there; but, the mo- <lb/>ment any of theſe loſe the living prin-
            <lb/>ciple, they become ſubject to the digeſ- <lb/>tive power of the ſtomach. If, ſays
            he, <lb/>it were poſſible, for example, for a man's <lb/>hand to be introduced into the
            ſtomach <lb/>of a <hi rend="italic">living</hi> animal, and kept there for <lb/>ſome
            conſiderable time, it would be <lb/>found that the diſſolvent powers of the <lb/>ſtomach
            could have no effect upon it: <lb/>but, if the ſame hand were ſeparated <lb/>from the
            body, and introduced into the <lb/>ſame ſtomach, we ſhould find that the <lb/>ſtomach
            would immediately act upon it: <lb/>indeed, if this were not the caſe, we <note
              place="below" rend="size(0.8)">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>* After long faſting, if a perſon eats hear- <lb/>tily and fills his ſtomach,
                the gaſtric juice <lb/>being now very active, digeſtion goes on <lb/>faſt; and the
                air contained in the food, being <lb/>ſet at liberty too faſt, diſtends the ſtomach
                <lb/>more than the food itſelf, and thereby creates <lb/>flatulency, ſickneſs, pain,
                &amp;c. </p>
            </note>
            <pb n="889"/>
            <cb n="1"/>
            <lb/>ſhould find that the ſtomach itſelf ought <lb/>to have been made of indigeſtible
            ma- <lb/>terials; for, if the <hi rend="italic">living principle</hi> was <lb/>not
            capable of preſerving animal ſub- <lb/>ſtanccs from undergoing that proceſs, <lb/>the
            ſtomach itſelf would be digeſted. <lb/>But we find, on the contrary, that the
            <lb/>ſtomach, which at one inſtant, that is, <lb/>while poſſeſſed of the <hi
              rend="italic">living principle</hi>, <lb/>was capable of reſiſting the digeſtive
            <lb/>powers which it contained, the next <lb/>moment, viz. when deprived of the <hi
              rend="italic">liv- <lb/>ing principle</hi>, is itſelf capable of being <lb/>digeſted,
            either by the digeſtive powers <lb/>of other ſtomachs, or by the remains of <lb/>that
            power which it had of digeſting <lb/>other things. </q> Thus Mr. Hunter found, <lb/>
          <q rend="paradiple">that when bodies were opened ſome <lb/>time after death, whilſt the
            ſtomach <lb/>was digeſting food, a conſiderable aper- <lb/>ture is frequently found at
            the greateſt <lb/>extremity of the ſtomach, and the con- <lb/>tents of the ſtomach are
            generally found <lb/>looſe in the cavity of the abdomen. In <lb/>many ſubjects, this
            digeſtive power ex- <lb/>tends much farther than through the <lb/>ſtomach. I have found,
            ſays he, that, <lb/>after it has diſſolved the ſtomach at the <lb/>uſual place, the
            contents of the ſtomach <lb/>had come into contact with the ſpleen <lb/>and diaphragm,
            and had partly diſſolved <lb/>the adjacent ſide of the ſpleen. </q> By the <lb/>above
          obſervations of Mr. Hunter it ap- <lb/>pears, that by digeſtion continuing ſome <lb/>time
          after death, and the <hi rend="italic">living principle</hi>
          <lb/>being deſtroyed from the bottom of the <lb/>ſtomach, the contents therein ſtill con-
          <lb/>tinuing their digeſting power, they di- <lb/>geſted and diſſolved the ſtomach itſelf,
          <lb/>nay, that the digeſtive power was car- <lb/>ried by the contents of the ſtomach to
          <lb/>the ſpleen, and partly diſſolved it. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>From what has been ſaid it may be <lb/>obſerved, that the food, after being diſ-
          <lb/>ſolved and digeſted in the ſtomach, is <lb/>carried into the jejenum, &amp;c. which
          <lb/>are filled with chyle-veſſels, by which <lb/>the chyle is conveyed into the vena
          <lb/>cava, and thence, through the pul- <cb n="2"/>
          <lb/>monary artery, into the lungs, the <lb/>blood-veſſels of which it completely fills
          <lb/>to the ſmalleſt capillary exhalent veſſels <lb/>which enter the air-veſicles of the
          tra- <lb/>chea, and the air contained in them is <lb/>heated, rarefied, and expanded, by
          <lb/>which means the moiſt vapour breath is <lb/>forced out by the mouth; at this mo-
          <lb/>ment the atmoſphere, with all its weight <lb/>or force <note place="bottom"
            rend="size(0.8)" n="*">
            <cb n="1 2" type="footnote"/>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Thus the hot ſteam exhaling from the exhaling arteries enters the bronchia, or
              air- <lb/>veſſels of the lungs, rarefies and expands the air contained therein, and,
              by its heat, cauſes <lb/>a vacuum, and gives leaſt reſiſtance to the preſſure of the
              atmoſphere, the power of which <lb/>is greater than it is often conſidered to be, its
              weight being more than 3000lb. and ſufficient <lb/>to raiſe a column of water more
              than thirty feet in height. This preſſure is greater or leſs, <lb/>in proportion to
              the rarefaction or heat of the blood thrown into the lungs. </p>
          </note>, preſſes through the mouth <lb/>into the lungs, and with it the <hi rend="italic"
            >vivify- <lb/>ing ether</hi>
          <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.8)" n="†">
            <cb n="1 2" type="footnote"/>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>† This vivifying ether being of a moſt ſubtile and penetrating nature enters the
              blood- <lb/>veſſels, and adds life and activity to the blood, and perhaps acts on it
              in the ſame manner as <lb/>cold air or ether does when it enters a fire, which it
              blows up and enlivens. </p>
          </note>; this meeting the blood and <lb/>chyle, which, together with the friction
          <lb/>through the blood-veſſels of the lungs, <lb/>gives freſh heat, colour, and activity,
          <lb/>to the blood. Hence, the cold atmo- <lb/>ſphere having filled every veſicle of the
          <lb/>lungs, by its great weight, ſtrength, <lb/>and power, forces the blood from the
          <lb/>ſmall veſſels of the lungs into the larger, <lb/>and preſſes the blood into the four
          pul- <lb/>monary veins, which open into the left <lb/>auricle of the heart <note
            place="bottom" rend="size(0.8)" n="‡">
            <cb n="1 2" type="footnote"/>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>‡ On the preſſure of the air into the lungs the blood is prevented from returning
              back into <lb/>the right auricle of the heart by the <hi rend="italic">creſcent
                membrane</hi>, or valve. This valve was diſcovered <lb/>by <hi rend="italic"
                >Euſtachius</hi>. </p>
          </note>, and thence in- <lb/>to the left ventricle, which it diſtends <lb/>till its power
          is ſufficient to open the <lb/>valve of the aorta. As ſoon as this is <lb/>done, the power
          of the blood diſtending <lb/>the heart being removed into the aorta, <lb/>the <hi
            rend="italic">vis inſita</hi> of the nerves forces the <lb/>heart to contract, and throw
          out the <lb/>blood it contained into the aorta; by <lb/>which force, together with the
          power in <lb/>the blood itſelf, and the contractive <lb/>power of the arteries, forces the
          blood <lb/>from valve to valve, and from artery to <lb/>artery, till it arrives into the
          ſmalleſt <lb/>capillary arteries on the ſurface of the <lb/>body, where they unite with
          the ſmalleſt <lb/>veins: but theſe very ſmall arteries and <lb/>veins are not diſcoverable
          unleſs in ſome <lb/>particular parts of living animals, and <lb/>in them by the microſcope
          only; but the <lb/>microſcope itſelf has not enabled us to <lb/>perceive the orifices of
          the <hi rend="italic">exhalent</hi>
          <lb/>branches of arteries. The veins have <lb/>been proved to have no inhalent ori-
          <lb/>fices. The ſweat is diſcharged by the <lb/>arteries; they are the only veſſels which
          <lb/>carry fluids towards the ſkin. The red <pb n="890"/>
          <cb n="1"/>
          <lb/>veins and lymphaticks have their fluids <lb/>in the oppoſite courſe, that is, towards
          <lb/>the heart or centre. The ſmall arteries, <lb/>or their exhalents, are conſtantly
          throw- <lb/>ing out a fluid into all the cavities of <lb/>the body, to keep the ſurfaces
          moiſt, <lb/>and make motion eaſy. This fluid <lb/>would accumulate, and produce drop-
          <lb/>ſies, if its redundance were not carried <lb/>off by the <hi rend="italic">cellular
            membrane</hi>
          <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.8)">
            <cb n="1 2" type="footnote"/>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* The uſes of the cellular membrane ſeem at preſent not to be perfectly
              underſtood. It <lb/>ſeems to appear that, when we drink more than is neceſſary for the
              ſupport of our body, <lb/>and faſter than it can be carried off by perſpiration, it is
              ſecreted on the cellular membrane, <lb/>and carried by that membrane to the ureters
              and kidneys, where it is readily and plentifully <lb/>diſcharged. This appears to be
              the quick and eaſy method Nature makes uſe of when a <lb/>large quantity of liquids
              are drunk. That the cellular membrane acts in this manner ſeems <lb/>to be confirmed
              by ſcarifications on the legs of dropſical perſons; thoſe ſcarifications need <lb/>to
              be no deeper than juſt through the ſkin, to reach the cellular membrane, by which
              means <lb/>a drain or outlet for the water is made; and, as the water runs off from
              the parts near the <lb/>ſcarifications, theſe voids continue to be immediately filled
              again by other water near them. <lb/>This appears to be the caſe if you rub the arms,
              legs, &amp;c. with oil of turpentine; as ſoon <lb/>as its volatile parts enter the
              cellular membrane, it is carried, with the liquid contained <lb/>therein, to the
              kidneys and bladder, and gives a violet-ſmell to the urine. </p>
          </note> and ab- <lb/>ſorbed by the lymphaticks. The lymph <lb/>abſorbed by the lymphaticks
          may be <lb/>ſuppoſed to be particularly uſeful (tho' <lb/>at preſent we do not know its
          uſe). Mr. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Cruikſhank</hi> ſuſpects that this fluid is in <lb/>part
          the coagulable lymph of the blood. <lb/>This fluid is certainly different from <lb/>that
          exhaled on the ſurfaces of the body; <lb/>this coagulating from extravaſation, or
          <lb/>from reſt in the dead body. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Thus it may be obſerved, that the <lb/>blood, forced by the heart and arteries
          <lb/>to the ſmalleſt arteries on the ſurface of <lb/>the body, part of it enters the
          ſmalleſt <lb/>capillary veins, whilſt other parts are <lb/>ſecreted into the cellular
          membrane, <lb/>and other parts are exhaled by the pores <lb/>of the ſkin. The influence of
          the heart <lb/>and arteries having performed their of- <lb/>fice, another power is
          neceſſary to re- <lb/>turn the blood through the veins to the <lb/>heart. This is the
          preſſure of the at- <lb/>moſphere, together with the contractile <lb/>power of the veſſels
          themſelves. The <lb/>preſſure of the atmoſphere, as has been <lb/>obſerved, is more than
          3000lb weight, <lb/>and muſt have great influence in forcing <lb/>the blood from the ſmall
          veins into the <lb/>larger, and ſo on to the vena cava; this <lb/>is rendered more eaſy as
          it meets with <lb/>no reſiſtance, but, on the contrary, <lb/>there is a kind of
          attraction, as the lar- <lb/>ger veins into which they enter are <lb/>nearer the centre,
          and contain more <lb/>heat. When they arrive at the vena <lb/>cava, the blood, together
          with a freſh <lb/>addition of chyle, is thrown into the <lb/>heart and lungs, to undergo
          the ſame <lb/>circulation as before. </p>
        <signed rend="align-right">P—. </signed>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
