<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Review of New Publications. The London Medical Journal. Vol.
          XI. Part I. 8vo. </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Review of New Publications. The London Medical Journal. Vol. XI. Part I. 8vo.
            </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine: and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed by John Nichols, at Cicero's Head, Red Lion Passage,
                  Fleet-Street: And Sold by Eliz. Newbery, the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard,
                  Ludgate-Street. 1792. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1792</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">62</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">354</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1792_GM_0354">
    <body>
      <pb n="354"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <head rend="italic align-center">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">67.</hi> The <hi rend="roman">London</hi> Medical Journal. <lb/>Vol.
        XI. Part I. 8vo. </head>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">ARTICLE I.</hi> A Caſe of Suppreſſion <lb/>of Urine, in which Relief was
        obtained <lb/>from puncturing the Bladder above the <lb/>Pubis, but which afterwards
        terminated <lb/>fatally; with an Account of the Appear- <lb/>ances on Diſſection: and ſome
        Remarks on <lb/>the Paracenteſis of the Bladder. Commu- <lb/>nicated, in a Letter to Dr. <hi
          rend="roman">Simmons</hi>, <lb/>F. R. S. by Mr. <hi rend="roman">Francis Turner</hi>,
        Surgeon <lb/>at <hi rend="roman">Yarmouth</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Art. II.</hi> Caſe of a Schirrous Affec- <lb/>tion of the Stomach; with
        an Account of <lb/>the Appearances on Diſſection. By Mr. <lb/><hi rend="roman">William
          Loftie</hi>, Surgeon at <hi rend="roman">Canterbury</hi>. <lb/>Communicated in a Letter to
          <hi rend="roman">John Hun- <lb/>ter</hi>, Eſq. F.R.S. and by him to Dr. <lb/><hi
          rend="roman">Simmons</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Art. III.</hi> Farther Account of a new <lb/>Method of treating Diſeaſes
        of the Joints <lb/>of the Knee and Elbow. Communicated, <lb/>in a Letter to Dr. <hi
          rend="roman">Simmons</hi>, by Mr. <hi rend="roman">H. <lb/>Park</hi>, one of the Surgeons
        of the <hi rend="roman">Liver- <lb/>pool</hi> Infirmary. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the year 1783 Mr. Park publiſhed <lb/>a very ingenious pamphlet, pointing out a
        <lb/>mode of treating ſome of the affections <lb/>of the large articulations, which he then
        <lb/>thought had not been before attempted <lb/>by any other practitioner. This new
        <lb/>method he illuſtrated by an account of a <lb/>caſe in which he had adopted it with
        <lb/>ſucceſs. In the paper now before us he <lb/>with great candour relates an inſtance of
        <lb/>a ſecond attempt of the ſame nature, <lb/>which proved as unfortunate as the firſt
        <lb/>was ſucceſsful; and adds a letter from <lb/>Mr. Filkin, ſurgeon at Northwich, giv-
        <lb/>ing an account of a ſimilar operation, <lb/>performed with ſucceſs by that gentle-
        <lb/>man's father, about thirty years ago, but <lb/>with which Mr. Park was totally unac-
        <lb/>quainted till after the publication of his <lb/>pamphlet. </p>
      <pb n="355"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Art. IV.</hi> Obſervations on the Uſe of <lb/>Electricity in Deafneſs.
        Communicated, <lb/>in a Letter to Dr. <hi rend="roman">Simmons</hi>, by Mr. <lb/><hi
          rend="roman">William Blizard</hi>, F. R. S. and S. A. <lb/>Surgeon of the <hi rend="roman"
          >London</hi> Hoſpital. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In certain caſes of deafneſs, and of <lb/>obſtruction in the Euſtachian tube, Mr.
        <lb/>Blizard recommends the uſe of electri- <lb/>city. In ſuch caſes he tranſmits the
        <lb/>electric ſhock, by that tube, through the <lb/>drum of the ear. Several inſtances of
        <lb/>the good effects of this remedy are re- <lb/>lated; and annexed to the paper is an
        <lb/>engraving illuſtrative of this mode of <lb/>treatment. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Art.V.</hi> Obſervations on the <hi rend="roman">Anguſ- <lb/>tura</hi>
        Bark. Communicated, in a Letter <lb/>to Dr. <hi rend="roman">Simmons</hi>, F. R. S. by <hi
          rend="roman">Auguſtus <lb/>Brande</hi>, Eſq. Apothecary to the Queen. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This new and valuable drug, of which <lb/>the firſt accounts appeared in <hi
          rend="italic">The London <lb/>Medical Journal</hi>, vol. X. may be conſi- <lb/>dered as an
        acquiſition of no ſmall im- <lb/>portance to our <hi rend="italic">Materia Medica</hi>. It
        is <lb/>adminiſtered in caſes in which the uſe of <lb/>the Peruvian bark (to which it has
        the <lb/>greateſt affinity) is indicated; and, as a <lb/>tonic and ſtomachic, it has been
        conſider- <lb/>ed, by many who have tried it, as being <lb/>ſuperior to that celebrated
        drug. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Art. VI.</hi> Caſe of a Woman who un- <lb/>derwent the Section of the
        Symphyſis Pu- <lb/>bis. By Mr. <hi rend="roman">John Welchman</hi>, Surgeon <lb/>at <hi
          rend="roman">Kington</hi>, in <hi rend="roman">Warwickſhire</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This caſe is extremely intereſting, and <lb/>is the only inſtance, we believe, of the
        <lb/>operation being performed in this coun- <lb/>try. It was unſucceſsful; but the death
        <lb/>of the patient muſt be aſcribed rather to <lb/>her own imprudence than to the ope-
        <lb/>ration. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Art. VII.</hi> Some Remarks on Hydro- <lb/>cephalus Internus.
        Communicated, in a <lb/>Letter to Dr. <hi rend="roman">Simmons</hi>, F. R. S. by Mr.
          <lb/><hi rend="roman">Edward Ford</hi>, Surgeon of the <hi rend="roman">Weſtmin-
          <lb/>ſter</hi> General Diſpenſary. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The account here given of the diſeaſe <lb/>in queſtion is illuſtrated by two caſes, in
        <lb/>which Mr. Ford had an opportunity of <lb/>aſcertaining the morbid appearances in
        <lb/>the brain by diſſection. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Art. VIII.</hi> Some Account of a new <lb/>Extract of Bark, prepared in
          <hi rend="roman">South Ame- <lb/>rica</hi>. Communicated, in a Letter to Dr. <lb/><hi
          rend="roman">Simmons</hi>, by <hi rend="roman">William Saunders</hi>, M. D. <lb/>Phyſician
        to <hi rend="roman">Guy's</hi> Hoſpital. </p>
      <floatingText rend="size(0.8)">
        <body>
          <head rend="align-center">
            <lb/>
            <q rend="diple">To Dr. <hi rend="sc">Simmons</hi>. </q>
          </head>
          <salute rend="indent">
            <lb/>
            <q rend="diple" >Dear Sir, </q>
          </salute>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>
            <q rend="paradiple" >Agreeably to your requeſt, I now ſend <lb/>you the
              following particulars relative to the <lb/>new extract of Peruvian bark prepared in
              <lb/>South America, and lately imported into this <cb n="2"/>
              <lb/>country from Spain as an article of com- <lb/>merce. </q>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>
            <q rend="paradiple" >It is of a conſiſtence between the ſoft <lb/>and hard
              extracts of the ſhops; of a dark <lb/>colour, and beautifully tranſparent. It is
              <lb/>extremely ſoluble in the mouth, and has <lb/>none of that empyreumatic or burnt
              taſte, <lb/>ſo common to all extracts, and which ob- <lb/>ſcures their original powers
              ſo much as to <lb/>have brought them into general diſcredit. It <lb/>has the taſte and
              flavour of the beſt Peruvian <lb/>bark in a very concentrated form. It is very
              <lb/>ſoluble in boiling water; and when gently <lb/>agitated with it, in the
              proportion of two <lb/>drachms to a pint of water, it gives an im- <lb/>pregnation
              more powerful than that of a <lb/>decoction of bark in the proportion of an <lb/>ounce
              of bark to a pint of water, prepared <lb/>agreeably to the uſual formula for that pur-
              <lb/>poſe. It is more difficultly ſoluble in cold <lb/>water. </q>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>
            <q rend="paradiple" >One ounce of it, ſoftened with two <lb/>ounces of boiling
              water, and digeſted with <lb/>one quart of proof ſpirit, in a gentle heat, <lb/>gives
              a more powerful tincture than that of <lb/>the Diſpenſatory; the reſiduum left on the
              <lb/>filter weighs two ſcruples, and is perfectly <lb/>inſipid. </q>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>
            <q rend="paradiple" >It differs very materially from all other <lb/>extracts of
              bark with which it has been <lb/>compared; and even from ſome which was <lb/>carefully
              prepared from the beſt bark, and <lb/>ſlowly evaporated in a water-bath. In its
              <lb/>union with boiling water it reſembles ſo <lb/>much the decoction of the pale
              bark, both <lb/>in colour and ſenſible qualities, that the dif- <lb/>ference is not
              perceptible; and by this ſyn- <lb/>thetic teſt it may be diſtinguiſhed from all
              <lb/>other extracts of bark. </q>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>
            <q rend="paradiple" >In collecting, from various druggiſts, <lb/>extracts, with
              a view to a compariſon, many <lb/>of them evidently appeared to be ſophiſti-
              <lb/>cated by being chiefly compoſed of the ex- <lb/>tract of gentian, an article of
              the <hi rend="italic">Materia <lb/>Medica</hi> better formed for that proceſs than
              <lb/>almoſt any other. </q>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>
            <q rend="paradiple" >No information has been received rela- <lb/>tive to the
              method of preparing this extract <lb/>in South America; we are therefore left to
              <lb/>conjecture that it may have the advantage of <lb/>an aqueous ſolution from recent
              vegetable <lb/>matter, and that the inſpiſſation or evapora- <lb/>tion is conducted by
              an expoſure to air and <lb/>the heat of the ſun. </q>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>
            <q rend="paradiple" >All who have ſeen it admit its ſuperior <lb/>elegance, and
              that it poſſeſſes the ſenſible <lb/>qualities of the beſt bark in the moſt ſoluble
              <lb/>and concentrated form. I have made fre- <lb/>quent trials of it both in the
              hoſpital and in <lb/>private practice, and have uniformly found <lb/>that it has done
              every thing which could be <lb/>expected from the beſt Peruvian bark in any <lb/>form.
              I have had the ſame favourable re- <lb/>port of its operation from other
              practitioners. </q>
          </p>
          <pb n="356"/>
          <cb n="1"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>
            <q rend="paradiple" >It ſits eaſy on the ſtomach; and in caſes <lb/>of great
              emergence, as in gangrene and ma- <lb/>lignant fevers, or the putrid diſeaſes of warm
              <lb/>climates, where the life of a patient may de- <lb/>pend on the quantity of
              efficacious bark <lb/>taken in a few hours, it muſt have a decided <lb/>advantage. A
              patient may take four ounces <lb/>of this extract in a day, a quantity equal, in
              <lb/>power and effect, to a pound and a half of <lb/>the beſt bark. </q>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>
            <q rend="paradiple" >It is found efficacious in the cure of fe- <lb/>vers, in
              the form of a clyſter; for which <lb/>purpoſe I have diſſolved a drachm of it in
              <lb/>four ounces of water. This method of pre- <lb/>ſcribing it is well adapted to
              children, and <lb/>to ſuch patients as cannot retain bark in any <lb/>form on the
              ſtomach. </q>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>
            <q rend="paradiple" >The quantity at preſent in this country, <lb/>I am
              informed, is all that has been introduced <lb/>into Europe; and, unleſs frauds are
              commit- <lb/>ted, and it becomes the ſubject of adultera- <lb/>tion, it promiſes to
              become a very important <lb/>acquiſition to the liſt of our uſeful and active
              <lb/>remedies. </q>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>
            <q rend="paradiple">The ſolution of it in boiling water will <lb/>be found a
              ready and eaſy ſubſtitute for the <lb/>decoction of bark, and at an expence not ex-
              <lb/>ceeding the decoction of ſuch bark as ought <lb/>generally to be employed. </q>
          </p>
          <signed rend="indent">
            <lb/>
            <q rend="diple">I am, dear Sir, yours ſincerely, <lb/><hi rend="sc align-right"
                >William Saunders. </hi>
            </q>
          </signed>
          <dateline rend="italic">
            <lb/>
            New Broad Street, Feb. 11, 1790. 
          </dateline>
        </body>
      </floatingText>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/>
        <hi rend="sc">Art. IX.</hi> Obſervations on the Pro- <lb/>perties commonly attributed by
        Medical <lb/>Writers to Human Milk, on the Changes <lb/>it undergoes in Digeſtion, and the
        Diſeaſes <lb/>ſuppoſed to originate from this Source in <lb/>Infancy. By <hi rend="roman"
          >Joſeph Clarke</hi>, M. D. M. <lb/>R. I. A. From the Tranſactions of the <lb/>Royal <hi
          rend="roman">Iriſh</hi> Academy, for the Year 1788. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Art. X.</hi> A botanical and medical Ac- <lb/>count of the Quaſſia
        Simaruba, or Tree <lb/>which produces the Cortex Simaruba. <lb/>By <hi rend="roman">William
          Wright</hi>, M. D. F. R. S. <lb/><hi rend="roman">Lond.</hi> and <hi rend="roman"
          >Edin.</hi> and Phyſician General <lb/>in <hi rend="roman">Jamaica</hi>. From the
        Tranſactions of <lb/>the Royal Society of <hi rend="roman">Edinburgh</hi>, Vol. II. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The firſt knowledge we had of the Si- <lb/>maruba bark was in the year 1713, when
        <lb/>ſome of it was ſent to France; but the <lb/>tree that produces it does not ſeem to
        <lb/>have been accurately aſcertained till the <lb/>year 1772, when Dr. Wright diſcovered
        <lb/>it in Jamaica, and ſent ſpecimens of its <lb/>fructification, in ſpirits, to Europe.
        This <lb/>tree, of which we have here a very ſatiſ- <lb/>factory deſcription, is ſaid to be
        common <lb/>in all the woodlands in Jamaica, where <lb/>it grows to a great height and
        conſider- <lb/>able thickneſs. It is known in Jamaica <lb/>by the names of Mountain Damſon,
        <lb/>Bitter Damſon, and Stave Wood, which <lb/>latter name it has gotten from its wood <cb
          n="2"/>
        <lb/>ſplitting freely, and making excellent <lb/>ſtaves for ſugar hogſheads. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>With the bark of this tree, which is <lb/>the true <hi rend="italic">Cortex
          Simaruba</hi> of the ſhops, <lb/>we have hitherto been ſupplied chiefly <lb/>from Guiana;
        but now, it ſeems, we <lb/>have it from our own iſlands, at a mode- <lb/>rate expence. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
