<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: An Analysis of the Medicinal Water of Tunbridge
          Wells.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Analysis of the Medicinal Water of Tunbridge Wells. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine: and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed by John Nichols, at Cicero's Head, Red Lion Passage,
                  Fleet-Street: And Sold by Eliz. Newbery, the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard,
                  Ludgate-Street. 1792. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1792</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">62</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">447a</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1792_GM_0447">
    <body>
      <pb n="447"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <head rend="italic align-center">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">80.</hi> An Analyſis of the Medicinal Water of <lb/><hi rend="roman"
          >Tunbridge Wells</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">FOR many years the water was collect- <lb/>ed in two <hi rend="italic"
            >open</hi> ſtone baſons, perforated at the <lb/>bottom, and ſo placed over the ſprings
          that, <lb/>as the water roſe, it flowed into the baſons <lb/>from below, whilſt the waſte
          water paſſed <lb/>off by means of notches made in the edges <lb/>of the baſons for that
          purpoſe. But, very <lb/>lately, <hi rend="italic">one</hi> of theſe has been changed for a
          <lb/>baſon of marble, over which is fitted a mar- <lb/>ble dome, ſo as to incloſe it
          completely, ex- <lb/>cept at the marble notch, or opening, which <lb/>gives exit to the
          water nearly as uſual. This <lb/>alteration, inconſiderible as it may appear, <lb/>has
          given riſe to a difference of opinion; <lb/>ſome conceiving, that by thus excluding the
          <lb/>contact of the atmoſphere, the water was <lb/>not likely to loſe ſo much either of
          the elaſ- <lb/>tic fluids it contained, or of its properties as <lb/>a chalybeate; others,
          that by being deprived - <cb n="2"/>
          <lb/>of the cuſtom of dipping their veſſels into <lb/>the ſpring, as formerly, they have
          not the <lb/>water from ſo near the fountain-head, and, <lb/>conſequently, not ſo freſh
          and efficacious. <lb/>How far theſe opinions may be reconciled, <lb/>will be ſeen by the
          analyſis here ſubmitted; <lb/>which, it is hoped, will alſo determine two <lb/>other
          material poſitions, much diſputed by <lb/>authors, whether there be any eſſential dif-
          <lb/>ference between the waters of the <hi rend="italic">two</hi>
          <lb/>ſprings as they originally ſtood, and what is <lb/>the true nature of their
          impregnation. </q> pp. <lb/>2, 3. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">The author proved, by the moſt ſatiſ- <lb/>factory experiments, that the
          only advan- <lb/>tage that can be derived to the ſpring by a <lb/>cover is cleanlineſs,
          and that the water is <lb/>not alterable by its being either expoſed or <lb/>covered, ſo
          long as ſuch covering does not <lb/>entirely exclude the external air. The pro-
          <lb/>prietor, in compliance with the general opi- <lb/>nion, removed the cover; and the
          original <lb/>object of the preſent publication was thus <lb/>ſuperſeded. The author,
          however, finding <lb/>himſelf under ſome ſort of engagement to <lb/>ſatisfy the curioſity
          of friends, and reflecting <lb/>that no accurate analyſis of the Tunbridge <lb/>waters had
          hitherto been given, now offers <lb/>to the publick theſe pages, as the reſult of
          <lb/>careful experiments; wiſhing, at the ſame <lb/>time, not to appear to have been
          inattentive <lb/>to this particular ſubject, ſince it is not un- <lb/>reaſonable to
          ſuppoſe that a ſcientific inquiry <lb/>into the component parts of theſe ſprings <lb/>may,
          in ſome meaſure, aſſiſt us with reſpect <lb/>to the right application of them in medicine.
          <lb/>He likewiſe takes this opportunity of pub- <lb/>licly acknowledging his obligations
          to the <lb/>ingenious Mr. Babington, of Guy's hoſpital, <lb/>by whoſe ſkill and dexterity
          in executing <lb/>chemical experiments he was greatly aſſiſted <lb/>in this analyſis. </q>
        Introd. p. vi—viii. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
