<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Review of New Publications. The London Medical Journal. Vol.
          XI. Parts II. and III.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Review of New Publications. The London Medical Journal. Vol. XI. Parts II. and
              III.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine: and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed by John Nichols, at Cicero's Head, Red Lion Passage,
                  Fleet-Street: And Sold by Eliz. Newbery, the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard,
                  Ludgate-Street. 1792. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1792</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">62</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">1202</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1792_GM_1202">
    <body>
      <pb n="1202"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <head rend="italic align-center">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">279.</hi> The London Medical Journal. <lb/>Vol. XI. Parts II. and III.
        8vo. </head>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">ARTICLE I.</hi> A Caſe of Retention of <lb/>Urine, in which a Puncture
        of the Blad- <lb/>der, in the Hypogaſtric Region, proved, <lb/>under very unpromiſing
        Circumſtances, <lb/>ſucceſsful; to which are added, Three <lb/>other Caſes of Retention of
        Urine, and <lb/>ſome Remarks on Diſeaſes of the Urinary <lb/>Bladder. By Mr. <hi
          rend="roman">James Lucas</hi>, one of <lb/>the Surgeons of the General Infirmary at
          <lb/><hi rend="roman">Leeds</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Theſe caſes, which are all of them <lb/>extremely intereſting, cannot well be
        <lb/>abridged. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">II.</hi> An Account of the ſingular Effects <lb/>of Muſick on a
        Patient. By the ſame. </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">The ſon of a reſpectable farmer at Haſe- <lb/>wood was ſeized with a
          ſlow fever in March, <lb/>1759, by which, in eight weeks, he was re- <lb/>duced to a very
          weak ſtate. He was a ſtran- <lb/>ger to any intemperance; and, although of a <lb/>grave
          diſpoſition, there was no reaſon what- <lb/>ever to ſuſpect inſanity. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">On the 29th of May, a company of <lb/>young perſons paſſed by the houſe,
          carrying <lb/>oaken boughs, and playing upon a fiddle: <lb/>he no ſooner heard the muſick
          than he <lb/>ſtarted up in bed, ſeemed tranſported with <lb/>joy, and cried aloud, <q
            rend="quotes">Dance! dance! </q> The <lb/>young man had played upon the flute, but
          <lb/>had never been accuſtomed to dance. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">For two or three days he continued, al- <lb/>moſt inceſſantly, calling
          out <q rend="diple quotes">Dance! dance! <lb/>For God's ſake let me dance! </q> though his
          <lb/>father took uncommon pains to convince him <lb/>of the impropriety and danger of
          fatiguing <lb/>himſelf when in ſo weak a condition. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">On the arrival of a muſician, he exerted <lb/>himſelf in putting on his
          cloaths; and imme- <lb/>diately, upon hearing a ſtring of the violin <lb/>touched, he
          ſtarted back, and for a while <lb/>ſtood motionleſs; but, upon a tune being <lb/>played,
          he danced with great agility, though <lb/>in a ſtrange, frightful, and involuntary man-
          <lb/>ner. The muſick would often cauſe him at <lb/>firſt to move a hand; then a foot; a
          nodding <lb/>of the head would ſometimes follow; and he <lb/>would ſuddenly ſtart from his
          chair, make <lb/>the moſt ridiculous and antic diſtortions with <lb/>the muſcles of his
          face, and ſhake his limbs <lb/>as if he was by deſign acting the part of a
          <lb/>Scaramouch, or Merry Andrew. After he <lb/>had fallen upon the floor, the continuing
          of <lb/>the muſick would repeatedly rouſe him, un- <lb/>til fatigue prevented him from
          being affected <lb/>by the ſound. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">To this very ſtrange inclination he was <lb/>ſubject daily for about
          three weeks: the af- <lb/>fection ſometimes remained from then to <lb/>twenty minutes; at
          other times for two or <lb/>three hours together. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">His furious and menacing geſtures cauſed <lb/>ſtrangers to be much
          alarmed with him. He <pb n="1203"/>
          <cb n="1"/>
          <lb/>had a great averſion to a gloomy counte- <lb/>nance, but ſeemed to be much pleaſed
          with <lb/>a cheerful one. Although his motions were <lb/>too rapid to be voluntary, yet
          they appeared <lb/>to keep time with the muſick. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">Slow tunes, or even changing the tune, <lb/>provoked him much, unleſs it
          was to a more <lb/>lively one: if the change was made even the <lb/>following day, he was
          immediately ſenſible <lb/>of it. He would, for ſome hours together, <lb/>have a ſecret
          wiſh for muſick, though he did <lb/>not diſcover it until it was conjectured, by <lb/>his
          ſilence and anxiety, that he wanted it. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">As he was once dancing with great <lb/>alertneſs, it happened that a
          ſtring of the <lb/>fiddle broke; and, although the muſician <lb/>continued to play upon
          three ſtrings, the <lb/>young man ſtood motionleſs and was, for a <lb/>long time, much out
          of humour, ſaying, that <lb/>he was unable to deſcribe the diſagreeable <lb/>ſenſations
          produced in him by this accident. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">The fatigue of dancing made him per- <lb/>ſpire profuſely, and he was
          frequently ob- <lb/>liged to go to bed immediately; yet he was <lb/>ſo nuch relieved by
          it, that he ſlept better, <lb/>and in a few days after he began this exer- <lb/>ciſe he
          was able to walk near half a mile to <lb/>church. Upon obſerving that his ſpirits were
          <lb/>low in the evening, the fiddler was mention- <lb/>ed; when he acknowledged that he
          had <lb/>been endeavouring to conceal his deſire to <lb/>have him, becauſe it was Sunday.
        </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">During theſe uncommon attacks, a tune <lb/>called Tarantula was played
          to him, which <lb/>cauſed him to move after other tunes had <lb/>failed; but this was
          ſuppoſed to depend <lb/>merely on its being a very lively air. When <lb/>the fit was gone
          off, the action entirely ſub- <lb/>ſided, and he expreſſed great pleaſure at the
          <lb/>relief which it had afforded him. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">Such ſevere exerciſe frequently produced <lb/>a ſtiffneſs and itching in
          his limbs. To re- <lb/>move this uneaſineſs, he would ſometimes <lb/>prick them with holly
          until they bled. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">Inſtead of the periodical inclination for <lb/>muſick, he, by degrees,
          became ſeized with <lb/>convulſive fits, during which his hands were <lb/>clinched, his
          limbs ſtiff and immoveable, his <lb/>eyes rolled, his countenance was wild; he <lb/>kicked
          off the bed-cloaths; would not ſuffer <lb/>any one to ſpeak to him, or ſo much as to
          <lb/>look at him. He became inſenſible, ſpeech- <lb/>leſs, and had a locked jaw, which
          once con- <lb/>tinued ſo as to prevent him taking any nou- <lb/>riſhment for at leaſt 24
          hours. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">The convulſions ſometimes ceaſed in a <lb/>quarter of an hour; at others
          continued for <lb/>many hours. At firſt they were ſlight, and <lb/>ſoon over; but were
          afterwards more vio- <lb/>lent, and of longer duration. Upon his re- <lb/>covery, he
          remarked, that he did not ſuffer <lb/>ſo much during a fit as his friends ſeemed to
          <lb/>apprehend. His ſpaſmodic ſymptoms gra- <lb/>dually abated, but were ſucceeded by a
          hectic <lb/>fever, of which he died the latter end of <lb/>December. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">Dr. Dealtry, of York, and ſeveral other <lb/>medical gentlemen, were
          conſulted in this <lb/>uncommon caſe. The diſorder was ſaid, by <lb/>ſome, to be St.
          Vitus's dance; but, beſides <lb/>the effects of muſick, the motions ſubſiding, <lb/>and
          only returning at the time of a fit, ren- <lb/>dered the complaint materially different.
          It <lb/>did not appear that the patient had been bit- <lb/>ten by any inſect, or had read
          any account of <lb/>the tarantula before the 29th of May; nor <lb/>is it any wiſe probable
          that he was one of <lb/>thoſe impoſtors deſcribed as tarantuliſts. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">III.</hi> A Caſe of fractured Ribs, which <lb/>terminated fatally;
        with the Appear- <lb/>ances on Diſſection, and Remarks<choice>
          <corr>.</corr>
          <sic/>
        </choice> Com- <lb/>municated, in a Letter to Dr. <hi rend="roman">Simmons</hi>, <lb/>F. R.
        S. by Mr. <hi rend="roman">George Wilkinſon</hi>, Sur- <lb/>geon at <hi rend="roman"
          >Sunderland</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">IV.</hi> Caſe of an Abſceſs in the lower <lb/>Part of the Belly, which
        communicated <lb/>with the lnteſtine, and terminated fatally. <lb/>By Mr. <hi rend="roman"
          >George Grant</hi>, Surgeon. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">V.</hi> Extract of a Letter from Mr. <hi rend="roman">Phi- <lb/>lip
          Werner</hi>, Surgeon of the Royal Navy, <lb/>and of the <hi rend="roman">Britiſh</hi>
        Factory at <hi rend="roman">Algiers</hi>, to <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="roman">Simmons</hi>,
        containing ſome Account <lb/>of the Inoculation of the Small-pox at <lb/><hi rend="roman"
          >Algiers</hi>; together with other Miſcella- <lb/>neous Obſervations. </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">I have it from very good authority, </q>
        <lb/>ſays Mr. Werner, <q rend="paradiple">both from Franks or <lb/>Europeans, and from the
          natives of Algiers, <lb/>that the inoculation of the ſmall-pox has been <lb/>practiſed in
          that country for many centuries <lb/>paſt. At preſent, however, it is but little <lb/>in
          vogue in the capital, on account of ſeveral <lb/>children having died by it. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">They have two ways of inoculating, viz. <lb/>by buying <note
            place="bottom" n="*">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Mr. Bruce, in his account of Sennar, the <lb/>capital of Nubia, relates, that
                <q rend="quotes">the women, <lb/>both Blacks and Arabs, thoſe of the former
                <lb/>that live in plains, like the Shillook, or in- <lb/>habitants of El-aice, thoſe
                of the Nuba and <lb/>Guba, that live in mountains, all the various <lb/>ſpecies of
                ſlaves that come from Dyre and <lb/>Tegla, from time immemorial, have known <lb/>a
                ſpecies of inoculation, which they call <lb/><hi rend="italic">Tiſhteree el
                  Iidderee</hi>, or the buying of the <lb/>ſmall-pox. The women are the conductors
                <lb/>of this operation in the faireſt and drieſt <lb/>ſeaſon of the year, but never
                at other times. <lb/>Upon the firſt hearing of the ſmall-pox any <lb/>where, theſe
                people go to the infected place, <lb/>and, wrapping a fillet of cotton cloth about
                <lb/>the arm of the perſon infected, they let it <lb/>remain there till they bargain
                with the mo- <lb/>ther how many ſhe is to ſell them. It is ne- <lb/>ceſſary that the
                terms be diſcuſſed judaically, <lb/>and that the bargain be not made colluſively
                <lb/>or gratuitouſly, but that one piece of ſilver, <pb n="1204" type="footnote"/>
                <cb n="1" type="footnote"/>
                <lb/>or more, be paid for the number. This be- <lb/>concluded, they go home, and tie
                the <lb/>fillet about their own child's arm; certain, <lb/>as they ſay, from long
                experience, that the <lb/>child infected is to do well, and not to have <lb/>more
                than the number of puſtules that were <lb/>agreed and paid for. </q>—<hi
                rend="italic">Travels to diſcover the <lb/>Source of the Nile, by James Bruce, of
                Kin- <lb/>naird, Eſq. Vol. IV. p. 4<unclear>8</unclear>4. <hi rend="sc">Edit.</hi>
              </hi>
            </p>
          </note> or by begging the ſmall-pox <lb/>from thoſe who are affected with it. </q>
      </p>
      <pb n="1204"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">The firſt way is this: the parents, <lb/>whoſe child is to be
          inoculated, ſend a per- <lb/>ſon into a houſe where there is a good kind <lb/>of
          ſmall-pox, to beg the favour of them to <lb/>ſell them a ripe puſtule juſt ready to fall
          off. <lb/>The price uſually paid for this is a maroon <lb/>(about three halfpence), and
          they immedi- <lb/>ately tie the puſtule, thus purchaſed, upon <lb/>their child's arm,
          which they have taken <lb/>care previouſly to ſcratch with a pin or <lb/>needle. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">The ſecond way, or that of begging the <lb/>ſmall-pox, as it is called,
          is as follows:— <lb/>The child intended to be inoculated is ſent <lb/>for a whole day into
          an infected houſe, <lb/>where it takes the ſick child (whoſe puſtules <lb/>are on the
          turn) by the hand, and begs of it <lb/>to give him as good a ſort of ſmall-pox as its
          <lb/>own. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent   size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">In either of theſe ways infection is ge- <lb/>nerally communicated; but,
          in caſe it is not, <lb/>they never repeat the experiment, being per- <lb/>ſuaded, when
          this happens, that the child is <lb/>not to have the diſeaſe. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">Unfortunately for thoſe who are infected, <lb/>the Algerines continue to
          follow the method <lb/>(firſt introduced and ſtill adhered to by the <lb/>Spaniſh
          practitioners at Algiers) of keeping <lb/>the patients cloſely confined in a heated
          <lb/>room covered with many bed-cloaths, and <lb/>with their own cloaths on, for theſe are
          <lb/>never allowed to be changed till the puſtules <lb/>have entirely dried up and fallen
          off, by <lb/>which means they loſe a great many of <lb/>their children. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">The Cobatls, or inhabitants of the moun- <lb/>tains, have a quite
          different method from the <lb/>two I have mentioned; for they take a nee- <lb/>dle and
          thread, and paſs them firſt through <lb/>a ripe puſtule, and then through the ſkin
          <lb/>between the fingers of the child to be inocu- <lb/>lated, where the thread is left,
          tied in a bow- <lb/>knot. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">The operation is made in two places, by <lb/>way of ſecurity in caſe one
          of them ſhould <lb/>fail. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">Theſe people allow the patients to walk <lb/>about, if they are able,
          during the whole <lb/>courſe of the diſeaſe; and neither have re- <lb/>courſe to any
          internal remedies, nor confine <lb/>them to any particular regimen, but ſuffer <lb/>them
          to eat and drink as uſual. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">VI.</hi> Caſe of a Woman who, after hav- <lb/>ing been gored in the
        Abdomen by an Ox, <lb/>in the ſixth Month of Pregnancy, under- <lb/>went the <hi
          rend="roman">Cæſarean</hi> Operation. By <hi rend="roman">Fre- <cb n="2"/>
          <lb/>derick Auguſtus Fritſe</hi>, M. D. Phyſician <lb/>at <hi rend="roman"
          >Dillenburgh</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This very curious caſe is tranſlated <lb/>from the German. The ſubject of it <lb/>was a
        poor woman at Offdillen, in the <lb/>principality of Dillenburgh, who reco- <lb/>vered after
        undergoing the Cæſarean <lb/>operation, and died in a ſecond lying-in, <lb/>about a year
        afterwards. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">VII.</hi> An Account of the Effects of <lb/>Laurel-water, as obſerved
        in the Bodies <lb/>of Two Perſons who died at <hi rend="roman">Turin</hi>, <hi rend="roman"
          >Ja- <lb/>nuary 22, 1785</hi>. By M. <hi rend="roman">Penchienati</hi>, <lb/>Member of the
        Royal Academy of Sciences <lb/>at <hi rend="roman">Turin</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">lauro-ceraſus</hi>, ſo called by bo- <lb/>taniſts on account of
        the reſemblance <lb/>there is between its fruit and our cher- <lb/>ries, was brought from
        Trebizond into <lb/>France in 1576. Its pernicious effects, <lb/>however, when given to
        animals, were <lb/>known long before to the antient Greeks <lb/>and Romans, as we learn from
        the writ- <lb/>ings of Strabo, Pliny, and others: and <lb/>the obſervations of the moderns
        have <lb/>ſhewn that the diſtilled water of this <lb/>plant is one of the moſt ſudden and
        fatal <lb/>poiſons hitherto diſcovered. Notwith- <lb/>ſtanding the dangerous properties of
        this <lb/>water, however, it is ſaid to be ſtill occa- <lb/>ſionally employed in cookery;
        and the <lb/>two perſons whoſe caſes are related in <lb/>this paper were ſervants to a
        nobleman <lb/>at Turin, who found a bottle of this <lb/>water among ſome cordials intended
        for <lb/>the table; and, having each of them by <lb/>miſtake ſwallowed about two tea-ſpoon-
        <lb/>fuls, were inſtantly killed by it.—A very <lb/>full account is given of the appearances
        <lb/>that preſented themſelves on the diſſec- <lb/>tion of the dead bodies of theſe unfortu-
        <lb/>nate perſons. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">VIII.</hi> Obſervations on Gangrene. By <lb/><hi rend="roman">Charles
          White</hi>, Eſq. F. R. S. Surgeon at <lb/><hi rend="roman">Mancheſter</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">IX.</hi> Pathological Obſervations on the <lb/>Brain. By Mr. <hi
          rend="roman">Thomas Anderſon</hi>, <lb/>F. R. S. <hi rend="roman">Edin.</hi> Surgeon at
          <hi rend="roman">Leith</hi>. From <lb/>the Tranſactions of the Royal Society of <lb/><hi
          rend="roman">Edinburgh</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">X.</hi> An Account of a Diſtemper vulgarly <lb/>called the Mumps. By
          <hi rend="roman">Robert Hamilton</hi>, <lb/>M. D. F. R. S. <hi rend="roman">Edin.</hi> and
        Phyſician at <lb/><hi rend="roman">Lynn-Regis, Norfolk</hi>. From the ſame <lb/>Work. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XI.</hi> A Caſe of Diabetes. By Mr. <hi rend="roman">Phi- <lb/>lip
          Werner</hi>, Surgeon to the <hi rend="roman">Britiſh</hi> Fac- <lb/>tory at <hi
          rend="roman">Algiers</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XII.</hi> Deſcription of an improved In- <lb/>ſtrument for the Fiſtula
        in Ano. Commu- <lb/>nicated, in a Letter to Dr. <hi rend="roman">Simmons</hi>, <pb n="1205"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>F. R. S. by Mr. <hi rend="roman">J. Savigny</hi>, Surgical In- <lb/>ſtrument Maker in
          <hi rend="roman">London</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This deſcription is illuſtrated by an <lb/>engraving. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XIII.</hi> An Account of Two Caſes of <lb/>Amenorrhœa; with ſome
        Obſervations on <lb/>the Uſe of the Root of Madder in that <lb/>Diſeaſe. Communicated, in a
        Letter to <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="roman">Simmons</hi>, by Mr. <hi rend="roman">Peter
        Copland</hi>, <lb/>Surgeon at <hi rend="roman">Swayfield</hi>, near <hi rend="roman"
          >Colſterworth</hi>, <lb/>in <hi rend="roman">Lincolnſhire</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XIV.</hi> An Account of Two Caſes of <lb/>Pemphigus; to which is
        added, a Fact <lb/>relative to the early Practice of Inocula- <lb/>tion of the Small pox in
          <hi rend="roman">Wales</hi>. Commu- <lb/>nicated, in a Letter to Dr. <hi rend="roman"
          >Simmons</hi>, by <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="roman">John Ring</hi>, Surgeon in <hi rend="roman"
          >London</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From the facts relative to inoculation, <lb/>alluded to by Mr. Ring, it appears, that
        <lb/>the cuſtom of buying the ſmall-pox has <lb/>prevailed in South Wales from time
        <lb/>immemorial. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XV.</hi> Obſervations on Stone in the Uri- <lb/>nary Bladder, and on
        Lithotomy. By <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="roman">James Lucas</hi>, one of the Surgeons of <lb/>the
        General Infirmary at <hi rend="roman">Leeds</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This is a valuable paper, evidently the <lb/>reſult of much experience, and attention
        <lb/>to the ſubject. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XVI.</hi> Remarks on the Treatment of <lb/>Phthiſis Pulmonalis.
        Communicated, in a <lb/>Letter to Dr. <hi rend="roman">Simmons</hi>, F. R. S. by <hi
          rend="roman">Wil- <lb/>liam May</hi>, M. D. Phyſician at <hi rend="roman">Maidſtone</hi>,
        <lb/>in <hi rend="roman">Kent</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This paper, with ſome additional ob- <lb/>ſervations, has lately been republiſhed in
        <lb/>a ſeparate form. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XVII.</hi> Obſervations on the Luxation <lb/>of the Bones of the
        Pelvis. By M. <hi rend="roman">Enaux</hi>, <lb/>Profeſſor of Midwifery, &amp;c. at <hi
          rend="roman">Dijon</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Theſe obſervations, which are extract- <lb/>ed from the Memoirs of the Academy of
        <lb/>Sciences at Dijon, relate ſeems, with <lb/>reaſon, to rank among the more rare and
        <lb/>extraordinary events of ſurgery; and of <lb/>courſe they will be very valuable to
        <lb/>ſurgeons. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XVIII.</hi> Obſervations on the Diſeaſes <lb/>and Medical Practice of
          <hi rend="roman">Boutan</hi> and <lb/><hi rend="roman">Thibet</hi>. By Mr. <hi
          rend="roman">Robert Saunders</hi>, Sur- <lb/>geon at <hi rend="roman">Boglepoor</hi>, in
          <hi rend="roman">Bengal</hi>. From the <lb/>Philoſophical Tranſactions. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XIX.</hi> A Phyſical Inquiry into the <lb/>Powers and Operation of
        Medicines. By <lb/><hi rend="roman">Thomas Percival</hi>, M. D. F. R. S. and <lb/>S A.
        &amp;c. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A number of very curious facts are <lb/>brought together in this paper; but they
        <lb/>would ſuffer by an abridgment. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>[An account of Part IV. ſhall be <lb/>given in our ſucceeding volume.] </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
