<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Experiments and Observations on the Horley-green Spa, near
          Halifax</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Experiments and Observations on the Horley-green Spa, near Halifax. To which is
              added; A short Account of Two other Mineral Waters, in Yorkshire. By Thomas Garnett,
              M. D. late President of the Royal Physical and Natural History Societies, and Member
              of the Royal Society at Edinburgh, &amp;c. 8vo. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine: and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed by John Nichols, at Cicero's Head, Red Lion Passage,
                  Fleet-Street: And Sold by Eliz. Newbery, the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard,
                  Ludgate-Street. 1792. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1792</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">62</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">447b</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1792_GM_0447">
    <body>
      <pb n="447"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">81.</hi> Experiments and Obſervations on the <hi rend="roman">Horley-
          <lb/>green Spa</hi>, near <hi rend="roman">Halifax</hi>. To which is added; <lb/>A ſhort
        Account of Two other Mineral Wa- <lb/>ters, in <hi rend="roman">Yorkſhire</hi>. By <hi
          rend="roman">Thomas Garnett</hi>, <lb/>M. D. late Preſident of the Royal Phyſical <lb/>and
        Natural Hiſtory Societies, and Member of <lb/>the Royal Society at <hi rend="roman"
          >Edinburgh</hi>, &amp;c. 8vo. </head>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>FROM experiments, which appear to <lb/>have been accurately conducted, Dr. G.
        <lb/>concludes that a wine-gallon of Horley- <lb/>green water contains <table rows="6"
          cols="3">
          <row role="label">
            <cell/>
            <cell>dwts. </cell>
            <cell>grs. </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Of earth of iron, or ochre, </cell>
            <cell rend="align-center">1 </cell>
            <cell rend="align-center">0 </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Vitriolated iron, or ſal martis, </cell>
            <cell rend="align-center">8 </cell>
            <cell rend="align-center">8,8 </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Alum </cell>
            <cell rend="align-center">2 </cell>
            <cell rend="align-center">9,2 </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Vitriolated lime, or ſelenite, </cell>
            <cell rend="align-center">1 </cell>
            <cell rend="align-center">13 </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Dephlogiſticated martial vitriol </cell>
            <cell rend="align-center">0 </cell>
            <cell rend="align-center">14 </cell>
          </row>
        </table>
        <lb/>Aërial acid, or fixed air, 18 cubic inches. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The ſpecific gravity of diſtilled water <lb/>is to that of Horley-green as 1 to
        <lb/>1,0031. When the temperature of a <lb/>neighbouring ſpring, equally expoſed to <lb/>the
        air, was 48° of Fahrenheit, that of <lb/>the Horley-green ſpa was 49°. </p>
      <pb n="448"/>
      <cb/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This water, as is remarked by the <lb/>author, bears a near reſemblance to that <lb/>of
        the Hartfell ſpa, near Moffat, in <lb/>Scotland, of which an account is given <lb/>by Dr.
        Horſeburgh, in the firſt volume <lb/>of the Edinburgh Phyſical and Literary <lb/>Eſſays. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From the contents of the water, it is <lb/>evident that it muſt be uſeful as a tonic.
        <lb/>Dr. Garnett obſerves, </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">Since it contains two ſubſtances, which <lb/>are amongſt the moſt powerful
          of the claſs <lb/>of tonic remedies, viz. <hi rend="italic">vitriolated iron</hi> and
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">alum</hi>, hence we ſhall expect to find this wa- <lb/>ter very
          uſeful in diſeaſes depending upon <lb/>debility, where the ſolids are relaxed, and
          <lb/>the ſyſtem weakened In the numerous <lb/>claſs of nervous diſorders it has been found
          <lb/>highly beneficial, particularly when the or- <lb/>gans of digeſtion do not perform
          their func- <lb/>tions properly; ſuch complaints are gene- <lb/>rally attended with loſs
          of appetite, nauſea, <lb/>vomiting, heart-burn, acid eructations, ſpaſ- <lb/>modic pains
          in the ſtomach and bowels, and <lb/>coſtiveneſs. Theſe ſymptoms generally de- <lb/>pend
          upon a debility of the ſtomach, and <lb/>whole body, and may have been brought on <lb/>by
          any thing that relaxes the ſyſtem; ſuch <lb/>as intemperance, a ſedentary life, and too
          <lb/>cloſe application to ſtudy or buſineſs, cold, <lb/>the uſe of coffee, tea, tobacco,
          and ſpirituous <lb/>liquors. Theſe complaints yield readily to <lb/>the Horley-green
          water, when drunk in a <lb/>proper manner. Many ſcrophulous caſes <lb/>have been very much
          relieved, and ſome <lb/>cured by a judicious uſe of this water. Some <lb/>caſes of
          diabetes have been cured by it. It <lb/>is very uſeful in hypochondriac and hyſteric
          <lb/>caſes, and in ſevere head-achs which are of <lb/>the nervous kind, or proceed from a
          diſor- <lb/>dered ſtate of the ſtomach. In ſome dropſi- <lb/>cal and worm caſes it has
          been productive <lb/>of ſurpriſing effects, and particularly in the <lb/>latter. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is likewiſe recommended in the <lb/>atonic gout; in hæmorrhages attended <lb/>with
        great weakneſs; in ſome conſump- <lb/>tive complaints; and in caſes where the <lb/>ſtrength
        has been reduced by long and <lb/>tedious diſeaſes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The other waters which are noticed <lb/>are, Redmire ſpa, ſituated on Romald's
        <lb/>moor, near Bingley; and a ſpring on <lb/>the ſide of a hill at Batlev, near Dewſ-
        <lb/>bury. The former is a ſlight chalybeate; <lb/>and the latter is impregnated with hepa-
        <lb/>tic or ſulphureous air. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
