<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Dr. Rowley's Treatise on the Management of Female Breasts
          during Childbed</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Dr. Rowley's Treatise on the Management of Female Breasts during Childbed,
              &amp;c. &amp;c. (Concluded from p. 938) </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine: and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed by John Nichols, at Cicero's Head, Red Lion Passage,
                  Fleet-Street: And Sold by Eliz. Newbery, the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard,
                  Ludgate-Street. 1792. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1792</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">62</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">1024</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1792_GM_1024">
    <body>
      <pb n="1024"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">256.</hi> Dr. <hi rend="roman">Rowley's</hi> Treatiſe on the Manage-
        <lb/>ment of Female Breaſts during Childbed, &amp;c. <lb/>&amp;c. (Concluded from p. 938) </head>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>UNDER the next head, <q rend="quotes">On the <lb/>Conſequences of Scirrhous Breaſts
          when <lb/>not aſſiſted by Medicine, or ſurgical or <lb/>medical Preſcriptions, or
          Operations, </q> it <lb/>is aſſerted, that patients are ſafer with- <lb/>out than with
        medical aſſiſtance, in many <lb/>inſtances; diet is conſidered; and ſome <lb/>curious and
        intereſting examples of cure, <lb/>with the remedies by which they were <lb/>obtained. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">On the Management of the Cancer- <lb/>ous Ulcer, or <hi rend="italic"
            >manifeſt Cancer</hi>, of the <lb/>Breaſt. </q> 1. The commencement. 2. The
        <lb/>augmenting or ſeparating ſtage. 3. The <lb/>putrid abſorbing ſtage. Remedies and
        <lb/>forms of preſcriptions, on an entire new <lb/>plan. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">ſtages</hi> of the diſorder called <hi rend="italic">cancer</hi>
        <lb/>ſeem to have been aſcertained by long <lb/>obſervations and anatomical inquiry, and <pb
          n="1025"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>may merit the attention of the faculty. <lb/>As to remedies, the author acknowledges
        <lb/>their <hi rend="italic">fallibility</hi> and <hi rend="italic">inadequacy</hi> to the
        <lb/>diſorder, in many inſtances; but he re- <lb/>commends a long perſeverance in <hi
          rend="italic">mine- <lb/>ral alteratives</hi>, according to conſtitu- <lb/>tions, as the
        only probable means of <lb/>preventing the rapid progreſs of the <lb/>diſorder. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The medicines uſed for 30 years are <lb/>freely communicated in ſeveral elegant
        <lb/>preſcriptions, adapted to external and in- <lb/>ternal uſe. The Doctor, however, inti-
        <lb/>mates, that no remedy can be <hi rend="italic">uſeful</hi> but <lb/>in proportion as it
        may be early or <hi rend="italic">ra- <lb/>tionally applied</hi>; and therefore, following
        <lb/>the plan he recommends in his <hi rend="italic">Treatiſe <lb/>on Nervous Diſeaſes</hi>,
        the application of <lb/>medicine is adviſed to be <hi rend="italic">different</hi>, ac-
        <lb/>cording to <hi rend="italic">different habits</hi>; as the <hi rend="italic"
          >robuſt</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">weak</hi>, <hi rend="italic">pallid</hi>, <hi
          rend="italic">florid</hi>, <hi rend="italic">corpulent</hi>, <hi rend="italic">lean</hi>,
        &amp;c. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The author's ideas on theſe ſubjects <lb/>are certainly new, ſenſible, and judicious,
        <lb/>and muſt carry conviction to every un- <lb/>prejudiced mind capable of medical re-
        <lb/>flection. To preſcribe in all caſes of the <lb/>ſame diſeaſe, and expect ſucceſs, he
        con- <lb/>ſiders the height of credulity and folly. <lb/>Every conſtitution, in ſome
        meaſure, <lb/>differs; every conſtitution under diſeaſe, <lb/>therefore, requires ſome
        variation in <lb/>practice: this is alone to be determined <lb/>by ſkill and experience in
        the art; in <lb/>ſhort, by juſt rules treaſured up in the <lb/>mind, from long and acute
        obſervation. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">On the ſcirrhous and cancerous Ul- <lb/>cer of the Womb. </q> This is
        divided in- <lb/>to three <hi rend="italic">ſtadia</hi>, or ſtages — the <hi rend="italic"
          >ſcirrhous</hi>, <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">ulcerous</hi>, and the <hi rend="italic"
          >putrid ſeparating <lb/>ſtage</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Females often loſe their lives through <lb/>falſe delicacy in this dreadful diſeaſe of
        <lb/>the womb. The time to expect a cure <lb/>is in the <hi rend="italic">firſt</hi> ſtage;
        in the <hi rend="italic">ſecond</hi> it is <lb/>doubtful, and in the third it is abſolutely
        <lb/>incurable. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In this part are many practical obſer- <lb/>vations, which ſhew how neceſſary it is
        <lb/>for a phyſician, in ſuch caſes, to well <lb/>underſtand midwifery, as well as practi-
        <lb/>cal medicine. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He condemns the uſe of <hi rend="italic">nightſhade</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >hemlock</hi>, <hi rend="italic">henbane</hi>, <hi rend="italic">mercury alone</hi>,
        bleed- <lb/>ings, neutral ſalts, low diet, &amp;c. or ge- <lb/>neral plans of cure, which
        are not appli- <lb/>cable to individuals; and declares he <lb/>never ſaw ſuch methods
        ſucceſsful. He <lb/>gives reaſons why opium and other nar- <lb/>coticks are likely to fix
        the diſeaſe.— <lb/>Hence he proceeds to give an account of <lb/>all the remedies he has
        uſed; and re- <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>commends a peruſal of his treatiſe on <lb/>the cure of ulcerated legs, fourth edition,
        <lb/>where may be found much reaſoning on <lb/>the neceſſity of changing the ſtate of
        <lb/>blood in curing ulcers and diſeaſes of <lb/>the lymphatic ſyſtem, &amp;c. — The re-
        <lb/>medies are, <list rend="indentall">
          <item>
            <lb/>Æthiops mineralis. </item>
          <item>
            <lb/>— antimonialis. </item>
          <item>
            <lb/>Hydrargyrus and antimonial ſulphurs. </item>
          <item>
            <lb/>Kermes mineralis. </item>
          <item>
            <lb/>Nitrum. </item>
          <item rend="hanging">
            <lb/>Merc. dulc. xij. cies ſub. et lotus cum <lb/>ſulph. </item>
          <item>
            <lb/>Amat. antimon. </item>
          <item>
            <lb/>Camphora. </item>
          <item>
            <lb/>Neutral ſalts. </item>
          <item>
            <lb/>Antimonialia. </item>
        </list>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The modes of uſing the moſt active <lb/>preparations are, to preſcribe, firſt, very
        <lb/>ſmall doſes, at exact diſtances, and long <lb/>to continue their uſe. <q rend="quotes"
          >In ſhort, </q> ſays <lb/>the writer, <q rend="quotes">the general plan may be <lb/>ſeen
          in the ſingular caſe and cure given <lb/>in the letter on <hi rend="italic">medical
            vanity</hi>, where an <lb/>extraordinary cure of a cancerous womb <lb/>and ulcer of the
          rectum was effected by <lb/>alteratives. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The author, laſtly, treats of cancerous <lb/>affections of the <hi rend="italic"
          >eyelids</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ear</hi>, <hi rend="italic">noſe</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
          >lips</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">gums</hi>, <hi rend="italic">tonſil glands</hi>, <hi
          rend="italic">mouth</hi>, <hi rend="italic">fauces</hi>, <hi rend="italic">tongue</hi>,
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">axilla</hi>, &amp;c.; to comprehend which, the <lb/>book muſt be
        conſulted. A review of <lb/>all the methods adopted for the cure of <lb/>the cancer, for a
        period of 2000 years, <lb/>concludes the preſent work. In the in- <lb/>troduction to this
        part the writer ſays, <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">The learned reader will perceive, that <lb/>the modes of treatment I have
          adopted <lb/>and communicated are <hi rend="italic">new</hi>; and if they <lb/>now and
          then <hi rend="italic">ſnatch</hi> an <hi rend="italic">unfortunate <lb/>victim</hi> from
          death, or even palliate the <lb/>ſymptoms of the <hi rend="italic">incurable</hi>, it will
          not <lb/>only requite the author for his unremit- <lb/>ting reſearches, but perhaps point
          out <lb/>the paths to abler practitioners, and pro- <lb/>mote a ſpirit of emulation for
          the ac- <lb/>compliſhing future improvements. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the whole, this treatiſe well merits <lb/>the conſideration of the faculty; for, if
        <lb/>it does not hold out boaſting promiſes, <lb/>nor feed the unfortunate with vain ex-
        <lb/>pectations, yet it gives clearly the reaſons <lb/>why, under certain circumſtances, it
        is <lb/>the height of ignorance and folly to ex- <lb/>pect a cure in cancers.— <q
          rend="quotes">The actions <lb/>of theſe remedies, </q> ſays the author, <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">whether by liquifying the congeſted <lb/>matter, or rendering the
          impervious veſ- <lb/>ſels open in the <hi rend="italic">tela celluloſa</hi>, and its
          <lb/>minuteſt cells, are inquiries that have <pb n="1026"/>
          <lb/>much occupied my attention; the reſult <lb/>will hereafter be communicated. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The reaſons why cancers, in certain <lb/>inſtances, have, and muſt ever remain,
        <lb/>incurable, are fully explained. Then <lb/>follow the modes of palliating ſymptoms
        <lb/>where cures cannot be rationally expect- <lb/>ed; with an account of ſymptoms at-
        <lb/>tendant on cancers of the womb; as <lb/>fevers, ſuppreſſion of urine, hydatids,
        <lb/>coſtiveneſs, nauſea and vomiting, pur- <lb/>gings, putrid diſcharge, violent pains,
        <lb/>floodings, hiccups, comatoſe ſymptoms, <lb/>&amp;c. &amp;c. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Perhaps, as important a part as any in <lb/>this work is the chapter on <hi
          rend="italic">pretenders to <lb/>ſecrets</hi> in the cure of cancers; and if we <lb/>had
        room we ſhould gladly tranſcribe <lb/>the whole, as it might prevent, in future, <lb/>many
        deluſions practiſed on the unwary <lb/>by ignorance and knavery. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
