<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Dissertation on the Gout</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Dissertation on the Gout</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine: and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed by John Nichols, at Cicero's Head, Red Lion Passage,
                  Fleet-Street: And Sold by Eliz. Newbery, the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard,
                  Ludgate-Street. 1792. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1792</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">62</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">311</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1792_GM_0311">
    <body>
      <pb n="311"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <head rend="sc align-center">
        <lb/>Dissertation on the Gout; </head>
      <p rend="italic align-center">
        <lb/>(continued from p. 233.) </p>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(1.5)">F</hi>ACTS ſeem to confirm, that the <lb/>gout is hereditary in ſome
        families, <lb/>by the make of their parts being formed <lb/>like thoſe of their anceſtors;
        others ac- <lb/>quire this diſorder without the above <lb/>claim. However, let it proceed
        from <lb/>either cauſe, aſſiſtance may be obtained <lb/>by a proper regimen, air, and
        exerciſe; <lb/>but before we endeavour to point out a <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>cure, an examination ought to be made, <lb/>how and by what means the gouty mat-
        <lb/>ter is generated, and on what parts of <lb/>the body it acts, and where is the ſeat of
        <lb/>the diſeaſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It has already been obſerved, that the <lb/>cellular membrane is the ſeat of inflam-
        <lb/>mations, and the place where they act. <lb/>The firſt ſtadium of the gout being an
        <lb/>inflammation, <hi rend="italic">ſui generis</hi>, acts in the <lb/>ſame place, though
        with ſome difference, <lb/>as its inflammatory ſtadium generally at- <lb/>tacks the joints.
        In all probability this <lb/>is occaſioned by the violent and particu- <lb/>lar <hi
          rend="italic">heat</hi> of the gouty matter in the ſame <lb/>manner as heat will enter,
        and be greater <lb/>on the round top of a poker, ſtanding <lb/>near the fire, than at any
        other part; <lb/>thus the joints are formed by the firm <lb/>and cloſe texture of cartilages
        and ten- <lb/>dons, hence none but the mere active <lb/>part of the matter enters them; thus
        <lb/>this active part of the gouty matter exerts <lb/>its violence, and ſpends itſelf on one
        or <lb/>more joints! </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After the moſt fiery or active parts of <lb/>the gouty matter have ſpent themſelves
        <lb/>on the joints, and the conſtitution has been <lb/>greatly debilitated thereby, the
        reſidue, be- <lb/>ing of a mere ſluggiſh nature, remains on <lb/>the cellular membrane,
        amongſt the muſ- <lb/>cles; now the patient feels the ſame <lb/>pains as if beaten or
        bruiſed, the muſ- <lb/>cles not enduring the leaſt preſſure, and <lb/>he finds himſelf in a
        ſtate of great debi- <lb/>lity. The ſecond ſtadium, or the ſta- <lb/>dium of debility, is
        now preſent; the <lb/>urine, which was high-coloured in the <lb/>firſt ſtadium, now becomes
        pale. He <lb/>now requires quite a different treatment <lb/>than what he did in the firſt or
        in- <lb/>flammatory ſtadium, for as that was to <lb/>be treated by the antiphlogiſtick
        method, <lb/>ſo this muſt be ſupported by cordials, <lb/>opiates, and ſuch a generous diet
        as the <lb/>patient's ſtomach will require and bear; <lb/>the parts affected muſt ſtill be
        covered <lb/>with flannel, and kept warm, to give a <lb/>more eaſy paſſage to the remains of
        the <lb/>gouty matter, part of which goes off by <lb/>perſpiration, and other part is
        abſorbed <lb/>by the glands, and carried to the kid- <lb/>neys and guts, and paſſes off that
        way. <lb/>As the pain and wearineſs of the muſcu- <lb/>lar parts abate, air and exerciſe
        ſhould <lb/>be made uſe of. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Having deſcribed the fit or fits of the <lb/>gout (for a perſon who has many re-
        <lb/>turns of the gout, and is greatly afflicted <lb/>with it, will ſometimes have a re-
        <lb/>turn of the gouty fits on the ſame <lb/>parts again and again before he gets rid
        <lb/>of it) with the method of cure; I ſhall <pb n="312"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>now endeavour to trace out what it is <lb/>that occaſions thoſe fits, with the moſt
        <lb/>probable method of prevention. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It has already been obſerved, that the <lb/>adipoſe membrane is the ſeat of the gout;
        <lb/>that this membrane acts as a ſtore-houſe <lb/>for any overplus of nouriſhment receiv-
        <lb/>ed into the conſtitution, and with it the <lb/>ſeeds of the gout and many other diſ-
        <lb/>eaſes; that when a too great ſupply of <lb/>nouriſhment is added hereto, with a de-
        <lb/>ficiency of labour or exerciſe, Nature has <lb/>no other method of exonerating itſelf
        of <lb/>the gouty matter, but throwing it on the <lb/>extremities, and there paſſing it off
        by <lb/>perſpiration, &amp;c. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Experience having proved that the <lb/>gout is brought on as above, the proper
        <lb/>method of prevention will be to hinder <lb/>the generating this gouty matter, or diſ-
        <lb/>charging it by exerciſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The method to prevent the generating <lb/>of this gouty matter is to take ſuch food
        <lb/>as will not bring it on; or, if ſuch food <lb/>is taken, to carry off the redundancy by
        <lb/>labour or exerciſe. In order to do this, <lb/>phyſicians have pointed out different me-
        <lb/>thods, as vegetables and milk produce <lb/>leſs nouriſhment than fleſh to perſons
        <lb/>who have been ordered to live upon <lb/>thoſe only; or, if animal food was made
        <lb/>uſe of, to moderate its quantity, ſo as not <lb/>to exceed what could be carried off by
        <lb/>the labour or exerciſe of the patient. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>All experience ſhews us animal food <lb/>produces a ſtrong and rich blood, whilſt
        <lb/>milk and vegetables bring on a weak <lb/>and poor one. Perſons greatly afflicted
        <lb/>with the gout have been willing to <lb/>make uſe of any method, or to abſtain <lb/>from
        every thing that ſhould be thought <lb/>improper, for relief. On this ſuppoſition <lb/>many
        have made uſe of milk and ani- <lb/>mal food only, and generally have found <lb/>relief; but
        I don't remember ever to <lb/>have heard of any inſtance, but that it <lb/>ſhortened the
        life of the perſon who tried <lb/>it. The gout is a diſorder which at- <lb/>tacks perſons
        paſt the high ſtadium of <lb/>life, and whoſe habit is generally on <lb/>the decline before
        the attack of the gout; <lb/>therefore it ſhould not be ſtrictly perſe- <lb/>vered in.
        Neither ſhould the oppoſite, <lb/>viz. to live on animal food in great <lb/>quantity and of
        high quality, with ſtrong <lb/>liquors. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The moſt proper means of prevention <lb/>ſeems to be (unleſs your exerciſe is
        <lb/>ſtrong and laborious) to eat ſparingly of <lb/>animal food; together with a proper
        <lb/>quantity of vegetables. If your appe- <lb/>tite is very good and rather great, take <cb
          n="2"/>
        <lb/>the vegetables in greater quantity, and <lb/>the animal food leſs <note n="*"
          place="bottom" rend="size(0.8)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Fiſh, being of a nature of food between <lb/>animal and vegetable, producing leſs
            and <lb/>weaker nouriſhment than animal, but much <lb/>more than vegetable, are a proper
            food for <lb/>ſuch perſons as are inclinable to generate and <lb/>collect the gouty
            matter; but then this food, <lb/>though it is of the moſt eaſy digeſtion, ſhould
            <lb/>not be made uſe of alone; animal and ve- <lb/>getable ſhould be mixed with it,
            according <lb/>to the ſtrength and appetite of every perſon. </p>
        </note> ; but no method <lb/>will do without labour and exerciſe: you <lb/>ſhould rather
        take too ſmall a quantity <lb/>than too large of ſtrong drink, let the <lb/>ſort be what it
        will! </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From the account of the gout already <lb/>given it may be obſerved, that the gout,
        <lb/>as well as many other diſeaſes, is acquir- <lb/>ed by too great an indulgence of idle-
        <lb/>neſs, lazineſs, and luxury, particularly <lb/>by thoſe that eat a great deal of animal
        <lb/>food, and drink a quantity of ſtrong li- <lb/>quors; but all perſons are not equally
        <lb/>affected with this diſorder, as the make <lb/>of ſome of the ſolids greatly contribute
        <lb/>to the collecting ſuch a matter from the <lb/>nouriſhment received, ſo as to lay the
        <lb/>ſeeds of this future diſorder; hence it <lb/>becomes hereditary after the ſame man-
        <lb/>ner as children often have the parts of <lb/>the body alike in ſhape and make with
        <lb/>their parents. Thus children of large <lb/>and ſtrong parents are ſtout and luſty;
        <lb/>thoſe of ſmall ſtature are diminutive. <lb/>Parents inclinable to be fat often have
        <lb/>children of the ſame make. Thus it <lb/>may be obſerved, that all perſons are not
        <lb/>equally afflicted with the gout, though <lb/>they all uſe the ſame means to acquire
        <lb/>it. Such perſons whoſe habit of body <lb/>are inclinable to acquire gouty matter,
        <lb/>acquire it together with the <hi rend="italic">fat</hi>, and is <lb/>laid up in the <hi
          rend="italic">membrana adipoſa</hi>, as in a <lb/>ſtore-houſe for future call; this ſtore
        of <lb/>gouty fat becomes more or leſs in the <lb/>habit, in proportion to the nouriſhment
        <lb/>made uſe of, and the labour or exerciſe <lb/>uſed, and will increaſe or leſſen in pro-
        <lb/>portion as either of them prevail: hence <lb/>the neceſſity that the exerciſe ſhould be
        <lb/>in proportion to the meat and drink <lb/>made uſe of. If the conſtitution is ſtrong
        <lb/>enough, when the <hi rend="italic">vis matricis naturæ</hi>
        <lb/>finds herſelf overloaded with this fat <lb/>gouty matter, ſhe forces ſome of the
        <lb/>moſt fiery and active particles on joints <lb/>of the extremities, which immediately
        <lb/>produce an inflammation on the part; a <lb/>ſymptomatic fever is brought on, and
        <lb/>theſe active and fiery particles are thrown <lb/>off through the pores of the ſkin, and
        the <pb n="313"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>remainder by urine or <choice>
          <corr>ſtool</corr>
          <sic>ſtod</sic>
        </choice>. If the con- <lb/>ſtitution is ſo loaded with this gouty fiery <lb/>matter, that
        this fit is not ſufficient to <lb/>throw off enough of it; after a little <lb/>reſpite,
        another ſuch fit is brought on in <lb/>ſome other joint, before free of it; and <lb/>thus
        freſh fits are produced till enough <lb/>of it is diſcharged, when this firſt and
        <lb/>inflammatory ſtadium is at an end, <lb/>which is ſucceeded by the ſecond ſta-
        <lb/>dium, viz. that of debility; during this <lb/>ſecond ſtadium, great pain and unea-
        <lb/>ſineſs is now formed in and throughout <lb/>all the muſcular parts affected; dur-
        <lb/>ing this ſtadium the patient muſt be <lb/>ſupported with a generous way of liv-
        <lb/>ing, together with an opiate at night; <lb/>till the pains and ſwellings are gone.
        <lb/>Theſe pains and ſwellings will con- <lb/>tinue till the <hi rend="italic">vis matricis
          naturæ</hi> has <lb/>unloaded the cellular membrane of theſe <lb/>gouty remains, which are
        carried off, ei- <lb/>ther by perſpiration, or are taken up by <lb/>the lymphaticks, and
        diſcharged on the <lb/>kidneys or guts. It will be of great <lb/>uſe to guard the parts
        affected from <lb/>cold, during this ſtadium; thereby the <lb/>pores will be more open for
        the perſ- <lb/>piration of the offending matter, and <lb/>the gouty matter not made to
        retrocede <lb/>by cold. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The gout, by bad management, or <lb/>otherwiſe, retroceding falls on the vitals,
        <lb/>as on the ſtomach, lungs, kidneys, blad- <lb/>der, &amp;c. particularly to thoſe who
        have <lb/>been long ſubjects to it, and their con- <lb/>ſtitution greatly debilitated
        thereby; <lb/>whenever this happens, the moſt ſpeedy <lb/>and powerful aſſiſtance muſt
        immediately <lb/>be given, and ſuch as will occaſion the <lb/>removing the gouty matter from
        the in- <lb/>ternal, or vital parts, to the extremi- <lb/>ties; the patient ſhould be
        immediately <lb/>placed in a hot bath, as warm as he can <lb/>bear it with eaſe, and
        continue in <lb/>it half an hour, more or leſs, as his <lb/>ſtrength will ſupport it. The
        heat of <lb/>the bath ſhould be kept up, all the time <lb/>he is in it, by adding boiling
        water, as <lb/>is found neceſſary. By this an active <lb/>heat or warmth will be added to
        the <lb/>whole maſs of blood: when he is taken <lb/>out of the hot bath, he ſhould be imme-
        <lb/>diately put into blankets, to dry off the <lb/>moiſture on the ſkin as ſoon as
        poſſible; <lb/>then let him have a warm and dry ſhirt <lb/>on, and put into a warm bed; his
        arms <lb/>and legs ſhould be rubbed ſmartly with <lb/>dry flannels<unclear>;</unclear>
        cordial medicines, with <lb/><hi rend="italic">opiats</hi>, ſhould be immediately given to
        <lb/>encreaſe the <hi rend="italic">internal</hi> expanſion, and, if <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>poſſible, to force the gout from the in- <lb/>ternal to the external parts, which are
        <lb/>now debilitated, and becoming flaccid <lb/>by the perſpiration of the external heat,
        <lb/>and thereby leaving a vacuum, or place <lb/>reſiſting leſs for the gouty matter to be
        <lb/>forced into. Experience has ſhewn us, <lb/>that a perſon, ſubject to the gout,
        <lb/>ſpraining his ancle, whereby an inflam- <lb/>mation is brought on, or any other in-
        <lb/>flammation ſucceeding any accident, <lb/>even the ſmall inflammation which fol-
        <lb/>lows a bliſter, a fit of the gout generally <lb/>follows it. This points out to us,
        that <lb/>bliſters ſhould be applied to the legs, &amp;c. <lb/>Warm aromatic and ſpirituous
        gliſters, <lb/>together with opium, will be proper to <lb/>be made uſe of, in order to give
        ſtrength <lb/>to the internal expanſion, and force the <lb/>gout on the extremities. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
