<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: An Inquiry into the Nature and Causes of Sickness in Ships of
          War</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Inquiry into the Nature and Causes of Sickness in Ships of War; shewing the
              Error of its being chiefly ascribed to Maritime Diet, and that it cannot be prevented
              by the Acids so generally recommended; by what Means that Prevention may be most
              effectually attained, and with least Expence to the State. To which are added, A
              Review of Sir John Pringle's Discourse on preserving the Health of Mariners, with
              other Medical Disquisitions; including Remarks on the new Dispensatory of the London
              College of Physicians. By William Renwick, Surgeon to the Royal Navy. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine: and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed by John Nichols, at Cicero's Head, Red Lion Passage,
                  Fleet-Street: And Sold by Eliz. Newbery, the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard,
                  Ludgate-Street. 1792. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1792</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">62</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">839</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1792_GM_0839">
    <body>
      <pb n="839"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">179.</hi> An Inquiry into the Nature and Cauſes of <lb/>Sickneſs in
        Ships of War; ſhewing the Error <lb/>of its being chiefly aſcribed to Maritime Diet,
        <lb/>and that it cannot be prevented by the Acids <lb/>ſo generally recommended; by what
        Means <lb/>that Prevention may be moſt effectually attain- <lb/>ed, and with leaſt Expence
        to the State. To <lb/>which are added, A Review of Sir <hi rend="roman">John
          <lb/>Pringle's</hi> Diſcourſe on preſerving the Health <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>of Mariners, with other Medical Diſquiſitions; <lb/>including Remarks on the new
        Diſpenſatory of <lb/>the <hi rend="roman">London</hi> College of Phyſicians. By <hi
          rend="roman">Wil- <lb/>liam Renwick</hi>, Surgeon to the Royal Navy. </head>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>MR. RENWICK in this work ſteps <lb/>forth once more the friend of mankind,
        <lb/>particularly of that deſerving order of <lb/>men the ſailors, the great bulwark of this
        <lb/>nation, who are ſo much commended and <lb/>diſregarded, whoſe ſervices are ſo gene-
        <lb/>rally overlooked and their welfare neg- <lb/>lected. He laments and reprobates the
        <lb/>parſimony of Government in giving ſuch <lb/>ſmall allowance to navy ſurgeons as diſ-
        <lb/>courages men of abilities from continu- <lb/>ing long in the ſervice, and leaves the
        <lb/>health and lives of the ſeamen to be ſu- <lb/>perintended by perſons by no means qua-
        <lb/>lified for ſo arduous an undertaking. <lb/>Their diſeaſes, he ſays, have been gene-
        <lb/>rally miſunderſtood, or aſcribed to im- <lb/>proper and inadequate cauſes; and hence
        <lb/>the inefficacy of all the regulations that <lb/>have hitherto been recommended for the
        <lb/>prevention of them. He appears warm <lb/>and zealous in the cauſe he has under-
        <lb/>taken; and although his arguments do <lb/>not always carry conviction, and he fre-
        <lb/>quently mixes incongruous matter, yet <lb/>there are ſcattered through his pages
        <lb/>ſome obſervations that diſcover penetra- <lb/>tion and knowledge of his ſubject, and,
        <lb/>if adopted, might prove of conſiderable <lb/>utility. He conſiders the mephitic va-
        <lb/>pour ariſing from the bilge water as one <lb/>of the moſt powerful agents in pro-
        <lb/>ducing diſeaſes at ſea. This is ſome- <lb/>times ſo peſtilential as to kill new
        <lb/>hands, men not accuſtomed to the ſea, <lb/>in twenty-four hours. Seaſoned ſailors
        <lb/>are, from the ſame cauſe, affected with <lb/>ſcurvy and other chronic diſeaſes,
        <lb/>which, although more ſlow in their ope- <lb/>ration, are not leſs fatal in the end. To
        <lb/>the deſtroying and diſcharging this va- <lb/>pour, which can only be effectually
        <lb/>done by means of fire, he thinks our <lb/>whole endeavours ſhould tend. The
        <lb/>introducing ſour crout, oranges, and <lb/>other acids, has rather been productive
        <lb/>of miſchief than good, by turning the <lb/>attention into a wrong channel, and
        <lb/>leading us to neglect the true cauſe of <lb/>the diſeaſe, which no acids, or any ſpe-
        <lb/>cies of diet, can correct. The ſucceſs <lb/>ſuppoſed to have attended the regula-
        <lb/>tions purſued by the late Capt. Cook, <lb/>and recommended by Sir John Pringle, <lb/>in
        his diſcourſe on the methods of pre- <lb/>ſerving the health and lives of ſeamen, <lb/>he
        thinks very much over-rated; and <lb/>the healthineſs of the crews, which he <pb n="840"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>conſiders as by no means remarkable, <lb/>ought to be attributed, he ſays, to very
        <lb/>different cauſes than thoſe there aſſign- <lb/>ed; ſuch as, to the men being all prime
        <lb/>ſailors, and inured to a ſea-life; to <lb/>their number being much ſmaller than <lb/>is
        uſual on board ſhips of that bulk, <lb/>and, conſequently, to their being leſs <lb/>crowded;
        to their frequent debarkation, <lb/>the land-air contributing more than any <lb/>other agent
        both in preventing and cur- <lb/>ing ſea-diſeaſes; to their frequently let- <lb/>ting down
        fire-pots into the hold of the <lb/>ſhips, and by that means correcting and <lb/>expelling
        the mephitic vapour. This <lb/>leads him to conſider the preference that <lb/>has bern
        injudiciouſly given to Hales's <lb/>ventilator over the air-pipes of Sutton. <lb/>The
        former, he ſays, can neither be <lb/>uſed when there is much wind, nor <lb/>when there is
        too little to keep them <lb/>inflated: the fixing them alſo being at- <lb/>tended with
        conſiderable trouble, they <lb/>are ſeldom put up at night. <q rend="quotes">But it is
          <lb/>neceſſary that the purification of the air <lb/>ſhould be unremitted, and that the
          re- <lb/>medy ſhould be adapted to every ſeaſon, <lb/>and be independent of manual opera-
          <lb/>tion. </q> All theſe advantages Sutton's <lb/>pipes enjoy, beſides being much cheaper
        <lb/>than the ventilators, and leſs operoſe in <lb/>their ſtructure. The returning, there-
        <lb/>fore, to the uſe of them he conſiders as <lb/>of the firſt importance; <q rend="quotes"
          >for nothing <lb/>can be more deluſive, </q> he obſerves, <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">than to talk of remedies for ſickneſs <lb/>where the continuance of its
          cauſe muſt <lb/>either counteract the efficacy of pre- <lb/>ſcription, or renew the
          diſorder as ſoon <lb/>as the remedy is diſcontinued. </q> He <lb/>conſiders, in
        ſucceſſion, the ſeveral arti- <lb/>cles of diet, particularly biſcuit, which <lb/>being
        ſaved and taken out of ſhips re- <lb/>turning from a long cruize, and put on <lb/>board
        others that are going out, has <lb/>frequently entirely loſt its nutritive <lb/>quality
        before it is eaten. He takes no <lb/>notice of Mr. Hervey's method of pu- <lb/>rifying
        putrid waters; which is the <lb/>more wonderful, as he, with reaſon, at- <lb/>tributes ſo
        many of the diſeaſes of ſea- <lb/>men, particularly fluxes, to the bad <lb/>ſtate of that
        element. He is very warm <lb/>in his encomium of tea, and recom- <lb/>mends its introduction
        into the navy, as <lb/>a tonic, diaphoretic, and diuretic. It is, <lb/>he ſays, the ſafeſt
        cordial in the uni- <lb/>verſe, conſtantly imparting ſtrength and <lb/>ſpirits, without any
        of thoſe deleterious <lb/>effects which vinous ſpirits, taken daily, <lb/>never fail to
        produce.—He makes a <lb/>whimſical obſervation on the common <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>ſpirit of hartſhorn, with which we ſhall <lb/>cloſe this article: <q rend="quotes">What
          is denomi- <lb/>nated <hi rend="italic">liquor volatilis cornu corvi</hi>, </q> he
        <lb/>ſays, <q rend="quotes">might perhaps be oftener termed <lb/><hi rend="italic">urina
            diſtillata</hi>, many chemiſts being <lb/>ſaid to obtain this volatile liquor from
          <lb/>ſtale collections, in which the ſupplies, <lb/><hi rend="italic">ex virginibus et
            aliis</hi>, are indiſcrimi- <lb/>nately blended. It might be worth <lb/>while to enquire
          whether various diſ- <lb/>eaſes may not be communicated in the <lb/>exhibition of ſuch
          cordial drops, more <lb/>eſpecially where the ſtills are charged <lb/>from the
          repoſitories of St. James's <lb/>place. </q>
      </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
