<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - S. A.: A Remedy for Bruises</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>S. A.</persName>
            </author>
            <title>A Remedy for Bruises</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine: and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed by John Nichols, at Cicero's Head, Red Lion Passage,
                  Fleet-Street: And Sold by Eliz. Newbery, the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard,
                  Ludgate-Street. 1792. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1792</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">62</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">707</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1792_GM_0707">
    <body>
      <pb n="707"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <salute rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="sc">Urban</hi>, </salute>
      <dateline rend="align-right"><hi rend="italic">July</hi> 3. </dateline>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE extenſive peruſal of your Ma- <lb/>gazine renders it a proper
        channel <lb/>for communicating to the publick what- <lb/>ever may be of general uſe. Falls
        and <lb/>bruiſes frequently happen in country <lb/>places where there may not be any me-
        <lb/>dical aſſiſtance near. Accidents have <lb/>fully convinced me of the utility that
        <lb/>may attend the application of the fol- <lb/>lowing ſimple practice; and I therefore
        <lb/>requeſt your inſerting the following in- <lb/>ſtances in your publication: </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A coachman, in a ſtreet of London, <lb/>was, by a ſudden jolt, thrown off his <lb/>box,
        and in his fall his foot fell into a <lb/>hollow in the pavement, which occa- <lb/>ſioned a
        ſprain, attended with violent <lb/>pain, and a conſiderable inflammation. <lb/>A brother
        whip promiſed him a ſpeedy <pb n="708"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>cure. He ordered a gallon of porter to <lb/>be ſimmered in an earthen veſſel, till,
        <lb/>when cooled, it became of the conſiſt- <lb/>ence of a plaiſter. He ſpread this pla-
        <lb/>ſter on a thin old glove, and applied it <lb/>round the ankle. In three days he
        <lb/>mounted his box, being relieved of the <lb/>ſwelling and pain. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Another perſon, being ſurrounded by <lb/>pickpockets, in endeavouring to ſave <lb/>his
        money fell down, and ſtruck one <lb/>ſide of his loins upon a ſtone more pro- <lb/>minent
        than the reſt of the pavement. <lb/>Conſiderable pain and ſwelling were the
        <lb/>conſequences; and next day his back, <lb/>and the thigh on that ſide, became
        <lb/>greatly diſcoloured. An eminent ſur- <lb/>geon was called in, who ordered ſuch
        <lb/>applications as his judgement directed. <lb/>Having ſeen the ſucceſs of the porter-
        <lb/>plaſter in the former inſtance, I deſired <lb/>that the porter plaſter might be applied
        <lb/>to part of the back and thigh, while the <lb/>other parts were treated according to
        <lb/>art, that ſo a comparative experiment <lb/>might be made of the effects of each.
        <lb/>The ſwelling ſubſided nearly equally in <lb/>both; but the pain and the blackneſs of
        <lb/>the ſkin went off much ſooner in the <lb/>parts covered with the plaſter than in
        <lb/>the other parts. Accidents have ſince <lb/>afforded me ſeveral inſtances of ſimilar
        <lb/>ſucceſs attending the application of this <lb/>plaſter. Might not we expect that ſuc-
        <lb/>ceſs might attend the application of this <lb/>plaſter in other fixed pains in various
        <lb/>parts of the body? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As theſe accidents happened in Lon- <lb/>don, where porter is the malt liquor <lb/>moſt
        generally uſed, the plaſter was <lb/>made of it; yet I doubt not but that <lb/>other
        fermented malt-liquors, uſed in <lb/>the ſame manner, might have ſimilar <lb/>effects. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Where ſuch hurts are frequent, this <lb/>plaſter may be long kept in good con-
        <lb/>dition, if it is covered with a little oil <lb/>to prevent the evaporation of the fluid
        <lb/>particles. </p>
      <signed rend="align-right">S. A. </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
