<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: History of the Gout</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>History of the Gout</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine: and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed by John Nichols, at Cicero's Head, Red Lion Passage,
                  Fleet-Street: And Sold by Eliz. Newbery, the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard,
                  Ludgate-Street. 1792. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1792</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">62</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">102</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1792_GM_0102">
    <body>
      <pb n="102"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <div>
        <salute rend="indent">
          <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="sc">Urban</hi>, </salute>
        <dateline rend="dateline"><hi rend="italic">February</hi> 17. </dateline>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi>S I imagine your Magazine contains <lb/>more original eſſays
          in ſcience than <lb/>any other periodical publication, and is <lb/>more univerſally read
          by perſons of <lb/>ſcience than any other, I have ſent you <lb/>the following diſſertation
          on the Gout, <lb/>with a deſire that you will inſert it in <lb/>your Magazine; with a hope
          that it may <lb/>be of uſe to many of my brother ſuf- <lb/>ferers. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I think it will appear, from the fol- <lb/>lowing diſſertation on the gout, that it
          <lb/>is no longer to be reckoned the <hi rend="italic">opprobrium <lb/>medicorum</hi>, and
          from thence that it muſt <lb/>be left to Quacks and Empirics; but to be <lb/>conſidered as
          a diſorder as well underſtood <lb/>as a peripneumonic, or other inflammatory
          <lb/>diſorder, and much better than the ge- <lb/>nerality of chronical ones are, and may
          <lb/>be aſſiſted by the advice of the phyſician; <lb/>that is, that the violence of the
          fits may <lb/>be abated, and their continuance ſhort- <lb/>ened; and alſo, that when the
          fit is <lb/>gone, the return of another may be either <lb/>prevented, or the violence of
          it leſſened. </p>
        <signed rend="indent">
          <lb/>Yours, &amp;c. <hi rend="align-right">P. </hi>
        </signed>
      </div>
      <div>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>AS there is no forming a probable con- <lb/>jecture, who ſhall, or who ſhall not, be
          <lb/>afflicted with the gout, till it makes its <lb/>firſt attack, I ſhall therefore, <hi
            rend="italic">then</hi>, begin <lb/>my obſervations and enquiries. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This attack is in ſome of the joints, <lb/>often in the great toe or foot. The per-
          <lb/>ſon, juſt before his ſeizure, appears ge- <lb/>nerally in the beſt health and
          ſpirits. On <lb/>his going to bed, he is ſeized with great <lb/>pains, and inflammation,
          or redneſs, upon <lb/>or about the part affected, which is exqui- <lb/>ſitely painful,
          particularly on the ſmalleſt <lb/>touch. The inflammation of the part ge- <lb/>nerally
          increaſes for the firſt two or three <lb/>days; after which a ſwelling of the parts <pb
            n="103"/>
          <cb n="1"/>
          <lb/>comes on, and the pain abates. In a day <lb/>or two more a perſpiration of the parts
          <lb/>commences, and thus ends the fit. Dur- <lb/>ing all this time inflammatory ſymptoms
          <lb/>are preſent; which often begin, as moſt <lb/>other inflammations, by a cold, or chil-
          <lb/>lineſs. The urine has the ſame appearance <lb/>as in other inflammatory diſorders;
          high <lb/>coloured and clear, for the firſt three or <lb/>four days; when the criſis of
          the fit is <lb/>preſent, it becomes turbid, and lets fall <lb/>a ſediment, and thus ends
          the inflamma- <lb/>tory ſtadium, or fit of the gout. If this <lb/>is its firſt attack, the
          perſon has little <lb/>complaint, and ſoon recovers to his <lb/>healthy ſtate. If it
          happens to a perſon <lb/>who has been before afflicted, after a reſ- <lb/>pite of a day or
          two, another attack is <lb/>generally made on ſome other part, which <lb/>before had no
          complaint; as the other <lb/>great toe or foot. This freſh fit takes <lb/>the ſame round
          of ſymptoms as the other <lb/>had done before; and, at its proper period, <lb/>has the
          ſame criſis; and goes off in the <lb/>ſame manner. After another ſmall inter- <lb/>val, if
          it is a perſon who has been af- <lb/>flicted often with the gout before, an- <lb/>other
          attack on ſome other part or parts <lb/>may follow; nay, ſometimes the ſame <lb/>toe, or
          other joint, may undergo a ſe- <lb/>cond fit. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The above deſcribed diſeaſe is the firſt <lb/><hi rend="italic">ſtadium</hi> of a
          gouty fit, and may be pro- <lb/>perly called the <hi rend="italic">inflammatory</hi>. The
          pro- <lb/>per method of treatment is the ſame as in <lb/>other diſorders of the ſame
          claſs, <hi rend="italic">except <lb/>bleeding</hi>, which experience has found not <lb/>to
          be right or neceſſary, a plethora being <lb/>ſeldom the caſe, as the gout attacks very
          <lb/>few perſons till they are near forty, and <lb/>the ſtrength of their conſtitution
          begins to <lb/>abate. And ſome eminent phyſicians <lb/>think it a diſeaſe of debility from
          its be- <lb/><choice>
            <corr>ginning</corr>
            <sic>beginning</sic>
          </choice>; though, if the whole of this <lb/>ſtadium is carefully obſerved, it muſt be
          <lb/>allowed to be a regular inflammatory <lb/><choice>
            <corr>ſymptomatic</corr>
            <sic>ſymtomatic</sic>
          </choice> fever, from the beginning to <lb/>the end or criſis. At the criſis, great
          <lb/>care ſhould be taken to encourage the <lb/>perſpiration of the gouty matter, by co-
          <lb/>vering the parts well with flannel, &amp;c. For <lb/>want of this care and caution,
          the gouty <lb/>matter, by cold, may be prevented from <lb/>going off in the regular and
          natural way, <lb/>and ſo <unclear><choice>
              <corr>reverberate</corr>
              <sic>recerberate</sic>
            </choice></unclear> into the habit, which <lb/>is now greatly debilitated, and unable to
          <lb/>withſtand it, and hence fall on ſome in- <lb/>ternal part, not capable to force it
          out- <lb/>ward. It may be obſerved, that the gout <lb/>attacking the vital parts is moſt
          often oc- <lb/>caſioned by a wrong method of treatment. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>As it has been obſerved, the firſt attack <cb n="2"/>
          <lb/>of the gout goes off generally at the end <lb/>of the firſt ſtadium, from ſuch
          perſons <lb/>who never had it before, as the perſon <lb/>generally is ſtrong in habit,
          capable to <lb/>withſtand the ſecond ſtadium which is <lb/>always that of debility. On the
          going off <lb/>of the firſt ſtadium, the ſecond follows in <lb/>the following manner: the
          inflammation <lb/>from the joint, or joints, <choice>
            <corr>being</corr>
            <sic>beng</sic>
          </choice> gone, and <lb/>with it a great part of the pain; now, <lb/>all the muſcular
          parts bear their ſhare <lb/>with the joints; the perſon is affected, ſome- <lb/>times with
          cold, ſometimes with heat, great <lb/>pain, aching, and ſoreneſs, in and through- <lb/>out
          all the muſcular parts, ſuch as are <lb/>felt after being beat or bruiſed; and con-
          <lb/>tinue longer or ſhorter, till the remains <lb/>of that gouty matter are thrown off by
          <lb/>perſpiration of the parts, or are abſorbed <lb/>by the abſorbent veſſels; and then
          either <lb/>thrown off by the interior pores of the <lb/>ſkin, or carried by the
          lymphaticks to <lb/>the guts or kidneys, and there diſcharged. <lb/>When this is
          performed, the perſon, being <lb/>free of the diſorder, ſoon recovers to his <lb/>former
          ſtate of health! </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>As an improper method of treatment <lb/>may prove of very bad conſequence in <lb/>the
          firſt ſtadium of the gout, ſo it may <lb/>more particularly in this ſecond. The <lb/>firſt
          and ſecond ſtadium of the gout, as <lb/>may be obſerved, require quite different
          <lb/>treatment from each other; the firſt <lb/>ſtadium being ſymptomatic and inflam-
          <lb/>matory, whilſt the ſecond is debility <lb/>only, and muſt be treated as ſuch. This
          <lb/>ſecond ſtadium requires cordials and opi- <lb/>ates, with tolerable good eating and
          <lb/>drinking, if the ſtomach deſires it. Care <lb/>ſhould be taken not to admit the cold
          air <lb/>too ſoon or too freely, warmth being <lb/>ſtill required, till the greater part
          of the <lb/>gouty matter is got rid of. </p>
        <trailer rend="align-center italic">
          <lb/>(To be continued.) </trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
