<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Dissertation on the Gout.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Dissertation on the Gout. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine: and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed by John Nichols, at Cicero's Head, Red Lion Passage,
                  Fleet-Street: And Sold by Eliz. Newbery, the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard,
                  Ludgate-Street. 1792. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1792</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">62</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">232</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1792_GM_0232">
    <body>
      <pb n="232"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <head rend="sc align-center">
        <lb/>Dissertation on the Gout. </head>
      <p rend="italic align-center">
        <lb/>(continued from p. 103.) </p>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(1.5)">H</hi>AVING given the ſymptoms and <lb/>complaints throughout a fit
        of the <lb/><choice>
          <corr>gout</corr>
          <sic>got</sic>
        </choice>, I ſhall now endeavour to trace out <lb/><hi rend="italic">à poſteriori</hi> the
        ſeat and cauſe of this <lb/>complaint. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The firſt <hi rend="italic">ſtadium</hi> of the gout has the <lb/>ſymptoms and
        appearance of other in- <lb/>flammations, and it is ſome difficulty to <lb/>diſtinguiſh
        between the inflammation at- <lb/>tending the gout, and other inflamma- <lb/>tions; ſo
        difficult, that if a phyſician <lb/>does not know his patient at firſt ſight, <lb/>he will
        ſeldom determine poſitively. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In order to underſtand this caſe pro- <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>perly, the ſeat and progreſs of inflam- <lb/>matory ſwellings ſhould be enquired in-
        <lb/>to, from which enquiry it will be found <lb/>that the <hi rend="italic">cellular
          membrane</hi> is the part <lb/>affected, and the ſeat of <hi rend="sc">all</hi>. The
        <lb/>anatomical account of the <hi rend="italic">cellular mem- <lb/>brane</hi>, and its
        uſes, muſt therefore be <lb/>the ſubject of our firſt enquiry. Dr. <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Monro</hi> deſcribes it as follows: </p>
      <p rend="indent space size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">The <hi rend="italic">membrana adipoſa</hi> is an <hi
            rend="italic">univerſal</hi> in- <lb/>tegument of the human body. This is not,
          <lb/>however, a ſingle membrane, but a conge- <lb/>ries of a great number of membranous
            <hi rend="italic">laminæ</hi>, <lb/>joined irregularly to each other at different
          <lb/>diſtances, ſo as to form numerous interſtices <lb/>of different capacities, which
          communicate <lb/>with each other. Theſe interſtices have <lb/>been named <hi rend="italic"
            >cellulæ</hi>; and the ſubſtance they <lb/>compoſe, the <hi rend="italic">cellular
            ſubſtance</hi>. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">The thickneſs of the <hi rend="italic">membrana adipoſa</hi> is
          <lb/>not the ſame all over the body, and depends <lb/>on the number of <hi rend="italic"
            >laminæ</hi> of which it con- <lb/>ſiſts. It adheres cloſely to the ſkin, runs in
          <lb/>between the muſcles in general, and between <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">ſeveral</hi>
          fibres in particular, and commu- <lb/>nicates with the membranes which line the
          <lb/>inſide of the thorax and abdomen. The cel- <lb/>lular interſtices are ſo many little
          bags, or <lb/>ſachels, filled with an unctuous or oily juice, <lb/>more or leſs liquid,
          which is called fat. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">This ſubſtance (fat) increaſes in quanti- <lb/>ty be <hi
            rend="italic">reſt and good living</hi>; and, on the con- <lb/>trary, diminiſhes by <hi
            rend="italic">hard labour, and ſpare <lb/>diet</hi>. Why nouriſhment ſhould have this
          ef- <lb/>fect is eaſily conceived; and it is likewiſe <lb/>eaſy to ſee that an idle,
          ſedentary life muſt <lb/>render the fat leſs fluid, and conſequently <lb/>more liable to
          block up the paſſages of in- <lb/>ſenſible perſpiration, through which it would
          <lb/>otherwiſe run off. Hard labour diſſolves it, <lb/>and conſequently fits it for
          paſſing out of the <lb/>body with the other matter of inſenſible per- <lb/>ſpiration. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>From the above accurate anatomical <lb/>deſcription, it may be obſerved, that the
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">membrana adipoſa</hi> covers every part of <lb/>the body directly
        under the ſkin, and is <lb/>alſo diſtributed, not only on every <lb/>muſcle, but alſo
        between every fibre of <lb/>the muſcles, and juſt under the ſkin is <lb/>placed a great
        number of ſmall glands <lb/>in this membrane. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Notwithſtanding this cellular mem- <lb/>brane is ſo well deſcribed, and traced to
        <lb/>cover every fibre, and every muſcle, as <lb/>well the whole outſide and inſide of the
        <lb/>human body, which proves that it was <lb/>deſigned for ſome great and particular
        <lb/>uſe, yet little or no uſe has been attri- <lb/>buted to it. I ſhall therefore endeavour
        <lb/>to point out ſome of the uſes belonging <lb/>to this univerſal membrane. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the firſt place, it appears to be the <lb/>parts deſigned by Nature to carry on the
          <pb n="233"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>increaſe and growth of every part of the <lb/>body, from childhood to manhood, and
        <lb/>is analogous to the ſmalleſt capillary <lb/>fibres of the roots of vegetables. After
        <lb/>the nouriſhment received into the ſto- <lb/>mach, and by the chyle veſſels is car-
        <lb/>ried into the blood by the ſubclavian <lb/>vein, which empties itſelf into the <hi
          rend="italic">vena <lb/>cava</hi>, from thence to the right auricle <lb/>and ventricle of
        the heart, and after <lb/>paſſing through the lungs, it is ſent into <lb/>the left auricle
        and ventricle of the heart, <lb/>and there diſtributed, by the arteries, to <lb/>the extreme
        parts of the body, where it <lb/>again meets with the reſiſtance of preſ- <lb/>ſure of the
        atmoſphere, by which means <lb/>it is forced by the ſmall ramifications of <lb/>the arteries
        into the ſmall ramifications <lb/>of the veins. If this ſupply is more <lb/>than ſufficient
        for that purpoſe, a part <lb/>of it paſſes into the cellular membrane, <lb/>and other parts
        are perſpired by the pores <lb/>of the ſkin. Being arrived in this mem- <lb/>brane, every
        thing neceſſary for the in- <lb/>creaſe and ſupport of all parts of the <lb/>body is
        diſtributed to each part from it. <lb/>If a reſidue overplus remains, it is re- <lb/>ſerved
        therein in the form of <hi rend="italic">fat</hi>, as in <lb/>a ſtorehouſe, to ſupply any
        wants or oc- <lb/>caſion for it; after this, the neceſſary <lb/>overplus is abſorbed by the
        lymphatick <lb/>glands, and carried by the lymphatick <lb/>veſſels to the kidneys and guts,
        and <lb/>there diſcharged. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This membrane and its abſorbent <lb/>glands, are the parts whereby peſtilen- <lb/>tial
        infection is received, for theſe in- <lb/>fectious <hi rend="italic">miaſmata</hi> are here
        received, and <lb/>not by the lungs, as is generally, though <lb/>erroneousſly, ſuppoſed.
        Here the vari- <lb/>olous matter for the ſmall pox is intro- <lb/>duced by inoculation, and
        here it acts; <lb/>and after inflammation, at its criſis, mat- <lb/>ter is formed and
        diſcharged, and the <lb/>conſtitution relieved. In the ſame man- <lb/>ner all inflammations
        are formed on this <lb/>membrane, which muſt either be diſ- <lb/>perſed or abſorbed, and
        then diſcharged <lb/>on the ſkin, kidneys, or guts, or be <lb/>formed into pus, and then
        diſcharged; <lb/>as, if Nature is not ſtrong enough to <lb/>perform this, or is overloaded,
        it be- <lb/>comes putrid, and the patient ſinks un- <lb/>der it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Having deſcribed the <hi rend="italic">membrana adi- <lb/>poſa</hi>, with its uſes, and
        alſo having <lb/>ſhewn that it is the ſeat of inflamma- <lb/>tions and abſceſſes, and
        obſerving the firſt <lb/><hi rend="italic">ſtadium</hi> of the gout to be of that kind;
        <lb/>I ſhall next endeavour to trace out how <lb/>the gout is generated, and how it acts,
          <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>with the probable method of prevention <lb/>and cure. </p>
      <trailer rend="italic">(To be continued.) </trailer>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
