<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: A Treatise on Tropical Diseases</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknwon</persName>
            </author>
            <title>A Treatise on Tropical Diseases, on Military Operations, and on the Climate of
              the West Indies . By Benjamin Moseley, M. D. &amp;c. &amp;c. (Continued from vol. LXI.
              p. 1133.)</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine: and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed by John Nichols, at Cicero's Head, Red Lion Passage,
                  Fleet-Street: And Sold by Eliz. Newbery, the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard,
                  Ludgate-Street. 1792. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1792</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">62</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">60</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1792_GM_0060">
    <body>
      <pb n="60"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">10.</hi> A Treatiſe on Tropical Diſeaſes, on Military <lb/>Operations,
        and on the Climate of the <hi rend="roman">Weſt <lb/>Indies</hi>. By <hi rend="roman"
          >Benjamin Moſeley</hi>, M. D. <lb/><hi rend="roman">&amp;c. &amp;c.</hi> (Continued from
        vol. LXI. p. 1133.) </head>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>IN the Hiſtory of Epidemic Dyſen- <lb/>teries, Dr. M. has demonſtrated, that <lb/>the
        diſeaſe is a <hi rend="italic">fever of the inteſtines</hi>, de- <lb/>riving its origin from
          <hi rend="italic">obſtructed perſpira- <lb/>tion</hi>, depending on <q rend="diple quotes"
          >ſome ſecret influ- <lb/>ence in the atmoſphere, or ſudden <lb/>tranſitions of the air, or
          ſuch other <lb/>cauſes as expoſe people to have this <lb/>diſcharge haſtily ſtopped: </q>
        and from <lb/>the various opportunities which he has <lb/>had of treating it, he draws the
        follow- <lb/>ing important concluſion: that <q rend="diple quotes">he has <lb/>univerſally
          found it relieved by turn- <lb/>ing back that diſcharge to its natural <lb/>channel by the
          means of ſudorifics, <lb/>and that he has ſeldom found diffi- <lb/>culty in removing it
          ſpeedily, when <lb/>taken in the beginning. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After deſcanting on formulæ and me- <lb/>dicines, which have been reputed ſpe-
        <lb/>cifics in the bloody flux, Dr. M. ſhews <lb/>that their beneficial effects have really
        <lb/>been exerted at the cutaneous pores, as <lb/>diaphoretics; though this fact has hi- <pb
          n="61"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>therto been overlooked by practitioners. <lb/>This Dr. M. aſſerts is peculiarly the
        <lb/>caſe with all antimonials, after their e- <lb/>metic, or purgative, operation is over.
        <lb/>Antimonials alone, or with laudanum, <lb/>ipecacuanha, &amp;c. varied according to
        <lb/>circumſtances, are the principal agents <lb/>to be employed; but Dr. M. obſerves
        <lb/>that the cure depends <q rend="diple quotes">on a careful <lb/>continued courſe of
          ſudorifics, to keep <lb/>up a ſweat, in extent proportioned to <lb/>the violence of the
          diſeaſe; and not <lb/>on the trifling way of giving them in <lb/>ſmall doſes, while the
          patient is ex- <lb/>poſed, and their operation neglected. <lb/>The ſudorific employed muſt
          be ſuit- <lb/>able to the nature of the flux; the <lb/>ſtage of it; and the habit of the
          pa- <lb/>tient. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This is the outline of the great ſyſtem <lb/>which Dr. M. has promulgated for the
        <lb/>treatment of epidemic dyſenteries, when <lb/>raging in fleets, armies, and populous
        <lb/>cities. Thoſe, almoſt annual, dyſente- <lb/>ric complaints, which appear at the end
        <lb/>of ſummer, he obſerves, are eaſily re- <lb/>moved by purgatives, abſorbents, and
        <lb/>anodynes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Dr. M's practice is decidedly, in ge- <lb/>neral, antiphlogiſtic; and has eſtabliſhed
        <lb/>the law of phyſic in the Weſtern world. <lb/>Such was <hi rend="italic"
        >Sydenham's</hi>, and every popu- <lb/>lar phyſician's on record. The extra- <lb/>vagant,
        and <hi rend="italic">intoxicating</hi> doctrine of <lb/>Ασθένι <gap reason="illegible"/>,
        is the offspring of inexperience <lb/>and theory:—the miſchiefs of which, <lb/>have been
        more extenſive <choice>
          <corr>than</corr>
          <sic>that</sic>
        </choice> is gene- <lb/>rally known. It is queſtionable, whe- <lb/>ther practical writers in
        medicine have <lb/>done more good, than theoriſts injury, <lb/>to mankind. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In theory, the <hi rend="italic">bilious remittent fever</hi>, <lb/>the <hi
          rend="italic">putrid bilious fever</hi>, and what has <lb/>been improperly called the <hi
          rend="italic">yellow fe- <lb/>ver</hi>, of the Weſt Indies, have been <lb/>confounded
        together. In the practical <lb/>work before us, we ſee their ſpecific dif- <lb/>ference; and
        this knowledge ſeems to <lb/>have been much wanted in the Weſt <lb/>Indies. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the laſt diſeaſe, Dr. M. has be- <lb/>ſtowed a diſſertation of conſiderable ex-
        <lb/>tent; in which he has clearly evinced, <lb/>that the <hi rend="italic">yellow
          fever</hi> is an aggravated <lb/>degree of the European <hi rend="italic">cauſus</hi>. The
        <lb/>treatiſe on this diſeaſe was originally <lb/>publiſhed in Latin; and was Dr. M's
        <lb/>inaugural theſis, at the Univerſity of <lb/>Leyden, under the title, <q rend="quotes"
          >De Cauſo <lb/>Tropico Endemico, five Febre Flavâ, <lb/>quæ in Indiis Occidentalibus
          obſerva- <lb/>tur. </q>
      </p>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As the Latin original is before us, <lb/>we ſhall, in our next month's Magazine,
        <lb/>make our extracts from that, referring <lb/>our Engliſh readers to tiie Engliſh edi-
        <lb/>tion. </p>
      <trailer rend="italic align-center">
        <lb/>(To be continued.) </trailer>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
