<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: A very effectual Remedy for the Bite of a Viper</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>A very effectual Remedy for the Bite of a Viper</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine: and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed by John Nichols, at Cicero's Head, Red Lion Passage,
                  Fleet-Street; where letters are particularly requested to be sent, And Sold by
                  Elizabeth Newbery, the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard, Ludgate-Street. 1798.
                </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1798</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">68</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">479</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1798_GM_0479">
    <body>
      <pb n="479"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <salute rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="sc">Urban</hi>, </salute>
      <dateline rend="align-right"><hi rend="italic">June</hi> 6. </dateline>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>N anſwer to your correſpondent, <lb/>p. 392, who is deſirous of
        knowing <lb/>a remedy for the bite of that dangerous <lb/>reptile the viper, I beg to
        acquaint <lb/>him that the fat of the animal, or vi- <lb/>per-oil, which may always be had
        at <lb/>Covent-garden of the viper-catchers, <lb/>is ſaid to be the only ſpecifick uſed by
        <lb/>them, and conſidered as infallible. A <lb/>gentleman of my acquaintance ſays, <lb/>that
        he has known gooſe-greaſe ap- <lb/>plied to the limb bitten, and well rub- <lb/>bed-in, cure
        dogs: and I was told by <lb/>another that, in the Highlands of Scot- <lb/>land, where they
        are ſaid to be very <lb/>numerous in the extenſive heaths of <lb/>that country, the people
        apply a com- <lb/>mon oatmeal poultice, which ſoon diſ- <lb/>perſes the ſwelling. In the
        Eaſt In- <lb/>dies, where ſerpents of every ſpecies, <lb/>and of the moſt deadly nature,
        abound, <lb/>they have their conjurers, who pretend <lb/>to cure the bite of the Gomunda, or
        <lb/>hood-ſnake, by charms; but there is <lb/>nothing they rely ſo much upon as an
        <lb/>immediate application of the actual <lb/>cautery, where it can be done with
        <lb/>ſafety; and I have myſelf witneſſed its <lb/>beneficial effects in more than one in-
        <lb/>ſtance. But that neither of theſe re- <lb/>medies can be depended upon as ſpeci-
        <lb/>ficks to the venom of the viper, and <lb/>to prevent its ſpreading itſelf into the
        <lb/>habit, the following relation will ſhew. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I had the misfortune to be bitten <lb/>laſt ſummer by a viper on the outſide <lb/>of my
        right leg, a little above the an- <lb/>cle. I did not ſee the reptile, as I was <lb/>among
        ſome ſhrubs at the time, which <lb/>concealed it from my view. I imagine <lb/>I muſt have
        trod upon it, as it was <lb/>baſking in the ſun. I felt a ſmart <lb/>burning ſenſation,
        accompanied at firſt <lb/>with an intenſe itching, which ſoon <lb/>went off, but the burning
        continued, <lb/>which I could only compare to the <lb/>action of a cauſtick. I looked for
        the <lb/>animal, but it was gone. There was <lb/>a ſpot of blood upon my ſtocking, the
        <lb/>ſize of half a crown. As I was not <lb/>far from my houſe, I immediately <lb/>went
        home, and, on taking off my <lb/>ſtocking, I perceived the part ſwelled <lb/>and livid to
        the circumference of two <lb/>inches, with two punctures made by <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>the teeth of the reptile; and there was <lb/>a degree of numbneſs to the touch. I
        <lb/>ordered a large caſe-knife to be made <lb/>red hot, and immediately cauterized <lb/>the
        entire ſurface of the part ſwelled <lb/>with my own hand; and, to make <lb/>ſure, applied
        the knife a ſecond time. <lb/>I think that this operation was per- <lb/>formed within leſs
        than a quarter of an <lb/>hour from receiving the bite. I then <lb/>anointed that foot and
        leg well with <lb/>viper-oil, and the whole ſurface of my <lb/>body with common olive-oil,
        both <lb/>which I repeated that evening, and <lb/>applied a poultice of bread and milk
        <lb/>and oil to the wound. I continued the <lb/>ſame applications, and repeated the oil
        <lb/>univerſally three times the next day. <lb/>My ancle and the lower part of my leg
        <lb/>ſwelled conſiderably, became very <lb/>painful; and, the ſecond morning, I <lb/>found
        the joint ſo ſtiff that I could not <lb/>move it, and it was with the utmoſt <lb/>difficulty
        I could get down ſtairs; and <lb/>the burning heat in it was ſo great that <lb/>I could not
        bear it under the bed- <lb/>cloaths. I now began to be rather <lb/>alarmed, and ſent for my
        ſurgeon, <lb/>who ſeemed to think the precautions I <lb/>had taken ſufficient, and that the
        pain <lb/>and ſwelling might be occaſioned by <lb/>the cautery, and dreſſed it as a com-
        <lb/>mon burn. I felt from the firſt a de- <lb/>gree of irritability and quickneſs of
        <lb/>pulſe, and want of reſt, and a ſinking <lb/>in the bed as if my head wanted ſup-
        <lb/>port, although ſuſtained by two pil- <lb/>lows and a bolſter. The third evening <lb/>I
        felt my extremities unuſually cold, <lb/>although the weather was uncommonly <lb/>warm, the
        thermometer, in a North- <lb/>ern aſpect, having been that day above <lb/>80. On going
        to-bed, I had the ſame <lb/>ſinking ſenſation, and ſoon after was <lb/>attacked with a
        violent burning pain <lb/>and contraction of the ſtomach and <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >præcordia</hi>, as if the whole region was <lb/>compreſſed with a hot iron ligature,
        <lb/>attended with palpitations of the heart, <lb/>great difficulty of breathing bordering
        <lb/>on ſuffocation, ſpaſms, cramps, and <lb/>numbneſs, darting from the centre to <lb/>the
        extremities of my hands like elec- <lb/>trical ſhocks, with a diſpoſition to con-
        <lb/>tract, which I exerted my utmoſt muſ- <lb/>cular force to counteract. I was in
        <lb/>ſuch torture that I did not expect to <lb/>ſurvive till the morning. I took 40
        <lb/>drops of juniper peppermint, and re- <lb/>peated the doſe, without relief. My <lb/>wife
        would have ſent for my doctor; <lb/>but, as he lived at the diſtance of eight <pb n="480"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>miles, I told her that it was needleſs, <lb/>for that I ſhould be either dead or well
        <lb/>before he could come. She then fo- <lb/>mented my ſtomach with flannels <lb/>wrung out
        of hot water; and as the <lb/>end of an hour I felt ſome eaſe, and <lb/>the above ſymptoms
        gradually went <lb/>off. I then took a large wine-glaſs <lb/>full of Clarke's gout cordial,
        and im- <lb/>mediately felt the blood run warm to <lb/>my extremities, which till now had
        <lb/>remained cold. When I related my <lb/>ſufferings to my doctor next morning, <lb/>he
        ſaid that, if an abſorption of the <lb/>poiſon had taken place, I ſhould feel it <lb/>in the
        lymphaticks; and, on feeling <lb/>the inguinal gland, I found it hard, <lb/>ſore, and
        ſwelled to the ſize of a nut- <lb/>meg. I had likewiſe a ſlight numb- <lb/>neſs from my chin
        extending up to my <lb/>right ear, accompanied by a ſlight de- <lb/>gree of puffineſs. This
        ſoon ſubſided; <lb/>but the gland in my groin continued <lb/>ſore and enlarged for ſeveral
        weeks. <lb/>At firſt the wound had only a gleety <lb/>wateriſh ſanious diſcharge; but, in
        <lb/>about ten days it began to mend, but <lb/>continued uncommonly irritable and <lb/>ſore
        till nearly healed, which did not <lb/>take place till full ſeven weeks from <lb/>the
        accident. The ſkin remained of a <lb/>yellowiſh jaundice-like hue, wherever <lb/>the
        ſwelling had extended, for a con- <lb/>ſiderable time after, with a purpliſh <lb/>ſpot and
        ſoreneſs about the ancle; and <lb/>I felt a conſiderable degree of weak- <lb/>neſs in that
        ancle, with a ſlight numb- <lb/>neſs in my heel, till January laſt, full <lb/>ſix months
        from the accident. I had <lb/>ſeveral blind boils and blotches come <lb/>out upon that leg
        and thigh, and one <lb/>on the oppoſite ancle, in the courſe of <lb/>my cure. I felt a great
        degree of lan- <lb/>guor and laſſitude for above a month, <lb/>with a loſs of appetite. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>You will ſee from the above narra- <lb/>tive, Mr. Urban, that no precautions <lb/>can
        be conſidered as an effectual ſecu- <lb/>rity againſt the bite of theſe dangerous
        <lb/>reptiles. I took nothing internally. <lb/>No doubt, the viper-oil and unctions
        <lb/>were of ſervice; but I attribute my <lb/>recovery principally to the cautery,
        <lb/>which, I am perſuaded, muſt have de- <lb/>ſtroyed great part of the poiſon; and <lb/>I
        have the fulleſt conviction in my own <lb/>mind, that my life was preſerved by <lb/>that
        application, which I would ſtrong- <lb/>ly recommend to all perſons who may <lb/>be ſo
        unhappy as to experience the like <lb/>misfortune; and I have no doubt that <lb/>it would be
        equally effectual with ani- <lb/>mals. </p>
      <signed rend="align-right sc">Wm. Young. </signed>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <postscript>
        <p rend="indent space size(0.8)">
          <lb/>
          <label>⁂ </label> V. and B. ſays, <q rend="quotes">A ſolution of <lb/>common ſalt in warm
            water, applied early, <lb/>and continued ſome time to the wound, is <lb/>the beſt
            application. </q>
        </p>
      </postscript>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
