<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Acid of Lemons and Limes-and Raw Carrots-for
          Scurvy.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Acid of Lemons and Limes-and Raw Carrots-for Scurvy.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine: and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed by John Nichols, at Cicero's Head, Red Lion Passage,
                  Fleet-Street; where letters are particularly requested to be sent, And Sold by
                  Elizabeth Newbery, the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard, Ludgate-Street. 1798.
                </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1798</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">68</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">1029</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1798_GM_1029">
    <body>
      <pb n="1029"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <salute rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="sc">Urban</hi>, </salute>
      <dateline rend="align-right"><hi rend="italic">Dec.</hi> 7. </dateline>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi> AM pleaſed to ſee that my hints <lb/>reſpecting the uſe of <hi
          rend="italic">raw carrots</hi>
        <lb/>in the Sea-ſcurvy have ſerved to call <lb/>forth the attention of ſome of your
        <lb/>readers to this diſorder. It would <lb/>ſeem that your correſpondent (p. 945)
        <lb/>imagines he has ſuggeſted a new re- <lb/>medy againſt this complaint, when he
        <lb/>propoſes the <hi rend="italic">aqua vitriolica diluta</hi>, or <lb/>ſmall ſpirit of
        vitriol; but I beg leave <lb/>to inform him, that not only this, but <lb/>other mineral
        acids, have been em- <lb/>ployed for this purpoſe; and in many <lb/>inſtances they have had
        a beneficial <lb/>effect; but, on the whole, they have <lb/>been found much leſs powerful in
        <lb/>counteracting the Marine-ſcurvy than <lb/>the vegetable acids, and more eſpe-
        <lb/>cially than freſh fruits and freſh roots. <lb/>The elixir of vitriol (which is nothing
        <lb/>more than ſpirit of vitriol mixed with <lb/>brandy or ſpirit of wine, ſpiced with
        <lb/>cinnamon, ginger, &amp;c.) was recom- <lb/>mended long ago by Huxham; and <lb/>Dr.
        Addington (father of the preſent <lb/>Speaker of the Houſe of Commons) <lb/>propoſed the
        ſpirit of ſea ſalt, 10 drops <lb/>of which, added to a pint of freſh wa- <lb/>ter, give it
        an agreeable acidity. He <lb/>directed 20 drops to be taken by each <lb/>patient every day.
        The nitrous acid <lb/>has been tried by others; but, next to <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
          >freſh</hi> juice of lemons, vinegar, ſpi- <lb/>ced with ginger and muſtard-ſeed, is
        <lb/>the beſt acid that can be employed in <lb/>the Sea ſcurvy. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Your correſpondent ſays, that roots <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>of every kind (meaning all kinds of <lb/><hi rend="italic">eſculent</hi> roots) are
        antiſcorbutic; and <lb/>adds, that turneps would be as good <lb/>as carrots. But I will give
        ſome rea- <lb/>ſons why they are not. Turneps are <lb/>ſcarcely at all nutritious (though
        nu- <lb/>triment is much wanted in the <lb/>Scurvy); and they are, moreover, <lb/>ſo cold
        and watery, that, if they were <lb/>eaten <hi rend="italic">raw</hi> (as they muſt be when
        in- <lb/>tended to act as antiſcorbutics) they <lb/>would produce violent flatulence and
        <lb/>colic, which might end in death. It <lb/>is not ſo with carrots; they poſſeſs <lb/>much
        nutritive power; and, being <lb/>aromatic, may be eaten <hi rend="italic">raw</hi>, in con-
        <lb/>ſiderable quantities, without any of <lb/>the bad conſequences juſt mentioned. <lb/>On
        account of their periſhable nature, <lb/>it would be impoſſible to keep turneps <lb/>beyond
        a week or two at ſea; few <lb/>vegetable ſubſtance ſpoil and rot <lb/>ſooner than they do;
        whereas carrots <lb/>may be preſerved (in the way I have <lb/>before mentioned) for the
        ſpace of 10 <lb/>or 12 months. Packed up in caſks, <lb/>they would not occupy more room than
        <lb/>the caſks of ſour-crout, oranges and <lb/>lemons, apples, &amp;c. which are now
        <lb/>taken on-board during Winter-crui- <lb/>ſes; and, in regard to expence, they <lb/>would
        certainly coſt much leſs than <lb/>the vegetable ſubſtances laſt-men- <lb/>tioned. But your
        correſpondent re- <lb/>marks, that <q rend="quotes">the ſaccharine juices <lb/>of carrots do
          not appear from experi- <lb/>ence to be equal to aceſcent juices. </q>
        <lb/>I do not aſſert that they are equal to <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">freſh</hi> acid
        juices of lemons, oran- <lb/>ges, and apples; I only maintain <lb/>that they are ſuperior to
        theſe acid <lb/>juices after they have become ſpoilt <lb/>by long keeping: and that, as
        theſe <lb/>fruits are exceedingly dear, as they <lb/>cannot always be procured in ſuffi-
        <lb/>cient quantity, and as, moreover, they <lb/>cannot be kept for much length of <lb/>time
        without loſing their ſalutary pro- <lb/>perties; ſuch roots as the garden-car- <lb/>rots,
        which are not very dear, may <lb/>always be procured in this country, <lb/>will keep well,
          <hi rend="italic">and are known to be <lb/>antiſcorbutic</hi>, are, all circumſtances
        <lb/>conſidered, the beſt vegetable ſub- <lb/>ſtances that can be employed for the
        <lb/>prevention of the Scurvy on-board <lb/>of our ſhips. When your correſpon- <lb/>dent
        ſlights the ſweet juices of vege- <lb/>tables as antiſcorbutics, he ſeems not <lb/>to know
        that melaſſes have been <lb/>found of excellent dietetic uſe in the <pb n="1030"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>Marine-ſcurvy<unclear>:</unclear> and that the <hi rend="italic">freſh</hi>
        <lb/>juice of the ſugar-cane cures it effec- <lb/>tually. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I ſee no objection to letting the ſai- <lb/>lors have their daily allowance of wa-
        <lb/>ter of grog moderately acidulated with <lb/>ſpirit of vitriol, or ſpiced vinegar, at
        <lb/>the ſame time that they are uſing the <lb/><hi rend="italic">raw</hi> carrots; but it
        muſt be remem- <lb/>bered, that the acidulated drink alone <lb/>is not an adequate remedy. </p>
      <signed rend="sc align-right">
        <lb/>A Friend to the Navy. </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
