<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Sherwen: Dr. Sherwen's Letter on the Scurvy</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>John Sherwen</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Dr. Sherwen's Letter on the Scurvy Concluded</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine: and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed by John Nichols, at Cicero's Head, Red Lion Passage,
                  Fleet-Street; where letters are particularly requested to be sent, And Sold by
                  Elizabeth Newbery, the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard, Ludgate-Street. 1798.
                </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1798</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">68</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">192</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1798_GM_0192">
    <body>
      <pb n="192"/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <head rend="italic align-center">
        <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="sc">Sherwen's</hi> Letter to Dr. <hi rend="sc">Mil- <lb/>man</hi>.
        (Concluded from p. 108.) </head>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>T would, perhaps, have been pru- <lb/>dent in me to have reſted
        ſatisfied <lb/>with the honour or diſgrace of the pro- <lb/>poſal <note place="bottom" n="*"
          rend="size(0.8)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* To render the ſcurvy, like ſalivation, <lb/>the means of curing other diſeaſes.
          </p>
        </note>, without preſuming to point out <lb/>the particular caſes in which I may con-
        <lb/>ceive ſuch a proceſs as that of ſcorbu- <lb/>ticizing the ſyſtem likely to anſwer a
        <lb/>ſalutary purpoſe. I cannot, however, <lb/>refrain from offering a conjecture upon
        <lb/>this occaſion. I have long had it in <lb/>contemplation to propoſe, by means of
        <lb/>ſcorbuticiſing the ſyſtem, to render <lb/>the blood a <hi rend="italic">menſtruum</hi>
        for the ſolu- <lb/>tion of polypous concretions. Poſſi- <lb/>bly the idea may not be ſo new
        as it <lb/>appears to me. The view which I <lb/>have formerly taken of this diſeaſe
        <lb/>leads me to ſuppoſe, that the blood <lb/>and juices of ſcorbutic patients are <lb/>more
        acrimonious and ſaline than <lb/>thoſe of perſons in a good ſtate of <lb/>health <note
          place="bottom" rend="size(0.8)" n="†">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>† This being a diſputed point, candour <lb/>compels me to acknowledge that, in the
            <lb/>caſe of Mr. H—, the blood dropping <lb/>from his noſe had as florid a colour, and
            <lb/>was apparently of as good a conſiſtence, <lb/>as in any oher inſtance of hæmorrhage
            <lb/>from that part that I ever remember to have <lb/>ſeen. There was alſo a redneſs on
            his <lb/>cheeks, although much leſs now than what <lb/>was natural to him, yet ſuch as I
            ſhould <lb/>formerly have deemed altogether incom- <lb/>patible with the exiſtence of
            ſcurvy. The <lb/>fungus excreſcence on the ankle was alſo <lb/>longer in getting well
            than the <hi rend="italic">maculæ <lb/>ſcorbuticæ</hi> in diſappearing. This fungus at
            <lb/>laſt yielded to pledgits of lint wet with a <lb/>mixture of lemon-juice and
            tincture of <lb/>myrrh. </p>
        </note>. If ſuch be the caſe, and I <lb/>think ſome of the phænomena of the <lb/>diſeaſe
        warrant the ſuppoſition, may <lb/>it not be poſſible to diſſolve a poly- <lb/>pous
        concretion in the heart by uſing <lb/>ſalt as a medicine, or ſalted animal <lb/>food as
        diet, until ſcorbutic appearan- <lb/>ces take place? To inflict one diſ- <lb/>eaſe with a
        view to leſſen or alleviate <lb/>another is no new idea in phyſick ; and <lb/>the one here
        propoſed is ſo much in <lb/>our power, and ſo eaſy to be kept un- <lb/>der controul, that a
        patient might be <lb/>expoſed to its influence to a certain <lb/>degree for almoſt any
        length of time <lb/>with ſafety; ripe fruits and vegetable <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>acids being always at hand to be <lb/>thrown in whenever it ſhould appear <lb/>to be
        making too rapid a progreſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It may be alledged, that the pa- <lb/>thognomonic ſymptoms of polypous <lb/>concretions
        in the heart are not ſuffi- <lb/>ciently diſtinguiſhable from ſpaſmodic <lb/>affections of
        that organ, to enable us to <lb/>judge of their exiſtence with ſo much <lb/>certainty as to
        warrant the infliction of <lb/>a dangerous diſeaſe, even admitting <lb/>the probability of
        its <choice>
          <corr>anſwering</corr>
          <sic>aſwering</sic>
        </choice> a uſeful <lb/>purpoſe. I cannot, however, help <lb/>thinking that, by a diligent
        attention <lb/>to all the circumſtances, and to the pa- <lb/>tient's deſcription of his own
        feelings, <lb/>a very probable opinion may often be <lb/>formed. The peculiar <hi
          rend="italic">guſhing</hi> and <lb/><hi rend="italic">whizzing</hi> noiſe deſcribed by Mr.
        Hol- <lb/>der, in the caſe ſo well related by Dr. <lb/>Cheſton, of Glouceſter, in the 6th
        <lb/>volume of the Edinburgh Medical <lb/>Commentaries for 1785, appears to <lb/>me to
        convey irreſiſtible teſtimony to <lb/>the exiſtence of a polypus, or ſome <lb/>mechanical
        obſtruction, in the heart <lb/>in that particular caſe. Bloody or <lb/>grumous <hi
          rend="italic">Polypi</hi> are doubtleſs moſt <lb/>commonly formed in the moment of
        <lb/>Death; but a firm <hi rend="italic">coagulum</hi>, reſem- <lb/>bling the buff-coat of
        inflamed blood, <lb/>muſt have exiſted in the heart long <lb/>before the death of the
        patient in <lb/>whom it is found. The caſe of Mr. <lb/>Holder is in this reſpect deciſive;
        and, <lb/>had it been known to me in his life- <lb/>time, would have ſubjected him to the
        <lb/>obtruſion of this propoſal. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That polypous concretions are not <lb/>always formed in the heart in the mo- <lb/>ment
        of death will be evident from <lb/>the peruſal of a very extraordinary <lb/>tract which now
        lies before me, inti- <lb/>tuled, </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">A moſt certaine and true Relation of <lb/>a ſtrange Monſter or Serpent,
          found in <lb/>the left Ventricle of the Heart of John Pen- <lb/>nant, Gentleman, of the
          age of 21 yeares. <lb/>By Edward May, Doctor of Philoſophy <lb/>and Phyſick, and Profeſſor
          elect of them <lb/>in the Colledge of the Academy of No- <lb/>blemen, called the <hi
            rend="italic">Muſæum Minervæ</hi>; <lb/>Phyſitian alſo extraordinary unto her moſt
          <lb/>Sacred Majeſty, Queene of Great Britta- <lb/>ny, &amp;c. London, 1639. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This tract is dedicated <q rend="quotes">to the Right <lb/>Honourable Lord and highly
          renown- <lb/>ed Peere of this Kingdome, Edward, <lb/>Earl of Dorſet, </q> &amp;c. &amp;c.;
        and ap- <lb/>pears alſo in the form of <q rend="quotes">A Letter <lb/>to the right
          worſhipful Sir Theodore <lb/>Maiherne, Knight; chiefe Phyſitian <pb n=""/>
          <figure>
            <figDesc>An illustration of a heart, where a spiral-like polyp is visible. </figDesc>
          </figure>
          <pb n="193"/>
          <cb n="1"/>
          <lb/>unto his moſt Soveraigne Majeſty, <lb/>King of Great Brittany. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That a ſubſtance, under the form <lb/>deſcribed, was actually found in the <lb/>heart
        of Mr. Pennant cannot be <lb/>doubted; and the tract, being very <lb/>ſcarce and curious,
        will juſtify a few <lb/>extracts. It contains two plates, re- <lb/>preſenting, in different
        views, this <lb/>polypous concretion, for ſuch no <lb/>doubt every modem medical reader
        <lb/>will pronounce it, although it muſt be <lb/>confeſſed the figure under which it
        <lb/>appears, together with the teſtimonies <lb/>and description, would almoſt com- <lb/>pel
        one to believe it a large organized <lb/>reptile. </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">No ſooner was that ventricle emptied <lb/>but Mr. Heydon, ſtill
          complaining of the <lb/>greatneſſe and hardneſſe of the ſame, my- <lb/>ſelfe ſeeming to
          neglect his words becauſe <lb/>the left ventricle is thrice as thick of fleſh <lb/>as the
          right is in ſound men, for conſerva- <lb/>tion of vital ſpirits, I directed him to ano-
          <lb/>ther diſquiſition; but he, keeping his hand <lb/>ſtill upon the heart, would not
          leave it, <lb/>but ſaid againe that it was of a ſtrange <lb/>greatneſſe and hardneſſe;
          whereupon I <lb/>deſired him to cut the orifice wider; by <lb/>which meanes we preſently
          perceived a <lb/>carnouſe ſubſtance, as it ſeemed to us, <lb/>wreathed together in foldes
          like a worm or <lb/>ſerpent, the ſelf ſame form expreſſed in <lb/>the firſt icnography; at
          which we both <lb/>much wondered, and I entreated him to <lb/>ſeparate it from the heart,
          which he did, <lb/>and we carried it from the body to the <lb/>window, and there layed it
          out in thoſe <lb/>juſt dimenſions which are here expreſſed in <lb/>the ſecond figure. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">The body was white, of the very co- <lb/>lour of the whiteſt ſkin of
          man's body; <lb/>but the ſkin was bright and ſhining, as if it <lb/>had beene varniſhed
          over; the head all <lb/>bloody, and ſo like the head of a ſerpent, <lb/>that the lady
          Herris then ſhivered to ſee it, <lb/> and ſince hath often ſpoken it, that ſhe <lb/>was
          inwardly troubled at it, becauſe the <lb/>head of it was ſo truely like the head of a
          <lb/>ſnake. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">The thighs and branches were of <lb/>fleſh-colour, as alſo all thoſe
          fibres, <lb/>ſtrings, nerves, or whatſoever elſe they <lb/>were. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">After much contemplation and con- <lb/>jectures what ſtrange thing that
          part of the <lb/>heart had brought forth unto us, I reſol- <lb/>ved to try the certainty,
          and to make full <lb/>exploration; both for mine own experi- <lb/>ence and ſatisfaction,
          as alſo to give true <lb/>teſtimony to others that ſhould heare of it; <lb/>and thereupon
          I ſearched all parts of it, <lb/>to finde whether it were a pituitoſe and <lb/>bloody
          collection or the like, or a true or- <lb/>ganicall body and conception. I firſt <cb n="2"/>
          <lb/>ſearched the head, and found it of a thick <lb/>ſubſtance, bloody and glandulous
          about <lb/>the necke, ſomewhat broken (as I con- <lb/>ceived) by a ſudden or violent
          ſeparation of <lb/>it from the heart, which yet ſeemed to me <lb/>to come from it eaſily
          enough. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">The body I ſearched likewiſe with a <lb/>bodkin betweene the leggs or
          thighs, and <lb/>I found it perforate, or hollow, and a ſolid <lb/>body, to the very
          length of a ſilver bodkin, <lb/>as is here deſcribed; at which the ſpec- <lb/>tators
          wondered. And, as not crediting <lb/>me, ſome of them tooke the bodkin after <lb/>me, made
          tryal themſelves, and remained <lb/>ſatisfied that there was a gut, vein, or ar-
          <lb/>tery, or ſome ſuch analogicall thing, that <lb/>was to ſerve that monſter for uſes
          naturall; <lb/>amongſt whom the lady Herris and the ſur- <lb/>gian made tryall after me
          with their own <lb/>hands, and have given their hands that this <lb/>relation is true.
        </q> Pp. 5, 6, 7. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Unfortunately the remainder of the <lb/>account, although very copious in ab-
        <lb/>ſtruſe and learned phyſiognomical diſ- <lb/>quiſition, is very barren of the thing
        <lb/>moſt wanted, viz. an accurate hiſtory <lb/>of the manner of life and morbid
        <lb/>ſymptoms of the patient. Almoſt the <lb/>whole of this is contained in the fol-
        <lb/>lowing paragraph: </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">But I ſpeake more preciſely and punc- <lb/>tually, that now, in the left
          ventricle of the <lb/>heart, this worme or ſerpent hath beene <lb/>found; which the mother
          of the young <lb/>man ſaith was at leaſt of three yeares <lb/>growth, for ſo long he
          complained of his <lb/>breaſt, and as ſhe ſaith would never button <lb/>his doublet in the
          morning, but be open- <lb/>breaſted in all weathers, till he had waſhed <lb/>his hands and
          face; and was ſubject to <lb/>palpitations. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That peculiar pathological ſtate of <lb/>the animal œconomy, which we know <lb/>to be
        capable of diſſolving the ſolid <lb/><hi rend="italic">callus</hi> of a broken bone, or the
        firm <lb/>cicatrix of an old wound, may ſurely <lb/>act in the ſame manner upon a mere
        <lb/>depoſition of coagulable lymph. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Might not the ſame proceſs act upon <lb/>the bronchial polypus; a diſeaſe which, <lb/>I
        believe, never takes place but in <lb/>ſuch conſtitutions as thoſe which have <lb/>ſizy
        blood. This opinion will, I <lb/>think, be confirmed by a peruſal of <lb/>the caſe of
        bronchial polypus related <lb/>by Dr. Warren in the firſt volume of <lb/>the Medical
        Tranſactions. There is <lb/>alſo a caſe of the ſame nature, and <lb/>from which the ſame
        concluſion may <lb/>be drawn, in the Medical Commenta- <lb/>ries of Edinburgh for the years
        1783 <lb/>and 1784, vol. IX. p. 254. The diſ- <lb/>eaſe is here denominated <hi
          rend="italic">angina poly- <pb n="194"/>
          <cb n="1"/>
          <lb/>poſe</hi> by my worthy friend Dr. Joſhua <lb/>Dixon, phyſician at Whitehaven. It
        <lb/>has been aſſerted, that blood drawn <lb/>from ſcorbutic patients is ſometimes
        <lb/>ſizy; but I believe this to be a very <lb/>rare circumſtance, nor can I conceive
        <lb/>it poſſible to continue long in that <lb/>ſtate under the influence of ſuch a diſ-
        <lb/>eaſe. The teſtimony to this effect, as <lb/>related by Dr. Donald Monro, in the
        <lb/>ſecond volume of the Medical Tran- <lb/>ſactions, is not ſufficiently ſtrong to
        <lb/>admit of any concluſions being drawn <lb/>from it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is now prettv much the faſhion <lb/>for practitioners in ſurgery to apply
        <lb/>ſea-water, and ſolutions of common <lb/>ſalt in various forms, to hard and in-
        <lb/>dolent glandular ſwellings. There is <lb/>reaſon to believe that this practice is
        <lb/>ſometimes attended with ſucceſs; but <lb/>I have myſelf always preferred a ſolu-
        <lb/>tion of the common crude ſal-ammo- <lb/>niac. May not the efficacy of ſuch
        <lb/>applications be attributed rather to the <lb/>ſaline particles being taken into the
        <lb/>ſyſtem by abſorption, and giving acri- <lb/>mony to the general maſs of circula-
        <lb/>ting fluids, than to their acting merely <lb/>as topical applications? That they
        <lb/>may be admitted into the ſyſtem <hi rend="italic">ab <lb/>extra</hi>, ſo as to produce
        very powerful <lb/>effects, will probably appear from the <lb/>following caſe which fell
        under my <lb/>own obſervation: </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8) space">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">A. D. 1789. Virgo quædam, anno <lb/>ætatis ſuæ quadrageſimo-nono, habitu
          <lb/>corporis macro et attenuato, et colore oris <lb/>obſcuro, ob tumorem mammae durum,
          <lb/>quem per aliquot annos antea perſenſe- <lb/>rat, at jam, majore affecta dolore, et
          tu- <lb/>moris magnitudine creſcente, extractum <lb/>cicutæ ex ordine ingreſſa eſt. In
          reliquis <lb/>valetudine bona ſemper potita fuer<unclear>a</unclear>t. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">Extractum cicutæ, et cacut et ſtoma- <lb/>chum dolore afficiens
          omittebatur, et <lb/>chirurgi perclari conſilio, thermis ſalis ni- <lb/>gri (Anglice, <hi
            rend="italic">Bay-ſalt</hi>) et communis miſ- <lb/>tura ſaturatis, uti incipiebat
          ægrota. Hoc <lb/>genere thermarum bis ſingulis hebdomma- <lb/>dis conſtanter ſervato, et
          tumore nequa- <lb/>quam emendato valetudine quidem ſolita <lb/>potius diminuta, derelictæ
          ſunt thermæ. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">Medicina maxime putida, albo ex <lb/>vino et pulvere verrucarum equi
            admiſ<unclear>e</unclear>
          <lb/><unclear>ſ</unclear>arii parata, quaſi medicamentum cancri <lb/>certiſſimum jam
          commendata eſt. Hoc <lb/>uſque utebatur quoad pulveris unciæ qua- <lb/>tuor vel amplius
          exhauſtæ. Hoc tempo- <lb/>re, ægrota, gradatim et aperte, ſine ullo <lb/>alio peculiari
          morbi indicio, vires amitte- <lb/>re cæpit. Tantum fuit debilitatis incre- <lb/>mentum, ut
          demum erat neceſſe eam per <cb n="2"/>
          <lb/>ſcalas ſurſum deorſum portare, quamvis <lb/>ſæpe in periculo ne deficeret. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="paradiple">In hoc ſtatu dum nullo alio quam de- <lb/>bilitatis morbo laboraret,
          viſa eſt a medi- <lb/>cinæ Doctore Reynolds, qui cum magna <lb/>veritate atque etiam
          accuratione termina- <lb/>tionem fatalem prædixit, quod accidit ad <lb/>finem unius
          hebdommadæ a die quo illam <lb/>viſit. Duos ante mortem dies, ſanguis ex <lb/>gingivis
          conſtanter flucre cœpit, et minus <lb/>unâ horâ poſtquam expiraſſet. Facies et <lb/>corpus
          totum ad cæruleum perlevem mu- <lb/>tare cœpit. Color ſingulis horis lividior <lb/>fiebat
          donec fere extiterat penitus niger<unclear>;</unclear>
          <lb/>et quamvis corpus erat pertenue et tempus <lb/>frigidulum (quippe medio erat Martis
          <lb/>1790) putrefactio minus duobus diebus ſu- <lb/>peravit omnia quæ unquam memini in
          <lb/>hac regione vidiſſe in corporibus pleniſſimi <lb/>habitus, etiamque extremo momento
          ante <lb/>ſepulturam vel etiam fervidiſſimo tempore <lb/>æſtatis. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">Hunc fuiſſe caſum ſcorbuticum inſidi- <lb/>oſe tardeque repentem ſemper
          putavi ex <lb/>quo thermæ ſalitæ ſuiſſent adhibitæ. Hoc <lb/>conſtat thermas eſſe factas
          multo validiores <lb/>quam chirurgus juſſerat: valde ſuſpicor ſa- <lb/>turatam fuiſſe
          ſolutionem, propterea quod <lb/>ad imum balnei credo ſemper fuiſſe aliquod <lb/>ſal
          indiſſolutum. Hoc tamen pro vero non <lb/>aſſeverabo. Tres fere menſes poſt ther- <lb/>mas
          derelictas terminatio ſupervenit fatalis: <lb/>quam ſæpe utebantur jam non conſtat. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is a fact univerſally known, that <lb/>ſcorbutic perſons are very eaſily acted
        <lb/>upon by mercury; and there are few <lb/>ſurgeons who have not had opportuni- <lb/>ties
        of obſerving patients to whom it <lb/>is equally difficult, and almoſt impoſ- <lb/>ſible, to
        communicate the mercurial <lb/>ſtimulus by unction. Such patients <lb/>would ſoon feel its
        influence if put <lb/>upon a courſe of common ſalt or ſalted <lb/>animal food. May it not be
        preſumed <lb/>that, before the ointment can act upon <lb/>the ſyſtem, the mercurial globules
        <lb/>which it contains muſt undergo ſome <lb/>change analogous to calcination; or, <lb/>that
        they are formed in combination <lb/>with the neutral ſalts of the body, <lb/>whether
        ammoniacal or of whatever <lb/>nature, into a ſaline mercurial com- <lb/>pound. But the
        lymph and ſerum of <lb/>ſome patients may be ſo bland and <lb/>mild as not to act upon the
        mercu- <lb/>rial globules. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>With all the confidence of theoreti- <lb/>cal conjecture, I was on the point of
        <lb/>propoſing the ſame proceſs for the <lb/>more ſpeedy ſolution or diſcuſſion of
        <lb/>meſenteric and many other obſtruc- <lb/>tions and tumefactions of the lym- <lb/>phatic
        glands; but experience, which <lb/>is the beſt corrector of theory, obliges <pb n="195"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>me to ſpeak with diffidence here; be- <lb/>cauſe, very unfortunately for ſuch
        <lb/>conjecture, I find that Maſter H—, <lb/>the patient who has ſo lately under- <lb/>gone
        the ſcorbuticiſing proceſs, has at <lb/>this moment one of the ſubmaxillary <lb/>glands hard
        and tumid; and I alſo <lb/>perceive a chain of three or four ſmal- <lb/>ler glands in a
        ſtate of induration im- <lb/>mediately <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.8)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* But theſe are now, March 1798, <lb/>nearly completely vaniſhed; and no atten-
            <lb/>tion has been paid to them ſince the ſcurvy <lb/>was cured. </p>
        </note> behind the <hi rend="italic">maſtoidæus</hi> muſ- <lb/>cle in the neck, although
        there is no <lb/>exulceration nor moiſt diſcharge from <lb/>any of the neighbouring parts,
        nor <lb/>has any bliſter been applied. It muſt, <lb/>therefore, be recommended with equal
        <lb/>diffidence to patients in whom we ſuſ- <lb/>pect the exiſtence of tubercles in the
        <lb/>lungs; but, a doubtful remedy being <lb/>better than no remedy at all in a deſ-
        <lb/>perate diſeaſe, ſuch an idea may not <lb/>be altogether unworthy of attention. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To the candour and liberality of the <lb/>profeſſion I ſubmit theſe crude con-
        <lb/>jectures; truſting that, ſhould they <lb/>hereafter in any inſtance lead to inju-
        <lb/>rious practice, they will not be treated <lb/>with ſeverity of criticiſm: they are
        <lb/>offered with all the diffidence of con- <lb/>jecture, not obtruded with confidence
        <lb/>and preſumption. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Permit me, ſir, before I conclude <lb/>this tedious epiſtle, to remark, that,
        <lb/>having in a former publication offered <lb/>a propoſal to the Lords of the Admi-
        <lb/>ralty for the cure of the ſcurvy on- <lb/>board ſhips at ſea, with all the confi-
        <lb/>dence of a man ſure of his point, it <lb/>may now be demanded why I have <lb/>not made
        uſe of the ſame remedy in <lb/>the caſes which have ſo lately fallen <lb/>under my care. To
        this it is only <lb/>neceſſary to anſwer, that the caſes of <lb/>ſcurvy which have been here
        related <lb/>came ſuddenly and unexpectedly under <lb/>my notice, as they muſt always do in
        <lb/>private practice on ſhore. To have <lb/>waited, therefore, eight or ten days <lb/>till
        a proper quantity of vegetating <lb/>beans could have been procured, <lb/>when better and
        more efficacious <lb/>means were at hand, would have <lb/>been to trifle with the lives of
        my pa- <lb/>tients, merely to prove, by experiment, <lb/>what the experience of mankind has
        <lb/>already proved in ten thouſand inſtan- <lb/>ces, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> that the
        true ſcurvy may <lb/>always be ſpeedily cured by the uſe of <lb/>every kind of recent
        vegetable matter <lb/>that is in its nature eſculent. </p>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Some may be ſurprized to find ſo <lb/>much dependance placed on beans as <lb/>a cure
        for the ſcurvy at ſea, ſince it <lb/>has been clearly demonſtrated, by Dr. <lb/>Trotter,
        that the ſlaves in the African <lb/>trade, who are chiefly nouriſhed by <lb/>beans and other
        articles of leguminous <lb/>food, are prone to the diſeaſe, and <lb/>often ſuffer ſeverely
        under its ravages. <lb/>The Voyages of Monſ. Briſſon afford <lb/>a paſſage which will
        ſufficiently ac- <lb/>count for the ſcurvy making its ap- <lb/>pearance amongſt the negroes
        while <lb/>ſubſiſting upon leguminous food, <lb/>which certainly can have no tendency
        <lb/>in itſelf to generate that diſeaſe: </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">Of all diſeaſes the ſcurvy is that which <lb/>attacks the Negroes moſt
          fatally. It will <lb/>ſometimes almoſt depopulate a veſſel in a <lb/>few days. The
          Banbarras, </q> he adds, <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">are more ſubject to this plague than the <lb/>other Negroes. Care muſt be
          taken, <lb/>therefore, to ſupply them with the freſheſt <lb/>proviſions that can be
          procured, without <lb/>paying any regard to their predilection <lb/>for every thing that
          is ſalt; for, having no <lb/>ſalt in their own country, they no ſooner <lb/>get the taſte
          of it in their captivity, than <lb/>they contract an immoderate liking to it, <lb/>and mix
          it profuſely with every thing they <lb/>eat. Great care muſt be taken to prevent <lb/>the
          dangerous conſequences of this habit. </q>
        <lb/>Briſſon's Voyage to the Coaſt of Africa. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>We have here one of the moſt po- <lb/>tent occaſional cauſes of ſcurvy added <lb/>to
        poor nouriſhment. The tranſlator <lb/>injures the meaning of his author <lb/>when he ſays,
        the Negroes ought to be <lb/>ſupplied, &amp;c. <hi rend="italic">without paying any re-
          <lb/>gard to their predilection for every thing <lb/>that is ſalt</hi>. The original
        writer muſt <lb/>ſurely have meant, that the ſtricteſt <lb/>regard ought to be paid to this
        circum- <lb/>ſtance, in order to prevent them from <lb/>indulging ſuch predilection. </p>
      <signed rend="sc align-right">
        <lb/>John Sherwen. </signed>
      <dateline rend="align-right">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Enfield</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Apr.</hi> 21, 1797. </dateline>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
