<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: Suggestions for preventing the Spreading of the Yellow
          Fever</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Suggestions for preventing the Spreading of the Yellow Fever</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Gentleman's Magazine: and Historical Chronicle.</title>
            <author>
              <persName type="pseudo">Sylvanus Urban</persName>
            </author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed by John Nichols, at Cicero's Head, Red Lion Passage,
                  Fleet-Street; where letters are particularly requested to be sent, And Sold by
                  Elizabeth Newbery, the Corner of St. Paul's Church Yard, Ludgate-Street. 1798.
                </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1798</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">68</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">919b</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="1798_GM_0919">
    <body>
      <pb n="919"/>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <salute rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="sc">Urban</hi>, </salute>
      <dateline rend="align-right"><hi rend="italic">Chard, Somerſet</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
          >Nov.</hi> 14. </dateline>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">W</hi>ITH the ſenſible writer of the <lb/>letter ſigned Humanus, who
        <lb/>takes the lead in your laſt, I perfectly <lb/>agree; for, I am convinced, having
        <lb/>lately gone through your Magazines <lb/>from their commencement to the pre- <lb/>ſent
        period, that they abound with im- <lb/>portant medical hints and well-narra- <lb/>ted caſes,
        ſufficient to fill ſeveral vo- <lb/>lumes. With the good Humanus, I <lb/>alſo am deeply
        impreſſed with concern <lb/>whenever I recollect the ravages made, <lb/>and that are ſtill,
        I am afraid, making, <lb/>by the Yellow Fever, ſince it ſeems to <lb/>have baffled the
        united ſkill of Phyſick <lb/>and Philoſophy: Philoſophers and <lb/>Phyſicians appear equally
        ignorant of <lb/>its nature. As to their notion of its <lb/><unclear>ariſing</unclear> from
        a diffuſion of the <unclear>Septic</unclear>
        <pb n="920"/>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>Nitrous Acid, this, I fear, will be <lb/>found an hypotheſis only generated by <lb/>the
        ardent imagination of modern <lb/>chemiſts. It is curious to obſerve, <lb/>that the Gas,
        ſuppoſed to contain the <lb/>germ of the diſeaſe on the other ſide <lb/>the Atlantic, is the
        very vapour em- <lb/>ployed <hi rend="italic">here</hi> to ſubdue the Miaſm ge- <lb/>nerated
        in the progreſs of putreſcence, <lb/>as is ſhewn by a publication of Dr. <lb/>Carmichael
        Smyth. </p>
      <p rend="size(0.8)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">Who ſhall decide when Doctors diſagree? </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is well known, Mr. Urban, the <lb/>moſt ingenious writers on Peſtilence <lb/>ſuppoſe
        its riſe, ſpread, and continu- <lb/>ance, owing to a vicious impregnation <lb/>of the
        atmoſphere. Indeed, that the <lb/>air is ſuſceptible and capable, for a <lb/>time, of
        retaining highly-noxious, nay, <lb/>deleterious taints, none, who have <lb/>thought deeply
        on this ſubject, doubt. <lb/>We find, when the Plague raged in <lb/>London, it was cuſtomary
        to light <lb/>large fires, in hopes to correct the mor- <lb/>bid ſtate of this
        life-ſuſtaining fluid; a <lb/>method, by-the-bye, of combating <lb/>Peſtilence juſtly
        condemned by the ju- <lb/>dicious Mead and others. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Drs. Prieſtley and Ingenohouſz have <lb/>proved, that Nature has furniſhed
        <lb/>vegetables with the powers of correct- <lb/>ing and reſtoring to its vital functions
        <lb/>vitiated (hydrogenous) air, by having <lb/>beſtowed on them an appetite to receive
        <lb/>on their <hi rend="italic">pabulum</hi> foul, and, by their <lb/>organized œconomy, to
        return pure <lb/>(oxyginated) air. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Is it improbable, that the kind and <lb/>infinite y-wiſe Governor and Father of
        <lb/>Nature has alſo directed, that a reci- <lb/>procity of action ſhould be continually
        <lb/>parried on between the ſurface of the <lb/>earth and the immediately ſuperin-
        <lb/>cumbent atmoſphere, favourable to <lb/>animal health? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is well known that, in ſeaſons of <lb/>long-continued drought, the ground
        <lb/>perſpires conſiderably (ſee the Bp. of <lb/>Landaff's Chemical Eſſays). Morn- <lb/>ing
        and evening miſts hovering near <lb/>the earth's ſurface are a demonſtra- <lb/>tion of this
        fact. It has been for <lb/>ages a prevailing notion, and the <lb/>opinion appears well
        founded, that <lb/>ground newly turned up gives out <lb/>ſomething extremely ſalutary; ſince
        <lb/>it is notorious that perſons labouring <lb/>under pulmonary complaints have re-
        <lb/>ceived benefit; and that, even in bad <lb/>caſes, cures have been effected by fol-
        <lb/>lowing the plough. One of the wri- <lb/>ters on the Yellow Fever of Philadel- <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>phia obſerves, that perſons employed <lb/>in digging graves remarkably eſcaped
        <lb/>infection. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Quere. In cities (<hi rend="italic"><unclear>flagrante morbo</unclear></hi>), <lb/>the
        ſurfaces of which are, I believe, <lb/>always cloſely covered with a compact <lb/>thick
        pavement of granite, or ma- <lb/>terials of the ſame kind, totally <lb/>preventing all
        communication between <lb/>earth and air, might not a rational <lb/>hope be entertained of
        the moſt bene- <lb/>ficial conſequences enſuing from <hi rend="italic">unpa- <lb/>ving</hi>
        and ploughing up the ſtreets, <lb/>lanes, &amp;c. of places infected with un-
        <lb/>commonly-deſtructive peſtilential epi- <lb/>demics, more eſpecially if they ſeemed
        <lb/>endemic? The ploughing ſhould be <lb/>repeated every three or four days, cut- <lb/>ting
        in ſomething deeper each time; <lb/>and the ſurfaces, ſhould the weather <lb/>be ſultry and
        dry, frequently ſprinkled <lb/>by means of a water-cart. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Quere. By pavements preventing <lb/>the action and re-action of earth and <lb/>air, may
        not a moſt ſalutary proceſs in <lb/>the œconomy of Nature be deſtroyed, <lb/>and be among
        the cauſes of populous <lb/>cities having been emphatically called <lb/>the <q rend="quotes"
          >graves of mankind? </q> Hence <lb/>may ariſe, in my humble opinion, in- <lb/>deed do
        ariſe, Fevers, and thoſe of the <lb/>worſt type, as deſtructive, and there- <lb/>fore as
        much to be dreaded and <lb/>guarded againſt, as the genuine <lb/>Plague. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I am <hi rend="italic">ſeriouſly</hi> impreſſed with a belief <lb/>that, during the
        prevalence of ſuch a <lb/>fell ravager as Humanus juſtly ſtyles <lb/>the Yellow Fever, now,
        or lately, <lb/>raging in America, the ſtate of the <lb/>air might be conſiderably
        meliorated, <lb/>and the malignity of the diſeaſe (won- <lb/>derfully becauſe ſuddenly)
        checked, <lb/>by the ſimple method which I have, <lb/>with the beſt intention, pointed out.
        <lb/>The known philanthropy of Mr. Ur- <lb/>ban will, I doubt not, enable me to
        <lb/>diſſeminate my ideas on this moſt im- <lb/>portant ſubject; and thus convey them
        <lb/>acroſs the Atlantick; where, perhaps, <lb/>they may catch the eye of ſome ma-
        <lb/>giſtrate, humane and ſenſible as the <lb/>writer in the laſt Gentleman's Maga-
        <lb/>zine, whoſe letter emboldened me to <lb/>meet the public eye with theſe <hi
          rend="italic">hints</hi>. </p>
      <signed rend="indent">
        <lb/>Yours, &amp;c. <hi rend="sc align-right">Medicus. </hi>
      </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
