<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Unknown: The Necessity and Usefulness of the Dispensaries</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">The necessity and usefulness of the dispensaries lately set up by the
              College of Physicians in London, for the use of the sick poor. Together with an answer
              to all the objections rais'd against them by the apothecaries, or others.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T66956</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T66956"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed in the year, 1702</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1702</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="19"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW100716827</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K057538.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Public welfare and institutional"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_2" n="1"/>
      <head rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">THE </hi><lb/><hi rend="size(1.7)"><hi
            rend="italic">Neceſſity</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Uſefulneſs</hi>
        </hi><lb/>OF THE <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">DISPENSARIES.</hi>
      </head>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(4)">T</hi>HE Practice of <hi rend="italic">Phyſick</hi> in
          <hi rend="italic">London</hi> and ſeven miles <lb/>round, being for near two hundred Years
        ſetled by <lb/>Law wholly in the <hi rend="italic">College of Phyſicians</hi> in <hi
          rend="italic">London,</hi>
        <lb/>and ſuch as they approve of upon Examination, and <lb/>Licenſe; 'tis worth the while to
        enquire by what means they <lb/>come to enjoy ſo ſmall a part of it. Chymiſts and
        Diſtillers, <lb/>Aſtrologers and Mountebanks, Midwives and Nurſes, and the <lb/>whole Train
        of Broken-Tradeſmen-Doctors have every one <lb/>their ſhare. There are not a few that are
        their own Doctors, <lb/>and practiſe upon themſelves; and there is hardly any one ſo
        <lb/>unkind, as not to recommend to his ſick Friend what has done <lb/>himſelf good. The
        College can only blame theſe laſt for <w part="I">Indiſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">cretion</w>:
        And the former are the moſt of them hardly worth <lb/>the charge of a Proſecution: yet the
        College have been ever <lb/>and anon making an example of one or other of them, to ſtrike
        <lb/>terror into the reſt. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>But when I have reckoned up theſe and as many more ſuch as <lb/>theſe,
        they have hardly all of them invaded the tenth part of <lb/>the practice that one ſingle
        ſort of Men have uſurpt, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> the <lb/>Apothecaries. And theſe not
        only practiſe, but pretend to a <hi rend="italic"><lb/>Right,</hi> and to a <hi
          rend="italic">Neceſſity</hi> ſo to do. As to their <hi rend="italic">Right,</hi> tho' the
        <lb/>Honourable Court of Kings Bench have more than once quaſht <lb/>that pretence, and have
        ſufficiently determined the matter <lb/>againſt them; yet I ſhall preſume to give a touch at
        it, <w part="I">after-</w><pb xml:id="page_3" n="2"/><lb/><w part="F">wards</w> in this
        Paper. But as to the <hi rend="italic">Neceſſity</hi> which they plead, <lb/>I will conſider
        that here. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>They plead a <hi rend="italic">Neceſſity</hi> to practiſe upon the <hi
          rend="italic">Rich,</hi> becauſe <w part="I">ma-</w><lb/><w part="F">ny</w> times they
        cannot perſuade theſe to ſend for a Phyſician, <lb/>when yet 'tis neceſſary that ſomething
        ſhould be done, and <lb/>therefore <hi rend="italic">they muſt</hi> do it. Now this ſeems a
        very odd way of <lb/>arguing, That if the Patient will not ſend for a Phyſician, the
        <lb/>Apothecary <hi rend="italic">muſt needs</hi> undertake the Cure. For if the Patient
        <lb/>be covetous, or fool-hardy, or will not believe himſelf ill <w part="I">e-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">nough</w> to have the advice of a Phyſician, what's that to the <w part="I"
          >Apo-</w><lb/><w part="F">thecary?</w> Yes, for if one Apothecary will not give him <w
          part="I">ſome-</w><lb/><w part="F">thing</w>, another will; and ſo the firſt ſhall loſe a
        Patient. This <lb/>I muſt confeſs is a kind of neceſſity, <hi rend="italic">ſe
          defendendo,</hi> for one <w part="I">A-</w><lb/><w part="F">pothecary</w> to defend
        himſelf from the invaſion of another: But <lb/>this is far from proving a <hi rend="italic"
          >Neceſſity</hi> with reſpect to the Patient, <lb/>who I dare ſay had generally much better
        be without any of <lb/>them. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Another <hi rend="italic">Neceſſity</hi> to practiſe upon the <hi
          rend="italic">Rich,</hi> is, when they <lb/>are taken ſuddenly ill, and no Phyſician can
        be met with. As to <lb/>Practiſing in this caſe of neceſſity, ſo long as ſuch neceſſity
        <lb/>laſts, I dare ſecure the Apothecaries, or any other perſon that <lb/>does his beſt in
        ſuch urgent Caſes, that they ſhall never be <w part="I">trou-</w><lb/><w part="F">bled</w>
        for it by the College. But this Neceſſity is far from <w part="I">juſti-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >fying</w> the Apothecaries continuing to practiſe even upon ſuch <lb/>Patients from day
        to day, when better advice may be had. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Theſe two Caſes, I think, are the only ones for which they <lb/>can
        plead <hi rend="italic">Neceſſity,</hi> with reſpect to their practiſing upon the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Rich;</hi> and how far they are from excuſing or juſtifying their
        <lb/>practiſing upon any <hi rend="italic">ſuch</hi> for Weeks or Months together (as they
        <lb/>commonly do) is too obvious to be farther examin'd. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>But then how ſhall I get over the other <hi rend="italic"
          >Neceſſity,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">great <lb/>Neceſſity,</hi> with reſpect to the <hi
          rend="italic">Poor,</hi> who, if you will believe the <lb/>Apothecaries, would all periſh
        for want of looking to, if <hi rend="italic">they</hi>
        <lb/>did not take care of them: for the Phyſicians (of the College) <lb/>they ſay, will only
        viſit the Rich that can Fee them well. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>I believe, this accuſation of the College-Phyſicians was <hi
          rend="italic">never <lb/>true:</hi> But that for <hi rend="italic">ſeveral Years</hi>
        by-paſt it has been notoriouſly <lb/><hi rend="italic">falſe,</hi> is known to the whole
        Town. For, that the Phyſicians <pb xml:id="page_4" n="3"/><lb/>might clear themſelves of
        this <hi rend="italic">falſe charge,</hi> they have been <w part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >liged</w> to ſet their care of the Poor more in the eyes of the World <lb/>than
        heretofore; not only giving advice <hi rend="italic">gratis</hi> to the Poor at <lb/>their
        own and the Patients Lodgings, but appointing publick <lb/>Diſpenſaries alſo for the Poor to
        reſort to every day of the <lb/>week (except Sundays) where they may both have the beſt <w
          part="I">ad-</w><lb/><w part="F">vice</w>
        <hi rend="italic">gratis,</hi> and alſo proper Medicins for their reſpective <w part="I"
          >Ca-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſes</w> at the loweſt value: whereby the Poor are at once
        delivered <lb/>from the danger of the Apothecaries ignorance in practice, and <lb/>alſo from
        the oppreſſive charge of his Medicins. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>And the College have been forced to take this Courſe, not <lb/>only to
        clear themſelves of the aſperſions caſt upon them, but <lb/>alſo to make their charity in
        adviſing <hi rend="italic">gratis,</hi> truly ſerviceable to <lb/>the Poor: For unleſs
        Phyſicians could teach the Poor to make <lb/>ſomething themſelves, their advice was ſeldom
        followed; <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">cauſe</w> the Apothecaries uſed to make them
        pay ſo dear for their <lb/>Phyſick, and could by no Overtures or Arguments be induced
        <lb/>to abate of their prices, tho' often preſt to it by the Phyſicians, as <lb/>clearly
        appears in a Paper ſome years ago publiſhed under the <lb/>Title of <hi rend="italic">A
          ſhort Account of the proceedings of the College of Phyſicians,</hi>
        <lb/>London, <hi rend="italic">in relation to the ſick Poor of the ſaid City,</hi> &amp;c. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>And notwithſtanding that the Phyſicians, as appears in the ſaid
        <lb/>Paper, were ſo forward to adviſe the Poor <hi rend="italic">gratis,</hi> and the <w
          part="I">Apo-</w><lb/><w part="F">thecaries</w> ſo backward in contributing their part;
        yet theſe did <lb/>not only continue to inſinuate to the Town, that the care of <lb/>the
        Poor lay wholly upon them; but when about ſeven years <lb/>ago they petitioned the High
        Court of Parliament to be <w part="I">exempt-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> from Offices as the
        Phyſicians are, they had the confidence <lb/>to ſuggeſt the ſame <hi rend="italic"
          >there</hi> alſo, and endeavoured to get a Clauſe <lb/>in their Bill, that they might have
        liberty to give Phyſick to <lb/>the Poor, who otherwiſe were like to periſh for want of due
        <lb/>care to be taken of them. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Phyſicians being thus unjuſtly calumniated before the <lb/>whole
        Nation, 'twas high time for them to think of an effectual <lb/>remedy. Wherefore <hi
          rend="italic">Dec.</hi> 22. 1696. a Propoſal was made in the <lb/>publick College for a
        ſubſcription by the ſeveral Members thereof, <lb/>to raiſe a Fund for the furniſhing a
        Repoſitory of Medicins for <lb/>the uſe of the Poor: which Propoſal was then approved of,
          <pb xml:id="page_5" n="4"/><lb/>and a ſubſcription immediately made to the effect <w
          part="I">follow-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><q rend="quotes">Whereas the ſeveral Orders of the College of Phyſicians
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">London,</hi> for preſcribing Medicins <hi rend="italic"
            >gratis</hi> to the Poor Sick of <lb/>the Cities of <hi rend="italic">London</hi> and
            <hi rend="italic">Weſtminſter</hi> and parts adjacent, as <lb/>alſo the Propoſals made
          by the ſaid College to the Lord Mayor, <lb/>Court of Aldermen and Common Council of <hi
            rend="italic">London,</hi> in <w part="I">pur-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſuance</w> thereof,
          have hitherto been ineffectual, for that no <w part="I">Me-</w><lb/><w part="F">thod</w>
          hath been taken to furniſh the Poor with Medicins for <lb/>their Cure at low and
          reaſonable rates: We therefore whoſe <lb/>Names are here underwritten, Fellows or Members
          of the ſaid <lb/>College, being willing effectually to promote ſo great a <w part="I"
            >Chari-</w><lb/><w part="F">ty</w>, by the counſel and good liking of the Preſident and
          College <lb/>declared in their <hi rend="italic">Comitia,</hi> hereby (to wit, each of us
          ſeverally <lb/>and apart, and not the one for the other of us) do oblige our <lb/>ſelves
          to pay to Dr. <hi rend="italic">Thomas Burwel,</hi> Fellow and Elect of the <lb/>ſaid
          College, the ſumm of Ten Pounds apiece of Lawful <lb/>money of <hi rend="italic"
            >England,</hi> by ſuch proportions, and at ſuch times as<lb/>to the major part of the
          Subſcribers hereto ſhall ſeem moſt <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">venient</w>: Which
          Money when received by the ſaid Dr. <hi rend="italic">Thomas <lb/>Burwel,</hi> is to be by
          him expended in preparing and delivering <lb/>Medicins to the Poor at their intrinſick
          value, in ſuch <w part="I">man-</w><lb/><w part="F">ner</w>, and at ſuch times, and by
          ſuch Orders and Directions, as <lb/>by the major part of the Subſcribers hereto, ſhall in
          writing <lb/>be hereafter appointed and directed for that purpoſe. In <lb/>Witneſs whereof
          we have hereunto ſet our hands and Seals <lb/>this 22. <hi rend="italic">December</hi>
          1696.</q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>This was in a few days ſubſcribed by above <hi rend="italic">forty,</hi>
        (and has by <lb/>ſeveral more, ſince.) </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Subſcription being made, a College was called, That a <lb/>Grant
        might be forthwith made by way of Leaſe to the <w part="I">Subſcri-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >bers</w>, of the College-Laboratory, and other Rooms and <w part="I">conve-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">niencies</w> neceſſary for executing the intended Charitable deſign: <lb/>And a
        Grant was accordingly made and Sealed in open College. <lb/>Whereupon the Subſcribers
        preſently choſe a Committee of <lb/>twelve to manage this affair, who were ſo diligent in
        it, that <lb/>in about half a year they got it into a ſerviceable condition and <lb/>method. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_6" n="5"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>But this deſign being wholly new, no wonder if at firſt it was <lb/>not
        brought to that degree of Serviceableneſs it is now improved <lb/>to. At firſt thoſe Poor
        only were ſupplied with Medicins that <lb/>repaired for advice to the ſeveral Subſcribers
        Lodgings, or thoſe <lb/>whom they were called to in their reſpective Neighbourhoods;
        <lb/>which in compariſon were but few: for the Apothecaries ſtill <lb/>made a ſhift to keep
        moſt of them in their own hands, ſo loth <lb/>were they to part with their objects of
        Charity, for reaſons beſt <lb/>known to themſelves. Wherefore the Subſcribers thought it
        <lb/>adviſeable for the inlarging of their Charity, to appoint certain <lb/>days wherein two
        Phyſicians (by turns) ſhould attend at the <lb/>College, to give advice <hi rend="italic"
          >gratis</hi> to all the Poor that would reſort <lb/>thither; and to give notice of this
        not only in the publick Prints, <lb/>but alſo by Papers which they printed and gave away for
        the <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">formation</w> of the Town. By this means far greater
        Numbers <lb/>flocked for advice, and many from the remoteſt parts of the <lb/>Town; for
        whoſe conveniency it has been thought fit not only <lb/>to continue the Attendance (with the
        Diſpenſary for Medicins) <lb/>at the College; but alſo to erect two Diſpenſaries more, one
        in <lb/>S. <hi rend="italic">Martin</hi>'s Lane in the Fields, and the other in <hi
          rend="italic">Grace-Church <lb/>ſtreet,</hi> that the ſick Poor might not have too far to
        go for relief; <lb/>and might at one or other of theſe Places have advice any day in
        <lb/>the Week, and Medicins every day at all of them. Thus two <lb/>Phyſicians attend in the
        afternoons on <hi rend="italic">Monday</hi> in S. <hi rend="italic">Martin's</hi>, on
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Tueſday</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Grace-Church-ſtreet,</hi> on <hi
          rend="italic">Wedneſday</hi> at the College; and <lb/>ſo on <hi rend="italic"
          >Thurſday</hi> in S. <hi rend="italic">Martin</hi>'s, on <hi rend="italic">Friday</hi> in
          <hi rend="italic">Grace-Church-ſtreet,</hi>
        <lb/>and on <hi rend="italic">Saturday</hi> at the College. And the Phyſicians attendance
        <lb/>at theſe Places, is not intended at all to excuſe any Subſcriber <lb/>from giving
        advice <hi rend="italic">gratis</hi> at his own Houſe or in his <w part="I"
          >Neighbour-</w><lb/><w part="F">hood</w>: But becauſe a Phyſicians hours are uncertain,
        being <w part="I">obli-</w><lb/><w part="F">ged</w> to be abroad whenever called; that the
        Poor who can ill <lb/>loſe time, may not be diſappointed when they ſeek for advice, <hi
          rend="italic"><lb/>certain</hi> proviſion is made for them by theſe fixed <hi
          rend="italic">days</hi> and <hi rend="italic">places.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>By this means 'tis hoped the Phyſicians have ſufficiently wiped <lb/>off
        the Scandal they lay ſo long unjuſtly under, and the Poor <lb/>have that care taken of them,
        and kindneſs ſhew'd them, that we <lb/>challenge any City in <hi rend="italic">Europe</hi>
        to parallel. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Committee who are new choſen every Year, meet twice <pb
          xml:id="page_7" n="6"/><lb/>every Week for the looking after the due management of this
        <lb/>Undertaking: and they chuſe two Curators Monthly, whoſe <lb/>peculiar buſineſs it is to
        buy in the beſt Drugs they can meet <lb/>with, and to ſee that the Compoſitions for the
        Diſpenſaries be <lb/>duly prepared. And that theſe may be the better inſpected, <lb/>they
        are all ordered to be made at the College, and to be <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >veyed</w> from thence to the other two Diſpenſaries as they are <lb/>wanted. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>And as the Medicins at all the Diſpenſaries are the beſt that <lb/>can
        be made: So they are ſold out for no greater gains than <lb/>will juſt bear the Charge, <hi
          rend="italic">viz.</hi> of Houſe-Rent and Servants <w part="I">wa-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ges</w>. So that the Price is ordinarily 8<hi rend="italic">d.</hi> or 9<hi rend="italic"
          >d.</hi> in the <lb/>Shilling leſs than the Apothecaries uſe to exact. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>And now that the Poor are ſo very well taken care of by the
        <lb/>Subſcribers to the Diſpenſaries, one would think the <w part="I">Apotheca-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ries</w> ſhould be very thankful that ſo much trouble is taken off <lb/>their
        hands: But inſtead of that, (to ſhew that their <hi rend="italic">gains</hi> by
        <lb/>Practiſing upon the Poor, is more in their eye, than <hi rend="italic">their
          relief</hi>) <lb/>they rail every where againſt the Subſcribers as men that would
        <lb/>undo them, and have entred into a Combination to hinder them <lb/>of all the buſineſs
        they poſſibly can: while they careſs and bring <lb/>into buſineſs ſuch Phyſicians as have
        refuſed to be concerned in <lb/>the Subſcription. They make it their buſineſs alſo in all <w
          part="I">Com-</w><lb/><w part="F">panies</w>, to raiſe Objections againſt the
        Diſpenſaries, as well as <lb/>to miſrepreſent the deſigns of thoſe that have ſet them up. As
        <lb/>I have therefore plainly ſhewn the Subſcribers deſign to be the <lb/>moſt Laudable that
        can be; and that they were neceſſitated to <lb/>erect them, as well for the relief of the
        Poor, as in their own <lb/>vindication: So to prevent all groundleſs prejudices, I will give
        <lb/>a full Anſwer to all ſuch Objections as the Apothecaries have <lb/>raiſed againſt them. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Theſe <hi rend="italic">Objections</hi> may, I think, be reduced to ſix. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="1"><lb/>I. They ſay, <hi rend="italic">That Phyſicians ought not to give
          Phyſick, but only <lb/>preſcribe it.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="2"><lb/>II. <hi rend="italic">That they have no right to erect publick
          Diſpenſaries.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="3"><lb/>III. <hi rend="italic">That if the Diſpenſaries be ſuffered, the
          Apothecaries will all be <lb/>undone.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="4"><lb/>IV. <hi rend="italic">That Phyſicians Fees are as unreaſonable and
          oppreſſive, as the <lb/>Apothecaries prices.</hi>
      </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_8" n="7"/>
      <p rend="indent" n="5"><lb/>V. <hi rend="italic">That the Rich are ſupplyed with Medicins from
          the Diſpenſaries <lb/>as well as the Poor.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="6"><lb/>VI. <hi rend="italic">That the Diſpenſaries ſell Medicins as dear
          as the <w part="I">Apothe-</w><lb/><w part="F">caries</w>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Obj. 1. <hi rend="italic">That Phyſicians ought not to give Phyſick, but
          only <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſcribe</w> it.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Anſw.</hi> It might ſuffice in anſwer to this to ſay,
        that it is as <lb/>little the Apothecaries province to <hi rend="italic">adviſe</hi> the
        ſick, as they can <lb/>ſuppoſe it to be the Phyſicians to <hi rend="italic">give</hi> them
          <hi rend="italic">Phyſick:</hi> and yet <lb/>where is the Apothecary that does not do this
        every day? How <lb/>unfit then are the Apothecaries to impute that as a Crime to
        <lb/>Phyſicians, which they are ſo notoriouſly guilty of themſelves, <hi rend="italic"
          ><lb/>viz.</hi> of intruding into other Mens buſineſs? I ſay, this might <lb/>ſuffice as
        an Anſwer to <hi rend="italic">them:</hi> but I ſhall conſider the accuſation <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">it ſelf,</hi> and demonſtrate, that Phyſicians when they give Phyſick,
        <lb/>are in their own lawful proper buſineſs; and that Apothecaries <lb/>are not ſo, when
        they preſcribe it. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>When a Phyſician has arrived at the skill to know Diſeaſes <lb/>and
        their Symptoms, and to take Indications for their Cure as to <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">quid
          agendum;</hi> he muſt then proceed to find out the <hi rend="italic">quo, i. e.</hi>
        <lb/>Operations, or Medicins, to ſatisfie thoſe Indications: And <lb/>when he has found
        theſe out, can any Man think it reaſonable, <lb/>that he ſhould be obliged to communicate
        all his skill in every <lb/>particular Cure, to what perſon ſoever the Patient is pleaſed to
        <lb/>call in for an Apothecary, ſo as to make him preſently Maſter <lb/>of all thoſe Secrets
        that by long ſtudy and obſervation he has <lb/>arrived at the knowledg of? Whoſoever is the
        Author but of <lb/>one Invention uſeful to the Publick, has a right by Law to the <lb/>ſole
        benefit of it for many years: And ſhall Phyſicians that are <lb/>continually inventing new
        and more effectual Remedies for the <lb/>Diſeaſes of Mankind, be bound to divulge and
        proſtitute all <lb/>their Inventions to Men, that if <hi rend="italic">they</hi> can help
        it, will never let <lb/>the Inventors have twice the benefit of the ſame Preſcription,
        <lb/>but preſently uſurp the uſe of it themſelves, and leave the <w part="I">Phy-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ſicians</w> at leiſure to invent more? I know the Apothecary that <lb/>is
        ignorant of the Reaſons and Natures of things, by <hi rend="italic">unfitly
          <lb/>applying</hi> good Remedies ſhall never perform the ſame Cures that <lb/>the learned
        Phyſician can: but while the Apothecaries pretend <pb xml:id="page_9" n="8"/><lb/>to do it,
        and give thoſe remedies to Patients, tho' theſe receive <lb/>no benefit, the Phyſician is no
        leſs injur'd. I ſay then, 'tis <lb/>againſt all the reaſon and juſtice in the World, to
        hinder the <lb/>Phyſician himſelf from adminiſtring to the ſick ſuch remedies as <lb/>he has
        invented. 'Tis as abſurd, as to hinder a Workman from <lb/>uſing his own Tools which he has
        invented, and which he alone <lb/>knows the right uſe of. And the Parliament of 32 <hi
          rend="italic">H.</hi> 8. for <lb/>this, and other weighty reaſons, did wiſely enact, <q
          rend="quotes">That <lb/>any Phyſician being admitted by the Preſident and Fellowſhip
          <lb/>of Phyſicians in <hi rend="italic">London,</hi> may any where within this Realm
          <lb/>practiſe and exerciſe the Science of Phyſick in all and every <lb/>its members and
          parts.</q> Which Clauſe is plainly applied to <lb/>making and giving Medicins, in the
        Charter granted to the <w part="I">Apo-</w><lb/><w part="F">thecaries</w> by K. <hi
          rend="italic">James</hi> I. For after the Charter had granted <lb/>them divers Immunities,
        Powers and Privileges, particularly <lb/>the ſole making and vending of internal remedies,
          <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> at length <lb/>there is this Clauſe added: <hi
          rend="italic">Et deniq. volumus — quod <w part="I">Fræſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">deus</w>
          &amp; Communitas Medicor. (Civit. Lond.) omnesq; &amp; ſinguli Medici <lb/>de eodem
          Collegio ſive Communitate, &amp; ſucceſſores ſui, ſicut &amp; <w part="I">Me-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">dici</w> Regis, Reginæ &amp; Principum impoſterum debeant, &amp; pro arbitrio
          <lb/>ſuo poſſint artem medicam in omnibus ſuis partibus exercere,</hi> &amp;c. <hi
          rend="italic">i. e.</hi>
        <lb/><q rend="quotes">And laſtly we will — That the Preſident and Commonalty <lb/>of
          Phyſicians (in the City of <hi rend="italic">London</hi>) and all and every the
          <lb/>Phyſicians of the ſame College or Commonalty, and their <w part="I">Suc-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ceſſors</w>, as alſo the Phyſicians of the King, Queen and
          Princes,<lb/>hereafter ought, and at their pleaſure may exerciſe the Art of <lb/>Phyſick
          in all its parts.</q> And to drive the matter yet further <lb/>out of all diſpute, it is
        immediately added, <hi rend="italic">&amp; inſuper gaudebunt, <lb/>utentur &amp; fruentur,
          &amp; gaudere, uti &amp; frui valeant &amp; poſſint eiſdem <lb/>&amp; conſimil.
          juriſdictionibus, authoritat. ſupervis. &amp; correctionibus, ac <lb/>omnibus aliis</hi>
        poteſtatibus, privileg. <hi rend="italic">&amp; libertat. qualibus unquam <lb/>antehac
          Pharmacopolæ uſi &amp; gaviſi fuerunt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi>
        <q rend="quotes">And ſhall <lb/>moreover enjoy and uſe, and have a right to enjoy and uſe
          the <lb/>ſame and like Juriſdictions, Authorities, Superviſings and <w part="I"
            >Cor-</w><lb/><w part="F">rections</w>, and all other POWERS, PRIVILEDGES <lb/>and
          Liberties which the Apothecaries have ever hitherto uſed <lb/>and enjoyed, <hi
            rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi></q> What words can be more comprehenſive <lb/>and full to
        continue in the Phyſicians of the College an equal <pb xml:id="page_10" n="9"/><lb/><hi
          rend="italic">power</hi> and <hi rend="italic">priviledge</hi> with Apothecaries
        themſelves, to make and <lb/>vend Medicins? </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>But where is the clauſe in any Statute or Charter (even their <lb/>own)
        that gives or reſerves a power to the Apothecaries to <lb/>practiſe Phyſick, and to diſpenſe
        out all the Medicins in their <lb/>Shops to Patients without the preſcription or advice of
        any <w part="I">Phy-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſician?</w> If they can ſhew none, then I affirm,
        that they do this <lb/>againſt plain poſitive Law, while Phyſicians have Law as plain
        <lb/>and poſitive to empower them to prepare and give Phyſick. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Obj. 2. <hi rend="italic">That Phyſicians have no right to erect publick
            <w part="I">Diſpen-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſaries</w>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Anſw.</hi> To this I anſwer, that it ſeems ſtrange, if
        each particular <lb/>Phyſician have power by Law to prepare and give his own Phyſick,
        <lb/>(as has been ſhewn) that two or three, or any number of theſe <lb/>Phyſicians, may not
        for their own convenience prepare their <lb/>Medicins together, and have one common place
        from whence <lb/>to diſpenſe them; eſpecially when all the benefit of ſuch <w part="I"
          >conve-</w><lb/><w part="F">niency</w> accrues to the Patient, who by that means has his
          <w part="I">Medi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cins</w> conſiderably cheaper than they could be
        afforded, if every <w part="I">Phy-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſician</w> were at the charge to
        keep Servants and a Diſpenſary of his <lb/>own. But ſuppoſe there were any weight in this
        Objection, of what <lb/>advantage would it be to the Apothecaries to have the <w part="I"
          >Phyſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cians</w> debarr'd from this convenience? There would perhaps
        in <lb/>ſuch Caſe be as many Diſpenſaries as there are now Subſcribers <lb/>to the three in
        being: And whereas each Subſcriber ſends in <lb/>compariſon but few of his Patients at
        preſent to the Diſpenſaries; <lb/>if he had one at his own Houſe, he would probably ſupply
        all <lb/>his Patients with his own Medicins. The Objectors therefore <lb/>had much better,
        in my opinion, quietly endure three common <lb/>Diſpenſaries ſet up for the uſe of the Poor,
        than by <w part="I">endea-</w><lb/><w part="F">vouring</w> to pull theſe down, to give
        occaſion to ſet up forty or <lb/>fifty private ones, for the uſe of the Rich as well as the
        Poor. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Obj. 3. <hi rend="italic">That if the Diſpenſaries are ſuffered, the
          Apothecaries <lb/>will all be undone.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Ans.</hi> It muſt be confeſt, that part of their
        buſineſs, eſpecially <lb/>that relating to the Poor, muſt indeed be abated; and that <w
          part="I">bu-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſiness</w> which they retain, will hardly be ſo
        profitable to them <lb/>as formerly, when the Rich underſtand how unreaſonable their <pb
          xml:id="page_11" n="10"/><lb/>gains have been. But if the Apothecaries pleaſe, they may in
        <lb/>good part make up theſe Loſſes by contenting themſelves to live <lb/>in Houſes of leſs
        Rent, to bear only the port of Labouring or <lb/>handy-crafts-men (as indeed they are) but
        eſpecially by keeping <lb/>fewer Servants, and putting their own hands to their own work,
        <lb/>and by making ſuch Bylaws to their Company in relation to <w part="I">ta-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">king</w> Apprentices, as may leſſen the number of Apothecaries, <lb/>who are now
        grown ſo over numerous. And if <w part="I">notwithſtand-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>, they
        cannot get ſo much by their Trade as they <hi rend="italic">have</hi> done, <lb/>every
        unprejudic'd Man will conclude it more reaſonable and <lb/>juſt, that a few Men ſhould be
        leſſen'd in their gains and <w part="I">gran-</w><lb/><w part="F">deur</w>, than that a
        thouſand times their number ſhould be <w part="I">op-</w><lb/><w part="F">preſs'd</w> for
        the ſupport of them. And all muſt confeſs, that the <lb/>ambition of theſe Men is very
        Extravagant, that deſire with an <lb/>hundred pound Stock (many not with half ſo much) to
        vie with <lb/>the beſt Shop-keepers or Merchants in their Neighbourhood, that <lb/>employ
        fifty times as much in their buſineſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Obj. 4. <hi rend="italic">That Phyſicians Fees are as unreaſonable and
          oppreſſive as <lb/>the Apothecaries prices.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Anſw.</hi> 'Tis denied, that Phyſicians Fees are
        either <w part="I">unreaſona-</w><lb/><w part="F">ble</w> or oppreſſive: For how ſhould they
        be ſo, when the Patient <lb/>is at liberty to give what he pleaſes? Every one is the beſt
        <lb/>judge of his own condition and ability: And accordingly ſome give <lb/>a Guinea, ſome
        ten Shillings, ſome a Crown and ſome nothing: <lb/>And whatever other Phyſicians do, the
        Subſcribers to the <w part="I">Diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">penſaries</w> profeſs themſelves as
        ready to ſerve the two laſt as the <lb/>two firſt. And take theſe one with another, how far
        ſhort will <lb/>Phyſicians Fees come of thoſe of Lawyers, which yet are not <w part="I"
          >diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">puted?</w> And the diſproportion will ſtill appear the greater,
        <lb/>when it is conſidered, that for one Client the Lawyers have <hi rend="italic">in
          <lb/>forma pauperis,</hi> the Subſcribers to the Diſpenſaries have fifty or <lb/>an
        hundred <hi rend="italic">gratis</hi> Patients, there being ſeveral hundreds of them
        <lb/>every Week. So that take one Patient with another, Rich and <lb/>Poor, and I dare
        confidently aver, that no Phyſician that duly <lb/>attends at the Diſpenſaries, has a Crown
        a Bill for all the <lb/>Bills he writes through the Year; nay I can be poſitive, that ſome
        <lb/>have not half a Crown. And what ground then can there be <lb/>for this great cry
        againſt Phyſicians Fees? </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_12" n="11"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>But ſuppoſing they were indeed unreaſonable, this Objection <lb/>would
        only argue, that Phyſicians were not fit perſons to accuſe <lb/>the Apothecaries of
        exceſſive gains; but it does no way excuſe <lb/>or juſtifie <hi rend="italic">them.</hi> And
        I will make it appear, that there is no <lb/>proportion between <hi rend="italic">their</hi>
        gains and Phyſicians <hi rend="italic">Fees.</hi> In Chronical <lb/>Caſes, when the Patient
        can come to the Phyſician, he ordinarily <lb/>gives him but half a Fee; for which he expects
        to be put into a <lb/>courſe of Phyſick that ſhall cure him, which generally laſts
        <lb/>ſeveral Weeks. In this time the Phyſick commonly comes to <lb/>ſeveral pounds; of
        which, three parts in four at leaſt ſhall be <lb/>gains, (as I will undertake to prove, if
        it be denied.) And if the <lb/>ſame Patient chance to relapſe into the ſame Diſeaſe, he
        ſhall re-<lb/><w part="F">peat</w> the courſe <hi rend="italic">toties quoties</hi> without
        ever conſulting his Phyſician <lb/>again. So that by ſuch a Patient the Apothecary ſhall get
        (at time and <lb/>time) perhaps twenty times as much as the Phyſician. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Yea tho' the Patients Caſe be acute and require the daily <w part="I"
          >at-</w><lb/><w part="F">tendance</w> of the Phyſician, the Apothecary's gains ſhall far
          <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceed</w>
        <hi rend="italic">his</hi> Fees, eſpecially if the Phyſician be one of the Apothecaries
        <lb/>Friends, and have the knack of <hi rend="italic">writing well,</hi> as their cant is. I
        <lb/>could give Inſtances enow of this: But I appeal to the experience of <lb/>moſt that
        have been ſick of Fevers (for inſtance) wherein they <lb/>have had an Apothecary, with a
        Phyſician of <hi rend="italic">his</hi> recommending: <lb/>Let them caſt up the Phyſician's
        Fees, and compute three parts <lb/>in four (at leaſt) of the Apothecaries Bill to be gains,
        and they <lb/>ſhall generally find the latter greatly to outbalance the former. <lb/>Only I
        muſt here except two or three Phyſicians (not concerned <lb/>in the Diſpenſaries) who have
        got a way (under the ſpecious <lb/>pretence of being <hi rend="italic">careful</hi> Men) to
        viſit their Patients twice or <lb/>thrice a day, when once would ſerve, only to Multiply
        their <lb/>Fees. I am not writing an Apology for ſuch; but am content <lb/>they ſhould fall
        under the ſame cenſure with the Apothecaries, <lb/>of being unreaſonable and oppreſſive. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Obj. 5. <hi rend="italic">That the Rich are ſupplyed with Medicins from
          the <w part="I">Diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">penſaries</w>, as well as the Poor.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Anſw.</hi> The prime reaſon of ſetting up the
        Diſpenſaries was <lb/>(as has been ſhewed) the ſupplying the <hi rend="italic">Poor</hi>
        with Medicins at a <lb/>low rate: And that the Subſcribers do ſtill put them to this uſe,
        <lb/>hundreds of <hi rend="italic">poor</hi> People can Weekly teſtifie. And if there are
          <pb xml:id="page_13" n="12"/><lb/>any <hi rend="italic">Rich</hi> ſupplyed with Medicins
        from thence, the Apothecaries <lb/>may thank themſelves for it. For this I will affirm, that
          <w part="I">what-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſoever</w> Phyſicians (Subſcribers to the
        Diſpenſaries) ſend their <lb/>Rich Patients thither for Phyſick, it is for one or more of
        theſe <lb/>following Reaſons. Either <hi rend="italic">firſt,</hi> becauſe of the general <w
          part="I">Combi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nation</w> of the Apothecaries to keep out or turn out
        the <w part="I">Subſcri-</w><lb/><w part="F">bers</w> from all Patients where they have an
        intereſt to do it, in <lb/>order to bring in thoſe Phyſicians that will not be concerned in
        <lb/>the ſubſcription. And ſo the Subſcribers find this the only way <lb/>to retain ſome of
        thoſe they have left. Or <hi rend="italic">ſecondly,</hi> becauſe the <lb/>Apothecaries by
        ſending in ill prepared Medicins diſappoint <lb/>them in their Practice, on purpoſe to make
        the Patients queſtion <lb/>their Phyſician's skill, and to ſend for ſome other of <hi
          rend="italic">their</hi>
        <w part="I">recom-</w><lb/><w part="F">mendation</w>. (Which I have often known to be done.)
        Or <hi rend="italic">Thirdly,</hi>
        <lb/>when the Patients themſelves complain not only of the dearneſs <lb/>but of the badneſs
        of their Apothecaries Medicins, and deſire <lb/>they may be ſupplyed from the Diſpenſaries,
        where they are not <lb/>only cheap, but good. Or <hi rend="italic">fourthly,</hi> when the
        Apothecary has for <lb/>many days together (even in dangerous and acute Diſeaſes) kept
        <lb/>the Patient in his own hands, till almoſt all opportunity of <w part="I"
          >bene-</w><lb/><w part="F">fiting</w> him is loſt: For in ſuch Caſes the Subſcribers think
        it <lb/>juſt, that the Apothecaries ſhould receive ſome check, to deter <lb/>them from ſuch
        unfair and dangerous Practices. Or <hi rend="italic">Laſtly,</hi>
        <lb/>when the Phyſician preſcribes ſome ſecret Medicin that is kept <lb/>at the
        Diſpenſaries, which he thinks not fit to make known to <lb/>the Apothecaries, leſt they
        ſhould preſently (as is uſual with them) <lb/>fall a practiſing therewith themſelves to his
        diſadvantage. And <lb/>to theſe I may add a <hi rend="italic">Sixth</hi> reaſon, which is
        only accidental, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
        <lb/>When Perſons of Condition come to the Diſpenſaries for <hi rend="italic">gratis</hi>
        <lb/>advice on the uſual days, <hi rend="italic">in forma pauperum,</hi> and the Phyſicians
        <lb/>attending are ignorant of their quality, and ſo are impoſed upon. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Theſe Reaſons I alledge in anſwer to this <hi rend="italic">fifth</hi>
        Objection, not <lb/>that the Subſcribers need give a reaſon for what they do in this
        <lb/>particular (for they have an undoubted right to give Phyſick to <lb/>whom they pleaſe,
        as I have proved before in the anſwer to <hi rend="italic">Obj.</hi>
        <lb/>1.) but that all the World may ſee, how <hi rend="italic">every way</hi> juſtifiable
        <lb/>the Subſcribers are, as to any complaint the Apothecaries make <pb xml:id="page_14"
          n="13"/><lb/>againſt them. And after all the noiſe of ſending the Rich to <lb/>the
        Diſpenſaries for Medicins, I dare ſay, take all the <w part="I">Subſcri-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >bers</w> together, and they do not ſend one Bill in thirty (that <lb/>they write for the
        Rich) thither: And if ſome ſend more than <lb/>others, it is upon account of greater
        injuries and affronts they <lb/>have met with from the Apothecaries, for appearing more <w
          part="I">for-</w><lb/><w part="F">ward</w> than their Brethren in this charitable
        Undertaking. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Obj. 6. The laſt <hi rend="italic">Objection</hi> is, <hi rend="italic"
          >That the Diſpenſaries ſell Medicins <lb/>as dear as the Apothecaries.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Anſw.</hi> 'Tis confeſt, that ſome Apothecaries,
        eſpecially the <lb/>Wholeſale ones, do ſell ſome Medicins as cheap as the <w part="I"
          >Diſpen-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſaries</w> can afford them. But pray what Medicins are they?
        They <lb/>are either ſimple Medicins and Drugs, the nature and value <lb/>whereof moſt
        people know; or ſuch ſingle compound Medicins <lb/>as are kept ready prepared in Shops, to
        be ſold out when call'd <lb/>for, by their proper and peculiar names, the value whereof is
        <lb/>as commonly known as that of Drugs and Simples. As for <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ſtance</w>, Venice Treacle, Mithridate, <hi rend="italic">Diaſcordium,</hi>
        &amp;c. tho' very <lb/>compounded Medicins, are ſold as cheap (I will not ſay ſo good)
        <lb/>by the Wholeſale Apothecaries as at the Diſpenſaries; and the <lb/>reaſon is, the Buyer
        underſtands what he buys, and the current <lb/>price of it, and ſo cannot be impoſed upon by
        the Apothecary. <lb/>And the gains the Apothecary has by theſe Medicins thus ſold, <lb/>was
        never called unreaſonable and exceſſive by the Subſcribers <lb/>to the Diſpenſaries. But the
        gain complain'd of as unreaſonable <lb/>and oppreſſive, is, when Medicins either ſimple or
        compound <lb/>are mixt together, or diſguiſed, and have a new name put upon <lb/>them,
        denoting only their form, or their uſe and virtue, and <lb/>the Patient is ignorant what
        they conſiſt of. As for inſtance, a <lb/>Cordial <hi rend="italic">bolus</hi> ſhall be
        priced at 1 <hi rend="italic">s.</hi> 6 <hi rend="italic">d.</hi> (by ſome at 2 <hi
          rend="italic">s.</hi> 6 <hi rend="italic">d.</hi>) <lb/>when the Ingredients of it are not
        worth 2 <hi rend="italic">d.</hi> A doſe of purging <lb/>Pills at the ſame price with the
        Cordial <hi rend="italic">bolus,</hi> when they are <w part="I">on-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ly</w> half a dram of <hi rend="italic">extract. Rudii, Pil. Ruffi,</hi> or <hi
          rend="italic">Cochiae,</hi> worth 2 <hi rend="italic">d.</hi> A <lb/>Cordial draught ſhall
        be 1 <hi rend="italic">s.</hi> 6 <hi rend="italic">d.</hi> when the Waters and Syrup of
        <lb/>which it conſiſts, are dear of 3 <hi rend="italic">d.</hi> A Vomit is 1 <hi
          rend="italic">s.</hi> 6 <hi rend="italic">d.</hi> (or 2 <hi rend="italic">s.</hi> 6 <hi
          rend="italic">d.</hi>) <lb/>when it is not intrinſecally worth above 1 <hi rend="italic"
          >d.</hi> or 2 <hi rend="italic">d.</hi> A <w part="I">Sto-</w><lb/><w part="F">machick</w>
        Apozem of a quart is never rated at leſs than 2 <hi rend="italic">s.</hi> 6 <hi
          rend="italic">d.</hi>
        <lb/>when the Ingredients that are boil'd in the water are bought for <pb xml:id="page_15"
          n="14"/><lb/>3 <hi rend="italic">d.</hi> or leſs, as in the bitter Decoction. And many
        Apothecaries <lb/>are ſo void of all Conſcience, as to make eight Shillings of ſuch <lb/>an
        Apozem, by dividing the quart into eight parts, and <w part="I">ſend-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ing</w> it in to the Patient for ſo many draughts (with ſome cramp <lb/>name annexed) at
        1 <hi rend="italic">s. per</hi> draught. The like extravagant way <lb/>of increaſing the
        price do they very often take, by dividing an <w part="I">E-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >lectuary</w> worth (it may be) 1 <hi rend="italic">s.</hi> into twelve parts or more, and
        <lb/>ſending in the parts ſo divided to the Patient under the name of <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >bolus</hi>'s at 1 <hi rend="italic">s.</hi> a piece at leaſt. And ſo if a Phyſician
        preſcribe a <lb/>powder of an ounce, to be taken by half a dram at a time: <lb/>Though the
        whole ounce be dear of a Shilling, as conſiſting <w part="I">on-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w>
        of teſtaceous Powders, <hi rend="italic">Sal prunellae,</hi> Sugar of Roſes, <hi
          rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> yet <lb/>the Apothecary by officiouſly dividing the ounce into
        ſixteen <lb/>Papers, ſhall make 8 <hi rend="italic">s.</hi> of it, <hi rend="italic"
          >viz.</hi> 6 <hi rend="italic">d.</hi> a Paper. Now whoſoever <lb/>will take the pains to
        enquire, at what rate the very ſame <hi rend="italic">bolus</hi>'s, <lb/>Pills, Vomits,
        Cordial draughts, Apozems, Powders, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> are <lb/>priced at the
        Diſpenſaries, he will ſee that they are generally <lb/>at leaſt 9 <hi rend="italic">d.</hi>
        in the Shilling cheaper than what the Apothecaries <lb/>fell them for. Who then does not ſee
        a notorious fallacy in the <lb/>Objection, when they affirm, that <hi rend="italic"
          >they</hi> ſell Medicins as cheap as <lb/>the Diſpenſaries, when it holds not true in a
        fiftieth part? <lb/>And only in thoſe, wherein the People cannot be impoſed <lb/>upon? </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>And beſides, there is another circumſtance that makes it yet
        <lb/>exceedingly dearer to have Phyſick from the Apothecaries, than <lb/>from the
        Diſpenſaries; and that is, that if either the <w part="I">Apothe-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >cary</w> be Doctor himſelf and ſend in Medicins to the ſick of his own <lb/>head; or if
        he be able to bring in a Favourite Phyſician that is <lb/>an Enemy to the Diſpenſaries, they
        ſhall either of them pour in <lb/>upon the Patient three times as much Phyſick as the
        Subſcribers <lb/>to the Diſpenſaries uſually preſcribe in like Caſes, the greateſt <lb/>part
        whereof, I dare be bold to ſay, is nothing to the purpoſe <lb/>of the Cure, but ſerves only
        for Pomp and to raiſe the <w part="I">Apothe-</w><lb/><w part="F">caries</w> Bill, or
        perhaps does the Patient a great deal of harm. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>So that take all conſiderations together, and who ſees not, <lb/>that
        the Diſpenſaries are the greateſt relief to the Poor that can <lb/>be imagined, when, for it
        may be, five Shillings they ſhall have <lb/>as much help in their reſpective Caſes, as the
        Rich who are <w part="I">ſup-</w>
        <pb xml:id="page_16" n="15"/><lb/><w part="F">plyed</w> with Medicins from the Apothecaries,
        can have for five <lb/>pounds? and at the ſame time have the eaſe of taking only a <lb/>few
        neceſſary Medicins, when the others are cramm'd and<lb/> drench'd all day and night long with one
        ſlap or other? </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>And now that I have given a full Anſwer to all the <hi rend="italic"
          >Apothe-<lb/>caries</hi> Objections againſt the <hi rend="italic">Diſpenſaries,</hi> I
        ſhould have put an <lb/>end to this Paper, were there not two <hi rend="italic"
          >Objections</hi> more, <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">monly</w> to be met with in
        the Town, which it may be neceſſary <lb/>to ſay ſomething to, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
        One on the Apothecaries behalf, <w part="I">a-</w><lb/><w part="F">gainſt</w> Phyſicians
        having the whole adviſing part of Phyſick; <lb/>and the other againſt one particular in the
        preſent Management <lb/>of the Diſpenſaries. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="1"><lb/>1. On the Apothecaries behalf people argue, <hi rend="italic">That
          an <w part="I">Apo-</w><lb/><w part="F">thecary</w> who has for many Years made up
          Phyſicians Preſcriptions <lb/>for Patients, and has obſerved their Operations and effects,
          ought to <lb/>have a right to adminiſter ſuch Medicins as have had good effects, <lb/>to
          other Patients in like Caſes, when he is deſired, without conſulting <lb/>any
          Phyſician.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Ans.</hi> In anſwer to this, we will firſt ſuppoſe,
        that the <w part="I">Apo-</w><lb/><w part="F">thecary</w> is of a capacity to make
        obſervations, and to know <lb/>when a like Caſe occurs; And yet in ſuch caſe I affirm, that
        he <lb/>ought not of his own head to adminiſter the moſt ſucceſſful <lb/>remedy to any other
        Patient than him for whom ſuch remedy, <lb/>was firſt preſcribed, unleſs in caſe of urgent
        neceſſity, and when the <lb/>Phyſician that preſcribed it cannot be had. For a
        <lb/>Phyſician has a <hi rend="italic">double property</hi> in his Preſcriptions: <hi
          rend="italic">Firſt,</hi> in <lb/>that when a Phyſician preſcribes for a Patient, he
        preſcribes <lb/>only <hi rend="italic">pro hoc &amp; nunc,</hi> for this Man and at this
        time; and for <lb/>doing that alone he receives his Fee. He does not ſell his
        <lb/>Preſcription by way of alienation, ſo that it ſhould be to his <lb/>Patient and to his
        Heirs or Aſſigns for ever; much leſs does <lb/>he paſs any title over to the Apothecary, who
        is only employed <lb/>by the Patient to make it up, and who ought to return the Bill
        <lb/>when he is paid for it, either to the Patient, or to the <w part="I">Phyſi-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">cian</w> that writ it: and if he either detain it, or tranſcribe it, <lb/>in
        order to make uſe of it to other Patients, without the firſt <lb/>Preſcribers lieve or
        direction, he is manifeſtly guilty of <w part="I">frau-</w><lb/><w part="F">dulently</w>
        uſurping anothers Property. <hi rend="italic">Secondly,</hi> a Phyſician <pb
          xml:id="page_17" n="16"/><lb/>has another <hi rend="italic">property</hi> in his
        Preſcriptions, in that no Man yb <lb/>Law has a right to preſcribe but himſelf: And as I
        take it, <lb/>there is as real a property in <hi rend="italic">Practice,</hi> as in <hi
          rend="italic">Eſtate.</hi> No Man <lb/>ought to meddle in that <hi rend="italic"
          >profeſſion,</hi> that he is not brought up to, <lb/>or has not a Legal admiſſion into.
        Not to mention the <hi rend="italic">Miniſtry;</hi><lb/>this is plain in the <hi
          rend="italic">Law,</hi> wherein no Sollicitor or Attorney, <lb/>how long ſoever they have
        practiſed, and how well ſoever <lb/>verſed in their buſineſs, can take upon them the
        practice of a <lb/>Lawyer either in the Chamber or in Court. Preparing of <w part="I"
          >Me-</w><lb/><w part="F">dicins</w> is but one, and that the meaneſt and moſt mechanick
        <lb/>part of Phyſick: this part is committed to the Apothecaries by ſuch <lb/>Phyſicians as
        will not undergo the more ſervile and toilſome <lb/>part of their Profeſſion, or through
        multitude of buſineſs are <lb/>not at leiſure for it; but ſtill it remains inſeparable from
        it, <lb/>and whatſoever Phyſician will, may exerciſe it. But the <w part="I">Apo-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">thecary</w>, whoſe ſole Trade is to prepare Medicins according to <lb/>the
        Diſpenſatories, or Recipe's put into his hands by Phyſicians, <lb/>has no more a right to
        invade the adviſing and preſcribing part, <lb/>than the Sollicitor or Attorney the practice
        of Councel learned <lb/>in the Law. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>But letting paſs this argument from <hi rend="italic">property,</hi> I
        will in further <lb/>Anſwer to the <hi rend="italic">Objection</hi> demonſtrate, <hi
          rend="italic">that Apothecaries are not <w part="I">ca-</w><lb/><w part="F">pable</w> of
          making obſervations, nor of judging of like Caſes,</hi> and <w part="I">there-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">fore</w> ought not to have the <hi rend="italic">Right</hi> contended for. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Every one knows an Apothecary's Education to be, to come <lb/>to the
        Trade from a Grammar School, where he has learned <lb/>to conſtrue or to make a little
        Latin; 'Tis very rare that any <lb/>deſigned for that employment, have any ſmattering in the
        Greek. <lb/>Thus qualified he comes Prentice, and is preſently ſet to the <lb/>Peſtil and
        Mortar, to run of errands, &amp;c. And after a Year or <lb/>two when he has learned to know
        one thing in the Shop from <lb/>another, and to read a Phyſicians Bill, he begins to be
        employed <lb/>in making up Medicins and carrying them out to Patients, and <lb/>continues ſo
        to do till his time runs out. All this while he has <lb/>neither time to read, nor can have
        capacity to underſtand ſuch <lb/>Books as teach the Art of Phyſick: Nor can he know any
        thing <lb/>(to any purpoſe) of the Diſeaſes for which the Medicins he <w part="I"
          >car-</w><lb/><w part="F">ries</w> out are adminiſtred. For any Patient would reckon it <w
          part="I">Sanci-</w><pb xml:id="page_18" n="17"/><lb/><w part="F">neſs</w> in Boys to be
        inquiſitive about their Caſes, in the enquiry whereinto a <lb/>Man muſt be very nice and
        particular, or he ſhall be never the wiſer. And <lb/>during this time of his Apprenticeſhip
        he generally loſes the little Latin that <lb/>he had when he came from School, ſaving what
        the Phyſicians Bills preſerve. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Well, now he is out of his time, what muſt he do but ſet up? excellently
        <lb/>qualified for the Practice of Phyſick no doubt! Yes, there were ſuch and ſuch
        <lb/>famous Doctors writ to his Maſter's Shop, and he ſaw all their Bills, and made
        <lb/>many of them up and carried them out to Patients, of whom he ſaw ſome live, <lb/>and
        ſome die; and ſo he muſt needs know ſomething of the matter! Well, to <lb/>judge of that,
        let us conſider what the matter is, viz. <hi rend="italic">The Art of Phyſick.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>This Noble <hi rend="italic">Art</hi> conſiſts of five parts, of which
        the preparing of Medicins is <lb/>but the <hi rend="italic">leaſt</hi> part of <hi
          rend="italic">one.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>There is I. the <hi rend="italic">Phyſiologick,</hi> which treats of the
        Subject and the end of <w part="I">Phy-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſick</w>, and ſo includes the
        Anatomy of an humane Body, and explains its <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ſtitution</w> and that of all its parts, with their uſes and actions, and the faculties
        <lb/>of the Animal Soul. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="2"><lb/>II. The <hi rend="italic">Pathologick,</hi> which treats of the
        nature, differences and cauſes of <lb/>Diſeaſes and their Symptoms, and explains every
        Particular wherein an humane <lb/>Body departs from its natural conſtitution. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="3"><lb/>III. The <hi rend="italic">Semiotick,</hi> which teaches the ſigns
        whereby it may be known whether <lb/>a Man is well or ill, and how diſeaſes latent in the
        body, with their cauſes, <lb/>and events, may be diſcovered: Which ſigns are commonly called
          <w part="I">Diagno-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſticks</w> and Prognoſticks. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="4"><lb/>IV. The 4<hi rend="italic">th</hi> part contains the knowledge of
        thoſe things which are as it <lb/>were the matter of health, and are uſually called
        Non-naturals; as Air, Meat <lb/>and Drink, Affections of the mind, exerciſe and reſt,
        Venery, Sleep and <w part="I">Watch-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>, with Excrements and
        Retents: And it contains alſo the knowledge of the <lb/>right uſe of theſe Non-natural
        things, ſo as that health may be preſerv'd thereby. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>And V. the fifth part, called the <hi rend="italic">Therapeutick,</hi>
        ſhews how loft health may be <lb/>reſtored, and diſeaſes with their cauſes and Symptoms
        removed. And to this <lb/>end 'tis neceſſary to be inſtructed, firſt in <hi rend="italic"
          >Method,</hi> whereby according to <w part="I">indi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cations</w> one
        may find out due <hi rend="italic">helps;</hi> and then in the <hi rend="italic">matter</hi>
        of ſuch helps, whether <lb/>contained under Diet, Surgery, or Pharmacy. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Now this very laſt thing (viz. <hi rend="italic">Pharmacy</hi>) is all
        that an Apothecary by <lb/>his education can pretend to the knowledge of: And it is but the
        leaſt part <lb/>of this neither that he can have ſuch pretence to. For the <hi rend="italic"
          >Pharmaceutick</hi>
        <lb/>part contains not only the preparing of Medicins, but the knowledge of the <lb/>Natures
        and Virtues of all thoſe things that are the matter of Medicins, <w part="I">whe-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ther</w> Vegetables, Animals, or Minerals, and this knowledge he is a ſtranger
        <lb/>to. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>With what patience then can a Man animadvert upon the aſſuming <w
          part="I">confi-</w><lb/><w part="F">dence</w> of theſe Men, who will ſet up for Practiſers
        in ſuch a difficult and <w part="I">myſte-</w><lb/><w part="F">rious</w> Art, that
        underſtand not any one part of it? A man is like to make <lb/><hi rend="italic">ſpecial
          Obſervations</hi> that neither knows the Subject affected, nor the nature <lb/>nor cauſe
        of the Diſeaſe, nor the nature of the Medicins that cure it. And <lb/>he muſt needs be a
        Witch at judging of <hi rend="italic">like</hi> Caſes, that for the mentioned <lb/>defects
        could never be a competent judge of any one Caſe. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_19" n="18"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Caſe in ſhort is this: An Apothecary when he learns his Trade, is
        <lb/>taught to know one Drug from another, can tell which will melt, and which <lb/>will
        powder, nay may obſerve which will purge, which vomit, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> He
        <lb/>learns alſo to make them up into different forms according to the preſcripts <lb/>of
        Phyſicians; and I will grant he has opportunity to obſerve, that ſome are <lb/>given moſt
        commonly in Fevers, others in Conſumptions, others in Dropſies, <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >&amp;c.</hi> But will any Man conclude, that becauſe an Apothecary knows and may
        <lb/>have obſerved theſe things, that therefore he can judge with due accurateneſs
        <lb/>either of theſe Diſeaſes, or the Methods or Reaſons of their Cure? There is <lb/>no
        general Remedy nor Method for any one Diſeaſe: different Medicins and <lb/>different Methods
        muſt be made uſe of in different Subjects, tho' the Diſeaſe <lb/>in the main be the ſame.
        And hereof no Man can be a fit Judge, but one <lb/>who is well verſed in all the parts of
        Phyſick. And therefore if there were no <lb/>Law to reſtrain Apothecaries from practiſing,
        their undeniable iggnorance <lb/>ought to keep all who value their Health or Lives, from
        depending on their <lb/>advice. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="2"><lb/>2. The other <hi rend="italic">Objection</hi> that the People
        make, is againſt one particular thing <lb/>in the preſent management of the Diſpenſaries,
        and is to this purpoſe: <hi rend="italic">If,</hi> ſay <lb/>they, <hi rend="italic">the
          Diſpenſaries ſell Medicins ſo cheap and ſo good, why may not any body <lb/>have ſuch
          Medicins there as they have occaſion for, without the trouble of going <lb/>to one of the
          Subſcribers for a Note?</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>I anſwer, 1. that People are not competent Judges of what they ail, or
        what <lb/>will help them; and ſo the Phyſicians are willing to prevent their doing <w
          part="I">them-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſelves</w> a miſchief by taking improper things. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="2"><lb/>2. Unleſs the Subſcribers be ſtill more provok't by the
        Apothecaries injuries, <lb/>they are very unwilling to make that of common uſe, which was
        purely <w part="I">deſign-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> for the relief of the Poor only. For
        they have no intention to injure the <lb/>Apothecaries in their proper Calling, if they will
        keep themſelves to that, will <lb/>make good Medicins, and be content with moderate gains. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>But 3. the Principal reaſon is, that Medicins are given out from the <w
          part="I">Diſpen-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſaries</w> by Servants, who are (generally) directed
        what to take for every <w part="I">Medi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cin</w>, by him that preſcribes
        it. And it might be very prejudical as well to <w part="I">Pa-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >tients</w>, as to the Subſcribers themſelves, if the Servants might ſell out what
        <lb/>they pleas'd without order, and might take of the Patient what they pleas'd <lb/>for
        it. For they would be under a great temptation to ſell things and either <lb/>never bring
        them to account at all; or to take more of the Patient then the <lb/>ſtated price, and to
        put the Overplus into their own Pockets. And therefore <lb/>how inconvenient ſoever it may
        ſeem to ſuch as would be their own Doctors, <lb/>not to have from the Diſpenſaries what they
        think would do them good, the <lb/>Subſcribers can by no means, for theſe reaſons, recede
        from their eſtabliſh'd <lb/>method in this Particular. </p>

    </body>

    <back>

      <p rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="italic">LONDON,</hi>
        <lb/>Printed in the Year 1702. </p>

    </back>

  </text>
</TEI>
