<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: Deplorable state of the sick</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">THE Deplorable State of the SICK from the Impious Treacheries of many
              Physicians and Surgeons to the Patients and their Professios, Represented (with the
              obvious Remedies) to the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and the Commons of Great
              Britain. </title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T186734</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T186734"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for John Morphew near Stationers-Hall, MDCCVII.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1707</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="62"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">Bodleian Library, Oxford</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW104858081</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Public welfare and institutional"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="1"/>
    <body>
      <pb n="3"/>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>A horizontal double-line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <head rend="align-center space">
        <lb/>A <lb/><hi rend="size(3.0)">LETTER </hi>
        <lb/>OF AN <lb/><hi rend="size(2.0)">Eminent Divine, </hi>
        <lb/>TO THE <lb/><hi rend="sc size(1.5)">Dispensary Physicians. </hi>
      </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">I</hi> Had in my Sermon diſcours'd, That the Creator of <lb/>the World
        had given Reaſon to Mankind, to adapt <lb/>the Governments and Laws to their various Circum-
        <lb/>ſtances; as the Foods and Medicines, which are beſtow'd <lb/>on us in the greateſt
        abundance, have been prepar'd from <lb/>Obſervation and Experience, in the different
        Climates, for <lb/>the Preſervation of Life. All the Governments have been <lb/>and muſt be
        proſperous, when (as all the parts of our <lb/>Body are deſign'd for the common Life of the
        whole) the <lb/>People ſhall with Courage defend the Prince, and cheer- <lb/>fully obſerve
        the Laws; and when the Supreme and In- <lb/>feriour Magiſtrates ſhall vigilantly preſerve
        the Properties <lb/>of the Subjects. The firſt and the greateſt Property is <lb/>Life, which
        demands the Preſervation, by the Laws, of <lb/>the Plenty of all things neceſſary to
        maintain it. As all <lb/>the Parts of our Body aſſiſt the other, every Subject is <pb n="4"/>
        <lb/>oblig'd to defend one the other, muſt repell all Aſſaults, <lb/>muſt demand of the
        inferiour Magiſtrates their Care of the <lb/>Publick Welfare. The happineſs of Mankind is
        inſur'd <lb/>to us on theſe Conditions only, and are not loſt and be- <lb/>tray'd but by our
        own Follies; as our Health, by Luxu- <lb/>ry and Exceſs, and our Life in Diſeaſes by the
        neglect or <lb/>unhappy application of Medicines. It is Impious to ex- <lb/>pect Miracles to
        ſupply our Negligence of our own Pre- <lb/>ſervation. The Clergy are appointed to act, as
        the De- <lb/>puties of the Supreme Power, to admoniſh the Prince and <lb/>the People, to
        exact the great mutual Duties of Juſtice, <lb/>Obedience, and the Care of the Publick
        Proſperity. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>You will be ſurpriz'd, Gentlemen, how much this Diſ- <lb/>courſe inflam'd my
        Pariſhioners, to debate and diſcover <lb/>if any Care is taken of the People in Sickneſs, it
        has from <lb/>them recoyl'd on me, and ſav'd me, as thoſe that heard <lb/>it. I could not
          <unclear>viſit</unclear> any one Family, but I was moſt ſen- <lb/>ſibly affected. We are
        the moſt neglected, tho' moſt op- <lb/>preſt People in the World. The Poor, the Servants,
        the <lb/>meaner Tradeſmen are undone in every Sickneſs. We are <lb/>cheated for one Dram and
        for one Spoonful of the Reme- <lb/>dies in a greater degree of Expence, than the Govern-
        <lb/>ment formerly did, and now can and muſt ſecure to us a <lb/>Pound and a Gallon of the
        beſt Medicines in the Uni- <lb/>verſe; and then to multiply theſe Frauds, we muſt in e-
        <lb/>very Diſeaſe take the oppreſſive, pernicious Multitude of <lb/>the little ſhamming
        Doſes. In other Houſes, <hi rend="italic">Lord have <lb/>Mercy on us!</hi> VVhat do the
        Magiſtrates think, to ſuffer <lb/>every Boy ſetting up the Trade of an <hi rend="italic"
          >Apothecary</hi> (whoſe <lb/>Skill has never been examin'd) and every Vagabond from
        <lb/>Foreign Countries to impoſe on our Weakneſs by a Thou- <lb/>ſand Lyes, to undertake all
        the dangerous Diſeaſes? Do <lb/>they ſee and hear, that many near them are daily kill'd by
        <lb/>their Ignorance of the Diſeaſe, by the Numbers of Medi- <lb/>cines, by which only they
        pay themſelves for their deadly <lb/>Care and Advice? Are they inſenſible of all Humanity,
        of the <lb/>Guilt they contract, as Accomplices? The Eternal Uni- <pb n="5"/>
        <lb/>on of the Inhabitants of the Iſland is gloriouſly accom- <lb/>pliſh'd, ſhall we be
        wretchedly heedleſs of ſecuring the <lb/>Union of the Soul and Body of every Inhabitant? VVe
        <lb/>muſt imitate the excellent Diſcipline of the <hi rend="italic">Britains</hi> of the
        <lb/>Northern Part, encourage Virtue and the Publick Spirit, <lb/>and repel the raging
        Libertinage and Contempt of all <lb/>Order and the Laws deſtructive to all Societies. Are
        the <lb/>furious Inroads and Devaſtations and Butcheries of the <lb/>Borders aboliſh'd, and
        all the Profeſſions of Religion, the <lb/>Law and Phyſick without defence, laid open to the
        Inva- <lb/>ſions of every impudent Pretender, with the Arts only <lb/>and Abilities to cheat
        and delude the People, deſtitute of the <lb/>Advice and Defence of the Magiſtrates? The
        VVicked <lb/>Phyſicians and Surgeons are the firſt and Principal Cauſe <lb/>of our Miſeries,
        they baſely juſtify to us their wretched <lb/>Quackery, when call'd in at the Extremity;
        they vainly <lb/>labour to mend the Miſtakes by contrary Methods, and <lb/>they improve the
        Robbery by appointing the ſame endleſs <lb/>quantities of the little Doſes, many ſuperfluous
        and neg- <lb/>lected, many more than they uſe in their own Houſes. <lb/>Theſe two Enormous
        Crimes (the Phyſicians and Surge- <lb/>ons have almoſt cngroſs'd to themſelves) deſerve
        Death. <lb/>The College and the Company ſupported by the Govern- <lb/>ment can only ſave us.
        But there are Phyſicians and Sur- <lb/>geons more Honeſt and Learned than our Enemies, who
        <lb/>would ſecure us from this Robbery and Deſtruction, and <lb/>preſerve the College and
        Company to improve all the <lb/>Members in the reſpective Arts and Sincerity to the Pati-
        <lb/>ents, they are both aſſaulted by the perjur'd Perfidiouſneſs <lb/>of many of both the
        Societies. Dr. <hi rend="italic">R.</hi> ſwears every day <lb/>he will damn and deſtroy it;
        that there is, and ſhall be no <lb/>other Phyſician in the Nation but himſelf. The largeſt
        <lb/>part of the Phyſicians delude us fatally, commending the <lb/>vile VVork the Apothecary
        has made, deſign nothing <lb/>more in the Preſcription than his Profit, ruin their own
        <lb/>Profeſſion to gain the prevalent Recommendation, the Pre- <lb/>ference in the
        Apothecaries favour. There is a Surgeon <pb n="6"/>
        <lb/>of the ſame Principles and Morals with the Bravo Doctor, <lb/>who breaks his Company,
        and the Improvements and Sub- <lb/>ſiſtence of his Prentices, that he may be nois'd as the
        on- <lb/>ly Judge and Operator. The others, by a deadly piece of <lb/>Work they are now and
        then prefer'd to. What will be <lb/>the Fate of the miſerable <hi rend="italic"
        >Engliſh</hi>, when the Apothecaries <lb/>are increas'd by two or three Prentices in all the
        Shops, <lb/>when the College and Company ſhall be deſerted, and <lb/>our Life, and the two
        Profeſſions ſhall be deſtitute of the <lb/>Care of the Magiſtrate? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>You know, Gentlemen, I came lately to my Prefer- <lb/>ment here from the Univerſity; we
        have the ſame Uſage <lb/>in <hi rend="italic">Oxford</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
          >Cambridge</hi>. The Profeſſors are inſenſible, <lb/>that the Faculty is invaded, almoſt
        ruin'd. Do they in- <lb/>ſtruct the Students in the faithful and learned Practice, to
        <lb/>preſerve the Patients and the Profeſſion together? I ob- <lb/>ſerve the Outlyers
        affront the College, refuſe to unite <lb/>with it, betray it and themſelves, and the Sick,
        to the <lb/>Apothecaries Encroachments. Alarm'd with theſe Out- <lb/>rages, I demanded of
        many of the Apothecaries Phyſici- <lb/>ans, how long they intended to cultivate and increaſe
        the <lb/>fraudulent and pernicious Practice? They reply'd with <lb/>great Impudence, as long
        as the People cannot diſcover it, <lb/>as long as we muſt live by it. We own, that the Gen-
        <lb/>try and People are us'd by us in the moſt filthy man- <lb/>ners. We ſhall be call'd <hi
          rend="italic">Scavengers</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Reformers</hi>, if we <lb/>uſe them
        otherwiſe. We have no other ways to come <lb/>into Buſineſs, but yielding all the Diſeaſes
        to the Apothe- <lb/>caries, 'till Danger or Death appear; we muſt complement <lb/>the Choice
        of us to mend the matter, by extolling their <lb/>great Skill and Care, and by writing two
        or three Guineas <lb/>a Day of the ſmall Doſes, let the Caſe be what it will. We <lb/>will
        not riſque thoſe our only Fees and Reputation, to <lb/>ſave the Kingdom. Many Surgeons
        aſſur'd me, their <lb/>Caſe was the ſame, and oblig'd me with the Information <lb/>of the
        Remonſtrances of your College, which they ſaid, <lb/>aſſert Surgery as well as Phyſick, ſold
        at the <hi rend="italic">Crane</hi> in <hi rend="italic">St. <pb n="7"/>
          <lb/>Paul's Church-yard</hi>, to which no Phyſician or Surgeon had <lb/>dar'd to reply,
        which will amply inſtruct you, how great, <lb/>how many are the Calamities of the Sick, from
        our Trea- <lb/>cheries to them. The moſt infamous of both heartily <lb/>wiſh, the Government
        would chaſtiſe and reform us; <lb/>but who will call on the Magiſtrate, who do not know
        <lb/>their own Loſſes, and Pains, and Danger, and are ſtupi- <lb/>fied by the numberleſs
        Forgeries of the Apoſtate Phyſici- <lb/>ans and Surgeons, united with the innumerable
        Apotheca- <lb/>ries their Maſters, and the Governours of the Families? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Your College Diſcourſes have no other Deſign, but <lb/>the Preſervation of the Royal
        Family, the Nobility, Gen- <lb/>try and People, by the ſincere and learn'd Practice. The
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Diſpenſary Poem</hi>, writ at the Requeſt, and by the Inſtru-
        <lb/>ctions of the Preſident, and the Majority of the Society, <lb/>avows the deteſtable
        Knavery, and the moſt certain great- <lb/>eſt Ignorance of the Phyſicians, as well of the
        Medicines, <lb/>as Diſeaſes. The Surgeons muſt be in the ſame Circum- <lb/>ſtances with you. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On Saturday Morning, a great part of my Pariſh, of <lb/>the Church and Diſſenters,
        fill'd my Parlour. I obſerv'd a <lb/>Paleneſs, but a reſolv'd Air in all their Faces, as in
        the Al- <lb/>lies puſhing the <hi rend="italic">French</hi> at <hi rend="italic"
          >Ramillies</hi>. Their Onſet on the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Engliſh</hi>, who neglect the
        Laws, their Property and Life, <lb/>and the perfidious Phyſicians and Surgeons, more cruel
        <lb/>Enemies than the moſt raging Tyrant, was as brave, and <lb/>will gain the Victory.
        Their Language, I perceive, was <lb/>taken from your Treatiſes, which they had read, and of-
        <lb/>ten ſeriouſly debated: The Proofs of every Article are <lb/>publiſh'd in them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>We cry out to you for Juſtice, and our natural and le- <lb/>gal Right, the Puniſhment
        and Reformation of the moſt <lb/>impious Practiſers, who betray the only poſſible Improve-
        <lb/>ment of the young Phyſicians and Surgeons, who com- <lb/>bine with the Apothecaries to
        have us forc'd to take their <lb/>illegal, unexamin'd, unlicens'd Advice, by the inſuffera-
        <lb/>ble Payments for the Medicines; we are compell'd to <pb n="8"/>
        <lb/>hazard and loſe our Life, imploying them from the intole- <lb/>rable Expence, and kill
        the Growth of the Knowledge of <lb/>the two Profeſſions. You inform'd us from the Pulpit,
        <lb/>that Providence is not, and cannot be deficient in the Pro- <lb/>viſion of the greateſt
        Plenty of all the Neceſſaries to pre- <lb/>ſerve Mankind. The Magiſtrate is the Steward, and
        <lb/>muſt keep open thoſe Magazines of Bread, the Foods, and <lb/>all the other neceſſary
        Supports, and invite us to enjoy our <lb/>Shares of the vaſt Abundance. Our Government has
        for- <lb/>merly appointed the general Medicines of common and <lb/>moſt frequent Uſe, to be
        ſold for our Relief, which are <lb/>all of the cheapeſt Values: In the laſt Age, every Fami-
        <lb/>ly knew all thoſe Medicines, how to divide or mix them; <lb/>what were the low Prices
        of each. This Privilege is now <lb/>ſacredly preſerv'd in the other Parts of <hi
          rend="italic">Europe</hi>. We now <lb/>are undone, we are plunder'd by the ſcandalous
        Exacti- <lb/>ons of one Hundred Parts more than the juſt common <lb/>Rates. We have together
        warily examin'd all the Parti- <lb/>culars; we avow, the Remedies are in the ſmall Portions
        <lb/>of their Doſes cheaper than Bread, and the common Nou- <lb/>riſhments. Our vile
        Phyſicians and Surgeons are the <lb/>Contrivers or Abettors of the Cheats of the little
        Doſes, in- <lb/>ſtead of the larger Quantities, which they formerly or- <lb/>der'd the
        Houſes to buy, and to divide and mix, and uſe <lb/>in the more eaſie Caſes: we are now
        pillag'd by them in <lb/>the Proportions of 40, 50, 100 to one. VVe are forc'd <lb/>to
        explain it to you, by a vulgar, but moſt inſtructive <lb/>Example. If my Phyſician or
        Surgeon adviſe me to take <lb/>Old <hi rend="italic">Malaga</hi> VVine, ſhall they permit me
        to ſend for it <lb/>to the Vintner's, at 2 <hi rend="italic">s.</hi> and 6 <hi rend="italic"
          >d.</hi> the Quart, or ſhall <lb/>they add a fulſome Syrup to deceive me, to alter the
        <lb/>Colour, to make it more nauſeous and unwholſome? <lb/>Contrive with the Vintner to ſend
        it in by his Boys in di- <lb/>minutive Parcels, that the one Quart ſhall draw five
        <lb/>Pounds out of me? Do not the Fools engage me to ſtick <lb/>cloſe to the Vintner and his
        Boys, and to command them <lb/>to adviſe us? Since we muſt pay five Guineas for every <pb
          n="9"/>
        <lb/>Quart of <hi rend="italic">Malaga</hi>, we will make them ſave us all their <lb/>Fees. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>They ſaw me trembling, I was aſſur'd of their Affe- <lb/>ction, but they ruſh'd on me
        with a Rage not to be ex- <lb/>preſs'd to you. I paid ſix Guineas for the Vulgar <hi
          rend="italic">Bitter <lb/>Decoction</hi>, ſent in the ſmall Glaſſes, and the Ingredients
        <lb/>were heretofore, and may now be had for one Shilling. <lb/>The <hi rend="italic"
          >2d.</hi> I paid <hi rend="italic">30l.</hi> for <hi rend="italic">Perle Juleps</hi> in 14
        Days, when one <lb/>of them is worth but 8 <hi rend="italic">d.</hi> Then the <hi
          rend="italic">3d. Venice Treacle</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Diaſcordium Mithridate</hi>,
        are very cheap in the Pound. I <lb/>paid two Guineas every day, in a long Sickneſs, for the
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Dram Boles</hi> of them and the ſmall Draught to waſh them
        <lb/>down. Then a <hi rend="italic">4th.</hi> the common <hi rend="italic">Cordial
          Powders</hi> are not <lb/>worth a Farthing a piece. I knew a poor Woman reduc'd <lb/>to
        Beggary, by a Crown for every one of many of them <lb/>every day ſhe was ſick, 'till a
        Charitable Phyſician made <lb/>the Cure in a Week, with the Charge of one of them. <lb/>They
        all join'd in one Voice and Shout, We are <hi rend="italic">Mer- <lb/>chants</hi>, we are
          <hi rend="italic">Diſtillers</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Druggiſts</hi>, we have in our long
        <lb/>Services for our Maſters abroad, in all the Parts of <hi rend="italic">Eu-
          <lb/>rope</hi>, ſeen the more honeſt, and the vaſtly greater Suc- <lb/>ceſſes of the
        Phyſicians and Surgeons, and we know the <lb/>low Rates of many domeſtick Remedies lately
        communi- <lb/>cated to us by our faithful Phyſicians of the Diſpenſary <lb/>As God is the
        Preſerver of Men, the moſt Soverign Me- <lb/>dicines muſt be moſt plentiful, growing in our
        own Cli- <lb/>mates, or imported in large Quantities. Our Reaſon, as <lb/>well as the
        College, ſupported by all Antiquity, and all <lb/>the moſt eminent Phyſicians of the two
        laſt Centuries, aſ- <lb/>ſure us, that the Preparations muſt be moſt facil and ready,
        <lb/>rational and ſimple, not confounded and debas'd by Con- <lb/>fuſions of Ingredients, or
        corrupted by long pretended <lb/>Artifices, only to delude and rob us. But our Phyſicians
        <lb/>and Surgeons, during the Contrivance to take away our <lb/>Money, hazard, or take away
        our Life. They are not <lb/>able to plead and defend themſelves. <hi rend="italic"
          >Bezoar</hi>, the vilely <lb/>cheap <hi rend="italic">precious Stones</hi>, as they call
        them, the <hi rend="italic">Leaf Gold</hi>, <pb n="10"/>
        <lb/>are good for nothing, but being indiſſolvable in us, they <lb/>do all they can to
        deſtroy us: they lie unalter'd in us, in <lb/>the room of the moſt uſeful Medicines, we
        ſhould have <lb/>in their ſtead. Beſide the Demonſtrations of the College, <lb/>we know,
        they are not Medicines, they are not us'd a- <lb/>broad. How many Millions recover without
        them! VVe <lb/>import into <hi rend="italic">England</hi> but a ſmall Parcel of <hi
          rend="italic">Bezoar</hi>. You ſhall <lb/>hear the greateſt Impoſture ever wounded your
        Ears. <lb/>They pretend it muſt be in all the Boles and Juleps; all <lb/>the Remedies are in
        the Bills ſtyl'd <hi rend="italic">Bezoarti<unclear>ck</unclear></hi>. Our Ima-
        <lb/>gination muſt be tickled by the Bill, to <unclear>diſt</unclear>inguiſh the
        <lb/>Aſſault on our Money and Life. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I could not ſupport my Abhorrence of a Crime in all <lb/>its Circumſtances, more
        abominable than the Plunders on <lb/>the Road. A Remedy muſt, and ſhall be found out.— </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>They ſtopt me with the Acclamations of Victory, when <lb/>the Enemy runs. We have the
        wicked Phyſicians and <lb/>Surgeons under our Feet. Our Impeachment of them <lb/>will
        require and deſerve your Attention and Patience. <lb/>Our Government, as in all Parts of <hi
          rend="italic">Europe</hi>, commanded <lb/>the College to appoint Medicines for the general
        Uſe. By <lb/>this <hi rend="italic">Book</hi>, the Apothecaries muſt prepare all the
        Remedies <lb/>of their Shops. They are, as they muſt be, <hi rend="italic">perfect Me-
          <lb/>dicines</hi>, every one fully deſign'd to anſwer the ſeveral <lb/>Purpoſes, without
        the Delay and Trouble of Mixture, <lb/>as far as it is poſſible to contrive them. The
        Compound <lb/>are, and muſt be, every one compleat in the Kind, as the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">compound Waters</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Elixirs</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
          >Confections</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Powders</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Pills</hi>, <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Oils</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Ointments</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
          >Plaiſters</hi>. The Phyſicians and Surgeons <lb/>have their Reward for their Advice and
        Fidelity to us, <lb/>as in the Inſtance of the <hi rend="italic">old Malaga</hi>, and are
        oblig'd to <lb/>preſerve to us our Right, not to impoſe or ſuffer any Fraud <lb/>to be
        impos'd on us. They muſt report to us the Quan- <lb/>tities of each of theſe publick, and
        our Remedies to be <lb/>us'd. We can mix (as well as in old <hi rend="italic">England</hi>,
        and all o- <lb/>ther Nations) the <hi rend="italic">ſimple</hi>, and the <hi rend="italic"
          >compound Waters</hi>, the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Spirits</hi>, and <hi rend="italic"
          >Tinctures</hi>. We can divide their Doſes, and of <pb n="11"/>
        <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Confections</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Pills</hi>, and <hi
          rend="italic">Powders</hi>, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> with the ſureſt <lb/>Exactneſs.
        How many Remedies are every day and <lb/>hour now divided in our Houſes, the <hi
          rend="italic">volatile Spirits</hi>, the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Laudanums</hi>, the <hi
          rend="italic">Elixirs</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Rhubarb</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
          >Manna</hi>, and the <lb/><hi rend="italic">purging Salts</hi>? Our Abilities are equal to
        the Boys in the <lb/>Shop, and our Cautions to prevent any poſſible Errour <lb/>more
        powerful than of the playful Lads. They are now <lb/>preſcrib'd by the knaviſh Phyſicians
        and Surgeons, in <lb/>Mixtures of very many of them together, only to diſ- <lb/>guiſe them
        from our Knowledge, and the Price of the <lb/>whole. They are parcel'd by their Order into
        many <lb/>little ſhamming Doſes, to extort 3 or 4 Guineas a day, <lb/>when often we have all
        of them ready in the Cloſet, and <lb/>the greateſt Expence of them cannot be 3 or 4
        Shillings. <lb/>The Government demands, that we ſhall know the <hi rend="italic">Mix-
          <lb/>tures of the 4 or 5 Cordial Juleps</hi>, now only us'd, and the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Uſes</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Doſes of the publick Spirits</hi>, <hi
          rend="italic">Tinctures</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Confe- <lb/>ctions</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
          >Pills</hi>, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> for the common incidental Diſorders of
        <lb/>our Children, and Servants. All the Myſtery was in- <lb/>vented only to cheat us; we
        are baſely told, that the <lb/><hi rend="italic">excellent publick Remedies are good for
          nothing</hi>, unleſs <lb/>they play the Changes on them, by mixing them every <lb/>hour at
        all Hazards to blind us, that a <hi rend="italic">Grain or two <lb/>more or leſs of
          Diſacordium, Crabs-Eyes, and Coral</hi>, <lb/>would certainly kill or delay the Recovery.
        You muſt not <lb/>now (<hi rend="italic">the moſt God-like and raviſhing Charity, and of the
          leaſt <lb/>Expence</hi>) beſtow a <hi rend="italic">Julep</hi>, a <hi rend="italic"
          >Confection</hi>, or a <hi rend="italic">Pill</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">Powder</hi>,
        <lb/>on our Servants or poor Neighbours. They muſt be left for <lb/>the Apothecaries to
        devour by the Rapine of one Hun- <lb/>dred to one, more than we could purchaſe the
        Quantities. <lb/>Our Poor, have by Tradition, ſecur'd a ſmall part of their <lb/>Property;
        they run to the Shop for a <hi rend="italic">Penyworth</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Sa-
          <lb/>fron</hi>, of <hi rend="italic">Cordial-water</hi>, of a <hi rend="italic"
          >Powder</hi>, of <hi rend="italic">Mithridate</hi>. But <lb/>their Hearts are broken, they
        are told they are little worth, <lb/>if they are not ſhuffled with <hi rend="italic"
          >Bezoar</hi>, and the <hi rend="italic">other Impo- <lb/>ſtures</hi>. I was then permitted
        to declare my Reſentment, <lb/>that we muſt <hi rend="italic">abjure our Religion</hi>, and
          <hi rend="italic">throw up our Commiſ- <lb/>ſion</hi>, if we do not command, that the
        Divine Benefactions <pb n="12"/>
        <lb/>of the Neceſſaries of Life ſhall be equally diſtributed, by de- <lb/>nouncing from the
        Pulpits, and by our Admonitions of the <lb/>Magiſtrates of their Guilt, the Ravages of the
        People, by the <lb/>Violation of the Truſt we repoſe in our Phyſicians and Sur- <lb/>geons,
        and their Neglect in ſupporting the legal Powers of <lb/>the College and Company, to expoſe
        and puniſh theſe Cri- <lb/>minals. They ſhall be compelled to order the excellent
        <lb/>Medicines without <hi rend="italic">Mixture</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Diviſion</hi>,
        and to note the <lb/>Prices. <hi rend="italic">All the Families</hi> will gratefully
        receive, and ſoon <lb/>be <hi rend="italic">Maſters of the moſt gainful Inſtructions</hi>.
        We are oblig'd <lb/>by the Laws to make good all the Robberies in our Coun- <lb/>tries,
        unleſs we can apprehend the Robber, and convict <lb/>him. I and you are guilty of all theſe
        Devaſtations, if <lb/>we do not inform our Neighbours, rouze them to join <lb/>with the
        Magiſtrate to ſeize the Thieves. While I was <lb/>ſpeaking, my Friends, I perceiv'd, had
        their Breaſt full: <lb/><hi rend="italic">It is nothing</hi>, they ſaid, <hi rend="italic"
          >that we are cheated</hi>, and the Poor <lb/>reduc'd to Miſery; we are hazarded or
        deſtroy'd in every <lb/>Sickneſs. Theſe Colluſive knaviſh <hi rend="italic">Mixtures</hi>
        are oppreſ- <lb/>ſive to our Stomachs and Blood, often have no Opera- <lb/>tion for our
        Relief, becauſe the 8 or 10 perfect Medi- <lb/>cines (which are themſelves compoſitions) do
        violate and <lb/>obſtruct the juſt and neceſſary Operations of every Ingre- <lb/>dient. You
        will with Difficulty ſupport your ſelf, when <lb/>you hear the Injuries we receive from the
        perfidious Phy- <lb/>ſicians and Surgeons. <hi rend="italic">A ſower, fermenting, roapy,
          ſtink- <lb/>ing, or at beſt, ſugary and loathſome Syrup</hi> is caſt into the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Juleps</hi>, made by it moſt ungrateful to the Stomach, moſt <lb/>corruptive
        of the Blood. The temperate Powders are <lb/>heated by the Acrid, theſe are debas'd in their
        turns by <lb/>the abſorbing. The Gentle, and hot, and active <hi rend="italic">Pills</hi>
        are <lb/>mix'd to make a Doſe, when one of the ſorts was intended <lb/>ſor the occaſion of
        the Diſeaſe or Conſtitution. All the <lb/>Admirable <hi rend="italic">Confections</hi>, <hi
          rend="italic">Powders</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Extracts</hi>, are jumbled <lb/>with the <hi
          rend="italic">corrupted, ſtinking, ſticky Conſerves</hi>, and the <hi rend="italic">ab-
          <lb/>hor'd Syrups</hi>, to <hi rend="italic">make a fulſom, nauſeated Bole</hi>, which re-
        <lb/>quires the other condemn'd Mixture to waſh it down; <lb/>two Colluſive Medicines ſorc'd
        at once to oppreſs the mi- <pb n="13"/>
        <lb/>ſerable Patient. Our Nature feels and judges, and in <lb/>moſt Caſes abhors the baſe
        Medicines. They are reje- <lb/>cted with Abhorrence, and thrown away, and in a <lb/>Million
        of Inſtances, Nature then ſoon triumphs over the <lb/>Diſeaſe, aſſiſted by the excellent <hi
          rend="italic">natural Cordials</hi>, and o- <lb/>ther Remedies of the Family, or thoſe
        preſerv'd from the <lb/>Corruptions of the <hi rend="italic">Mixture</hi>. Our eminent
        Phyſicians and <lb/>Surgeons, who dare not write any one thing but for the <lb/>Apothecary's
        Profit, are by Cuſtom, train'd in directing <lb/>only theſe; they cannot appoint any other,
        they do not <lb/>know the Virtues and Uſes of the excellent Medicines to <lb/>be taken by
        themſelves, as the Government, from the Col- <lb/>lege, appoints. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I imagin'd, the Diſcourſe was drawing to its Conclu- <lb/>ſion. But will you, they went
        on, receive and believe <lb/>the greateſt Truth in the World, that the <hi rend="italic"
          >Ignorance</hi> of <lb/>theſe Phyſicians and Surgeons, <hi rend="italic">muſt certainly
          expoſe to De- <lb/>ſtruction, the Life of the Royal Family, the Nobility, Gentry <lb/>and
          People</hi>? VVhen they were faithful to us, and dire- <lb/>cted us to mix and divide the
        perfect publick Medicines, <lb/>or to infuſe or decoct many admirable Simples, (as the Di-
        <lb/>ſeaſe or Conſtitution requir'd, one or two of them toge- <lb/>ther,) they knew, with
        the greateſt Exactneſs, if the <hi rend="italic">Wa- <lb/>ter</hi>, the <hi rend="italic"
          >Spirit</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Tinctures</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Powder</hi>, <hi
          rend="italic">Pill</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">Confe- <lb/>ction</hi>, were good, or the
        worſt in the VVorld. They <lb/>would extol this, and <unclear>fling</unclear> away the
        other, and make us <lb/>ſend to ſuch an Apothecary for the beſt of his they had <lb/>lately
        taſted in another Houſe. But our vain preſuming <lb/>ignorant Phyſicians and Surgeons, when
        they now ſee or <lb/>taſt their fooliſh Mixtures (which they therefore never do) <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">cannot make any Judgment, if any one of the Ingredients is <lb/>good</hi>.
        As in the Tumults of the Rabble, their Numbers <lb/>ſecure them from Execution. They do not
        know one <hi rend="italic">Sim- <lb/>ple</hi>, cannot inform us that the <hi rend="italic"
          >Rhubarb</hi> is rotten, and the <lb/>Child will die, if he has not better; that theſe <hi
          rend="italic">Flowers</hi>, and <lb/><hi rend="italic">Seeds</hi>, and <hi rend="italic"
          >Roots</hi>, are not fit for uſe. All my Houſe was <lb/>fill'd with the Exclamations. They
        know nothing of any <pb n="14"/>
        <lb/>one Medicine. Dr. <hi rend="italic">R.</hi> has been caught a thouſand times <lb/>in
        his Blunders, has loſt the VVagers he wanted Sence to <lb/>avoid. The other Apoſtate
        Phyſicians and Surgeons, are <lb/>upon the level with him. They are not made to learn
        <lb/>them at the <hi rend="italic">Univerſities</hi>. VVe know they are here now
        <lb/>engag'd in worſe Company and Entertainments. The <lb/><hi rend="italic">Merchants</hi>,
          <hi rend="italic">Druggiſts</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Diſtillers</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
          >many other Traders</hi>, cry'd <lb/>aloud, VVe will maintain it before the <hi
          rend="italic">Parliament</hi>, before <lb/>all Mankind, that without frequently applying
        each ſingly <lb/>to their Senſes, by carefully comparing and detecting the <lb/>Differences,
        they ſhall never know a Medicine. VVe <lb/>cannot arrive to any Skill in our Goods, but by
        many, and <lb/>continual Examinations and Tryals. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>VVhen the Managers of this Part drew to the Con- <lb/>cluſion, many <hi rend="italic"
          >Merchants</hi> advanc'd to me with a Confu- <lb/>ſion and Trouble not to be deſcrib'd. It
        is from this Igno- <lb/>rance of our Phyſicians and Surgeons, that <hi rend="italic">the
          Apothecaries <lb/>dare make the moſt abhor'd ſophiſticated Medicines</hi>. Can you
        <lb/>conceive, that it is commonly ſaid, <hi rend="italic">Mine has good things, <lb/>and I
          pity the reſt of the City</hi>. This I believe makes very <lb/>good, and not one beſides.
        They ſell ſeveral ſorts of the <lb/>higher and loweſt Prices: The VVholeſale to a Retaler:
        <lb/>The ſweepings of the Druggiſt's Shop furniſh the Materi- <lb/>als. Can you conceive,
        that <hi rend="italic">ſix of our chief Apothecaries were <lb/>accus'd before the
          College</hi>, for making and vending the moſt <lb/>frequently us'd Medicines in the
          <unclear>ſa</unclear>feſt manners; the prin- <lb/>cipal Ingredients of many of them
        inhumanly detain'd from <lb/>the Sick? The Officers of the Company had injur'd an
        <lb/>Apothecary in the City; he order'd his Friends to buy <lb/>the Remedies moſt uſually
        adminiſtred. They were <hi rend="italic">con- <lb/>demn'd at the Hall by the unanimous Voice
          of the Venders of <lb/>many of them</hi>. The Names of the Men and the Medicines <lb/>are
        printed by the College. The Apothecary was the <lb/>Evidence againſt them; the Phyſicians
        (which is the in- <lb/>tolerable Grievance we now deplore) were not able to ſay <lb/>any
        thing to the matter. They would, they muſt have <lb/>paſt on any one of their Patients of
        the beſt Quality: Are <pb n="15"/>
        <lb/>they not rare Cures of Dr. <hi rend="italic">R</hi>'s working with ſuch Tools on
        <lb/>Diſeaſes, which are not able to deſtroy the Sick, when his <lb/>Apothecary in <hi
          rend="italic">Covent-Garden</hi>, is one of them, and his <lb/>Apothecary in the City, has
        been diſcover'd, and there <lb/>was a large Collection of their Poiſonous VVares, which
        <lb/>were not brought to that Tryal? Are not theſe ſuper- <lb/>excellent Phyſicians and
        Surgeons, who know not, who <lb/>care not what they order unto us? As the Trade and its
        <lb/>Poverty increaſes; as the Emulation and Neceſſity of <lb/>gaining the moſt they can
        from the Badneſs of the Medi- <lb/>cines, who ſhall enſure us, when the Adviſers cannot,
        <lb/>that they are not current in the <hi rend="italic">Royal Chamber</hi> and the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Nobility</hi>, as well as ours? The <hi rend="italic">Rhubarb
          Apothecary</hi> and his <lb/>Partners, were by the <hi rend="italic">Druggiſt</hi> accus'd
        before the <hi rend="italic">Commiſ- <lb/>ſioners of the publick Accounts</hi>, for robbing
        the late King, by <lb/>the exceſſive Prices for the Medicines ſold to him for no-
        <lb/>thing, and good for nothing, and for the Murthers of <lb/>many Thou<choice>
          <corr/>
          <sic> </sic>
        </choice>ſands of the Army in the firſt Deſcent in <hi rend="italic">Ire- <lb/>land</hi>. It
        is printed, that they took the Oaths of the Cri- <lb/>minals themſelves, were juſt neither
        to the King, nor the <lb/>vaſt Numbers barbarouſly deſtroy'd. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I had not the Power on my Mind, my Paſſion made <lb/>the Reply, <hi rend="italic">The
          Government ſhall not take care of ſuch Mon- <lb/>ſtrous Fools as you</hi>. You contrive
        your own Deſtruction, <lb/>and are angry, if any one endeavours to ſave you. You <lb/>will
        have the Apothecary come to your Houſe, enter the <lb/>Chamber of the Sick, when you ſhould
        command him to <lb/><hi rend="italic">the Still</hi>, <hi rend="italic">the Mortar</hi>, <hi
          rend="italic">the Scales</hi> and <hi rend="italic">the Meaſures</hi> to deli- <lb/>ver
        carefully all the quantities you want, to prevent your <lb/>being often expos'd, often
        kill'd (as the College proves in <lb/>many Particulars) by the <hi rend="italic">obvious
          Errors of the wanton idle <lb/>Boys</hi>. Was ever Madneſs thus violent and fatal as
        Yours? <lb/>How long a Liſt of the <hi rend="italic">Squires</hi> can you make, who ſend
        <lb/>for the <hi rend="italic">Vintner</hi> to the Parlour, make him fill and meaſure
        <lb/>each Glaſs, order the Numbers they ſhall take off, and <lb/>make the Reckoning of ſo
        many Draughts at his own <lb/>Pleaſure and Occaſions? Are you acquainted with the <pb n="16"/>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Changelings</hi>, who deſire the <hi rend="italic">Baker</hi> and the
          <hi rend="italic">Poulterer</hi> to <lb/>carve and ſend in the Parcels they have deſign'd
        for every <lb/>Member of the Houſe? There are <hi rend="italic">Nurſes not blind and
          <lb/>decrepit</hi>, who can give the <hi rend="italic">Glyſters</hi>, and <hi
          rend="italic">dreſs the Bliſters</hi>, <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">apply the Melilote</hi>,
        your Friends and Servants to at- <lb/>tend. You have a Phyſician not far from you, examin'd
        <lb/>and allow'd by the Government, as the <hi rend="italic">Judge on the Cir- <lb/>cuit, or
          your Miniſter</hi>, who makes all the neceſſary Ob- <lb/>ſervations, attends in all the
        neceſſary Caſes, and appoints <lb/>the Diviſions and Mixtures, and the juſt Seaſons of admi-
        <lb/>niſtring the Medicines. Will the Apothecary diſcourſe <lb/>more copiouſly, of the moſt
        abſtruſe Cauſes and diffe- <lb/>rences of Diſeaſes, of the Reaſons and Progreſs of all the
        <lb/>Symptoms, on all the Energies of every Remedy, and if <lb/>he is buſy in another Place,
        fend his Journeyman or any <lb/>one of his Prentices to diſcourſe on the Affairs, nor you
        <lb/>nor they can underſtand? A notable <hi rend="italic">Writer on their ſide</hi>
        <lb/>aſſerts his own great Skill, and not of many more, but <lb/>proteſts, That <hi
          rend="italic">the Maſter and Wardens of the Company</hi> are <lb/>not able, and are not to
        be truſted with the Examination <lb/>of ſuch Abilities as theſe. The Man and his Lads
        furniſh <lb/>the Prattle, do all the <hi rend="italic">Drudgeries</hi> for the <hi
          rend="italic">Nurſes</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Foot- <lb/>men</hi>, bring the Doſes, and
        run on the Errands, and pre- <lb/>ſent them with Cordials and Gratuities, when in Health,
        <lb/>and abundance of them, when they complain. The <hi rend="italic">Go- <lb/>vernour of
          the Houſe muſt be thruſt from the Chamber, and <lb/>the Concerns of the Life and Expence,
          is allow'd no freedom of <lb/>Speech, or Vote in the Choice of the Phyſician or
          Conſultation</hi>. <lb/>When the Rout is begun, and the Ship is ſinking, we will <lb/>have
        the beſt General and Pilot of his Appointment. <hi rend="italic">Tho' <lb/>that Life is
          beſt, he ſhall inform the Apothecary the Methods <lb/>and Medicines to ſave the next in
          courſe</hi>. I aſſert, that he <lb/>muſt not, will not, is not able to inſtruct the
        Invader of <lb/>his Profeſſion. Do you know any <hi rend="italic">Art or Trade</hi> which is
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Felo de ſe</hi>? And the General imploy'd only in Rallying <lb/>the
        runaway Troops, can never project or make a glori- <lb/>ous Campaign: Your Phyſician is a
        Stranger to the great <pb n="17"/>
        <lb/>Deſign of repelling the Diſeaſes at the Beginning, and of <lb/>aſſiſting Nature then in
        its greateſt vigour; does he know <lb/>the Remedies then Neceſſary? No; he rarely or never
        <lb/>uſes them. But he will communicate what he knows. <lb/>No; he muſt raiſe ſo much out of
        the Diſeaſe for the <lb/>Ruler of the Affair, who will not prepare with the ex-
        <lb/>traordinary trouble the appropriate Remedy, when the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
        >Waters</hi>, &amp;c. lie always ready in the <hi rend="italic">Shop</hi> to be mixt up,
        <lb/>and divided in an inſtant; and if our <hi rend="italic">Specifick Medicine</hi> de-
        <lb/>monſtrates the juſt Application and its Efficacy, the Diſ- <lb/>eaſe ſhall vaniſh, <hi
          rend="italic">before the tenth part of the Sum is rais'd</hi>. <lb/>This is the Duty and
        Employment of the Phyſician and <lb/>Surgeon prefer'd, as now in all your Houſes, to the
        Ser- <lb/>vice. And when the Apothecaries ſhall by their two or <lb/>three Prentices have
        Eight or Ten Habitations only from <lb/>one Shop to another, they muſt then, as uſually at
        this <lb/>time, finiſh as well as begin, and to advance their Repu- <lb/>tation, and the
        Peoples ſureſt Confidence in them, bring <lb/>in to commend, extoll, and ſet them off, the
        moſt pre- <lb/>par'd Knaves and Blockheads of them both. What will <lb/>you think of that
        ſort of Phyſicians and Surgeons, the <lb/>Men of no Religion or Manners, who ply the
        Gentlemen <lb/>of perpetual Surfeits and their other uſual Diſorders, who <lb/>by their
        Banter and Atheiſtical Impudence extinguiſh in <lb/>them all Sence of Honour and Concern ſor
        the Publick <lb/>Welfare, uſe them as their Engines of Noiſe and Violence <lb/>to deſtroy
        the College and the Company, which can only <lb/>(as <hi rend="italic">Merchants in
          Conſort</hi>, as <hi rend="italic">Councils of Courts and Armies</hi>) <lb/>raiſe the
        Improvements and Fidelity of the two Profeſſions, <lb/>and prompt the Madmen to cry them up,
        the only great <lb/>and all-ſufficient Phyſicians and Surgeons, againſt the <lb/>ſtrongeſt
        Evidences of their Reaſon and Senſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I ſaw Floods of Tears guſh from the Eyes of many of <lb/>my Friends, which oblig'd me
        to relieve their Trouble <lb/>and mollify their Pain. <hi rend="italic">You may be happy, as
          ſoon as you <lb/>pleaſe </hi>. I will preſent you with the greateſt Wiſdom Mor- <lb/>tal Man can
        aſpire to, the moſt profitable Invention, its <pb n="18"/>
        <lb/>Produce is equal to the Silver Mines; all our Forefathers <lb/>were Maſters of it, we
        have loſt it by the Fooliſh Purſuits <lb/>of Luxury and Pleaſure, and ſuffered our
        Inheritance of <lb/>Underſtanding to lie neglected and waſt. Entertain your <lb/>Phyſicians
        and Surgeons, as the Kings do, in your reſpe- <lb/>ctive Proportions. You will then engage
        and ſubdue <lb/>them by the irreſiſtible Powers of their own Intereſt to ren- <lb/>der you
        ten Thouſand Services more than I can enume- <lb/>rate. Suppoſe your only Son is ſeiz'd with
        a Fever, your <lb/>Phyſician then muſt by all the Viſits, to apprehend all the <lb/>moſt
        Minute and moſt Important Obſervations, by his <lb/>vigilancy to lay hold on all the
        occaſions, by his inceſſant <lb/>Peruſal of his Authors and his Practice, by his Judgment
        <lb/>more elaborated from the private Councils of the moſt <lb/>Eminent Phyſicians he will
        addreſs to, conclude the Cure, <lb/>if poſſible, in 3, 4, or 5 days, which Millions of
        Events <lb/>atteſt, and not permit the Diſeaſe to eſcape him, and run <lb/>off to 15, 20
        days, and acquire daily more violence and <lb/>danger. Will not your Surgeon's Intereſt
        oblige him to <lb/>the ſame faithful Treatment of all the Tumours and <lb/>Wounds? They will
        both inſtruct you in the Rates and <lb/>Diviſions of all the <hi rend="italic">Juleps</hi>,
          <hi rend="italic">Powders</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Confections</hi>, and <hi rend="italic"
          >in <lb/>every Caſe ſave you a Summ more bulky and affrighting than <lb/>the Salary</hi>.
        But I crave your ſharpeſt Attention, they will <lb/>by their Intereſt be neceſſitated to
        teach and inform you <lb/>in the Uſes and Applications of all the Medicines, that <lb/>you
        may wiſely and ſafely tamper with all the vulgar <lb/>Diſorders of the Family, and the moſt
        Divine Charity the <lb/>Relief of your poor Neighbours with your Council, and the
        <lb/>Medicines at no coſt, which now deſtroy and undo them. <lb/>VVhen the Caſe is more
        difficult, it is your Intereſt to re- <lb/>commend your Phyſician and Surgeon to all the
        opportu- <lb/>nities which ſhall increaſe their Knowledge and Experience. <lb/>How ſecure
        will you make your ſelves, fortify your Minds <lb/>with the ſtrongeſt Confidence of Succeſs,
        when you know <lb/>he has cur'd 500 of the Diſeaſe, which has ſurpriz'd you? <lb/>You muſt
        not object, that you muſt have a burniſht Phy- <pb n="19"/>
        <lb/>ſician, as Dr. <hi rend="italic">R.</hi> or an impudent all-aſſuming Surgeon, as
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">C. B.</hi> Your Phyſicians Learning ſhall not be <hi rend="italic"
          >gliſtring Tin- <lb/>ſel</hi>, as Dr. <hi rend="italic">R.</hi> but have all the <hi
          rend="italic">weight and richneſs</hi> of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Metal</hi>. If all
        our Knowledge is ſeeing the differences of <lb/>Diſeaſes, of their Symptoms and the Event
        after the uſe of <lb/>the Remedies, the vain Pretenders may have more Wit <lb/>and artful
        Negligence: But yours will have more Art and <lb/>Succeſs in proportion to the Numbers of
        his Patients near <lb/>him, and the careſul Journals he has enter'd of the Courſe <lb/>of
        their Voyage. This copious and aſſiduous Practice <lb/>will make your Phyſician warranted to
        you from the <lb/>ſtricteſt Education and Examination at the College, an <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Hippocrates</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Galen</hi>, and <hi rend="italic"
          >Sydenham</hi>, furniſh'd with the <lb/>two <hi rend="italic">neceſſary Parts of the
          Mixture, Integrity and Science</hi>. As <lb/>the Princes and People fearfully depend in a
        dubious War, <lb/>on the Art and Courage of the Generals and Admirals, all <lb/>the Crown'd
        Heads, and the Knees of the Subjects pro- <lb/>ſtrate themſelves, do and muſt bow down and
        bend to the <lb/>two Profeſſions, when under the Terrour of inſulting Di- <lb/>ſeaſes. The
        greateſt Honours and Regards engage the <lb/>proportion'd Zeal and Affection. They are
        aſſaulted and <lb/>worried in no part of the Univerſe, as by the deluded, <lb/>unthinking
          <hi rend="italic">Engliſh</hi>. The Rabble only judge the Merits <lb/>of the Victory; the
          <hi rend="italic">Aged, the Wiſe and obſerving Gentry <lb/>are loſt, or dare not appear,
          and humbly offer their Judg- <lb/>ment</hi>. The Apothecary, as the Midwife, is call'd to
        all <lb/>the innumerable ſafe and natural Labours of the Diſtem- <lb/>pers, he only
          <unclear>ſaves</unclear> all the Mothers and Children; but the <lb/>Artiſt ſent for in the
        inſuperable Difficulties is condemn'd, <lb/>they ply their Engines and Waters at all the
        Outcries <lb/>of Fires breaking forth, the other has nothing left to at- <lb/>tempt, but
        blowing up, and laying the Houſes in an <lb/>Heap of Ruines. The Rabble are accuſtom'd to
        the Numb- <lb/>ers of Doſes and irrational caſting them into, and againſt the <lb/>Diſeaſe.
        The Phyſician is accus'd of the Death of the Pa- <lb/>tient, if he pretends, by Reaſon, and
        the Cautions of ruf- <lb/>fling the natural Motions by the numberleſs Remedies, <pb n="20"/>
        <lb/>to ſeize the juſt Informations, and prevent the fatal Effect <lb/>of any one violently
        oppoſing the natural Deſigns of the <lb/>Recovery. But, as the Mob are for fighting
        inſtantly, <lb/>and are well contented, tho' they are beaten, if a great <lb/>many are
        killed, our wretched People judge only by the <lb/>boiſterous Management, with the vaſt
        Exceſs of the Ran- <lb/>dom Shots of the Medicines. If one preſumes to give the <lb/>firſt
        and the richeſt Cordial, the Proſpect of certain Re- <lb/>coveries, will you dare go on as
        you begin, let Nature <lb/>recover it ſelf. Dr. <hi rend="italic">R.</hi> and the bluſtering
        Surgeon, take <lb/>away all the hope of Recovery at firſt ſight. They ſwear <lb/>and damn
        they ſhall die, and ſome do ſo; but when one <lb/>does well, we magnifie the Cure, and are
        infinitely pleas'd <lb/>with the moſt hazardous Eſcape. Thus every <hi rend="italic"
          >Fever</hi> and <lb/><hi rend="italic">Small Pox</hi>, tho' the Kind, reigning then, may
        be ſafe, muſt <lb/>have every two Hours, <hi rend="italic">ſuch a Quantity of Boles and
          <lb/>Draughts, &amp;c.</hi> as the Apothecaries will have made the <lb/>Faſhion, tho' we
        ſee in a thouſand Inſtances, many have <lb/>their Healths reſtor'd by ten times fewer. The
        People <lb/>will not ſee the Dangers they were preſerv'd from, when <lb/>an equal Proportion
        remains on the Table. You ſhall <lb/>hear them lament, that tho' ſeven of the Houſe got over
        <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Small-Pox</hi> by the honeſt Treatment, they loſt one dear
        <lb/>Child, they fear had not all the Remedies could be taken. <lb/>The judicious Phyſician
        muſt grievouſly ſuffer, and the <lb/>poor Patients with him, when <hi rend="italic">profuſe
          and frequent Bleedings</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">the rudeſt Vomits</hi>, <hi
          rend="italic">Cupping</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Scarifying</hi>, and <hi rend="italic"
          >much Bliſte- <lb/>ring, and bloody Water and Pain ſhall give the grand Reputa-
          <lb/>tion</hi>, as the Vulgar cry up <hi rend="italic">Surgeons from cutting off a Limb,
          <lb/>gaſhing, and letting out of a deal of Matter, and trepanning <lb/>the Skull</hi>. I
        have lately been aſſur'd by ſeveral Phyſicians, <lb/>that no Credit can be acquir'd by
        ſaving the Life of a Pa- <lb/>tient, by preventing the deadly Symptoms, by conducting
        <lb/>and ſupporting the natural Powers. The healthy Enter- <lb/>tainment and Feaſt is
        rejected, and the Luxury and De- <lb/>bauchery are the Demonſtration of much Reſpect and Af-
        <lb/>fection: tho' the Stomach and the Head terribly ſuffer, <pb n="21"/>
        <lb/>and a dreadful Fever follows the Surfeit. The Phyſicians <lb/>have compell'd me to
        believe them, that their Fame was <lb/>uſually advanc'd after the Patients had fall'n by the
        Load <lb/>of ungrateful oppreſſive Doſes, the World never knew be- <lb/>fore: That they
        lamented from their Souls, the Calami- <lb/>ties of the Sick, when the Dr. is every day
        driven on by <lb/>the Apothecary, add vehemently drag'd forward by the <lb/>Attendants to
        oppoſe the Life, by the half Sheet of Pre- <lb/>ſcriptions in every Viſit of many Doſes, and
        to be pleas'd <lb/>when the next Day they remain from the Sleep interve- <lb/>ning, or the
        fortunate Averſion of the Patient. When we <lb/>do not comply with the Importunities for the
        ſuperfluous <lb/>Remedies, we muſt trick the fooliſh People, with the <hi rend="italic">odd
          <lb/>ſilly Advices of an Iſſue on the top of the Head, or a Seton, or <lb/>going to <hi
            rend="roman">Bath</hi> or <hi rend="roman">Turnbridge</hi>, what ever the Diſeaſe
          is</hi>, when <lb/>there are very many may be uſed to better purpoſe than <lb/>two Waters
        only. Shou'd you at any time diſcover one <lb/>of the many Deaths, that you loſt your Son by
        the exceſ- <lb/>ſive Doſing, or a little impertinent Whimſey of diſtin- <lb/>guiſhing
        Advice, and cry out for Juſtice on the Murthe- <lb/>rers; you muſt be reprimanded, that you
        do not conſult <lb/>the ancient Gentlemen of the oldeſt and wiſeſt Obſerva- <lb/>tions, that
        you cannot ſee with your own Eyes, that <lb/>Millions of Children have ſaved themſelves by
        the fierce <lb/>Cries, and beating off, and ſpattering out the Boles; that <lb/>thouſands of
        old Men and Women had protected their <lb/>Life to the longeſt Periods, by the Chamber, and
        Abſti- <lb/>nence, and the Dread of too many Medicines. But you <lb/>muſt, with all your
        Power, maintain the Honour and <lb/>Diſcipline of the College, which can only, by the mutual
        <lb/>Improvements of the learned and faithful Practice, give <lb/>you the great Standards to
        judge by. You muſt uſe your <lb/>Reaſon, the Methods the Government has given you, and
        <lb/>not cry out to be help'd, like the careleſs Child, who <lb/>will be taken up, when he
        might have kept his Legs, if <lb/>he pleas'd. If the <hi rend="italic">Mirmils</hi>, <hi
          rend="italic">Querpoes</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Bards</hi>, and the <hi rend="italic">Up-
          <lb/>ſtarts</hi>, have carried the Patrons daily Earnings of two or <pb n="22"/>
        <lb/>three Guineas a Day, too far in moſt of the Diſeaſes, and <lb/>you can prove the Sick
        were grievouſly injur'd, or dy'd by <lb/>the modern and growing Practice, you muſt appeal to
        the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Cenſors of the College, who have publiſh'd them as Homicides
          <lb/>and Villans</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>All the Company call'd aloud, we will oppoſe the Apo- <lb/>thecaries, the Origine of
        all our Sufferings, and not pay <lb/>the Bill of two or three Guineas a day, which we can
        <lb/>have in the Quantities for two or three Shillings. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I anſwer'd them, you will expoſe your Folly, and the <lb/>Apothecary ſhall come off
        victorious in the Tryal; he <lb/>ſhall have his Bill juſtified, tho' he ſets down many Pow-
        <lb/>ders daily not worth two Farthings, at 4 <hi rend="italic">s.</hi> and 6 <hi
          rend="italic">d.</hi> and <lb/>ſhall have the Coſt of the Suit. The Court and the Jury
        <lb/>ſhall denounce your Sentence; we will never examine <lb/>the Merit, the Value of any
        Doſe. You ſhall be cheated <lb/>and undone. Is the Bill 30 <hi rend="italic">l.</hi> in one
        Fever? It ſhall <lb/>paſs, were it 300 <hi rend="italic">l.</hi> Is it 200 <hi rend="italic"
          >l.</hi> for a Clap? You ſhould <lb/>pay it, were it 2000<hi rend="italic">l.</hi> If moſt
        of the Boles and Draughts <lb/>after them, we know are all worth but 2 <hi rend="italic"
          >d.</hi> rated now to <lb/>you at 5 <hi rend="italic">s.</hi> were ſet down at 5 <hi
          rend="italic">l.</hi> at 50 <hi rend="italic">l.</hi> you ſhou'd be <lb/>forc'd to pay it;
        which, as their Numbers and their <lb/>Wants improve, they will ſwear is the common Reck-
        <lb/>oning for them. Do you trouble the Court in a revenge- <lb/>ful Proſecution, that all
        the Money you can ſpare for <lb/>your Health and Life, is wreſted and taken from you by
        <lb/>the Apothecary? The Government has appointed, that <lb/>all theſe Medicines, prepar'd
        in the Shop, ſhall be bought <lb/>in Quantities at the ſmalleſt Values, to be eaſily mix'd
        and <lb/>divided by you. Why do you uſe any Phyſicians, that <lb/>are not honeſt and juſt to
        you, do not inform you of the <lb/>Proviſion of all the Neceſſaries of Life, your Property,
        <lb/>and the obvious Skill of adapting them to the frequent <lb/>Occaſions? Are you Fools to
        be govern'd by the Apo- <lb/>thecary? Are you Fools to ſuffer him to defraud your
        <lb/>Phyſician? You ſhall be whipt with the Rods you <lb/>prepare. Begone from the Court,
        and report to all you <pb n="23"/>
        <lb/>know the Decree we make, that we will not be the Col- <lb/>lege Beadles. The Law has
        impower'd them to reſtrain the <lb/>Apothecaries from Quacking our of their Shops, and can,
        <lb/>if you pleaſe to ſupport it, deter and puniſh their Mem- <lb/>bers, and prevent the
        Exactions and Deſtruction of a <lb/>wanton Nation, proud of their Laws and Liberties they
        <lb/>are always breaking. I ſuppoſe they had the diſmal Re- <lb/>membrance of the vaſt
        Yearly Payments, of the Death of <lb/>their Children, of the Defeats in the Tryals with the
        Apo- <lb/>thecaries; I heard the Shrieks, and Groans, and Gnaſh- <lb/>ing of Teeth, as in
        the <hi rend="italic">Old Baily</hi>, when the Sentence is <lb/>pronounc'd to the Barr full
        of Criminals. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I muſt confeſs to you, I ſympathiz'd with them. But <lb/>all was calm and ſerene in a
        Moment, after I had aſſur'd <lb/>them, that the miſerable <hi rend="italic">Engliſh</hi>
        ſhould not fall, as in the <lb/>ſacred Hiſtory, into the Hands of Thieves, be ſtript and
        <lb/>wounded to death by them. The Prieſt and the Magi- <lb/>ſtrate ſhall not paſs by on the
        other ſide, regardleſs of <lb/>their Calamities. You ſhall be reſtor'd to your Proper-
        <lb/>ty, the Knowledge of the Prices and Uſes of all the pub- <lb/>lick Remedies the
        Government has preſented to you. <lb/>The Phyſicians and Surgeons ſhall not be ignorant, as
        <lb/>now, if they are honeſtly or treacherouſly prepar'd, and <lb/>paſs, as it may happen,
        the vileſt Medicine on the Sick, <lb/>when the Life depends, in the Juncture of many Circum-
        <lb/>ſtances, on the Doſe. They ſhall be compell'd to learn <lb/>the great Variety of the
        Simples, and not, as now, delude <lb/>and deſtroy, with 30 or 40 of the general Remedies
        only. <lb/>They ſhall not dare to confound theſe together in an uſe- <lb/>leſs Maſs, then to
        be broken into little Doſes, to blind <lb/>our Knowledge of the Values, and expoſe our Life.
        They <lb/>ſhall not, with the moſt abhor'd Perjury, aſſault their <lb/>own Societies, and
        deliver to the Apothecary's Ignorance, <lb/>all the Caſes which can only nouriſh and
        increaſe their <lb/>Knowledge, and by the Communications, the Stock of <lb/><choice>
          <corr>Science</corr>
          <sic>Sience</sic>
        </choice> of the two Profeſſions. The Sick formerly were <lb/>expos'd in the Temples, and
        the Porches of their Houſes, <pb n="24"/>
        <lb/>to the Views and Advice of all the Spectators, we are en- <lb/>compaſs'd only with the
        Impoſtures of the Apothecaries, <lb/>the moſt wicked Phyſicians and Surgeons, without the
        <lb/>Knowledge of the Goodneſs and Virtues of the Medicines, <lb/>or the different
        Circumſtances of our Diſeaſes. We will <lb/>implore the <hi rend="italic">Lords Spiritual
          and Temporal</hi>, to addreſs to the <lb/>Fountain of Juſtice for the Viſitation of them,
        and the moſt <lb/>ſevere Inſpection into the State of the Nation, the Health <lb/>and Life
        of the Subjects. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I was almoſt deter'd from the Purſuit of my Deſign, <lb/>fearing the Nobility and
        Gentry would not receive the In- <lb/>formation, and the common People boyſterouſly rage,
        <lb/>when aſſur'd, that their eminent Phyſicians and Surgeons, <lb/>are only the Setters and
        Sweetners for the Apothecaries to <lb/>pilfer them, that they have not the Learning and
        Abili- <lb/>ties which will preſerve them in any one very dangerous <lb/>Diſeaſe. But then,
        the College aſſerts both in many parts <lb/>of their Remonſtrances, and our moſt Religious
        and <lb/>moſt Learned K. <hi rend="italic">Charles</hi> I. and the Lords of this Council,
        <lb/>and all the Judges of <hi rend="italic">England</hi>, did moſt ſolemnly avow,
        <lb/>that, without the one Soverein Remedy, the Profeſſion <lb/>muſt be more and more
        corrupted to the Conſumption of <lb/>all its Virtue and Knowledge. You have try'd many Me-
        <lb/>dicines without Succeſs. Your College, and the Surge- <lb/>ons Company, muſt humbly
        addreſs to her Majeſty, who <lb/>derives all the Royal Virtues from your great Patron,
        <lb/>K. <hi rend="italic">Charles</hi> I. You will excuſe me, when I urge the Ne-
        <lb/>ceſſity of ſaving your Societies, and the Life of the Pub- <lb/>lick, by the Addreſs to
        her Majeſty in Council, from the <lb/>moſt weighty and irrefragable Reaſons the College Diſ-
        <lb/>courſes have abundantly furniſh'd me with. All the <hi rend="italic">Eng-
          <lb/>liſh</hi> Gentlemen will excuſe my Confidence, my Pre- <lb/>ſumption, when I <choice>
          <corr>aſſert</corr>
          <sic>aſlert</sic>
        </choice>, that you cannot be refus'd, that <lb/>the College and Company ſhall be reſtor'd
        to their <lb/>Dignity and Power of relieving the moſt oppreſt Peo- <lb/>ple. That the Decree
        muſt be the ſame, which was made <lb/>by that moſt Religious, and moſt Learned Prince. I <pb
          n="25"/>
        <lb/>ſcorn, and defie all the Objections the deluded <hi rend="italic">Engliſh</hi>
        <lb/>Gentlemen can invent. Are they more wiſe than the <lb/>King? Have they more Honour than
        the Lords of the <lb/>Council in that Reign? Is not the moſt profound Learn- <lb/>ing of the
        Judges, at that time, admir'd in this? To come <lb/>cloſe to my Adverſaries, your College
        demonſtrated, that <lb/>the Profeſſion of Phyſick muſt be deſtroy'd, when the
        <lb/>Apothecaries are ſuffer'd to intrude into the Chambers of <lb/>the Sick, leaving their
        Station and Duties of preparing, <lb/>and carefully delivering the Medicines in the Shop,
        hav- <lb/>ing no Reward, but what they contrive out of the Multi- <lb/>tude and Dearneſs of
        the Doſes. Their Numbers force them <lb/>to ſuggeſt all the Forgeries imaginable, to cry up
        that <lb/>ſort of Phyſicians, who ſhall fatally deceive the People, <lb/>ſupport their moſt
        abſurd and pernicious Advices, and <lb/>juſtifie and improve the Proſit from the many and
        dear <lb/>Medicines. They muſt cry down the other ſort, who ſhall <lb/>caution them for the
        future, againſt the unexamin'd, il- <lb/>literate Pretenders, and maintain the Property of
        the Uſe <lb/>of the publick Remedies, and preſerve their Knowledge of <lb/>the ſmall Prices
        of the moſt generous Medicines. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>His Majeſty and the Council, allow'd the cleareſt and <lb/>the greateſt Truth. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>You then proceed to avow, that it is the greateſt Folly, <lb/>that God has not
        afflicted Mankind with the Permiſſion of <lb/>any more deadly Infatuation,. than to take an
        Apotheca- <lb/>ries Judgment, in the tender or furious Begining of Di- <lb/>ſeaſes, whoſe
        Capacity was never examin'd, to force <lb/>him to pay himſelf what he pleaſes, 1, 2, 3 <hi
          rend="italic">l.</hi> a Day, by <lb/>the Number of the Doſes, and the fraudulent Prices,
        when <lb/>all the Parts of the Univerſe have obſerv'd, that many ſe- <lb/>vere Diſeaſes paſs
        off by the Strength of Nature, aſſiſted <lb/>or not diſorder'd, and that the largeſt Part of
        the Medi- <lb/>cines of our own Growth, are, and muſt be of the loweſt <lb/>Rates. But that
        the unhappy People will eaſily be im- <lb/>pos'd on by the Impoſtures of no Efficacies in
        the moſt <lb/>plentiful, of the few pretended to be dear, being mix'd <pb n="26"/>
        <lb/>in every thing they ſhall take, eſpecially when the per- <lb/>jur'd Phyſicians are
        ready to vouch all the Articles of the <lb/>Forgery. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Your College then, with a Generoſity never to be pa- <lb/>rallel'd, confeſs'd, that the
        Phyſicians Knowledge of Di- <lb/>ſeaſes was almoſt loſt; that by treacherouſly commending
        <lb/>every Practice of the Apothecaries, they were by degrees, <lb/>more and more neglected;
        that the Diſeaſe is broken from <lb/>the natural Types every day, by the improper and hourly
        <lb/>intruded Remedies, that preſcribing in that Confuſion of <lb/>the genuine and unnatural
        Symptoms, they can never <lb/>judge of the Diſeaſe: That their Violations of the Laws of
        <lb/>Phyſick muſt deſtroy all the Patients, unleſs the natural <lb/>Vigour is able to oppoſe
        them, and perform the Cure. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Phyſicians muſt loſe all the Knowledge of Me- <lb/>dicines, not able to diſcern the
        beſt from the moſt So- <lb/>phiſticate, not commend or reject the Uſe of them in <lb/>the
        moſt hazardous Caſes, and not diſtinguiſh the true <lb/>Qualites and Virtues, or judge of
        the Operations, when <lb/>they conſpire with the Apothecaries to blend together, <lb/>with
        the moſt fatal Inhumanity to the Sick, the perfect, <lb/>complete Remedies, deſign'd to be
        us'd in their full <lb/>Power, unmix'd. The Confuſion of them confounds and <lb/>breaks the
        Efficacy to be rely'd on. This muſt be <lb/>the great Art and Myſtery of the Practice to
        kill and ob- <lb/>literate the Peoples Diſcernment of their Prices, and their
        <lb/>Application of them in the more eaſie and frequent Di- <lb/>ſtempers. The Apothecaries
        will inſult the Phyſician's <lb/>Ignorance, will affront them, if they pry into the Secrets
        <lb/>of the Shop, and obſerve the ſingle unmix'd Medicines <lb/>there, will reject the
        Preſcription, which ſhall give the <lb/>unuſual Trouble of Preparation, in the place of the
        Vul- <lb/>gar, always ready to be clapt together, will command the <lb/>Phyſicians, fearing
        their Diſpleaſure, never to examine a- <lb/>ny Qualities or Virtues of any Simple, or
        contrive any <lb/>more rational Preparation, or bring to the Teſt, any for- <lb/>merly or
        lately publiſh'd. They will demand in all the <pb n="27"/>
        <lb/>Houſes they govern, their faithful Aſſurance, that they <lb/>will decry all the
        Improvements of the Learning in Me- <lb/>dicines in the publick Laboratory of the College or
        their <lb/>own, and report it Scandalous to reflect, what Medicines <lb/>their Patients
        ſhall take. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When the Phyſicians of more cultivated Learning and <lb/>Experience, ſhall with
        Reluctance betray their Patients, <lb/>the Apothecaries will ſelect the poor and
        neceſſitous, and <lb/>daring Impudence of the Novices, who have not had <lb/>the
        Obſervations of Diſeaſes or Remedies to compare and <lb/>form a jaſt Judgment of. Theſe muſt
        unite and blaſt <lb/>the Phyſicians of long Practice and Diſcernment of <lb/>the Succeſſes
        of the various Methods of Cure, whoſe In- <lb/>ſtructions and Cautions can only educate and
        raiſe to <lb/>Perfection the Crude Attempts of the Practice lately <lb/>begun. They ſhall
        never or after the Deſtruction of <lb/>many of the Sick begin to correct their Errors, and
        fear <lb/>there may be more rational ways of treating the Diſ- <lb/>eaſes and better
        Medicines to be employ'd. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>His Majeſty, and the Lords of the Council, and the <lb/>Judges were pleas'd to allow
        the moſt neceſſary Conſe- <lb/>quences in the Art of Phyſick, and in all other Profeſſions,
        <lb/>and therefore determin'd to diſſolve the Apothecaries <lb/>Company, to appoint the
        competent Number in the <lb/>City. The Application was prevented by the Rebellion
        <lb/>breaking forth ſoon after. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Your College generouſly imitates your Learned and pub- <lb/>lick Spirited Predeceſſors:
        You have preſented to the No- <lb/>bility and Gentry the boldeſt Diſcovery of the Ignorance
        <lb/>of the Phyſicians in all the Diſeaſes and Medicines. You <lb/>aſſert that <hi
          rend="italic">the great Enquiries are no more</hi>, and by a large <lb/>variety in the
        firſt and laſt Pages you endeavour to <lb/>convince them, <hi rend="italic">that the
          Profeſſion</hi> (and the Surgeons cannot <lb/>be ſecluded,) <hi rend="italic">has no
          Honour or Conſcience, no Deſign or In- <lb/>duſtry, or Ability to procure Health and
          Life</hi>. It will be <lb/>unpreſidented to admit Dr. <hi rend="italic">R.</hi>
        <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> to enter their Proteſta- <pb n="28"/>
        <lb/>tion, when the Majority of the Society has included them<unclear>,</unclear>
        <lb/>and they can plead no Cauſe of Exception. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I know our Gentlemen are proud of their Wit and Im- <lb/>provements from Converſation,
        and fancy that Divinity, <lb/>Law and Phyſick are learned by Rote and by the Ear, and
        <lb/>in good Company. Becauſe ſome uſeful, many very ri- <lb/>diculous Inventions have
        entertain'd the Age, they ima- <lb/>gine, that it excells all the preceding times. All
        before <lb/>us were nothing to us. The <hi rend="italic">French</hi>, they ſay, conquer'd
        <lb/>the Iſland in the Reign of our King <hi rend="italic">Henry</hi>, V. the <hi
          rend="italic">Spani- <lb/>ards</hi> ſubdued us in 88, that the Reformers of our Reli- <lb/><choice>
          <corr>gion</corr>
          <sic>on</sic>
        </choice> had no Learning, that the Judges and the Lawyers <lb/>were not regarded, that they
        had then no Phyſick: That <lb/>we are wiſer than all the World beſide, and have more
        <lb/>Courage and Bravery, that they would conquer the <hi rend="italic">French</hi>
        <lb/>ſooner, without any Allies. Tho' our preſent Phyſici- <lb/>ans are not inſtructed by
        the Profeſſors in the Univerſity, <lb/>nor by any one ever after at all wiſer than
        themſelves, tho' <lb/>they pretend to little Study and Diligence, value them- <lb/>ſelves on
        the general Learning, preliminary only to, and ne- <lb/>ceſſary to enter all the
        Profeſſions, or are very elaborate <lb/>in Trifles nothing to their Purpoſe, they aſſume a
        Cha- <lb/>racter they have no Pretence to, a Grandeur and Luſtre <lb/>to cover the Crimes,
        of which you accuſe them. I am <lb/>therefore oblig'd to deduce the Hiſtory of Phyſick from
        <lb/>its Original, out of your Books, and the Comments on <lb/>them to the almoſt total
        Corruption and Death of it in <lb/>our Age. The Records are authentick, your Obſervati-
        <lb/>ons moſt juſt, that the noiſy Admirers of the Modern Ac- <lb/>compliſhments ſhall be
        forc'd to confeſs their Folly and <lb/>repair the Weakneſs of their Underſtanding. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The firſt Labours and Induſtry of Mankind were ex- <lb/>ercis'd in diſcovering the
        Fruits, and Grains, and Fountains, <lb/>the grateful and preſent Remedies of Hunger and
        Thirſt, <lb/>then in diſcovering the Caverns of Rocks, and building, <lb/>in imitation of
        them, their Securities and Defences from the <lb/>Cold and the Ravages of the Beaſts of
        Prey, till they <pb n="29"/>
        <lb/>had learnt from them to aſſault and deſtroy their own kind. <lb/>The firſt Surfeits and
        Pains, and Fevers, Bruiſes and <lb/>wounds, rais'd their moſt eager Affections to relieve,
        and <lb/>the moſt unwearied Solicitudes to find the Medicines, which <lb/>ſhould be able in
        the parallel Dangers to preſerve them- <lb/>ſelves. The Plants they had taſted in their
        ſearches after <lb/>Food, and had rejected from their Qualities and Vertues <lb/>more
        powerfully affecting the Palate and the Stomach, <lb/>were inſtantly demanded and apply'd.
        The natural Cra- <lb/>vings and Inſtincts of the Patients were heard and regar- <lb/>ded,
        the Averſions and Antipathies were moſt warily ob- <lb/>ſerv'd and recorded. The
        obſervations of the various Suc- <lb/>ceſſes were made in the view and Inqueſt of all the
        little <lb/>Communities, and preſerved for the uſe of Poſterity. <lb/>When the ſmall
        Governments increaſt and multiply'd to <lb/>Kingdoms and Empires, the Medical Knowledge of
        pre- <lb/>venting and curing Diſeaſes was proportionably extended. <lb/>The firſt moſt
        populous Countries were therefore moſt <lb/>famous from the Improvements of Phyſick, before
        all the o- <lb/>ther Arts. <hi rend="italic">Apollo</hi> therefore and <hi rend="italic"
          >Æſculapius</hi> were immor- <lb/>taliz'd as the greateſt Benefactors, from the great
        Improve- <lb/>ments of the Science, which preſerves Life: they were a- <lb/>dor'd in their
        Temples, where all the Healthy and Diſeas'd <lb/>made their daily Sacrifices for their
        Protection and Preſer- <lb/>vation. Many of the other Deities were neglected, there <lb/>was
        no City, where <hi rend="italic">Æſculapius</hi> was not addreſt to for his
        <lb/>Inſpirations and Communications of the moſt Sovereign <lb/>Medicines. This alone was
        the Profeſſion, which engag'd <lb/>the moſt indefatigable Induſtry of all the Princes of
        both <lb/>Sexes, of all the Nobility, of the moſt ſagacious Popula- <lb/>cy, till after many
        Ages, a great Magazine of Obſervati- <lb/>ons of all Diſeaſes, and their moſt prevalent
        Remedies had <lb/>been collected, and the Application committed to the aſ- <lb/>ſiduous
        Practiſers of the Science. Can it be doubted, <lb/>that it was in many Centuries advanc'd to
        the greateſt <lb/>Height and Honours, when the Patients and Obſervations <lb/>innumerable
        had made infinite Records of all things inju- <pb n="30"/>
        <lb/>rious to Health, of the unhappy and moſt proſperous E- <lb/>vents of Millions of
        Attempts in all the different Diſea- <lb/>ſes and their Symptomes. They then had from the
        Di- <lb/>ctates of Nature, the good Sence the <hi rend="italic">Engliſh</hi> have now loſt
        <lb/>and cannot recover, to deſire in the firſt Invaſions of the <lb/>moſt deadly Enemies,
        the moſt celebrated and moſt pre- <lb/>par'd Adviſer? Navigation and Commerce communicated
        <lb/>from the <hi rend="italic">Eaſt</hi> and from <hi rend="italic">Egypt</hi> to the <hi
          rend="italic">Greeks</hi>, the Know- <lb/>ledge of the differences of Diſeaſes, the
        various Methods <lb/>to attempt the Recoveries. <hi rend="italic">Hippocrates</hi> is not
        the firſt Writer <lb/>of Antiquity, he records many before him. There were <lb/>many
        thouſand of Diſcourſes of Diſeaſes, and Medicines <lb/>to furniſh his admirable Collection,
        and the moſt ſublime <lb/>Philoſophy, of the Motions of our Nature, to relieve it <lb/>ſelf
        from the Violences of Diſeaſes, and in the Progreſs of <lb/>them, and of the moſt powerful
        Succours of its Allies, <lb/>the Operations of the Medicines, as many thouſand Poets
        <lb/>flouriſh'd before <hi rend="italic">Homer</hi>, who inflam'd his Emulation to
        <lb/>ſurpaſs them in his Poems, which have never been imi- <lb/>tated or equall'd. The moſt
        neceſſary Art was purſu'd <lb/>with the greateſt Ardour through many Ages, till <hi
          rend="italic">Galen</hi>
        <lb/>in the moſt eloquent and learned Volumes, collected the <lb/>Hiſtories of all the
        Diſeaſes, which can afflict us, and <lb/>almoſt all the Remedies, which are able to repell
        them. <lb/>Our Gentlemen will rave at my Aſſertion, but I aſſert, <lb/>that the Genius of
        Antiquity (when Human Nature was <lb/>rais'd to its greateſt Elevation, when the Governments
        <lb/>were ſecur'd by the moſt equal and wiſeſt Laws, when <lb/>the Courage and Arts of
        Invaſion and Defence, when <lb/>the Buildings of Magnificence and Uſe, the Hiſtories,
        <lb/>Poetry, Oratory, Painting, Statuary and Muſick, and all <lb/>the other Entertainments
        of Life ſurpaſs our juſt Compre- <lb/>henſion, as they explode our pretences to imitations)
        could <lb/>not be wanting or defective in advancing the Profeſſion of <lb/>conquering the
        moſt deadly and ſtubborn Diſeaſes to its <lb/>greateſt Perfection. The Gentlemen, who do not
        under- <lb/>ſtand me, will pelt me with moſt terrible Objections: I <pb n="31"/>
        <lb/>muſt in the firſt place requeſt them to conſider moſt ſe- <lb/>dately and maturely the
        moſt important Affair they have <lb/>ever examin'd and refer them to the moſt inſtructive
        Com- <lb/>ments on your College Publications. There are not many <lb/>Diſtempers, which are
        not largely treated of in the Writings <lb/>of the Antients. But they give the moſt
        neceſſary, the <lb/>infallible Rudiments, the only firm and ſolid Foundations, <lb/>on which
        alone the Superſtructure can be rais'd; all the <lb/>different Symptomes of Diſeaſes our
        Nature can be affli- <lb/>cted with, all their neceſſary Conſequences and Events, <lb/>which
        will paſs off by the Natural Efforts alone, and <lb/>which of them require the moſt tender
        Treatments or the <lb/>moſt vigorous Oppoſitions. As the <hi rend="italic">General</hi> does
        not learn <lb/>to conquer one Enemy and one Army, to beſiege one <lb/>Fortification only:
        Nor the <hi rend="italic">Maſter</hi> to conduct the Ship <lb/>into one Port, and govern it
        in the Storms of one Seaſon <lb/>of the Year. Had they great Plenty of the Medicines?
        <lb/>They were Maſters of the Knowledge of the Qualities <lb/>and Preparations of all the
        Plants the Univerſe produces. <lb/>Is a ſmall Pittance pretended to be lately diſcover'd ?
        How <lb/>vaſt a Number of theirs are known only by their Names? <lb/>their Properties and
        Uſes are now neglected, baniſh'd from <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Engliſh</hi> Enquiries and
        Practice? Our People fooliſhly <lb/>fond of the ſufficiency of the Moderns, will be angry
        <lb/>our Phyſicians ſhall be commanded to conſult <hi rend="italic">Hippocra- <lb/>tes</hi>,
          <hi rend="italic">Diaſcorides</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Galen</hi>. They have poſſeſs'd,
        engroſst all the <lb/>immenſe Wealth of Knowledge in their Treaſury. They <lb/>are the
        Originals and Maſter-pieces, which we muſt copy <lb/>after and labour to imitate.We muſt
        obey the immutable <lb/>Laws of Nature they have publiſh'd, and every Devia- <lb/>tion from
        the moſt perfect is erroneous and abſurd, and <lb/>in the preſent Caſe fatal to Life. They
        were examin'd, <lb/>approv'd, authoriz'd by all the Nations in many ſuccee- <lb/>ding Ages;
        the Diſeas'd muſt dye, if they cannot be pro- <lb/>tected and preſerv'd by them. Shall any
        one conceit, that <lb/>the Preparations of their Medicines were not then the moſt
        <lb/>exquiſite? Did they take care of their Bread and Wine <pb n="32"/>
        <lb/>only? Did they exceed us in all the Incentives of Luxury <lb/>and Debauchery, and
        neglect the moſt potent Preſervers <lb/>and Reſtorers of Life? Their Medicines were prepar'd
        in <lb/>the greateſt degrees of Perfection, not enervated or de- <lb/>baſt by the impudent
        Fallacy to amuſe and defraud the <lb/>Sick, not the colluſive Preſcripts, void of all Virtue
        and <lb/>Efficacy to delude, not the raging and violent, waſting <lb/>and conſuming the
        Blood and Spirits they pretend to ſup- <lb/>port. The Patients had all the natural mixture
        of their <lb/>Powers and Operations in the Subſtance, or in the Extracts, <lb/>or the
        admir'd innumerable Infuſions in their Wines or <lb/>other Liquors. But the Art, as the Life
        it defends, after <lb/>Maturity declines from its Beauty and Vigour. The Am- <lb/>bition,
        Emulation, and rapacious Avarice of Phyſicians <lb/>corrupted it. The Diſeaſes, the moſt
        terrible, had been <lb/>frequently cur'd, and Life extended to the longeſt Pe- <lb/>riods,
        but in Pain, in the dreaded Dangers, the ſolicitude <lb/>for a greater, for a new Medicine,
        more vigorous they <lb/>fancy in the firſt Invention, gave the Honours to all the
        <lb/>Innovations, the giddy Deſertions from, and the impu- <lb/>dent Affronts to all the
        eſtabliſhed and conſtant Succeſſes <lb/>of the general Uſe. The <hi rend="italic"
          >Grecians</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Romans</hi> were aſ- <lb/>ſaulted by barbarous
        Nations, they were prevented by <lb/>their Calamities, from debaſing their Phyſick by the
        im- <lb/>portunate Demands, and therefore indefatigable Purſuits <lb/>of their Phyſicians,
        after the endleſs Novelties of Prepara- <lb/>tions. The Proſperity of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Arabians</hi> unhappily deſtroy'd <lb/>the natural ſincere Practice, the Contagion from
        them <lb/>ſpread into <hi rend="italic">Europe</hi>. Our Age ſuſpects, becauſe the <hi
          rend="italic">Load- <lb/>ſtone</hi> was lately apply'd to direct our Navigation, that
        <lb/>the Ancients had no Ships, or Commerce: becauſe <lb/><hi rend="italic">Printing</hi>
        was not long ſince invented, that they knew <lb/>not the Art of Writing; that they made War
        with <lb/>Clubs and Stones, for want of our Powder and Artil- <lb/>lery. It muſt be
        repeated, as the firſt and greateſt Point <lb/>in the Controverſie, that the <hi
          rend="italic">Eaſtern Nations</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Greci- <lb/>ans</hi> and the <hi
          rend="italic">Romans</hi>, who excell'd the <hi rend="italic">Moderns</hi> in all things
          <pb n="33"/>
        <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Neceſſity</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Grandeur</hi>, has all the
        moſt rational <hi rend="italic">Prepara- <lb/>tions</hi> of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Infuſions</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Decoctions</hi>, all the <hi rend="italic"
          >Extracts</hi>, the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Artifices</hi> of all the <hi rend="italic"
          >Balſams</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Ointments</hi>, eſpecially the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Externals</hi> for all the various Purpoſes; that they were able <lb/>to comprehend the
        two firſt and greateſt Laws of Medi- <lb/>cine, that the Remedy, whoſe Qualities and Virtues
        have <lb/>been examin'd, and confim'd by the Experience of repeated <lb/>Succeſs, muſt be
        given to the Patient without the Load <lb/>and Incumbrance of many Ingredients of uncertain,
        of <lb/>ſuſpected, of contrary Qualities, but only to convey the <lb/>great Specifick more
        pleaſantly to the Palate and Stomach, <lb/>to bribe the one, and fortifie the other, to
        receive the Re- <lb/>medies for the whole Body. The other Inſtance of their <lb/>Wiſdom and
        Fidelity, demands our Gratitude and Imita- <lb/>tion. As the <hi rend="italic">Fruits</hi>
        muſt be eaten before they are dead <lb/>and rotten; <hi rend="italic">Bread</hi>, before it
        is dry and mouldy; <hi rend="italic">Fleſh</hi>, <lb/>without Salt, and dry'd in the Smoak;
        when the newly <lb/>prepar'd is moſt agreeable to the Taſte, and Appetite, and
        <lb/>Digeſtion. In this manner, were the Remedies then ad- <lb/>miniſtred: the great
        Specifick, which governs the Cure, <lb/>(by altering and reducing the obſerv'd vicious
        Intempera- <lb/>tures of the Blood and Spirits) or inſtantly powder'd, late- <lb/>ly
        extracted, infus'd, or decocted, the entire unevapora- <lb/>ted Powers were preſented to the
        Sick. But the hot and <lb/>reſtleſs <hi rend="italic">Arabians</hi>, with the parallel Folly
        of rejecting the <lb/>noble Models of the <hi rend="italic">Grecian</hi> Architecture, 'till
        they know <lb/>the Elements of Marble; the Nature of the Cement, all <lb/>the Qualities of
        the Iron Tools; with the Madneſs of re- <lb/>fuſing to ſail, to acquire the Wiſdom and
        Wealth of re- <lb/>mote Nations; 'till they have diſputed on, and reſolv'd <lb/>the Cauſes
        of the Winds, and of the Ebbing and Flow- <lb/>ing of the Sea, loſt the Subſtance for the
        Shadow, heated <lb/>one another with the never-ceaſing Diſputes concerning <lb/>the Cauſes
        and Modes of all the Operations of, and on the <lb/>Humours of the Body, when the firſt are
        felt and diſcove- <lb/>red by a thouſand Signs, and the other are obvious to all <lb/>our
        Senſes. The <hi rend="italic">Churchmen</hi> were more early corrupting <pb n="34"/>
        <lb/>in the ſame manner, <hi rend="italic">Religion</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
        >Morality</hi>, by their end- <lb/>leſs Controverſies, to adjuſt the plaineſt Truths to the
        <lb/>Notions of <hi rend="italic">Plato</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Ariſtotle</hi>. But to
        return to the Me- <lb/>dicines; the <hi rend="italic">Arabians</hi> inſulted, and affronted
        all the moſt <lb/>faithful Obſervations of the great Effects of the moſt natu- <lb/>ral and
        rational Preparations, and impos'd on their Prin- <lb/>ces, Nobility and People, the moſt
        abſurd and ſophiſtica- <lb/>ted, deſir'd for their Novelty by the Imagination debauch'd
        <lb/>by the aſſum'd grater Induſtry and Penetration of the <lb/>Impoſtors. Theſe could not
        be ſtop'd in their Career of <lb/>Riches and Glory, to be acquir'd by the new Faſhions of
        <lb/>Medicines: They ſtrove to outdo one another, vitiating <lb/>and deſtroying the genuine
        Preparations and Mixtures of <lb/>the Sovereign Simples, by their newly diſcovered <hi
          rend="italic">ſimple</hi>
        <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">compound Waters</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Conſerves</hi>, and
          <hi rend="italic">Syrups</hi>. The <lb/>obvious Frauds of the Craft, prompted and incited
        their <lb/>Dillgence, to invent <hi rend="italic">many Thouſand new Waters, and Con-
          <lb/>ſerves, and Syrups</hi>. To prepare theſe, there muſt be a <hi rend="italic">Le-
          <lb/>gion of Apothecaries</hi>, they and the Phyſicians unite, in Con- <lb/>federacy, all
        their Forces, to damn and decry all the ap- <lb/>plauded Remedies: The new, tho' infinite,
        will not ſubſiſt <lb/>them without Deceit, and the Artifices of mending the <lb/>Trade. An
          <hi rend="italic">Arabian Prince and Phyſician</hi> had his Army <lb/>peſter'd with
        another Army of <hi rend="italic">Apothecaries</hi>, as numerous. <lb/>He reſolv'd to leſſen
        their Numbers, by ſeparating the <lb/>Honeſt from the Knaves. He appointed an unintelligible
        <lb/>Jargon of inſignificant Words, to be publiſh'd as a Receit <lb/>of a general Remedy;
        many Thouſands undertook to <lb/>prepare it, were detected buſie in the compounding it,
        <lb/>and were diſcarded. 'Tis now time to return to <hi rend="italic">Europe</hi>, <lb/>and
          <hi rend="italic">England</hi>, to obſerve how we have been, and how we <lb/>are treated
        at this time. </p>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="30"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
