<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Guybon: An Essay Concerning the Growth of Empiricism; Or the
          Encouragement of Quacks.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Francis Guybon</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">AN ESSAY Concerning the Growth of Empiricism; Or the Encouragement of
              Quacks. WHEREIN The Present State of Physick in this Kingdom is fairly represented;
              with some Reasons for the Necessity of a Regulation in the Practice of it. </title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T116355</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T116355"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for R. Parker, at the Unicorn under the Royal Exchange;
                  and sold by J. Morphew, near Stationers Hall, 1712.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1712</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="7"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="84"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW107054429</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Public welfare and institutional"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="7"/>
    <body>
      <pb n="1"/>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>A horizontal double-line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <head rend="align-center space">
        <lb/><hi rend="size(0.75)">AN</hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="size(2.0)">ESSAY</hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="size(0.75)">Concerning the</hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic size(1.25)">Growth of Empiriciſm</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="size(0.75)">Or
          the</hi>
        <lb/>Encouragement of <hi rend="italic size(1.25)">Quack</hi>s. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">H</hi>EALTH being the great- <lb/>eſt of Natural Bleſſings, <lb/>'tis
        as needleſs to ſay any <lb/>thing in its Praiſe as to enlarge up- <lb/>on the Uſefulneſs of
        Phyſick, which <lb/>preſerves and reſtores it. But as <lb/>there is nothing which would more
          <pb n="2"/>
        <lb/>advance the Uſefulneſs of that Di- <lb/>vine Art, (and is therefore of great- <lb/>er
        Importance to the Publick Good) <lb/>than a Regulation in the Practice <lb/>of it; ſo there
        is nothing conſe- <lb/>quently more recommendable to <lb/>the Conſideration of the Queen and
        <lb/>Parliament than the preſent State <lb/>of Phyſick in this Kingdom. The
        <lb/>Encouragement which Quacks and <lb/>Empiricks have lately met with, is <lb/>not only ſo
        ſurprizingly great, but ſo <lb/>vaſtly detrimental, that in the beſt <lb/>of Governments,
        where Civil and <lb/>Religious Properties are ſo hap- <lb/>pily ſecured, there ſeems nothing
        <lb/>more wanting than ſome ſpeedy <lb/>and powerful Expedient to reſtrain <lb/>ſo growing
        an Evil. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But before I proceed to offer any <lb/>of my Reaſons for the Neceſſity of <lb/>a
        Regulation in the Practice of Phy- <lb/>ſick, or enter into a Detail of the <lb/>evil
        Conſequences (deſervedly to <pb n="3"/>
        <lb/>be lamented by all who have juſt <lb/>Senſe of them) which attend the
        <lb/>Encouragement of Quacks and Em- <lb/>piricks, 'twill not be improper to <lb/>give the
        Definition of, or to let the <lb/>Reader know what I deſire may be <lb/>underſtood by the
        Words. The Word <lb/><hi rend="italic">Quack</hi>, ſays the <hi rend="italic">Gazophylacium
          An- <lb/>glicanum</hi>, is of a <hi rend="italic">Dutch</hi> Original, <lb/>ſignifies a
        frivolous and vain Tat- <lb/>ler, and ſo is applicable to all Per- <lb/>ſons of any
        Profeſſion, who oſten- <lb/>tatiouſly pretend to a great deal of <lb/>Skill and Knowledge in
        Matters <lb/>which they are really ignorant of, <lb/>or do very little underſtand: And
        <lb/>by a Quack or Empirick, I mean <lb/>any and every one of thoſe who <lb/>pretend to
        practiſe Phyſick without <lb/>Knowledge of the <hi rend="italic">Prærequiſita</hi> to
        <lb/>that moſt uſeful but moſt difficult <lb/>Art. There are ſome, 'tis true, <lb/>who would
        fain perſwade us, that <lb/>the Medical Art is only to be pro- <pb n="4"/>
        <lb/>moted by Experiments, or obſer- <lb/>ving what things are hurtful, what <lb/>beneficial
        in Diſeaſes; that the <lb/>Study of Nature and the Know- <lb/>ledge of the Body are only
        trifling <lb/>Curioſities, and things altogether <lb/>ſuperfluous. But it's agreed, I am
        <lb/>apt to think, amongſt the more in- <lb/>telligent part of Mankind, that <lb/>there are
        ſeveral things perfectly <lb/>and abſolutely neceſſary to be <lb/>known, before a Man can
        reaſon, <lb/>and make Judgment either of the <lb/>Nature of Diſeaſes, or the Uſe of
        <lb/>Methods and Medicines for the re- <lb/>medying them, and therefore ought <lb/>to be
        underſtood before he preſumes <lb/>to take the Care of Mens Lives in- <lb/>to his hand: For
        how can he pre- <lb/>tend to cure Diſeaſes, unleſs he firſt <lb/>apprehends what they are,
        and in <lb/>what they conſiſt? How can he <lb/>rationally preſcribe Medicines if he
        <lb/>underſtands not their Operations? <pb n="5"/>
        <lb/>Or how can he expect any manner <lb/>of Advantage from them if he does <lb/>not
        conſider the Relation between <lb/>the Diſeaſe and the Operation? <lb/>And how can he be
        qualified to do <lb/>any of theſe things, unleſs he be <lb/>firſt acquainted with the
        Nature, <lb/>Properties and Functions, of a hu- <lb/>man Body, the Subject of his Art,
        <lb/>and to which they relate? And <lb/>that this was the Opinion of the <lb/>ancient
        Phyſicians, is evident from <lb/>the Variety of Medical Introducti- <lb/>ons and
        Inſtitutions publiſh'd by <lb/>them. For it was not in thoſe <lb/>days thought proper that
        the Care <lb/>of Mens Lives ſhould be entruſted <lb/>with Perſons, till they were in-
        <lb/>ſtructed in the Methods of preſer- <lb/>ving them. </p>
      <p rend="indentall space">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="italic">——Abrotanum ægro <lb/>Non audet, niſi qui didicit, dare— </q>&gt; <lb/><hi
          rend="roman align-right">Hor. Epiſt. </hi>
      </p>
      <pb n="6"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But that there are ſeveral things <lb/>abſolutely neceſſary to be known <lb/>by Men
        before they ought to pre- <lb/>tend to the Practiſe of Phyſick, and <lb/>which are what I
        mean by the <hi rend="italic">Præ- <lb/>requiſita</hi> to the Medical Art, will <lb/>more
        fully appear by a particular <lb/>Enumeration of them, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> the
        <lb/>Knowledge of <list rend="indentall space">
          <item>
            <lb/>I. The learned Languages. </item>
          <item>
            <lb/>II. Natural Philoſophy. </item>
          <item>
            <lb/>III. The Animal Oeconomy. </item>
          <item>
            <lb/>IV. Pharmacology. </item>
          <item>
            <lb/>V. Noſology. </item>
        </list>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>I. The firſt of the <hi rend="italic">Prærequiſita</hi>
        <lb/>then, which I ſhall mention, is the <lb/>Knowledge of the learned Langua- <lb/>ges: For
        Phyſick being the Wiſ- <lb/>dom which is heap'd up in the va- <lb/>rious Labours and
        Obſervations of <lb/>the Learned of all Ages, or the <lb/>Judgments of many Men wound up,
          <pb n="7"/>
        <lb/>as it were into one <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Cum unius hominis vita ad omnium in- <lb/>ventionem ſufficere nequeat, longi
            temporis <lb/>obſervationes Hiſtoria colligit, ut ejus benefi- <lb/>cio tanquam ex
            multis tot ſæculorum homini- <lb/>bus unus efficiatur eruditiſſimus. <hi rend="italic"
              >Galen. de ſub- <lb/>figur. Empir.</hi> Cap. 9. </p>
        </note>, 'twill be <lb/>found neceſſary in a Phyſician to be <lb/>vers'd in the Writings of
        the An- <lb/>cients as well as the Moderns, and <lb/>to be well acquainted with their
        <lb/>Rules, Cautions and Remedies, they <lb/>having laid the firſt Foundation of <lb/>the
        moſt excellent Art, by both <lb/>obſerving and deſcribing the Na- <lb/>ture of Diſeaſes.
        Moſt of the Di- <lb/>agnoſtick and Prognoſtick Signs of <lb/>Diſeaſes are the Reſult of
        their la- <lb/>borious and ſolid Obſervations, and <lb/>will continue to be faithful Guides
        <lb/>to all that can make Uſe of them, <lb/>as long as human Bodies and Na- <lb/>ture it
        ſelf remain. Nothing there- <lb/>fore can be more previouſly ne- <pb n="8"/>
        <lb/>ceſſary to the Practice of Phyſick <lb/>than an Acquiſition of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Greek</hi>
        <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">Latin</hi> Tongues; for as in thoſe <lb/>Languages the Art is
        deliver'd; <lb/>ſo without them the Terms in the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Engliſh</hi>
        Tranſlations are not poſſibly <lb/>to be underſtood. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>II. The next of the <hi rend="italic">Prærequiſita</hi>
        <lb/>is Natural Philoſophy: For as the <lb/>Art of Phyſick is only the Natural
        <lb/>Knowledge apply'd to the Preſer- <lb/>vation of Health and Life; ſo <lb/>whoever intend
        to apply themſelves <lb/>to that Art will find it neceſſary to <lb/>conſider the Human Body,
        the Sub- <lb/>ject of their Art, as a meer Natu- <lb/>ral Subſtance, before they proceed
        <lb/>to the Conſideration of it as an A- <lb/>nimated Being. For tho' the Hu- <lb/>man Body,
        as an Animated Be- <lb/>ing, is, ſtrictly ſpeaking, the im- <lb/>mediate Subject of their
        Care; <lb/>yet the peculiar Properties of A- <pb n="9"/>
        <lb/>nimated Subſtances cannot well <lb/>be diſtinguiſh'd or underſtood, un- <lb/>leſs the
        common Affections of Mat- <lb/>ter be firſt known, out of which, <lb/>the Human as well as
        other Ani- <lb/>mated Bodies are compos'd. And <lb/>notwithſtanding thoſe Particles of
        <lb/>Matter, which are modify'd into a <lb/>Human Body, during that State, <lb/>are enrich'd
        with Properties and <lb/>Perfections, diſtinguiſhing them <lb/>from all other Beings, yet
        there re- <lb/>main in them ſome Affections com- <lb/>mon to other animated Beings, and
        <lb/>ſome promiſcuouſly to be found in <lb/>all Natural Subſtances. Whoever, <lb/>therefore
        deſigns to apply himſelf to <lb/>the Art of Phyſick, ought to com- <lb/>prehend the general
        Properties and <lb/>Affections of Matter; the Origin <lb/>and tranſitory Nature of Forms and
        <lb/>Qualities; and how the Parts of a <lb/>Human Body conſider'd as a Na- <lb/>tural
        Subſtance may be mov'd, be- <pb n="10"/>
        <lb/>fore he begins to inform himſelf <lb/>(or indeed rightly can) of the Af- <lb/>fections
        obſervable in a human Bo- <lb/>dy, as animated or endued with <lb/>Life. And this ſeems to
        have been <lb/>the Method by which Novices were <lb/>heretofore initiated into that Art,
        <lb/>as appears by the Inſtitutes of <hi rend="italic">Ga- <lb/>len</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
          >Rhaſes</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Sennertus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Fuchſius</hi>, <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> as likewiſe in that they have <lb/>blended and interwoven the
        Philo- <lb/>ſophy eſteem'd in thoſe Ages with <lb/>that moſt excellent Art, and have
        <lb/>form'd that proverbial Saying, </p>
      <p rend="italic indentall hanging space">
        <lb/>Ubi deſinit Phyſicus, ibi incipit Me- <lb/>dicus. </p>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/>But Natural Philoſophy is not on- <lb/>ly abſolutely neceſſary to form a <lb/>right
        Apprehenſion of the Human <lb/>Body as a Part or Portion of Mat- <lb/>ter, but alſo to frame
        a true Idea <lb/>of Medicines and their Operations, <pb n="11"/>
        <lb/>as will more fully appear under that <lb/>Head. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>III. The next of the <hi rend="italic">Prærequiſi- <lb/>ta</hi> is the Knowledge of the
        Animal <lb/>Oeconomy, or the Conſideration of <lb/>the human Body as animated or <lb/>endued
        with Life, and that as well <lb/>in its natural or healthful, as in its <lb/>præternatural
        or morbid State; it <lb/>being altogether neceſſary to un- <lb/>derſtand the natural State
        of the <lb/>Body before the Nature of a Diſ- <lb/>eaſe can be rightly comprehended. <lb/>The
        Animal Body is now known <lb/>to be a pure Machine, and its A- <lb/>ctions and Motions
        demonſtrated to <lb/>be the neceſſary Conſequences of its <lb/>Structure. And as the Actions
        of <lb/>the Body, from which Life and <lb/>Health do flow, are the neceſſary
        <lb/>Conſequences of its Oeconomy; ſo <lb/>likewiſe Diſeaſes and all their <lb/>Symptoms,
        are nothing but Alte- <pb n="12"/>
        <lb/>rations or Diſorders in it. It de- <lb/>monſtratively therefore follows, <lb/>that the
        greater the Knowledge of <lb/>the one is, the better the Nature <lb/>of the other muſt be
        known; and <lb/>that a Phyſician ignorant of the A- <lb/>nimal Oeconomy is ignorant of the
        <lb/>Structure and Uſes of the Machine <lb/>he undertakes to regulate. The <lb/>Parts of
        Animated Bodies are aptly <lb/>and uſefully divided into Solid and <lb/>Fluid. Anatomy, or
        the Art of <lb/>Diſſecting the ſolid Parts of Ani- <lb/>mal Bodies, in order to an exact
        <lb/>Diſcovery of their Situation, Stru- <lb/>cture, Uſes, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> as
        it is abſolutely <lb/>neceſſary to the Knowledge of the <lb/>Animal Oeconomy, ſo it has ever
        <lb/>been juſtly eſteem'd one of the <lb/>Foundation Pillars of Phyſick. Nor <lb/>indeed of
        leſs Uſe is the Doctrine <lb/>of the Fluids; under which Head <lb/>I include a right
        Apprehenſion of <lb/>the general and particular Proper- <pb n="13"/>
        <lb/>ties of the Animal Fluids, and of <lb/>their different Motions, Natures, <lb/>Uſes,
        Offices, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> There are ſe- <lb/>veral other things alſo included
        in <lb/>the Knowledge of the Animal Oe- <lb/>conomy (and ſome few of them I <lb/>ſhall juſt
        mention) which tho' not <lb/>ſtrictly referable to either Branch of <lb/>the above-mention'd
        Diviſion of <lb/>the Parts, are yet equally neceſſa- <lb/>ry to be underſtood; <hi
          rend="italic">viz.</hi> the dif- <lb/>ferent Dependencies the Parts have <lb/>on, and the
        different Relations they <lb/>bear to each other; the Powers of <lb/>Motion (both Voluntary
        and In- <lb/>voluntary) and Senſation; the ge- <lb/>neral Reaſon and Nature of Secre-
        <lb/>tion; the Velocity of the Blood's <lb/>Circulation, with the Reaſon of its
        <lb/>Differences at different Diſtances <lb/>from the Heart; the Neceſſity of <lb/>Breathing
        after Birth, with the <lb/>Force of the Air upon the Blood in <lb/>that Action, <hi
          rend="italic">&amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c.</hi> But an <pb n="14"/>
        <lb/>exact Knowledge of the Animal <lb/>Structure and Oeconomy, will after- <lb/>wards
        appear more particularly ne- <lb/>ceſſary, as well to explicate the Vir- <lb/>tues and
        Operation of Medicines, <lb/>as to aſcertain the Diagnoſis, and <lb/>comprehend the Ætiology
        of Diſ- <lb/>eaſes. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>IV. Another of the <hi rend="italic">Prærequiſita</hi>
        <lb/>is Pharmacology; comprehending <lb/>the Knowledge, 1. Of ſimple Na- <lb/>tural
        Medicines, whether of the <lb/>Animal, Vegetable, or Mineral <lb/>Kingdom. 2. Of the ſeveral
        Parts <lb/>of Pharmacy, both Galenical and <lb/>Chymical. 3. Of the general Na- <lb/>ture,
        Virtues, and Operation of <lb/>Medicines. For as a Man cannot <lb/>be ſaid to underſtand an
        Art, with- <lb/>out underſtanding the Inſtruments <lb/>as well as the Subject of that Art;
        <lb/>ſo the Human Body being the Sub- <lb/>ject, and Medicines the Inſtru- <pb n="15"/>
        <lb/>ments of this Art, the Knowledge <lb/>of the one muſt conſequently be as <lb/>neceſſary
        as the Knowledge of the <lb/>other. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I. By the Knowledge of ſimple <lb/>Natural Medicines, I here mean <lb/>that of the
        Subſtances themſelves <lb/>as well as of their Medicinal Vir- <lb/>tues and Efficacies.
        'Twould be <lb/>altogether needleſs to waſt any <lb/>Time in inſiſting upon the Neceſſi-
        <lb/>ty of underſtanding this part of <lb/>Pharmacology: For as without <lb/>knowing the
        Subſtances, a Man in <lb/>his Practice muſt wholly confide in, <lb/>or rely upon the
        Gatherers and <lb/>Venders of Medicines; ſo indeed <lb/>the Knowledge of their Virtues and
        <lb/>Efficacies, without knowing the <lb/>Subſtances themſelves, ſeems to me, <lb/>if of
        any, of a very dangerous Uſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>2. Pharmacy contains the Man- <lb/>ner of Preparing and the Method of <lb/>making ſuch
        ſimple Subſtances into <pb n="16"/>
        <lb/>Medicines, and conſiſts of ſeveral <lb/>Parts, whether according to the Ga-
        <lb/>lenical or Chymical Forms. All the <lb/>ſeveral Parts of Pharmacy, and of
        <lb/>Chymiſtry in particular, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> as it <lb/>teaches the moſt
        Compendious and <lb/>Efficacious Preparation of Medi- <lb/>cines, are, and have been ſo
        often <lb/>demonſtrated to be ſo abſolutely <lb/>neceſſary to be underſtood by all <lb/>who
        deſign for the Practice of Phy- <lb/>ſick, that as there is nothing in <lb/>which Men ſeem
        more agreed than <lb/>in the Neceſſity of underſtanding <lb/>theſe things; ſo it would be
        but <lb/>Loſs of Time to enlarge any further <lb/>upon them. I ſhall therefore con-
        <lb/>clude what I have to offer under this <lb/>Head, with the following Obſer- <lb/>vation;
        That ſince it is ſo neceſſa- <lb/>rily incumbent upon every one <lb/>who pretends to the
        Practice of Phy- <lb/>ſick, to underſtand all the Parts of <lb/>Pharmacy, there can be no
        Obje- <pb n="17"/>
        <lb/>ction made upon that Account, I <lb/>mean, againſt a Phyſician's prepa- <lb/>ring his
        own Medicines, but either <lb/>by ignorant or intereſted Men. <lb/>But tho' this Obſervation
        is ſuffici- <lb/>ent to excuſe the Phyſicians for gi- <lb/>ving their own Medicines (which
        <lb/>indeed is only reſuming what their <lb/>Anceſtors either out of Pride or La-
        <lb/>zineſs left off) yet it does not fol- <lb/>low that there is any manner of A-
        <lb/>pology to be made for the Apothe- <lb/>caries intruding themſelves into the
        <lb/>Practice of Phyſick, as will more <lb/>fully afterwards appear. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>3. Under the third Branch of <lb/>Pharmacology is compriz'd the <lb/>Knowledge of the
        general Nature, <lb/>Virtues and Operation of Medi- <lb/>cines. And as Natural Philoſophy
        <lb/>was proved to be neceſſary towards <lb/>forming a right Notion of the Hu- <lb/>man
        Body, ſo 'twill be found as <lb/>neceſſary towards comprehending <pb n="18"/>
        <lb/>the general Nature, Virtues, and O- <lb/>perations of Medicines. For Medi- <lb/>cines
        being only natural Subſtan- <lb/>ces, only Parts or Portions of Mat- <lb/>ter, 'tis evident,
        that their Powers <lb/>and Properties are not only under <lb/>the ſame common Laws and Rules
        <lb/>which are obſerved in the other <lb/>Parts of Matter, but are alſo to be <lb/>explain'd
        in the ſame Methods; and <lb/>therefore Medicines are not only <lb/>Natural Subſtances, but
        they alſo <lb/>operate in a Natural Way, [<hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi> by <lb/>different
        Kinds and Degrees of Mo- <lb/>tion] ſuch Natural Subſtances loo- <lb/>ſing only their
        Denomination, and <lb/>not their Natures, by being term'd <lb/>or applied as Medicines. By a
        <lb/>due Apprehenſion of theſe things, <lb/>and without which it is impoſſi- <lb/>ble for a
        Practitioner in Phyſick to <lb/>be really uſeful or ſerviceable in his <lb/>Generation, Men
        will know what <lb/>Effects to expect, and be prevent- <pb n="19"/>
        <lb/>ed from a credulous Expectation of <lb/>Effects, which can in no wiſe pro- <lb/>ceed
        from them in a natural Way. <lb/>Medicines, notwithſtanding the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Materia Medica</hi> is made up of ſo <lb/>vaſt a Variety of Natural Subſtan- <lb/>ces,
        may, in reſpect of their gene- <lb/>ral Virtues or Operation, be com- <lb/>priz'd under ſuch
        as produce ſome <lb/>Evacuation, or ſuch as only effect <lb/>ſome Alteration in the Body.
        And <lb/>not only Natural Philoſophy, but a <lb/>due Knowledge alſo of the Animal
        <lb/>Oeconomy is abſolutely neceſſary <lb/>towards framing a right Notion of <lb/>theſe
        Things: For unleſs Men un- <lb/>derſtand the Structure, and com- <lb/>prehend the Uſes and
        Offices of the <lb/>Parts of the Body, it is impoſſible <lb/>for them to know how, or by
        what <lb/>Organs, or in what Regions, Parts <lb/>or Juices, Medicines perform their
        <lb/>Operations. </p>
      <pb n="20"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>V. The fifth and laſt of the <hi rend="italic">Præ- <lb/>requiſita</hi>, which I ſhall
        mention, is <lb/>Noſology; containing whatever re- <lb/>lates to the General Nature, Signs,
        <lb/>Cauſes, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> of Diſeaſes. For as <lb/>the Conſideration of
        the Human <lb/>Body, in its natural or healthful <lb/>State, is, by Phyſicians, only in
        <lb/>order to the Conſideration of it in <lb/>its Præternatural or Morbid one; <lb/>ſo
        conſequently there can be no- <lb/>thing more previouſly neceſſary to <lb/>the Practice of
        Phyſick than what- <lb/>ever relates to the Knowledge of <lb/>the General Nature, Signs,
        Cau- <lb/>ſes, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> of Diſeaſes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>1. And firſt the Want of a clear <lb/>Idea of the General Nature of Diſ- <lb/>eaſes
        muſt be a certain Means of <lb/>laying a neceſſary and afterwards <lb/>unalterable
        Foundation of Error <lb/>and Miſcarriage in Practice. One <lb/>would be tempted to think,
        from <pb n="21"/>
        <lb/>the erroneous Proceedings of unin- <lb/>telligent Practitioners, that Diſeaſes
        <lb/>were really ſeparate Eſſences, (or <lb/>I know not what ſubſtantial Forms) <lb/>and as
        ſuch enter'd and poſſeſs'd <lb/>the Bodies of Men. Whereas, by <lb/>a due Conſideration of
        their Na- <lb/>tures, they will be found to be no- <lb/>thing different or diſtinct from the
        <lb/>Body, but only Changes or Altera- <lb/>tions in the Modification of its con-
        <lb/>ſtituent Parts, or different Modes of <lb/>Indiſpoſition in the ſame Body. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>2. Secondly, the Doctrine of the <lb/>Signs, both Diagnoſtick and Prog- <lb/>noſtick,
        is not leſs neceſſary to be <lb/>throughly underſtood, before a <lb/>Man undertakes the
        Practice of <lb/>Phyſick, than the General Nature <lb/>of Diſeaſes. For as by a due Know-
        <lb/>ledge of the Diagnoſtick Signs, he <lb/>may be inſtructed truly to diſtin- <lb/>guiſh
        one Diſeaſe, tho' never ſo <lb/>much alike, from another; ſo <pb n="22"/>
        <lb/>thro' want of that Knowledge, one <lb/>Diſeaſe is very often miſtaken for <lb/>and
        treated as another. How of- <lb/>ten, for Inſtance, has a <hi rend="italic">Colica</hi> and
        a <lb/><hi rend="italic">Nephritis</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">Fluor Albus</hi> and a <hi
          rend="italic">Go- <lb/>norrhæa</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">Chloroſis</hi> and a <hi
          rend="italic">Phthiſis</hi>
        <lb/>been confounded? So that the <lb/>Foundation of Cure ſeems prima- <lb/>rily to be laid
        in a right Apprehen- <lb/>ſion of the Diagnoſtick Signs of each <lb/>Diſtemper. But here it
        ought to <lb/>be obſerved, that the better a Man <lb/>underſtands the Animal Structure
        <lb/>and Oeconomy, the more capable <lb/>he will be both of comprehending <lb/>and
        aſcertaining the Diagnoſis, and <lb/>that a Man ignorant of thoſe things <lb/>muſt
        neceſſarily miſlead himſelf by <lb/>the Uſe of a common Name, and <lb/>apply it to denote
        Circumſtances <lb/>which are ſo far from being always <lb/>alike, that they will be
        ſometimes <lb/>found extremely different. </p>
      <pb n="23"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>And as to the Prognoſtick Signs <lb/>of Diſeaſes; tho' it be certain that <lb/>the
        Recovery of the Sick is the <lb/>great Deſign of the Medical Art, <lb/>and undoubtedly more
        neceſſary <lb/>than Preſaging the Event of Di- <lb/>ſtempers, yet the Advances which
        <lb/>have been made in the Prognoſtick <lb/>Part of Medicine, as acquiring no <lb/>ſmall
        Eſteem and Authority to the <lb/>Phyſician, ought diligently to be <lb/>collected from the
        Obſervations of <lb/>the Ancients, particularly of the <lb/>Divine <hi rend="italic"
          >Hippocrates</hi>, as well as from <lb/>the Writings of the Moderns. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>3. Thirdly, the Ætiology of <lb/>Diſeaſes; I mean more particular- <lb/>ly as to the
        immediate and conjunct <lb/>Cauſes, will be found as neceſſary <lb/>to be known be every
        Practitioner, <lb/>as either the General Nature of <lb/>Diſeaſes, or the Doctrine of the
        <lb/>Signs. For if, as is very evident <lb/>in Practice, Diſeaſes even of the <pb n="24"/>
        <lb/>ſame Denomination, ariſing from <lb/>different Cauſes, do adminiſter <lb/>different
        Indications, or indicate <lb/>different Methods of Cure; the <lb/>Ætiology muſt conſequently
        be a <lb/>grand Source from whence Ratio- <lb/>nal Indications can be drawn. <lb/>'Twere
        very eaſie to give Inſtances <lb/>in almoſt all the Diſeaſes incident <lb/>to the Human
        Body, but thinking <lb/>it altogether needleſs, becauſe the <lb/>Medical Writings are ſo
        full of them, <lb/>I ſhall conclude this Head with ob- <lb/>ſerving, That as an exact Know-
        <lb/>ledge of the Animal Structure and <lb/>Oeconomy is abſolutely neceſſary <lb/>to
        comprehend the Ætiology of <lb/>Diſeaſes; ſo the Modern Improve- <lb/>ments in Anatomy have
        very conſi- <lb/>derably advanc'd the Ætiological <lb/>Part of Medicine. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Having thus, with the utmoſt <lb/>Brevity demonſtrated, that there <pb n="25"/>
        <lb/>are ſeveral things perfectly and <lb/>abſolutely neceſſary to be known <lb/>by Men
        before they ought to <lb/>pretend to the Practice of Phy- <lb/>ſick; my preſent Deſign does
        <lb/>not at all oblige me to enquire <lb/>whether I have enumerated all the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Prærequiſita</hi> to the Medical Art; <lb/>but from that Enumeration of them
        <lb/>which I have made, and from <lb/>what I have advanc'd, under each <lb/>of thoſe Heads,
        may very fairly <lb/>venture to draw the following Con- <lb/>cluſions, <hi rend="italic"
          >viz.</hi>
        <list rend="indentall space">
          <item rend="hanging">
            <lb/>I. That Experience alone will <lb/>not make a Phyſician. </item>
          <item rend="hanging">
            <lb/>II. That the Enumeration of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Prærequiſita</hi> to the
            Medi- <lb/>cal Art is a ſufficient Argu- <lb/>ment with what Difficulty a <lb/>due
            Qualification for the <lb/>Practice of it is attain'd. </item>
          <pb n="26"/>
          <item rend="hanging">
            <lb/>III. That it is a plain Demon- <lb/>ſtration, how unqualified the <lb/>Quacks are
            for exerciſing the <lb/>Profeſſion they pretend to. </item>
          <item rend="hanging">
            <lb/>IV. That it is an evident Indi- <lb/>cation to the rational Part of <lb/>Mankind,
            who do, and who <lb/>do not, and that the far great- <lb/>eſt Part of the Practitioners
            <lb/>in Phyſick do come under <lb/>the Denomination of Quacks. </item>
          <item rend="hanging">
            <lb/>V. That an Apothecary can no <lb/>more be ſaid to be Qualified <lb/>for the
            Practice of Phyſick, <lb/>than any other Mechanical <lb/>Tradeſman. </item>
        </list>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>I. That Experience alone will <lb/>not make a Phyſician: For if there <lb/>are, as I
        have already proved, ſe- <lb/>veral things abſolutely neceſſary <lb/>to be known by Men,
        before they <lb/>can judge of the Nature of Diſea- <lb/>ſes or Remedies, which are what I
          <pb n="27"/>
        <lb/>mean by the <hi rend="italic">Prærequiſita</hi> to the <lb/>Medical Art: It evidently
        follows <lb/>that Experience alone, <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi> Expe- <lb/>rience without
        the <hi rend="italic">Prærequiſita</hi> will <lb/>not make a Phyſician. The Art of
        <lb/>Phyſick then may very aptly and uſe- <lb/>fully be ſaid to conſiſt of two Parts,
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> The Theoretical and Practical. <lb/>And as there is
        nothing truer on the <lb/>one hand, than that the Theory, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
        <lb/>the Knowledge of the <hi rend="italic">Prærequiſita</hi>
        <lb/>is, as has been fully prov'd, abſo- <lb/>lutely neceſſary to the Practice: <lb/>ſo
        there is nothing more evident on <lb/>the other, than that the Know- <lb/>ledge of the
        Theory, tho' previ- <lb/>ouſly neceſſary, is only in order <lb/>to, and therefore uſeleſs
        without, <lb/>the Practice. For tho' 'tis impoſſi- <lb/>ble (I affirm) a Man ſhould make
        <lb/>any conſiderable Figure in the Pra- <lb/>ctice, who is ignorant of the præli-
        <lb/>minary Arts which compoſe the <lb/>Theory of Phyſick: And if with- <pb n="28"/>
        <lb/>out the Knowledge of thoſe Arts, a <lb/>Man jumps, as I may ſay, into <lb/>Practice,
        ſuch a one is never to be <lb/>truſted, tho' he had ſeen Thouſands <lb/>of Patients, and ten
        thouſand Pre- <lb/>ſcriptions; yet do I not (as it is ri- <lb/>diculous to) ſuppoſe, that
        Men <lb/>ſhould reſt here, or dwell upon the <lb/>Theory; or that the ſpeculative <lb/>Part
        of Phyſick ſhould teach them <lb/>to cure all manner of Diſtempers in <lb/>their Cloſets,
        without a conſtant <lb/>Attendance on the Sick, without a <lb/>diligent and unwearied
        Obſerva- <lb/>tion on Diſeaſes. A due Appre- <lb/>henſion of theſe things may be a
        <lb/>Means to determine the many un- <lb/>neceſſary Diſputes concerning the <lb/>Preference
        of one Part of Phyſick <lb/>to the other; the Knowledge of <lb/>the one abſolutely depending
        on, <lb/>and conſequently being altogether <lb/>as neceſſary as that of the other. <lb/>And
        as Theory and Practice, ſo <pb n="29"/>
        <lb/>Reaſon and Obſervation ought not <lb/>to be compar'd with, or oppos'd <lb/>to, each
        other, but join'd together, <lb/>as mutually adorning and illuſtra- <lb/>ting one another,
        to the fully com- <lb/>pleating of a Phyſician. A Man <lb/>may be an Advocate for
        Experience, <lb/>and well appriz'd of the Uſefulneſs <lb/>of accurate Obſervations, and at
        <lb/>the ſame time not diſcard the Uſe <lb/>of Reaſon in Phyſick. True Ob- <lb/>ſervations
        will never be found to <lb/>contradict Right Reaſon, nor will <lb/>Right Reaſon exert it
        ſelf in oppo- <lb/>ſition to matter of Fact. But leſt <lb/>any of the Empirical Tribe ſhould
        <lb/>pretend to take Shelter under Au- <lb/>thorities, or to interpret what <hi
          rend="italic">Ba- <lb/>glivi</hi> ſays concerning Experience and <lb/>Obſervation in
        favour of themſelves, <lb/>I've purpoſely read over all the <lb/>Works of that celebrated
        Author, <lb/>and from innumerable Paſſages in <lb/>his Writings, think nothing more <pb
          n="30"/>
        <lb/>evident, than that it is a Literate, <lb/>and not an Empirical Experience, <lb/>which
        he contends for. 'Tis not <lb/>Experience without the <hi rend="italic">Prærequiſi-
          <lb/>ta</hi>, but ſuch a well grounded Ex- <lb/>perience as a Man duly qualify'd <lb/>for
        the Practice of Phyſick, may <lb/>daily with Reaſon, be ſuppos'd to <lb/>acquire. And 'tis
        as evident, that <lb/>what he has advanc'd, concerning <lb/>the Importance of Obſervation in
        <lb/>the Way of Phyſick, ought to be <lb/>interpreted in that very Senſe. For <lb/>tho' he
        ſays, That nothing ſo na- <lb/>turally tends to the Improvement <lb/>of Phyſick, as
        Experiments and <lb/>Obſervations, yet 'tis certainly true, <lb/>that he deſires it might be
        under- <lb/>ſtood (as indeed it ought to be) of <lb/>Experiments directed by the Know-
        <lb/>ledge of the Animal Oeconomy, <lb/>and of Obſervations grounded on <lb/>that and the
        other <hi rend="italic">Prærequiſita</hi>. So <lb/>notwithſtanding what Dr. <hi
          rend="italic">Syden- <pb n="31"/>
          <lb/>ham</hi> declares, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
        <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* <hi rend="italic">Vid.</hi> Epiſt. Ded. Obſ. Med. </p>
        </note>
        <q rend="italic">Artem Medi- <lb/>cam haud rectius eſſe perdiſcendam, <lb/>quam ab ipſius
          Artis Exercitio atque <lb/>Uſu </q>; and <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)" n="†">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>† <hi rend="italic">Vid.</hi> Tract. de Podagra. <hi rend="italic">p.</hi> 80. <hi
              rend="italic">Edit. Lugd. <lb/>Bat.</hi>
          </p>
        </note>
        <q rend="italic">Praxin eſſe Medicinæ <lb/>Profitentium Lapidem Lydium </q>, 'tis
        <lb/>evident from Paſſages enough in <lb/>that worthy Author, particularly <lb/>from the
        whole 81ſt Page of the <lb/>laſt mention'd Treatiſe, that he <lb/>never deſign'd, by what he
        <lb/>ſays, to advance an Empirical Ex- <lb/>perience, or to preclude the Ne- <lb/>ceſſity of
        underſtanding the <hi rend="italic">Præ- <lb/>requiſita</hi>. As there is nothing more
        <lb/>ridiculous than to ſuppoſe all Men <lb/>capable of making a good Uſe <lb/>of
        Experience, or able to draw <lb/>right Concluſions from the Motions <lb/>of Nature; ſo
        Quacks and Empi- <lb/>ricks, who ſet out without either <pb n="32"/>
        <lb/>Light or Method muſt undoubt- <lb/>edly prove ſtupid and erroneous <lb/>Obſervators: It
        being indeed im- <lb/>poſſible that Men ignorant of the <lb/>Medical <hi rend="italic"
          >Prærequiſita</hi>, ſhould be <lb/>capable of improving either them- <lb/>ſelves or the
        Art by their Experi- <lb/>ence and Obſervations. What there- <lb/>fore is daily ſaid in
        praiſe of Expe- <lb/>rience (to which no one pays a <lb/>greater Deference than my ſelf)
        <lb/>and in Recommendation of expe- <lb/>rienc'd Phyſicians, ought to be un- <lb/>derſtood
        with ſuch a Reſtriction as <lb/>not to include the Practitioners, <lb/>who never had
        Opportunities of <lb/>Underſtanding the <hi rend="italic">Prærequiſita</hi>. <lb/>How
        ridiculous then is the Folly <lb/>of thoſe People who magnifie an <lb/>Empirical Experience,
        or cry up a <lb/>Quack or whatſoever Figure or <lb/>Fame, for a Man of Experience,
        <lb/>which wanting a Foundation, can- <lb/>not be of any real Uſe and Ser- <pb n="33"/>
        <lb/>vice either to himſelf or others. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>II. That the Enumeration of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Prærequiſita</hi> to the Medical
        Art, <lb/>is a ſufficient Argument with what <lb/>Difficulty a due Qualification for
        <lb/>the Practice of it is attain'd. For <lb/>if it be ſo abſolutely neceſſary, as <lb/>has
        been already prov'd, to under- <lb/>ſtand the <hi rend="italic">Prærequiſita</hi> to that
        Art, <lb/>'tis very eaſie to infer, both what <lb/>Length of Time and Labour of <lb/>Thought
        the Acquiſition of ſo <lb/>much Knowledge will require. 'Tis <lb/>not then a Raw and
        Superficial <lb/>Knowledge of Receipts and Medi- <lb/>cines of Diſeaſes and their Cures,
        <lb/>which will qualifie a Man for the <lb/>Practice of Phyſick, but a gradual
        <lb/>Advancement thro' all the above- <lb/>mention'd Foundations of the Art. <lb/>'Tis not
        to be ſuppos'd, that the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ars longiſſima</hi> ſhould be ſo quickly
        <lb/>acquir'd, or the moſt difficult of <pb n="34"/>
        <lb/>Sciences ſo inſtantly attain'd. And <lb/>this Truth is not only confim'd by <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Hippocrates</hi>, in his very firſt <lb/>Aphoriſm <note n="*"
          rend="size(0.5)" place="bottom">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Τέχνη Μακ<unclear>ρ</unclear>ή. </p>
        </note>, and in his Enume- <lb/>ration of the Neceſſaries which <lb/>he requires to
        conſtitute a Good <lb/>Phyſician <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)" n="†">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>† Διδασκαλία. Παιδομαθία. Φικοπονία. Χρόν <gap reason="illegible"/>. <lb/><hi
              rend="italic">Hippocr. Lex.</hi>
          </p>
        </note> ; but by the con- <lb/>current Teſtimonies, both of the <lb/>Ancients and Moderns.
        Yet <lb/>notwithſtanding what has been ad- <lb/>vanced, concerning the <hi rend="italic"
          >Prærequiſi- <lb/>ta</hi> to the Medical Art, and the <lb/>Difficulty of acquiring the
        Know- <lb/>ledge of them; it is very ſurpri- <lb/>zing to conſider what a vaſt Num- <lb/>ber
        of Perſons there are, who would <lb/>fain become Phyſicians without La- <lb/>bour and Study,
        and be ſaluted <lb/>Sons of <hi rend="italic">Apollo</hi>, without any man- <pb n="35"/>
        <lb/>ner of Right to the Title. But <lb/>all and every one of thoſe who are <lb/>ignorant of
        the Preliminary Arts, <lb/>which compoſe the Theory, are <lb/>but Pretenders in Phyſick, do
        jump, <lb/>as I ſaid, into Practice, and are ne- <lb/>ver to be truſted tho' they had ſeen
        <lb/>thouſands of Patients, and ten thou- <lb/>ſand Preſcriptions. But I now pro- <lb/>ceed,
        in the third Place, more par- <lb/>ticularly to conſider, </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>III. That the Enumeration of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Prærequiſita</hi> to the
        Medical <lb/>Art, is a plain Demonſtration how <lb/>unqualified the Quacks are for ex-
        <lb/>erciſing the Profeſſion they pretend <lb/>to. And if, as has been prov'd, <lb/>there
        are ſo many things abſolute- <lb/>ly neceſſary to be known, before a <lb/>Man can either
        reaſon or judge of <lb/>Diſeaſes; it evidently follows, that <lb/>a Quack, ignorant of thoſe
        things, <lb/>is abſolutely unqualified for that <pb n="36"/>
        <lb/>Profeſſion. Were but the Matter <lb/>indeed, as impartially conſider'd <lb/>as it ought
        to be, there ſeems no- <lb/>thing more ridiculous than to <lb/>pretend to the Practice of
        Phy- <lb/>ſick, without a previous Know- <lb/>ledge of them; it being im- <lb/>poſſible but
        ſuch People muſt make <lb/>either Improper, Dangerous and <lb/>Deſtructive, or Inſignificant
        and <lb/>Uſeleſs Applications. It is not on- <lb/>ly true in Fact, that the moſt ge-
        <lb/>nerous often prove the moſt dead- <lb/>ly Medicines, if adminiſtred with- <lb/>out
        Judgment; but it is an every <lb/>day's Obſervation, that thoſe very <lb/>things which have
        the Reputation <lb/>of being harmleſs and inoffenſive, <lb/>if improperly applied, do too
        often <lb/>create very great Miſchiefs. In the <lb/>Practice of Phyſick there is requir'd
        <lb/>not only great Labour of Thought, <lb/>in ſearching into the ſeveral Ap- <lb/>pearances
        and Circumſtances of <pb n="37"/>
        <lb/>Diſeaſes, but alſo great Strength of <lb/>Judgment in duly weighing and <lb/>comparing
        them together. And <lb/>it is not here, as in many other <lb/>Caſes, where Experiments may
        be <lb/>repeated without any great Injury; <lb/>for this perhaps admits but of one
        <lb/>ſingle Tryal, which poſſibly may <lb/>terminate in the Death of a Man, <lb/>and one
        falſe Step, eſpecially in an <lb/>acute Diſeaſe, may be of the moſt <lb/>fatal Conſequence.
        Phyſick, 'tis <lb/>true, abounds with a very large <lb/>Number of excellent Medicines:
        <lb/>But Medicines, being Relations to <lb/>Human Bodies, can only be ſaid <lb/>to be good
        or bad, as applied; and <lb/>like all other Inſtruments to do ei- <lb/>ther Good or Hurt,
        according to <lb/>the Nature of the Hand which u- <lb/>ſes them. As there is nothing
        <lb/>more conſpicuous on the one hand, <lb/>than the uſeful Effects of Medi- <lb/>cines,
        when Methodically and Ju- <pb n="38"/>
        <lb/>diciouſly adminiſtred: So there is <lb/>nothing more obvious on the other, <lb/>than
        the deadly Effects even of <lb/>thoſe of the very firſt Rank, when <lb/>us'd, without either
        Method or <lb/>Judgment. Can any thing then <lb/>more fully demonſtrate the Vanity <lb/>of
        Empiriciſm than the daily Ex- <lb/>perience how Inefficacious and Uſe- <lb/>leſs, even the
        moſt celebrated Spe- <lb/>cificks are without a Judicious and <lb/>Methodical Application?
        For tho' <lb/>a more Noble Specifick than the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Cortex</hi>, for
        Inſtance, was never <lb/>known, yet Experience convinces <lb/>us how frequently we are
        forced <lb/>even in intermitting Fevers, to call <lb/>in to our Aſſiſtance, the Know-
        <lb/>ledge of Animal Oeconomy; <lb/>and by Vomiting, Purging, or o- <lb/>ther proper Means,
        to render that <lb/>Specifick uſeful, which would o- <lb/>therwiſe have been of no Effect:
        So <lb/>that nothing ſeems more ridiculous <pb n="39"/>
        <lb/>than for a Man to pretend to cure <lb/>Diſeaſes, tho' arm'd with the beſt <lb/>of
        Medicines, without the Know- <lb/>ledge of the Animal Oeconomy, <lb/>and the Noſological <hi
          rend="italic">Prærequiſita</hi>. <lb/>It may as well be expected that a <lb/>blind Man
        ſhould ſhoot flying, or <lb/>a deaf one tune an Organ. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I cannot therefore conclude this <lb/>Head without obſerving (which <lb/>indeed
        naturally flows from the <lb/>foregoing Conſiderations) how un- <lb/>accountably infatuated
        they are, <lb/>who apply themſelves to any of the <lb/>Empirical Tribe; there being no-
        <lb/>thing ſo monſtrous as their Preten- <lb/>ces; nothing, but the no leſs mon- <lb/>ſtrous
        Credulity of thoſe who em- <lb/>ploy them. But, </p>
      <p rend="space indentall hanging">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="italic">Quos perdere vult Jupiter, prius <lb/>dementat. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/>Does any one Man more deſerve <pb n="40"/>
        <lb/>to be ridicul'd, than he, who thinks <lb/>his Gold Watch of too great Value <lb/>to be
        put into the Hands of an un- <lb/>der Workman, and at the ſame <lb/>time, truſts his Body, a
        Machine <lb/>of infinitely more curious Structure, <lb/>with an ignorant Pretender in Phy-
        <lb/>ſick. Can a Man put a greater <lb/>Affront upon his Reaſon? Or can <lb/>he give an
        odder Demonſtration of <lb/>his Kindneſs to Wife, Children or <lb/>Friends, than to commit
        any of <lb/>them to the Care of ſuch unequal <lb/>Managers? In Matters of far leſs
        <lb/>Moment, Men generally are more <lb/>guided by the Dictates of Reaſon, <lb/>and not ſo
        eaſily impos'd upon by <lb/>any kind of empty Pretenſions. If <lb/>the Title of an Eſtate,
        wherein <lb/>they are concern'd, be never ſo lit- <lb/>tle ſuſpected, they immediately ap-
        <lb/>ply to the Beſt Advice, and will <lb/>ſpare neither Coſt nor Pains for a <lb/>Right
        Information; but which is <pb n="41"/>
        <lb/>the moſt unaccountable Piece of <lb/>Folly imaginable, are extremely <lb/>leſs
        ſollicitous about the Care of <lb/>their Bodies than their Eſtates. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>IV. That the Enumeration of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Prærequiſita</hi> to the Medical
        Art, <lb/>is an evident Indication to the Ra- <lb/>tional Part of Mankind, who do, <lb/>and
        who do not, and that the far <lb/>greateſt Part of the Practitioners <lb/>in Phyſick do come
        under the De- <lb/>nomination of Quacks: I appeal <lb/>to the Rational Part of Mankind,
        <lb/>becauſe they are the fitteſt Judges <lb/>in the Matter; for as they are ca- <lb/>pable
        of diſtinguiſhing who have, <lb/>and who have not, had Opportuni- <lb/>ties of underſtanding
        the <hi rend="italic">Prærequi- <lb/>ſita</hi>; ſo they cannot but at the ſame <lb/>time be
        convinc'd, that the far <lb/>greateſt Part of the Practitioners in <lb/>Phyſick, come under
        the Deno- <lb/>mination of Quacks. There is no- <pb n="42"/>
        <lb/>thing more Evident than that there <lb/>are Pretenders in Phyſick, who are <lb/>ſo far
        from having any Knowledge <lb/>of the learned Languages, that <lb/>they cannot write their
        own; are <lb/>ſo far from having made any Search- <lb/>es into the vaſt Collection of An-
        <lb/>cient Learning, that they never <lb/>perus'd even the Obſervations of <lb/>the Moderns;
        are ſo far from un- <lb/>derſtanding Natural Philoſophy or <lb/>the Animal Oeconomy, that
        they <lb/>never had Opportunities of learn- <lb/>ing Anatomy or Chymiſtry; ne- <lb/>ver ſaw
        a Diſſection, or one Pro- <lb/>ceſs of the Preparation of Medi- <lb/>cines. What a
        melancholy Re- <lb/>flection then is it, that ſuch a Trade <lb/>of deceiving ſhould be
        carried on <lb/>under the Pretences to ſo uſeful an <lb/>Art; and to conſider, what a Num-
        <lb/>ber of People there are who ha- <lb/>ving no other Foundation but Im- <lb/>pudence and
        Ignorance, bubble ſo <pb n="43"/>
        <lb/>many Thouſands out of their Mo- <lb/>ney and Lives? </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>V. That an Apothecary can no <lb/>more be ſaid to be Qualified for <lb/>the Practice of
        Phyſick than any <lb/>other Mechanical Tradeſman. Tho' <lb/>the Preparation of Medicines,
        ac- <lb/>cording to the Preſcript is properly <lb/>ſpeaking the Buſineſs of an Apothe-
        <lb/>cary, and which Preparation re- <lb/>quires only the Knowledge of the <lb/>Subſtances
        themſelves, and not of <lb/>their Medicinal Virtues and Effi- <lb/>cacies; yet let us
        ſuppoſe an Apo- <lb/>thecary endued with that Know- <lb/>ledge alſo, and let us conſider how
        <lb/>far it will qualify him for the Pra- <lb/>ctice of Phyſick. We will then <lb/>ſuppoſe
        him to know that this Me- <lb/>dicine will purge; this, vomit; and <lb/>this produce other
        Evacuations, or <lb/>perhaps only Alterations in the Bo- <lb/>dy. But as to know what is
        Indi- <pb n="44"/>
        <lb/>cated is one thing, and how to an- <lb/>ſwer ſuch an Indication another; <lb/>ſo the
        Knowledge of the Virtues <lb/>and Efficacies of Medicines will <lb/>not at all inſtruct or
        direct him in <lb/>the Application of them. For Me- <lb/>dicines being Relations to Human
        <lb/>Bodies, can be only good or bad, <lb/>as juſtly or unjuſtly applied: And
        <lb/>therefore, as I inſtanc'd , tho' we <lb/>ſuppoſe a Man to know that ſuch <lb/>a
        Medicine will undoubtedly Purge, <lb/><hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi> ſollicit the Bowels into
        that <lb/>Motion we call ſo; yet whether <lb/>this will be to the Advantage of the
        <lb/>Perſon to whom it is given, de- <lb/>pends not on the Man's Know- <lb/>ledge of the
        Medicine's Operation, <lb/>but on the Fitneſs and Diſpoſition <lb/>of the Patients Body to
        receive it. <lb/>Again, a Man may know, that <lb/>there are ſome Preparations of An-
        <lb/>timony, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> which will always pro- <lb/>duce Vomiting. But
        tho' by the <pb n="45"/>
        <lb/>Exhibition of a Vomit, a Vitiated <lb/>Stomach is ſometimes reſtor'd; yet <lb/>when the
        Stomach is deprav'd from <lb/>a Cauſe which cannot be removed <lb/>by Vomiting, 'tis plain,
        that the <lb/>Uſe of ſuch Medicines cannot poſ- <lb/>ſibly effect its Recovery. And a
        <lb/>great many more Inſtances might <lb/>be given in reſpect to the Opera- <lb/>tion of
        Medicines, which only pro- <lb/>duce ſome Alteration in the Body. <lb/>The Excellency then
        of the Medi- <lb/>cal Art conſiſts in a right Appre- <lb/>henſion of the Relation between
        <lb/>the Powers of the Medicine, and <lb/>the Circumſtances of the Diſeaſe. <lb/>Now ſuch a
        right Apprehenſion of <lb/>this Relation, as is ſufficient to <lb/>qualify a Man for the
        Practice of <lb/>Phyſick, cannot poſſibly be acquir'd <lb/>by the Knowledge of Medicines,
        <lb/>their Preparation and Virtues; but <lb/>of all the abovemention'd <hi rend="italic"
          >Prære- <lb/>quiſita</hi> to the Art. And this ſingle <pb n="46"/>
        <lb/>Conſideration of the Relation be- <lb/>tween the Medicine and the Body, <lb/>as it
        diſtinguiſhes a Regular from <lb/>an Empirical Practice; ſo it ſuffi- <lb/>ciently expoſes
        the Vanity of con- <lb/>fiding in Receipts or <hi rend="italic">Noſtrums</hi>, <lb/>and
        plainly demonſtrates that the <lb/>moſt celebrated Preparations (even <lb/>of the
        Philoſophers by Fire) are <lb/>not capable of curing Diſeaſes, <lb/>without a Judicious and
        Methodi- <lb/>cal Application, and that there <lb/>can be nothing conſequently more
        <lb/>ridiculous than to ſuppoſe an Apo- <lb/>thecary capable of adviſing from <lb/>ſeeing
        the Preſcripts of Phyſici- <lb/>ans. If then the Knowledge of <lb/>the Preparation of
        Medicines, if <lb/>the Knowledge of their Virtues, <lb/>and Efficacies, nay, if ſeeing
        <lb/>the very Preſcripts of Phyſicians, <lb/>will not amount to a Qualifica- <lb/>tion; it
        demonſtratively follows <lb/>that an Apothecary can no more <pb n="47"/>
        <lb/>be ſaid to be Qualified for the Pra- <lb/>ctice of Phyſick, having no other <lb/>Means
        or Opportunities of acqui- <lb/>ring the reſt of the <hi rend="italic">Prærequiſita</hi>,
        than <lb/>any other Mechanical Tradeſ-man. <lb/>That ſmall Pittance of Learning <lb/>which
        is acquir'd at School, if not <lb/>afterwards loſt in the ſervile Offi- <lb/>ces of the
        Shop, can claim no man- <lb/>ner of Conſideration: No; the <lb/>Prolix and Laborious Study
        of Phy- <lb/>ſick, ought aſſuredly to commence <lb/>upon a more Literate Foundation;
        <lb/>and the Knowledge of it is not poſ- <lb/>ſibly attainable, but by an Educa- <lb/>tion
        of a quite different Nature. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>'Twill be very pertinent to my <lb/>preſent Deſign, and not unaccepta- <lb/>ble to my
        Reader, I hope, to ac- <lb/>quaint him, how the Apothecaries <lb/>firſt crept into Houſes,
        and intro- <lb/>duc'd themſelves into the Practice <lb/>of Phyſick. Their officious Viſits
        <lb/>were at firſt made under Pretence <pb n="48"/>
        <lb/>of carrying the Phyſick themſelves, <lb/>which indeed might procure them <lb/>the
        Reputation of careful Men, <lb/>tho' by running on the Errands 'tis <lb/>plain they chang'd
        Offices, with <lb/>their Servants, and left them at <lb/>home to do the Duty of their Ma-
        <lb/>ſters. This gave them Opportu- <lb/>nities of inſinuating themſelves in- <lb/>to
        Nurſes, Servants, and other <lb/>weak Perſons attending the Sick; <lb/>and by their Means of
        being ad- <lb/>mitted to give their Opinions; and <lb/>thence under Pretence of good
        <lb/>Husbandry for the Patient, to re- <lb/>peat the Phyſician's Bills, without <lb/>his
        Order; and at laſt to preſcribe <lb/>without his Advice. Yet I am <lb/>not, I muſt confeſs,
        for wholly <lb/>laying aſide this Order of Men, <lb/>they being, in my Opinion very
        <lb/>uſeful and ſerviceable in their pro- <lb/>per Station and Buſineſs, which is <lb/>the
        Preparation of Medicines ac- <pb n="49"/>
        <lb/>cording to the Preſcript of the Phy- <lb/>ſician. But when an Apothecary <lb/>deſerts
        his Station in the Shop, <lb/>neglects the Buſineſs of his Trade, <lb/>and runs about
        adviſing in all Di- <lb/>ſtempers; he becomes an Empi- <lb/>rick, and invades a Profeſſion
        which <lb/>he cannot be ſuppos'd to under- <lb/>ſtand. Can any thing be more a-
        <lb/>ſtoniſhing than the levelling of a <lb/>Learned Liberal Science, with a <lb/>Mechanick
        Trade of the Hand di- <lb/>rected by that Science? I could <lb/>wiſh the Fool's Character
        had been <lb/>preſerved in our Chronicles, or <lb/>that his Features were now to be
        <lb/>ſeen in his Statue of Braſs, who <lb/>firſt ſent for the Handy-craft La- <lb/>bourer of
        the Medicines to anſwer <lb/>any Queſtions concerning the Na- <lb/>ture of the Diſtemper. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There is certainly no more Re- <lb/>lation between the Buſineſs of an <lb/>Apothecary,
        and that of a Phyſi- <pb n="50"/>
        <lb/>cian, than between the Grinding of <lb/>Colours and the Art of Painting: <lb/>And
        therefore an Apothecary, who, <lb/>without Knowledge of the <hi rend="italic">Prære-
          <lb/>quiſita</hi>, pretends to the Practice of <lb/>Phyſick, is altogether as ridicu-
        <lb/>lous as a Colour-grinder, who, <lb/>without any Skill in Drawing, <lb/>ſhould preſume
        to manage a Pen- <lb/>cil. The one may hear the Pa- <lb/>tients examin'd, make up the Me-
        <lb/>dicines himſelf, and obſerve their <lb/>Effects; the other may ſee the firſt
        <lb/>Stroaks chalk'd out, prepare the <lb/>Colours himſelf, and afterwards <lb/>ſee his
        Maſter at Work; yet nei- <lb/>ther of them, without being firſt <lb/>inſtructed in the
        various Rules as <lb/>well as firſt Rudiments of the re- <lb/>ſpective Arts, ſhall enter
        into the <lb/>Skill of either the Phyſician or <lb/>Painter, tho' they look'd on them
        <lb/>till Dooms-day. What Pity 'tis <lb/>the Imitations of both cannot be e- <pb n="51"/>
        <lb/>qually expos'd to view, that the <lb/>unskilful Management of the one <lb/>might be as
        conſpicuous as would <lb/>be the ridiculous dawbing of the <lb/>other. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There is alſo another Body of <lb/>Men, I mean the Surgeons, who <lb/>notoriouſly
        enough (tho' not in- <lb/>deed ſo frequently in great Towns <lb/>as the Apothecaries) invade
        the <lb/>Profeſſion of Phyſick. But as the <lb/>Rules above-mention'd are ſuffi- <lb/>cient
        to diſtinguiſh an Empirical Pre- <lb/>tender from a Qualified Practitio- <lb/>ner; ſo by the
        Application of thoſe <lb/>Rules to the Surgeons, 'tis very ea- <lb/>ſily demonſtrable, that
        they cannot <lb/>but come under the Denomination <lb/>of Quacks in Phyſick. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Tho' from what has been alrea- <lb/>dy advanc'd, both concerning the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Prærequiſita</hi> and the Concluſions <lb/>which have been drawn from the
        <lb/>Enumeration of them, it may ſeem <pb n="52"/>
        <lb/>altogether needleſs; yet I ſhall now <lb/>proceed to offer three or four Rea- <lb/>ſons
        more, which will further de- <lb/>monſtrate the Neceſſity of a Re- <lb/>gulation in Phyſick:
        And thoſe <lb/>may be ſaid to regard, <list rend="indentall space">
          <item rend="hanging">
            <lb/>I. The Good of the Publick in <lb/>General. </item>
          <item rend="hanging">
            <lb/>II. The Univerſities in Parti- <lb/>cular. </item>
          <item>
            <lb/>III. The Art of Phyſick it ſelf. </item>
          <item>
            <lb/>IV. The Regular Profeſſors of it. </item>
        </list>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>I. The firſt Reaſon then for the <lb/>Neceſſity of ſuch a Regulation <lb/>(concerns the
        Good of the Publick <lb/>and) is the Loſs of her Majeſties <lb/>Subjects. And if I affirm
        that the <lb/>Encouragement of Quacks tends as <lb/>much to the diſpeopling of the
        <lb/>Kingdom as the Wars; The Com- <lb/>putation muſt be allow'd to be mo- <pb n="53"/>
        <lb/>deſt, provided they kill as many <lb/>in other Parts of the Kingdom as <lb/>they do in
        thoſe within the Sphere <lb/>of my own Obſervation. But the <lb/>Truth of this Aſſertion
        will more <lb/>evidently appear to any one who <lb/>does but fairly conſider the Num-
        <lb/>ber of Quacks with which every <lb/>Corner of this Kingdom has the <lb/>Misfortune to
        abound. For what <lb/>but the moſt diſmal Execution up- <lb/>on the Lives, or the moſt
        dreadful <lb/>Deſtruction of Mankind, can be ex- <lb/>pected from ſuch a Prodigious
        <lb/>Number of Men, who under- <lb/>ſtanding not what they profeſs; <lb/>may truly be ſaid
        to be Qualified, <lb/>as they are Licenc'd, to kill. And <lb/>tho' the moſt horrid
        Slaughters are <lb/>daily committed without any Fear <lb/>of Puniſhment or Reproof; yet 'tis
        <lb/>not a more melancholy Reflection <lb/>to conſider what a vaſt Number of <lb/>Men fall
        by the Hands of theſe <pb n="53"/>
        <lb/>Executioners, than that the Execu- <lb/>tioners themſelves ſhould eſcape <lb/>the Hands
        of Publick Juſtice. I <lb/>am not able to expreſs my Indig- <lb/>nation againſt ſuch
        preſumptuous <lb/>Homicides: They ought to be ex- <lb/>tirpated, if not at once, yet by
        <lb/>Degrees, as the Wolves out of the <lb/>Kingdom. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But to return; I hope to be ex- <lb/>cus'd (for whoſoever is well appriz'd <lb/>of her
        Powers may be pardon'd) for <lb/>aſſerting, That it is better truſting <lb/>to Nature than
        to an ignorant Pre- <lb/>tender in Phyſick. That Phyſicians <lb/>are only Servants to
        Nature, and <lb/>that ſhe is <hi rend="italic">Morborum Medicatrix</hi>, are <lb/>Truths
        known to the Ancients, <lb/>and confirm'd by the irrefragable <lb/>Experience of the
        Moderns. And <lb/>as Nature alone will conquer ſome <lb/>Diſeaſes, and judiciouſly aſſiſted
        <lb/>the greateſt part; ſo nothing is a <lb/>brighter Demonſtration of the <pb n="55"/>
        <lb/>Greatneſs of her Strength, than that <lb/>even the Miſmanagement of Nur- <lb/>ſes,
        Apothecaries and other Quacks, <lb/>is not able to hinder the Recovery <lb/>of very large
        Numbers, which fall <lb/>under their Hands. The greateſt <lb/>part of the Symptoms of
        Diſeaſes <lb/>are the Efforts of Nature, but <lb/>which Efforts being eaſily diſturb'd,
        <lb/>or ſoon oppos'd, require the moſt <lb/>ſtrict and wary Obſervance, and <lb/>without
        Judgment, we may ſooner <lb/>injure than aſſiſt her; ſooner op- <lb/>preſs than relieve her.
        A Phyſici- <lb/>an ought therefore religiouſly to <lb/>obſerve and obey the Motions of
        <lb/>Nature, to look upon them as his <lb/>ſureſt Guides in the Cure of any <lb/>Diſtemper,
        and to be advis'd, ac- <lb/>cording to them, what to do, and <lb/>when, and in what manner
        to pro- <lb/>ceed. The Art of Phyſick is not <lb/>underſtood till the Artiſt compre-
        <lb/>hends, in the Words of my Lord <pb n="56"/>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Bacon</hi>, <q rend="italic">Quid Natura ferat, &amp; faciat </q>.
        <lb/>But if the Calamities of the Sick <lb/>are encreas'd by the very Means <lb/>which are
        uſed for their Relief; if <lb/>inſtead of carefully aſſiſting Na- <lb/>ture in her
        Progreſſes to the Pre- <lb/>ſervation of Life, ſhe be clogg'd <lb/>with uſeleſs and
        inſignificant, or <lb/>oppreſs'd with dangerous and de- <lb/>ſtructive Applications: I may
        juſt- <lb/>ly conclude the Condition of thoſe <lb/>People who have the Misfortune to
        <lb/>fall under ſuch Hands, to be indeed <lb/>a very deplorable one; and the <lb/>Loſs of
        her Majeſties Subjects, from <lb/>the fatal Miſmanagement of ſo vaſt <lb/>a Number of
        Quacks, to be con- <lb/>ſequently ſo very great, that <lb/>the Encouragement of them may
        <lb/>truly be ſaid to tend as much to the <lb/>diſpeopling of the Kingdom as the <lb/>Wars. </p>
      <pb n="57"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>II. Another Argument for the <lb/>Neceſſity of a Regulation in Phy- <lb/>ſick, is, that
        the Encouragement <lb/>of Empiriciſm has already been a <lb/>very great, and will hereafter
        be a <lb/>far greater Detriment to the Uni- <lb/>verſities: For it can never be ſup-
        <lb/>pos'd, that Men will be at the Ex- <lb/>pence of ſending their Sons to any <lb/>of the
        Seminaries of Good Litera- <lb/>ture and ingenuous Education, <lb/>when the Honours and
        Employ- <lb/>ments of a Faculty may be obtain'd <lb/>without it, and there is ſo little
        <lb/>Diſtinction made between a Regu- <lb/>lar and an <hi rend="italic">extempore</hi>
        Doctor. The <lb/>Apothecaries, and other Quacks, <lb/>now openly avow their Reſolutions
        <lb/>of ſeizing on the Practice of Phy- <lb/>ſick; and of excluding in time all <lb/>the
        Univerſity Phyſicians. They <lb/>give not only Examples, but alſo <lb/>Aſſurances of Succeſs
        to all the In- <pb n="58"/>
        <lb/>truders into Divinity, and others, <lb/>of the pretended Education in the <lb/>Liberal
        Sciences. It would indeed <lb/>be no great Matter of Wonder or <lb/>Complaint, were
        Empiricks encou- <lb/>raged only by the Ordinary Sort of <lb/>People; or as the <hi
          rend="italic">French</hi> call them, <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Petits Gens</hi>; there
        being, as I <lb/>have often obſerv'd, a Sort of Sym- <lb/>pathy between Underſtandings.
        <lb/>But 'tis very unaccountably ſurpri- <lb/>zing, and a juſt Matter of Com- <lb/>plaint,
        that any of the diſtinguiſh'd <lb/>Part of Mankind ſhould venture e- <lb/>ven in dangerous
        Caſes to employ <lb/>ſuch illiterate, and conſequently <lb/>ignorant Pretenders. And what
        <lb/>ſtill enhances my Amazement is, <lb/>that any of thoſe Gentlemen, and <lb/>eſpecially
        any of the Clergy, who <lb/>have had the Happineſs of an Uni- <lb/>verſity Education; ſhould
        give any <lb/>manner of Encouragement to this <lb/>ſort of People. They have all laid <pb
          n="59"/>
        <lb/>themſelves under the higheſt Ob- <lb/>ligations of Preſerving the Honour <lb/>and
        Dignity of thoſe Fountains of <lb/>Learning. And the Phyſicians of <lb/>the Soul in
        particular being obliged <lb/>to viſit their Pariſhioners in Sick- <lb/>neſs, ought not only
        to inform <lb/>them that it is their Duty, but to <lb/>preſs them alſo to apply to the
        <lb/>Phyſicians of the Body, whom the <lb/>Divine Laws <note n="*" place="bottom"
          rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Eccleſiaſt. 38. 1—12. </p>
        </note> as well as our own <lb/>have appointed; inſtead of either <lb/>making uſe of
        Empiricks them- <lb/>ſelves, or adviſing others to make <lb/>uſe of them. I can never
        ſufficient- <lb/>ly deplore theſe Indignities offer'd <lb/>to our Univerſities, nor ever e-
        <lb/>nough blame and condemn the A- <lb/>bettors and Promoters of them; <lb/>but am not
        without Hopes that ſuch <lb/>growing Miſchiefs as theſe are, <pb n="60"/>
        <lb/>will ſometime be thought worthy <lb/>the Conſideration of thoſe in whom <lb/>alone is
        lodg'd the Power of Re- <lb/>dreſſing them. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>III. Another Argument for the <lb/>Neceſſity of a Regulation in Phy- <lb/>ſick, regards
        the Art it ſelf; the <lb/>Encouragement of Quacks and Em- <lb/>piricks threatning the Ruin
        of the <lb/>Profeſſion as well as of the People. <lb/>'Twould be no very difficult Task to
        <lb/>demonſtrate the Certainty of the <lb/>Medical Principles, and conſequent- <lb/>ly the
        real Uſefulneſs of Phyſick to <lb/>Mankind. But ſuch an Attempt <lb/>does not at all ſeem
        neceſſary in <lb/>my preſent Deſign; becauſe 'tis not <lb/>to be ſuppos'd, that Perſons
        ſhould <lb/>apply themſelves even to the moſt <lb/>ignorant Pretenders in Phyſick, un-
        <lb/>leſs ſuch Perſons really thought they <lb/>ſhould receive ſome Benefit from <lb/>the
        Directions of thoſe to whom they <pb n="61"/>
        <lb/>did apply. Yet notwithſtanding <lb/>Phyſick is undoubtedly eſtabliſh'd <lb/>upon ſuch
        Principles as do wholly <lb/>free it from thoſe Reproaches of <lb/>Uncertainty which it has
        often, <lb/>tho' falſly, been charg'd with; it <lb/>muſt, at the ſame time, be con-
        <lb/>feſs'd, that the Malignity of ſome <lb/>Acute, and the Stubbornneſs of ſome
        <lb/>Chronical Diſeaſes, do often elude <lb/>all the Aſſiſtances of Human Art: <lb/>For the
        moſt judicious and the <lb/>moſt experienc'd Phyſicians can <lb/>have no Power, as the Wiſe
        Man <lb/>expreſſes it, in the Day of Death. <lb/>But this can be no manner of Ob-
        <lb/>jection to the Certainty of the Me- <lb/>dical Principles, becauſe it may <lb/>happen
        and not proceed from any <lb/>Defect in the Rules of the Art it <lb/>ſelf. For from a due
        Conſidera- <lb/>tion of the Materials which com- <lb/>poſe a human Body, the Elegancy
        <lb/>of its Structure, and the continued <pb n="62"/>
        <lb/>Flux of its Parts, 'tis very evident <lb/>that it muſt neceſſarily be obnoxi- <lb/>ous
        to Diſorders, which are Diſea- <lb/>ſes; and ſooner or later as neceſſa- <lb/>rily to a
        Diſſolution, which is Death. <lb/>So that whoever is well appriz'd of <lb/>the wonderful
        Fabrick of the Hu- <lb/>man Body, how curiouſly contriv'd <lb/>and divinely faſhion'd a
        Machine <lb/>it is, may conſequently be rather <lb/>amaz'd at our living ſo long, than
        <lb/>at our dying ſo ſoon. But tho' it <lb/>muſt be acknowledg'd that it is not <lb/>in the
        Phyſician's Power at all times, <lb/>or in all Extremities, to retrieve or <lb/>preſerve his
        Patients from the Jaws <lb/>of Death, (ſince to die is an Entail <lb/>upon our Natures) yet
        it may with <lb/>Modeſty be affirm'd, Experience <lb/>abundantly proving it, that there
        <lb/>is ſo much Power in Medicines, <lb/>and ſo much Virtue in Methods, as <lb/>to enable
        him, if he but heedfully <lb/>weighs and judiciouſly applies them, <pb n="63"/>
        <lb/>to give Eaſe to ſuch as are in Pain, <lb/>Sleep to ſuch as are wearied out <lb/>with
        Watching, and Strength to <lb/>withſtand the Approaches of grim <lb/>and dreaded Death. But
        a Phy- <lb/>ſician cannot, I ſay, be ſuppos'd <lb/>capable of doing theſe things with-
        <lb/>out a due Conſideration of Circum- <lb/>ſtances, and a Judicious Applica- <lb/>tion of
        Medicines. For if Medi- <lb/>cines are promiſcuouſly us'd in all <lb/>Conſtitutions, or
        without Regard <lb/>to the Circumſtances of each Caſe, <lb/>'tis no Wonder they ſo often de-
        <lb/>ceive Men in their Expectations of <lb/>Succeſs. And therefore as the <lb/>Knowledge of
        the <hi rend="italic">Prærequiſita</hi> is <lb/>the only Means of Qualifying a <lb/>Man for
        a ſucceſsful Practice in <lb/>Phyſick, and conſequently of ad- <lb/>vancing the Credit and
        Reputation <lb/>of the Art; ſo the Ignorance of <lb/>Quacks, both of the Nature, Cau-
        <lb/>ſes, and Cure of Diſeaſes, muſt <pb n="64"/>
        <lb/>neceſſarily produce ſo many and <lb/>ſo groſs Miſmanagements as can- <lb/>not but
        extremely prejudice Man- <lb/>kind in their Opinion of the Art. <lb/>Their ill Succeſſes are
        doubtleſs <lb/>imputed to the Uncertainty of the <lb/>Art it ſelf, eſpecially by the Un-
        <lb/>diſtinguiſhing, which is much the <lb/>larger Part of Mankind; and Men <lb/>from their
        leſſen'd Opinion of it, <lb/>will by Degrees neglect to apply to <lb/>any Advice at all;
        whereas the <lb/>truly Noble and Divine Art it ſelf <lb/>ought by no Means to be charg'd
        <lb/>with what is only to be imputed <lb/>to the Ignorance of thoſe who pre- <lb/>tend to
        profeſs it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Beſides, 'tis a true and general <lb/>Obſervation, that Arts and Sciences <lb/>do
        improve and grow uſeful, accor- <lb/>ding to the Encouragement of thoſe <lb/>who profeſs
        them. But the fre- <lb/>quent Application to Quacks and <lb/>Empiricks, by Men of all Ranks
          <pb n="65"/>
        <lb/>and Degrees, even to the moſt ex- <lb/>alted Stations, is ſo publick and ſo <lb/>vaſt a
        Diſcouragement to the Pro- <lb/>feſſors of Phyſick, that it may truly <lb/>be ſaid to
        threaten the very Ruin <lb/>and Deſtruction of the Art it ſelf. <lb/>For as ſuch a
        Diſcouragement muſt <lb/>neceſſarily leſſen the Number of <lb/>the Profeſſors in Phyſick; ſo
        it will <lb/>conſequently obſtruct the glorious <lb/>Progreſs of the Art, by hindring
        <lb/>further Inventions, and future Im- <lb/>provements in it. And how inca- <lb/>pable the
        illiterate Pretenders in <lb/>Phyſick are of improving either <lb/>themſelves or the Art,
        has been al- <lb/>ready demonſtrated. We may then <lb/>very fairly ſuppoſe there will be but
        <lb/>few Students in Phyſick, if after all <lb/>the Labour and Pains of Acquiring <lb/>that
        Knowledge, and after all the <lb/>Expences of a Learned Education; <lb/>their Bread ſhall be
        taken off their <lb/>Trenchers, as we ſay, by every Il- <pb n="66"/>
        <lb/>literate Pretender. What a moſt <lb/>ingenious Author obſerves upon a- <lb/>nother
        Occaſion is very applicable <lb/>to this. If we conſider, ſays he, <lb/>the Expenſiveneſs of
        the Voyage, <lb/>which is made in ſearch of Know- <lb/>ledge, 'tis very hard the Under-
        <lb/>takers ſhould be plunder'd of what <lb/>they bring home by Privateers; <lb/>under the
        very Canon which ſhould <lb/>protect them. All which Conſide- <lb/>rations are ſufficient to
        ſhew, how <lb/>far the Encouragement of Quacks <lb/>and Empiricks obſtructs the Pro-
        <lb/>greſs of that glorious Art which <lb/>teaches the Recovery as well as the
        <lb/>Preſervation of Health; and con- <lb/>ſequently threatens the Ruin of the
        <lb/>Profeſſion as well as the People. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>IV. The fourth and laſt Argu- <lb/>ment which I ſhall offer for the <lb/>Neceſſity of a
        Regulation in the <lb/>Practice of Phyſick, regards the <pb n="67"/>
        <lb/>Phyſicians themſelves, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> That <lb/>no Profeſſion is ſo
        invaded with un- <lb/>qualify'd Pretenders, as theirs. I <lb/>do not doubt, but 'twill
        evidently <lb/>appear, that ſuch an Invaſion is <lb/>ſingular to the Profeſſion of Phy-
        <lb/>ſick, notwithſtanding what ſome <lb/>have endeavour'd, tho' without a- <lb/>ny Colour
        of Reaſon, to maintain. <lb/>'Tis well known that Divinity and <lb/>Law have their
        Paliſadoes and In- <lb/>trenchments; for who dare pretend <lb/>in their Pulpits or Courts,
        but <lb/>thoſe who are fairly initiated ac- <lb/>cording to Form and Cuſtom? <lb/>Whereas
        the Cobweb Fences of <lb/>Phyſick are every Day invaded, <lb/>any broken Weaver, Taylor,
        Shoe- <lb/>maker, or merry Andrew, dub- <lb/>bing himſelf a Doctor <hi rend="italic"
          >Extempore</hi>, <lb/>and ſetting up for an <hi rend="sc">Æsculapius</hi>. <lb/>So that
        Quacking and Ale-keeping <lb/>are now a days become the laſt <lb/>Employments, to which Men
        of <pb n="68"/>
        <lb/>decay'd Fortunes apply themſelves <lb/>to get Bread. And as none but <lb/>thoſe who are
        fairly Initiated or <lb/>Admitted do preſume upon the <lb/>Profeſſions either of Divinity or
        <lb/>Law; ſo there is but one way of <lb/>Initiating or Admitting Perſons <lb/>into the
        Exerciſe of them. Where- <lb/>as on the other ſide, Men are ad- <lb/>mitted to practiſe
        Phyſick by the <lb/>moſt Unreaſonable, and as they are <lb/>at preſent manag'd, I may with
        Im- <lb/>punity, I hope, venture to ſay, <lb/>ſcandalous Methods; I mean by <lb/>Licences
        out of the Eccleſiaſtical <lb/>Courts. But that the Hardſhip of <lb/>the Phyſicians Caſe may
        be ſet in <lb/>the cleareſt Light, 'twill be neceſ- <lb/>ſary to enquire into the original
        <lb/>End and Deſign, as well as pre- <lb/>ſent Management of ſuch Eccleſia- <lb/>ſtical
        Licences: I am well enough <lb/>ſatisfy'd that their original End and <lb/>Deſign was very
        good and laudable. <pb n="69"/>
        <lb/>The Statute of <hi rend="italic">Hen.</hi> 8. 3. <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)"
          n="*">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* <hi rend="italic">Vid.</hi> Pulton's <hi rend="italic">Statutes</hi>. </p>
        </note> very <lb/>pathetically expreſſes the Inconve- <lb/>niencies enſuing by Ignorant Per-
        <lb/>ſons practiſing Phyſick, to the high <lb/>Diſpleaſure of God, great Infamy <lb/>to the
        Faculty, and the grievous <lb/>Hurt, Damage, and Deſtruction of <lb/>his Majeſties liege
        Subjects. For <lb/>all which Reaſons it enacts that the <lb/>Biſhop of each Dioceſe, or his
        Vi- <lb/>car-General, be empower'd to ex- <lb/>amine all thoſe (except Graduates) <lb/>who
        ſhall practice Phyſick in that <lb/>Dioceſe. But the Wiſdom of the ſame <lb/>Statute is no
        leſs remarkable in obli- <lb/>ging either of them to call to him <lb/>ſuch expert Perſons in
        the ſaid Fa- <lb/>culty, as his Diſcretion ſhall think <lb/>fit. For I hope, I may venture
        to <lb/>declare my Opinion thus far, that <lb/>I cannot but think the Gentlemen <lb/>of
        thoſe Courts very unfit Judges <pb n="70"/>
        <lb/>of a Man's Capacity to practice <lb/>Phyſick. And therefore in 14 and <lb/>15 of <hi
          rend="italic">Hen.</hi> 8. 5. it is ſtill, I think, <lb/>more prudentially enacted, That
        <lb/>none ſhall practice in the Country, <lb/>without a Teſtimonial of his Suffi-
        <lb/>ciency from the Preſident of the <lb/>College of Phyſicians, and three of <lb/>the
        Electors. I ſhall not here pretend <lb/>to determine how far this poſterior <lb/>may be ſaid
        to abrogate or null <lb/>the prior Act. But the very End <lb/>and Deſign of theſe
        Eccleſiaſtical <lb/>Licences, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> Prevention of the
        <lb/>Inconveniences enſuing by Ignorant <lb/>Perſons practiſing Phyſick, is not <lb/>only,
        as they are manag'd at pre- <lb/>ſent, wholly fruſtrated, but entire- <lb/>ly perverted: For
        they are now a- <lb/>days ſo far from preventing, that <lb/>they are the only Means of
        bringing <lb/>thoſe Miſchiefs and Inconvenien- <lb/>cies upon us, which the Statute
        <lb/>mentions, by admitting ſuch Shoals <pb n="71"/>
        <lb/>of unqualified Perſons to practice <lb/>Phyſick. That the Examination <lb/>previous to
        Admiſſion was former- <lb/>ly ſtrict and ſevere, is as cer- <lb/>tain as that now a days
        Perſons are <lb/>admitted without any manner of <lb/>Examination at all. Nay, ſo far <lb/>is
        the Practice of theſe Courts cor- <lb/>rupted, and the very End and De- <lb/>ſign of theſe
        Licences perverted, <lb/>that they are now a days granted e- <lb/>ven from a Teſtimonial of
        two Li- <lb/>centiates. Can any thing then be <lb/>more evidently apparent than the
        <lb/>Neceſſity of regulating theſe Mat- <lb/>ters? For tho' (as I before obſerv'd) <lb/>the
        firſt End and Deſign of theſe <lb/>Licences was undoubtedly Good <lb/>and Laudable, and tho'
        they were <lb/>not Injurious (and I am apt to think <lb/>they were not originally deſign'd
        <lb/>to be or indeed really were) to the <lb/>Regular Phyſicians; yet if the Rea- <lb/>ſon
        of a Law ceaſes, the Law <pb n="71"/>
        <lb/>it ſelf ought to be annull'd. But <lb/>ſince the Method of Examina- <lb/>tion is ſo
        very much alter'd; the <lb/>Original End and Deſign of <lb/>theſe Licences, ſo manifeſtly
        per- <lb/>verted, and they themſelves be- <lb/>come ſo vaſtly Injurious both to <lb/>the
        Faculty, and the Regular Pro- <lb/>feſſors of Phyſick; theſe very Con- <lb/>ſiderations are
        ſo many Arguments <lb/><hi rend="italic">a fortiori</hi> for the Neceſſity of a Re-
        <lb/>gulation. And now I appeal to <lb/>the ſenſible Part of Mankind, whe- <lb/>ther any
        Profeſſion be ſo invaded <lb/>with unqualified Pretenders as <lb/>Phyſick; and conſequently
        whe- <lb/>ther the Phyſicians have not the <lb/>greateſt Reaſon in the World to
        <lb/>complain. And to whom ſhould <lb/>they complain, but to the Legiſla- <lb/>ture? For
        doubtleſs, it was one <lb/>of the Ends of Parliamentary In- <lb/>ſtitution to receive the
        Complaints, <lb/>and redreſs the Grievances of the <pb n="73"/>
        <lb/>Injur'd. Nay, do we not find the <lb/>Legiſlature frequently interpoſing <lb/>in other
        Profeſſions to prevent or <lb/>remove Grievances; but what Re- <lb/>gard has there been to
        the moſt e- <lb/>normous ones in Phyſick? Are <lb/>not our Lives worthy the Care <lb/>of the
        Laws, as well as our Souls <lb/>or Eſtates? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I ſhall now endeavour to obviate <lb/>ſome Objections which are general- <lb/>ly made,
        tho' indeed without any <lb/>Shadow of Reaſon, againſt what I <lb/>have advanc'd. And it has
        been <lb/>objected in the firſt Place, that ſuch <lb/>a Regulation would be an Abridg-
        <lb/>ment of the Natural Rights and <lb/>Liberties of Mankind, to follow <lb/>thoſe
        Employments whereby they <lb/>may get a Livelihood. I ſhould <lb/>be the moſt unwilling Man
        in the <lb/>World to advance any thing which <lb/>has the leaſt Tendency to ſuch an
        <lb/>Abridgment. No, I have the ten- <pb n="74"/>
        <lb/>dereſt Regard to their Civil as well <lb/>as Religious Properties. But this
        <lb/>Objection would equally hold a- <lb/>gainſt the Suppreſſion of Gaming <lb/>and other
        diſorderly Houſes, of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Royal Oak</hi>, and other ſuch publick
        <lb/>Nuſances. For if the Good of the <lb/>Publick ought not to be conſider'd <lb/>and
        prefer'd to that of private Per- <lb/>ſons, which I take to be an undenia- <lb/>ble Maxim in
        all Governments; the <lb/>Natural Liberties of Mankind may <lb/>as properly be ſaid to be
        abridg'd <lb/>by ſuch a Suppreſſion, as by ſuch <lb/>a Regulation as I contend for. The
        <lb/>ſame Anſwer will ſerve to ſome <lb/>other Objections, which are much <lb/>of the ſame
        Nature, and of no <lb/>greater Force than the former, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
        <lb/>That the Legiſlature is under no <lb/>manner of Obligation to concern it <lb/>ſelf in
        Miſchiefs which Men vo- <lb/>luntarily pull upon themſelves; <lb/>That all flouriſhing
        Governments <pb n="75"/>
        <lb/>will encourage their People ſome <lb/>Way or other to employ them- <lb/>ſelves; That
        every Man is <hi rend="italic">ſui Ju- <lb/>ris</hi>, and has a Natural Right of <lb/>making
        Uſe of any Body he <lb/>pleaſes, and if he be ſatisfy'd with <lb/>the Riſque he runs, what
        has any <lb/>one to ſay in contradiction to his <lb/>Humour. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I now proceed to invalidate ſome <lb/>Excuſes which are frequently made <lb/>in
        Extenuation of thoſe Practices <lb/>which I have been condemning. <lb/>And a great many
        People I am apt <lb/>to believe, will think to clear them- <lb/>ſelves from the Imputation
        of En- <lb/>couraging Quacks and Empiricks, <lb/>by ſaying, That it is only in the
        <lb/>Beginning of Diſeaſes they apply <lb/>to them; That in Caſes of Dan- <lb/>ger, they
        generally have Recourſe <lb/>to better Advice; and, That this <lb/>Cuſtom being ſo very
        common, <lb/>does not ſeem to need any manner <pb n="76"/>
        <lb/>of Excuſe: But upon a ſtricter En- <lb/>quiry into this Matter, the Cuſtom <lb/>of
        firſt ſending for an Apothecary <lb/>or other Quack, will not, I am apt <lb/>to think,
        appear the leſs ridicu- <lb/>lous, for being ſo frequent. For, <lb/>as the Beginning of a
        Diſtemper is <lb/>a very ſeaſonable Opportunity of <lb/>Aſſiſting Nature, towards the Re-
        <lb/>covery of Health, ſo the Conduct <lb/>of thoſe People cannot be ſufficient- <lb/>ly
        condemn'd, who neglect to im- <lb/>prove that Opportunity, by not <lb/>then calling in a
        judicious Aſſiſtant. <lb/>But far more egregious is the Fol- <lb/>ly of thoſe who then apply
        them- <lb/>ſelves to any of the Empirical <lb/>Tribe; it being impoſſible, as has <lb/>been
        obſerv'd, but ſuch Perſons <lb/>muſt make either inſignificant and <lb/>uſeleſs, or
        dangerous and deſtru- <lb/>ctive Applications. And as the <lb/>Conſideration of neglecting
        the Im- <lb/>provement of this Opportunity <pb n="77"/>
        <lb/>ſufficiently condemns the Applica- <lb/>tion to thoſe who are call'd ſafe <lb/>Men;
        who, as they ſay themſelves, <lb/>will do no Hurt if they do no Good; <lb/>ſo the
        preſumptuous Tamperers, <lb/>on the other Side, may not only ir- <lb/>reperably injure the
        Patient, but ſo <lb/>quite change the Face of a Diſtem- <lb/>per, as to render it very
        difficult, if <lb/>poſſible, for even a judicious Phyſi- <lb/>cian, when call'd in, to
        diſcover <lb/>its Nature. But when a Phyſici- <lb/>an has the Care of a Diſeaſe from
        <lb/>the Beginning, he is able to make <lb/>right Obſervations of the Progreſs <lb/>and
        Alteration of its Symptoms; <lb/>and conſequently, not only to form <lb/>a ſurer
        Prognoſtication of its Event, <lb/>but more effectually to aſſiſt Nature <lb/>in the
        Preſervation of Life. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Again, there are others who pre- <lb/>tend to excuſe themſelves for not ap- <lb/>plying
        to the beſt Advice upon the <lb/>Account of ſaving Charges; tho' this <pb n="78"/>
        <lb/>Conſideration can be of no manner <lb/>of Force, unleſs it can be thought an
        <lb/>Excuſe to have the Chance of be- <lb/>ing kill'd cheap. But would thoſe <lb/>very
        People, who ſatisfy themſelves <lb/>with the Advice of an Empirical Pre- <lb/>tender, but
        uſe their Arithmetick, <lb/>they would ſoon be convinc'd, they <lb/>acted as much againſt
        their Intereſt <lb/>as Reaſon. For by phyſicking the <lb/>Symptoms, and neglecting the
        <lb/>Cauſe of a Diſeaſe, the Length of <lb/>the Bill, as well as the Diſtemper, <lb/>muſt be
        conſequently encreas'd. <lb/>'Tis not the colluſive Pretence of <lb/>giving Advice without a
        Fee, <lb/>which can or ought to be eſteem'd <lb/>an Equivalent. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There are ſome again who pre- <lb/>tend to excuſe themſelves by plead- <lb/>ing, that
        thoſe to whom they ap- <lb/>ply, are Maſters of ſome magni- <lb/>fied Receipt, or pretended
        infalli- <lb/>ble Remedy for this or that Diſtem- <lb/>per. </p>
      <pb n="79"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But the Vanity of confiding in <lb/>ſuch Trifles has been ſufficiently ex- <lb/>pos'd
        by the plaineſt Demonſtration, <lb/>That the moſt celebrated Prepara- <lb/>tions even of the
        Philoſophers by <lb/>Fire are not capable of curing Diſ- <lb/>eaſes, without a Judicious and
        Me- <lb/>thodical Application. I ſhall there- <lb/>fore only ſubjoin another Confide-
        <lb/>ration, which is an unanſwerable <lb/>Argument of their Inſufficiency, <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">viz.</hi> That none of theſe magnified <lb/>Receipts or infallible <hi
          rend="italic">Noſtrums</hi> have <lb/>ever ſtood the Teſt of an Age. <lb/>Accordingly, our
        very own Experi- <lb/>ence is ſo far from confirming, that it <lb/>daily contradicts the
        Pretended Vir- <lb/>tues which the Alchymical Writers, <lb/>and the publick Venders of Quack
        <lb/>Medicines, with a peremptory Aſ- <lb/>ſurance aſcribe to them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>'Tis urg'd again, that tho' it muſt <lb/>be confeſs'd, that very eaſily cu- <lb/>rable
        Diſeaſes are often made fatal <pb n="80"/>
        <lb/>by Quacks; yet 'tis equally true, <lb/>that ſeveral Perſons recover under <lb/>their
        Hands. To this I anſwer, <lb/>That they recover, 'tis true, when <lb/>the Patients have more
        of their na- <lb/>tural Vigour than the others are <lb/>able to deſtroy, and rather to the
        <lb/>Strength of Nature is the happy E- <lb/>vent to be aſcrib'd, than to the <lb/>Judgment
        of the Medicinal Admi- <lb/>niſtrator; ſuch Particular Caſes <lb/>being no more Arguments of
        their <lb/>Skill than a blind Man's throwing <lb/>Stones, and hitting ſome People in <lb/>a
        Crowd is an Argument of the <lb/>Goodneſs of his Aim. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Having thus fairly and impar- <lb/>tially repreſented the preſent State <lb/>of Phyſick
        in this Kingdom, plainly <lb/>indicated the Number of Quacks, <lb/>with which it is ſo
        unhappy as to <lb/>abound; and fully demonſtrated <lb/>not only the Impoſſibility of their
        <lb/>being ſerviceable, but the abſolute <pb n="81"/>
        <lb/>Neceſſity of their being injurious <lb/>to it, in the Exerciſe of the Pro- <lb/>feſſion
        they pretend to: I think no- <lb/>thing can be more conſequentially <lb/>evident than the
        Neceſſity of a Re- <lb/>gulation in the Practice of Phyſick. <lb/>And I am not without
        Hopes, that <lb/>ſome of the above-mention'd Rea- <lb/>ſons, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> The
        Good of her Ma- <lb/>jeſty's Subjects in General; The <lb/>Honour and Advantages of Her
        <lb/>Univerſities in particular; The <lb/>Life and Reputation of ſo uſeful an <lb/>Art as
        Phyſick; or the Particular <lb/>Hardſhips, which the Gentlemen <lb/>of that Faculty have the
        Misfor- <lb/>tune to labour under; I am not <lb/>without Hopes, I ſay, that ſome <lb/>of
        theſe Reaſons will ſo far influ- <lb/>ence our Legiſlators, as to prevail <lb/>with them to
        take the Repreſenta- <lb/>tion of this Caſe into their imme- <lb/>diate Conſideration: It is
        a Caſe <lb/>undoubtedly, of the greateſt Mo- <pb n="82"/>
        <lb/>ment and Importance; for as the <lb/>Life and Health of every individu- <lb/>al
        Subject, ſo conſequently all <lb/>Ranks and Qualities, all Parties <lb/>and Diſtinctions of
        Men are in the <lb/>higheſt Degree, and equally con- <lb/>cern'd in it. And as the great Im-
        <lb/>portance of the Debate makes it not <lb/>unworthy the Cognizance and En- <lb/>quiry of
        our Legiſlators; ſo the ve- <lb/>ry Nature of it ſeems more particu- <lb/>larly to recommend
        it ſelf to their <lb/>Conſideration. For 'tis certainly a <lb/>great Shame, as well as an
        Unhap- <lb/>pineſs, that in a Kingdom where ſo <lb/>many good Laws are in Force, and <lb/>in
        which as much Care is taken of the <lb/>Liberties and Properties of the Sub- <lb/>ject, as
        in any Nation upon Earth, <lb/>the People ſhould lie open and un- <lb/>guarded in their
        deareſt and moſt va- <lb/>luable Enjoyments, Health and Life. <lb/>There is nothing,
        therefore, which <lb/>in my Opinion ſeems more plainly <pb n="83"/>
        <lb/>to demonſtrate a Deficiency in our <lb/>Laws, than the Want of ſome to <lb/>Regulate
        the groſs Miſcarriages and <lb/>enormous Abuſes in the Practice of <lb/>Phyſick. The College
        of Phyſicians, <lb/>'tis true, is veſted with ſome Mea- <lb/>ſure of Authority; But as their
        Au- <lb/>thority is confin'd to certain Limits; <lb/>ſo, through Want of an Enlarge-
        <lb/>ment of their Charter, it is not at <lb/>preſent of that Uſe as ſeems corre-
        <lb/>ſpondent to the Deſign of its Royal <lb/>Inſtitution: But either by enlarging <lb/>the
        Charter to the College of Phy- <lb/>ſicians, or by ſuch Ways and Means <lb/>as the Wiſdom of
        our Legiſlature <lb/>ſhall better approve of; there ſeems <lb/>nothing more feaſible than to
        make <lb/>a ſufficient Proviſion againſt theſe <lb/>pernicious and deſtructive Practices.
        <lb/>And whenever it ſhall ſeem expedi- <lb/>ent to thoſe who ſit at the Helm of <lb/>our
        excellent Government, to un- <lb/>dertake ſo uſeful and neceſſary a <pb n="84"/>
        <lb/>Work; I humbly recommend, </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>1. That the diſtinct Spheres of <lb/>Phyſicians, Surgeons, and Apothe- <lb/>caries, be
        limited and ſpecified; <lb/>The Surgeons reſtrain'd to their pro- <lb/>per Buſineſs; the
        Apothecaries con- <lb/>fin'd to their Shops; and all illite- <lb/>rate and Empirical
        Pretenders in <lb/>Phyſick ſuppreſs'd. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>2. That a Proviſion be made for <lb/>the Poor to have their Share in the <lb/>beſt
        Advice and Medicines. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As the Want of ſuch a Regulation <lb/>in Phyſick is one of the greateſt <lb/>Flaws in
        our Conſtitution; and <lb/>highly reflects upon the beſt of Go- <lb/>vernments, ſo ſuch a
        Regulation <lb/>would undoubtedly tend as much to <lb/>the Honour of our Nation, as the
        <lb/>Preſervation of its People; and <lb/>which not only the preſent, but all
        <lb/>ſucceeding Generations will have the <lb/>greateſt Reaſon in the World to ap-
        <lb/>plaud. </p>
      <trailer rend="italic align-center">
        <lb/>FINIS. </trailer>
      <gap reason="sampling" quantity="6" unit="pages"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
