<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Parker: An Essay upon the Duty of Physicians and Patients</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Samuel Parker</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">An ESSAY upon the DUTY of Physicians and Patients, the Dignity of
              Medicine, and the Prudential of Practice. In two DIALOGUES.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T33470</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T33470"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed by George James for Henry Clements at the Half-Moon in St.
                  Paul's Church-Yard, MDCCXV.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1715</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="6"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="134"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108326877</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Public welfare and institutional"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="6"/>
    <body>
      <pb n="1"/>
      <figure>
        <figDesc>An ornamental horizontal column. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/><hi rend="size(1.25)">AN </hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="size(2.5)">ESSAY </hi>
        <lb/>UPON THE <lb/><hi rend="size(2.0)">DUTIES </hi>
        <lb/>OF <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)"><hi rend="italic">Phyſicians</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
            >Patients</hi>, &amp;c. </hi>
      </head>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>An ornamented horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <div>
        <head rend="sc align-center space">
          <lb/>Olympia. Jasilla. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi>
          <hi rend="dc(4)">M</hi>ADAM, your Servant. I <lb/>give you Joy of your Re- <lb/>covery,
          but am ſorry to ſee <lb/>the Enemy Maſter of your <lb/>Face ſtill. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ja.</hi> I thank you, Madam. I am ſenſible <lb/>I owe the ſlow
          Return of my Health and my <lb/>Complexion to Miſmanagement. Had I <lb/>took no Advice or
          Phyſick but my own, or <lb/>my Aunt's, I had been better than ever I <lb/>was in my Life,
          two Months ago: But my <lb/>ſuperſtitious Brother could not be ſatisfy'd <lb/>'till
          Doctors and Apothecaries were ſent for. <pb n="2"/>
          <lb/>The Family Receipt-Book was not worthy <lb/>to be conſulted, but every thing muſt be
          <lb/>preſcrib'd and order'd in <hi rend="italic">Latin</hi>; as if the <lb/>Vulgar Tongue
          were as dangerous in Phy- <lb/>ſick, as the Papiſts make it in Divinity. <lb/>There was
          the uſual <hi rend="italic">Poſſe</hi> of Strokes crook- <lb/>ed and ſtreight, of Daſhes,
          and Dots, thoſe <lb/>coſtly Characters, which, for my part, I be- <lb/>lieve are only
          Show, and have no more <lb/>Meaning or Vertue in them, than the <lb/>Cant of a <hi
            rend="italic">High-German</hi> Artiſt over the Ex- <lb/>erciſe of his Fingers. However,
          the Phy- <lb/>ſician and his Confectioner had their Doſes <lb/>too in their Turn out of
          the Scrutore; and <lb/>ſo, you may be ſure, I was cur'd with all the <lb/>Deliberation and
          Art imaginable. If your <lb/>Mouth waters for the Philoſopher's Stone, <lb/>you may eaſily
          find it, Madam, in a Phyſi- <lb/>cian's Books, or an Apothecary's Gallipots. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi> Gently, good Lady: One would <lb/>think, by theſe peeviſh
          Reflections, your <lb/>Phyſician had been more unfriendly than you <lb/>repreſent him, and
          handed you out of a Fe- <lb/>ver into a Conſumption. <q rend="quotes">Such alas! is the
            <lb/>Pride of human Nature, </q> ſays <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5) italic">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Pleriq: ſunt qut malunt in ſua ignorantia peccare, quàm <lb/>alieno duce rectè
              facere. <hi rend="roman">Leon. Botallus, de Medic. &amp; Æ- <lb/>grot. Munere</hi>.
            </p>
          </note> a certain <lb/>Doctor, who ſeems to have been well ac- <lb/>quainted with it, that
          we had rather <lb/>
          <q rend="diple quotes">make forty falſe Steps, by following our <pb n="3"/>
            <lb/>own Advice, than one true one by taking <lb/>other People's. </q> Under Favour, you
          treat <lb/>the Faculty ill. Their Profeſſion is Signifi- <lb/>cant and Honourable. The
          Knowledge and <lb/>Learning it requires, are ſuch as anſwer up <lb/>to the Dignity of the
          Mind, and deſerve an <lb/>earneſt Application. Its Object is wide <lb/>and valuable. 'Tis
          the great Bleſſing of <lb/>Health, of which <hi rend="italic">Orpheus</hi>, in his Hymn
          to't, <lb/>ſays, <q rend="italic">The World's an uſeleſs Maſs when thou'rt <lb/>away </q>.
          And its Importance reaches farther <lb/>ſtill. The Buſineſs of it is not only to ma-
          <lb/>nage the Mechaniſm, and keep Diſſolution <lb/>at Bay; but Action, Employment, and Du-
          <lb/>ty, depend in a great Meaſure upon the <lb/>Phyſician. Without him, great Part of the
          <lb/>World would be loſt upon us; and the <lb/>Bounties of Providence imperfectly under-
          <lb/>ſtood. Human Nature would not know <lb/>the Eſtate ſhe is born to. Our Bodies would
          <lb/>be never the better for half the Proviſion God <lb/>has made for them; and the Mind,
          when in- <lb/>commoded by the Body, would often find <lb/>herſelf at a Loſs for a Remedy.
          Let me <lb/>add, <q rend="diple">That the Conſiderableneſs of the <lb/>Profeſſion </q>(as
            <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5) italic">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Mirandum non eſt, ſi ob negotii pondus, non ſolum vul- <lb/>gares homines, <hi
                rend="roman">&amp;c.</hi>
              <hi rend="roman">Gabriel a Fonſeca, Medic. OEconom.</hi>
            </p>
          </note> One, that had well weigh'd <lb/>it, obſerves) <q rend="diple quotes">appears too
            in the Extent <lb/>of its Juriſdiction, which takes in the <lb/>greateſt Monarchs, as
            well as the meaneſt <pb n="4"/>
            <lb/>Mortals. This holds the moſt abſolute <lb/>Princes in Coercion. Health itſelf does
            <lb/>not exempt them from Subjection to their <lb/>Phyſicians. And indeed 'tis a Homage
            <lb/>they do with Satisfaction; for they know <lb/>if they mutiny or murmur, they ſhall
            <lb/>ſmart for't. </q> And ſince, Madam, I have <lb/>now ſtept into Quotation, give me
          leave to <lb/>make farther Uſe of the Learned, and to <lb/>communicate what my little
          Reading affords <lb/>upon the Topick before us. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ja.</hi> Pray make the moſt of your Cauſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi> In general; <q rend="diple">To be qualify'd </q>(ſays <lb/>
          <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5) italic">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Nulla re ad Deum homines propius accedunt, <hi rend="roman">&amp;c.</hi>
              <hi rend="roman">Cic. <lb/>pro Ligario</hi>. </p>
          </note>
          <hi rend="italic">Tully</hi>) <q rend="diple">to conferr a good State of Health <lb/> and
            Habit of Body, implies a Sort of Affi- <lb/>nity to the Divine Attributes. </q>And <note
            place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.5) italic">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">†</hi>
              <unclear>Si</unclear> dare vitam proprium Dei munus eſt, <hi rend="roman">&amp;c.</hi>
              <hi rend="roman">Eraſmus. <lb/>Crocius</hi>. </p>
          </note> o- <lb/>thers obſerve to the ſame Effect, that, <q rend="diple">The <lb/>next
            Thing to giving Life, which is ſole- <lb/>ly in the Creator's Gift, is keeping it up
            <lb/>entire, and detaining it long. </q>I go on <lb/>with the ſame <note place="bottom"
            n="‖" rend="size(0.5) italic">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">‖</hi> Qui lymphatum, phreneticum, furioſum, reſtituit, <hi
                rend="roman">&amp;c.</hi>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">Eraſmus. Crocius</hi>, to the ſame Effect. </p>
          </note> Authors; <q rend="diple">He that recovers <lb/>a Madman, almoſt makes a Man of him
            in <lb/>the literal Meaning. He ſets a reaſonable <lb/>Being, as it were, together
            again. The <lb/>Divine may thank the Phyſician for many <lb/>a Penitent; If the Latter
            had not preſer- <pb n="5"/>
            <lb/>ved his Patient, the Former had miſs'd of <lb/>his Convert. A Lethargy makes a Man
            <lb/>deaf to the moſt Pathetick Addreſſes; and <lb/>the Confeſſor is like to do but
            little good <lb/>upon one that's held in his Bed. 'Till the <lb/>Brain and the Blood
            ſtand corrected in ſome <lb/>meaſure, there's no room for ghoſtly Ad- <lb/>vice. <note
              place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5) italic">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>* Parentibus nihil non debemus, quod per hos vitæ mu- <lb/>nus accepiſſe
                quodammodo videmur, <hi rend="roman">&amp;c.</hi>
                <hi rend="roman">Declam. in laud. <lb/>Art. Med.</hi>
              </p>
            </note> Every Man owes his Parents but <lb/>one Life, </q>(ſays <hi rend="italic"
            >Eraſmus</hi>) <q rend="diple quotes">and we think it a <lb/>great Debt; What Returns
            then may a <lb/>Phyſician challenge at that Man's Hands, <lb/>who ſtands indebted to him
            for ſeve- <lb/>ral? He that has interpoſed between <lb/>Us and Death in a Battle, and
            cut us out <lb/>a Retreat, when a ſtrong Body had ſhut us <lb/>in, is ſuch a Deliverer,
            as 'tis confeſs'd, has <lb/>a Title to very ſolemn Expreſſions of our <lb/>Gratitude.
            What does the Phyſician de- <lb/>ſerve then, that does as much for us every <lb/>Day?
            Agen; 'Till Phyſicians were in Buſi- <lb/>neſs; 'till Diſtempers came to be rightly
            <lb/>diſtinguiſh'd; and the <hi rend="italic">Materia Medica</hi> was <lb/>ſufficiently
            diſcover'd; how many People <lb/>dropt before their Time? And how many <lb/>that are now
            living and well, had never <lb/>been born, if the Art of bringing them <lb/>into the
            World had been leſs underſtood? </q>
          <pb n="6"/>
          <lb/>— But I'm unwilling to try your Patience <lb/>to the Length of my Collections. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ja.</hi> Let me ſee; have not I Authorities <lb/>againſt
          Authorities? — My Memory is a <lb/>ſhort one, but I think 'tis long enough for <lb/>my
          Learning..... I have a little Acquaintance <lb/>with <hi rend="italic">French</hi>
          Authors, and among the reſt <lb/>with Monſieur <hi rend="italic">Montaigne</hi>, who, as I
          re- <lb/>member, makes an Argument againſt you <lb/>of his Family's Longevity. <q
            rend="diple">My Father (ſays <lb/>he) liv'd ſeventy two Years, my Grandfa- <lb/>ther
            ſixty nine, my Great-Grandfather a- <lb/>bout fourſcore; and ne'r a one of them
            <lb/>ever ſwallow'd a Grain of Phyſick. </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi>
          <q rend="diple">It may be ſo, </q> (ſays a <note place="bottom" n="*"
            rend="size(0.5) italic">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Rara non ſunt Artis, <hi rend="roman">&amp;c.</hi>
              <hi rend="roman">Joan. Beverovicius contra <lb/>Montanum</hi>. </p>
          </note> Phyſician <lb/>that anſwers him.) <q rend="diple">Exceptions are no Rule.
            <lb/>Theſe Gentlemen, 'tis to be ſuppos'd, <lb/>were Men of exemplary Temperance and
            <lb/>Sobriety, true to the Intereſt of their Con- <lb/>ſtitutions, and manag'd
            themſelves <hi rend="italic">Medi- <lb/>cally</hi>, tho' perhaps they did not know
            <lb/>ſo much. There are indeed Inſtances eve- <lb/>ry Day, of People dying young, that
            have <lb/>liv'd faſt: But on the other hand, do not <lb/>we ſee Valetudinarians, that
            obſerve Rules, <lb/>and take care of themſelves, reach a good <lb/>old Age very
            commonly? <hi rend="italic">Galen</hi>, as he <lb/>tells us himſelf, brought a weak
            Conſtitu- <lb/>tion into the World; and yet he cultiva- <pb n="7"/>
            <lb/>ted and confirm'd it ſo effectually, that he <lb/>was ſcarce ever indiſpos'd; and
            lived to <lb/>a Hundred and forty: Tho' <hi rend="italic">Suidas</hi> ſays <lb/>he dy'd
            in his Seventieth Year; and <hi rend="italic">Alber- <lb/>tus ab Eybe</hi>, (upon whoſe
            Authority, I know <lb/>not) in his Eighty ſeventh. <hi rend="italic">Plato</hi> and <hi
              rend="italic">Ari- <lb/>ſtotle</hi> mention one <hi rend="italic">Herodicus</hi>, that
            was natu- <lb/>rally the moſt infirm and tender Man of his <lb/>Time; and yet by the
            Benefit of Art, and <lb/>a right Government of himſelf, held it out <lb/>to a Hundred.
          </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ja.</hi> The <hi rend="italic">Frenchman</hi> objects, <q
            rend="diple">That the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Romans</hi> had no Phyſicians for Six
            hundred <lb/>Years; and that <hi rend="italic">Cato</hi>, their celebrated <lb/>Patriot,
            advis'd them to live as long as <lb/>they could without them. </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi>
          <q rend="diple">And ſo they did, </q> (anſwers the <hi rend="italic">Dutch- <lb/>man</hi>)
            <q rend="diple">but not without Phyſick. There are <lb/>ſcarce any Phyſicians in <hi
              rend="italic">Turky</hi>, but then <lb/>they have their Druggs and Receits, and
            <lb/>certain eſtabliſh'd Maxims and Meaſures to <lb/>go by, both in Doctoring and
            Dieting <lb/>themſelves. And what, at laſt, was the <lb/>Reaſon why the <hi
              rend="italic">Romans</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Cato</hi> were ſo <lb/>averſe to
            Phyſicians? <hi rend="italic">Cato</hi> himſelf tells <lb/>you in <hi rend="italic"
              >Pliny</hi>. It ſeems they had none <lb/>among themſelves, and they durſt not truſt
            <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Greeks</hi>, becauſe they had enter'd into a <lb/>ſolemn
            Combination to give no <hi rend="italic">Barbarian</hi>
            <lb/>Quarter, that fell into their Hands. Now, <lb/>with Submiſſion, this was not
            keeping out <lb/>Phyſicians, but Ruffians. The Quarrel <pb n="8"/>
            <lb/>was not to the Profeſſion, but to the Men. <lb/>They did not deſire to ſtake
            Recovery a- <lb/>gainſt <hi rend="italic">Ratsbane</hi>; and they were in the right
            <lb/>of it. Agen; Medicine was not the only <lb/>Thing they were uncivilized in for
            ſeveral <lb/>Ages. <hi rend="italic">Tully</hi> complains their Common- <lb/>wealth had
            lain bare too long of other <lb/>Parts of Knowledge and Improvements of <lb/>the Mind,
            and particularly that no Philo- <lb/>ſophy had appear'd in the <hi rend="italic"
              >Roman</hi> Dreſs <lb/>or Language. But now will any one in- <lb/>ferr from hence,
            that <hi rend="italic">Cato</hi> declar'd againſt <lb/>a Profeſſion of ſuch Importance?
            If he <lb/>will, let him conſult <hi rend="italic">Cato</hi> himſelf in <hi
              rend="italic">Pliny</hi>, <lb/>and there he will find, it was by Rule of <lb/>Art he
            lengthened out his own and his La- <lb/>dy's Life to ſuch a remarkable Period. <lb/>
            <note rend="size(0.5) italic" place="bottom" n="*">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>* Catoni non placuit, <hi rend="roman">&amp;c.</hi>
                <hi rend="roman">Declam. in laud. Art. <lb/>Med.</hi>
              </p>
            </note> Another Reaſon of <hi rend="italic">Cato</hi>'s Antipathy (ſays <lb/><hi
              rend="italic">Eraſmus</hi>) was the Auſterity of his Tem- <lb/>per, and his Partiality
            to his <hi rend="italic">Romans</hi>. <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Greek</hi> Phyſicians
            made too great a Fi- <lb/>gure for him, and ſeem'd to reproach his <lb/>Countrymen's
            unpoliſh'd Circumſtances. <lb/>This made him baniſh all Philoſophy, not <lb/>becauſe it
            was not good, but becauſe it <lb/>was <hi rend="italic">Greek</hi>. 'Tis <hi
              rend="italic">Experience</hi>
          </q>(ſays he) <q rend="diple quotes">that <lb/>conſummates a Genius. All your
            Specu- <lb/>lations and Hypotheſes are Trifles. Phy- <lb/>ſicians and Apothecaries would
            ſoon be <pb n="9"/>
            <lb/>broke, if <hi rend="italic">Carduus</hi> and <note rend="size(0.5) italic"
              place="bottom" n="*">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>* <hi rend="roman">Braſſica</hi>. Homo durus, ad purgandum hominis corpus
                <lb/>ſufficere <hi rend="roman">Braſſicam</hi> &amp; erebros vomitus exiſtimabat.
              </p>
            </note>
            <hi rend="italic">Coleworts</hi> were <lb/>more commonly uſed when we find a
            <lb/>Foulneſs in the Stomach or Bowels. </q> You <lb/>may perceive the Stateſman was a
          little <lb/>ſmitten with Quackery himſelf. Beſides, <lb/>'tis worth notice here, that we
          have <hi rend="italic">Tully</hi>
          <lb/>againſt <hi rend="italic">Cato</hi>; and perhaps, all Things conſi- <lb/>der'd, the
          Former's Authority may be the <lb/>better of the Two. But not to tire you; <lb/>I muſt
          tell you in a word, both God and <lb/>Man, Scripture and Law, paſt Ages and <lb/>preſent,
          are all in the Phyſician's Intereſt, <lb/>and ſupport his Pretenſions. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ja.</hi> Don't miſtake me, Madam; I am for <lb/>Phyſick, Knowledge
          and Practice too, as <lb/>much as any one. But I don't underſtand, <lb/>why it muſt be the
          Privilege and Property <lb/>of a few Undertakers of the other Sex. You <lb/>are a Learned
          Woman, and have read a great <lb/>deal, Madam; Pray inform me how Princes <lb/>and
          Univerſities came by a Power of Farming <lb/>out Philoſophy. 'Tis hard, methinks, the
          <lb/>Women ſhould be made a Province thus to <lb/>the Men in every Thing. Why muſt we be
          <lb/>their Patients when we are ſick; and only <lb/>their Nurſes when they are ſo? Why
          ſhould <lb/>not we, who are at ſo much Pains to bring <lb/>Mankind into the World, have as
          good a <lb/>Title as the beſt of them, to the Liberty of <pb n="10"/>
          <lb/>ſending ſome People out of it? In ſhort, <lb/>they are downright <hi rend="italic"
            >Pharaohs</hi>: They let us <lb/>practiſe our Midwifery upon one another, <lb/>but as
          ſoon as the Children are born, they <lb/>take them out of our Hands. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi> And give me leave to ſay, they would <lb/>do us a
          Kindneſs, if they did not gratify us <lb/>thus far. Our Privilege in this Preliminary
          <lb/>has deſtroy'd not a few of us. I know Mo- <lb/>deſty is generally inſiſted on in the
          Caſe; <lb/>eſpecially by ſome Women, that are, perhaps, <lb/>as Vain as they are Vertuous.
          But in my o- <lb/>pinion, 'tis a Miſapplication of the Text; <lb/>For Modeſty conſiſts in
          an Abſtinence from <lb/>unlawful or indecent Pleaſures, and not in <lb/>an Affectation of
          unneceſſary Danger or <lb/>Pain. But not to loſe Sight of our Subject; <lb/>I perceive you
          are angry the Women are not <lb/><hi rend="italic">Licentiates</hi>. You don't envy the
          Phyſician <lb/>his Fee ſo much as his Figure. Your Con- <lb/>cern is not to be, but to be
          thought, as <lb/>Knowing as he is. You would have your <lb/>Degrees without doing
          Exerciſe, and make <lb/>a Diverſion of what others find a Fatigue. <lb/>You would leave no
          Diſtinction between <lb/>Practice and Tampering. Briefly, the Thing <lb/>you graſp at is
          the ſweet Prerogative of <lb/>Judging and Directing, without any of the <lb/>Study and
          Care that qualifies the Doctor <lb/>for his Duty, and follows him cloſe in the
          <lb/>Diſcharge of it. Now believe me, this is a <lb/>very ravenous Ambition. And, by the
          way, <pb n="11"/>
          <lb/>tho' it may begin, it ſeldom ſtops at any <lb/>Branch of Learning, or Inſtance of
          Improve- <lb/>ment. Quackery is an Eddy that ſucks in <lb/>every Thing. When it has
          ſwallow'd Phy- <lb/>ſick, it quickly fetches down Philoſophy, <lb/>Divinity, Law,
          Mathematicks, and the whole <lb/><hi rend="italic">Flota</hi> of Arts and Profeſſions,
          after it. Con- <lb/>feſs ingenuouſly, Madam; could you with <lb/>any Comfort confine
          yourſelf to ſo narrow a <lb/>Buſineſs as the Care and Cuſtody of Life and <lb/>Health?
          Would not the Miniſter's Preach- <lb/>ing, or the Lawyer's Pleading, ſoon ſet <lb/>your
          Mouth a watering agen? Could you <lb/>bear to live, and die at laſt, no more than <lb/>the
          Third Part of a great Scholar? </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ja.</hi> In my Conſcience, I believe not, <lb/>now you put me in
          mind of it. I hate Diſ- <lb/>ſembling; and therefore I tell you plainly, <lb/>both Goſpel
          and Law are as open to me, as <lb/>to any of my Neighbours. It could never <lb/>enter into
          my Head, that Porters of Colle- <lb/>ges and Inns of Court lock up the whole
          <lb/>Commonwealth of Letters every Night. <lb/>No, no; Knowledge does not grow, like
          <lb/>Moſs, upon old Walls. I am perſuaded, if <lb/>ſome Women were to enter of the Univer-
          <lb/>ſity <hi rend="italic">Incognito</hi>, they would acquit themſelves <lb/>as
          remarkably, in Study and Diſpute, as o- <lb/>thers have done in the Camp. 'Tis nothing
          <lb/>but Prejudice and Superſtition, Woman, <lb/>that keeps us out of Play. </p>
        <pb n="12"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi> A little Logick, I confeſs, might do <lb/>you no harm. You
          are beſide the Queſtion <lb/>already. What we might do, if we were <lb/>to keep up with
          the other Sex in Education; <lb/>if we did not part Company at the School- <lb/>Dame's
          Door; if we travel'd as many Sta- <lb/>ges as they do, from Reading and Writing <lb/>to
          Languages, from Languages to Books, <lb/>and a Taſte of Authors, from thence to an
          <lb/>Imitation of them, then forward, to the <lb/>more <hi rend="italic">Olympick</hi>
          Exerciſes of Diſtinguiſhing, <lb/>Comparing, Judging, Reaſoning, and all <lb/>theſe, <hi
            rend="italic">ſecundum artem</hi>, as they ſay; and <lb/>farther agen, to the
          Application of theſe <lb/>to Theory, and the Accommodating of Spe- <lb/>culation to
          Practice, and the Ripening of <lb/>Practice into Experience: What we might <lb/>do
          afterwards, if we went thro' all this firſt, <lb/>I will not diſpute. But for us to ſpread
          our <lb/>Sails, and venture to Sea without Chart or <lb/>Pilot, before we know how to turn
          a Rud- <lb/>der, or draw a Rope; What is this, but ca- <lb/>ſting ourſelves away, and all
          that truſt us? <lb/>Soul, Life, and Eſtate are too valuable Con- <lb/>cerns to be put into
          the Hands of Empyricks. <lb/>'Tis ſomewhat ſtrange, that we ſhould be <lb/>born Graduates
          in all Faculties, and yet <lb/>go to School to learn Plain-Work and Pa- <lb/>ſtry. But it
          ſeems, our Heads and our <lb/>Tongues can ſet themſelves at Work better <lb/>than our
          Fingers. </p>
        <pb n="13"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ja.</hi> Suppoſing your Diſtinction to the <lb/>purpoſe, (for I
          hate to be Poſitive) yet it <lb/>will not come up to the Point. For why <lb/>are only the
          Women deny'd their Birthright? <lb/>If Nature has qualify'd us, as well as the Men,
          <lb/>for the nobler Scenes and Offices of Life; <lb/>why are we excluded? 'Tis very hard
          the <lb/>Silver in our Ore ſhould be thrown away, on- <lb/>ly for want of Sifting. To urge
          Univerſal <lb/>Cuſtom and Preſcription againſt us, is only <lb/>to tell us the Thing is
          Fact, which we know <lb/>too well already; but by no means clears <lb/>the Merits of the
          Cauſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi> I can tell you then, the Defendant has <lb/>other Pleas to
          fill up his Anſwer. Remember, <lb/>Madam,we were born Subjects as well as Wo- <lb/>men,
          and the Conſtitution has prejudg'd us. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ja.</hi> What, in the free Uſe of our Under- <lb/>ſtandings? I'm
          for no ſuch Arbitrary Doings. <lb/>Belike, if there was an Act of Parliament,
          <lb/>ſtreightly charging and requiring us to go <lb/>Blindfold, and never open our Mouths,
          but <lb/>at Church or Meals; you are ſuch a dutiful <lb/>Daughter of the Commonwealth,
          that you <lb/>would be content we ſhould ſtand all the <lb/>Days of our Lives like Statues
          of Fortune, <lb/>with Mufflers upon our Eyes, and no <lb/>Tongues in our Mouths. Now I,
          that <lb/>have as great a Reſpect for the Legiſlature as <lb/>any one, muſt confeſs, I
          can't be ſo re- <lb/>ſign'd. I ſhall never ſubmit to a <hi rend="italic">Salique</hi>
          <lb/>Law for Ignorance and Inſignificancy. </p>
        <pb n="14"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi> And yet I am confident, there is not <lb/>one Woman in
          five hundred, that would ex- <lb/>change Education and Buſineſs with the <lb/>Men. If
          Dreſſing, Dancing, Viſiting, were <lb/>put in the Balance, againſt Confinement, <lb/>hard
          Study, and cloſe Attendance, the <lb/>lighter Scale would eaſily raiſe the heavier.
          <lb/>If we can buy good Bargains, let other <lb/>People ſtand behind the Counter. We
          <lb/>can't complain of hard Uſage. It coſts <lb/>the Men dear, what we purchaſe cheap.
          <lb/>Beſides, by your Argument, Madam, Com- <lb/>munity of Callings ſhould be a Branch of
          <lb/>the Law of Nature; Mankind muſt never <lb/>break Bulk; and the Grocery of the World
          <lb/>would lie unretail'd. We ſhould all be our <lb/>own Watchmakers, Upholſterers, and
          Sil- <lb/>ver-Smiths, too; and every Houſe a <hi rend="italic">Cheap- <lb/>ſide</hi>, as
          well as an Univerſity. Your Model <lb/>has more Abſurdities yet, Madam, if you <lb/>are
          inclin'd to know them. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ja.</hi> 'Tis pity you were not a Man, <hi rend="italic">Olym-
            <lb/>pia</hi>, tho' you will not allow me to be a Do- <lb/>ctor. I own you would have
          made an ex- <lb/>cellent Mountebank. You have a Volubili- <lb/>ty, which many a Barriſter
          and Recorder <lb/>would be glad of. You have ſaid luch fine <lb/>Things in Favour of our
          Maſters, that if <lb/>I did not know you to be a married Lady, <lb/>I ſhould believe you
          were a waining Virgin. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi> Before we part, it may be my Turn <lb/>to rally. But 'tis
          a Maxim of the Schools <pb n="15"/>
          <lb/>with me, never to Play till I have ſaid my <lb/>Leſſon. If you pleaſe to give me
          leave, I <lb/>will take this Opportunity to enter a little <lb/>deeper into the Subject
          before us. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ja.</hi> Controverſie carries lnfection. You <lb/>ſeem diſpos'd to
          give your Fancy a Breath- <lb/>ing, and ſo am I. Begin as you pleaſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi> With your leave, we'll return to <lb/>what I touch'd upon
          before, the Nobleneſs <lb/>and Importance of the Profeſſion. And from <lb/>this, with a
          little Help of that ſame Volu- <lb/>bility, we ſhall eaſily ſlide into a ſhort Con-
          <lb/>verſation about the Duties of Phyſicians and <lb/>Patients. Now, as to the Firſt, I
          have ſome- <lb/>times made it a Queſtion to myſelf, whether <lb/>Medicine ſhould not take
          place of Law. <lb/>'Tis true, Juſtice and Government are Mat- <lb/>ters of much greater
          Conſequence than <lb/>Health and Life; and the Laſt are very pre- <lb/>carious and
          defenceleſs without the Firſt. <lb/>Anarchy, Rapine, and Violence, 'tis certain, <lb/>do
          more Execution than the Plague. A <lb/>Child born with Fire and Sword in the <lb/>Room,
          is, in effect, an Abortion. And when <lb/>Laws lie dead, and Riot rules, a Man has
          <lb/>not ſo good a Chance for his Life, as <hi rend="italic">Romulus</hi>, <lb/>when he
          ſuck'd a Wolf. All this is true. But <lb/>then we muſt remember, Right and Order are
          <lb/>not Law itſelf, but the Foundation and End <lb/>of Law. For <hi rend="italic"
            >Law</hi>, as ſuch, is only a Hu- <lb/>man lnſtitution, Arbitrary and Reverſible.
          <lb/>And the Profeſſors of it are truly call'd <hi rend="italic">Ser- <pb n="16"/>
            <lb/>vientes ad Legem, Servants at Law</hi>, be- <lb/>cauſe they are oblig'd to follow
          the Directions <lb/>of their Superiors implicitly; and in this <lb/>reſpect they may be
          call'd <hi rend="italic">State Apothecaries</hi>
          <lb/>too. <q rend="diple quotes">
            <note rend="size(0.5) italic" place="bottom" n="*">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>* Cum illa (ſcil. Juriſprudentia) nunquam ſine aliorum of- <lb/>fe <gap
                  reason="illegible"/>, <hi rend="roman">&amp;c.</hi>
                <hi rend="roman">Grynæi Medicinæ Encom.</hi>
              </p>
            </note> Then there's this farther Difference <lb/>between the two Profeſſions. The Law
            <lb/>muſt light hard upon half the People, at <lb/>leaſt, it has to do with. Whereas
            Phyſick <lb/>is an univerſal Benefactor. One Man's <lb/>Health is not another Man's
            Loſs. All the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Chancery</hi> that can happen in Phyſick, is the
            <lb/>Length of the Proceſs. If a good Habit <lb/>of Body were <hi rend="italic"
              >Holding</hi>, and a Man could <lb/>be well by Acres; then, I confeſs, the
            <lb/>Phyſician would be more embarraſs'd and <lb/>confin'd in his Services. But there's
            no <lb/>Litigiouſneſs in a Cure, no Suing for <lb/>good Blood and Animal Spirits. If I
            ga- <lb/>ther Fleſh and Strength, 'tis not out of o- <lb/>ther People's Muſcles. </q>
          Agen; the Conſe- <lb/>quence we drive at, comes double arm'd, <lb/>if we conſider, that
          Redreſs of Wrong, and <lb/>Suppreſſion of Diſorder, are the Buſineſs of <lb/>the Military
          Men too, tho' in another Way: <lb/>And why ſhould not the End of their Pro- <lb/>feſſion
          ſet Them as well as the Lawyers a- <lb/>bove the Phyſicians? </p>
        <pb n="17"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ja.</hi> Eſpecially, conſidering the Odds be- <lb/>tween a Hero's
          Veins, and a Clerk's lnk- <lb/>bottle. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi> And withall, what continual Fatigues <lb/>and Hardſhips
          follow the Camp: How <lb/>ſtern and rugged the Diſcipline, and how <lb/>ſhort the Pay, as
          well as the Service. But <lb/>to return; the Phyſician's Code and Statute- <lb/>Book is
          Nature. He collects his Skill, and <lb/>compounds his Materials, on the foot of his
          <lb/>own Induſtry, Obſervation, and Sagacity. <lb/>Philoſophy is no Parliamentary
          Eſtabliſh- <lb/>ment: And there's no ſuch Thing as En- <lb/>acting a Man into a <hi
            rend="italic">Machaon</hi>. To trace the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Nile</hi> of Life and
          Vigour up to the Fountain- <lb/>Head; to unlock the Myſteries, and correct the
          <lb/>Obliquities of Mechaniſm; to adjuſt the Mix- <lb/>tures, and conduct the Motions of
          the Ele- <lb/>ments; to moderate between Solids and Flu- <lb/>ids, and keep the <hi
            rend="italic">Parties</hi> Under; in a word, <lb/>to preſerve Harmony amongſt the
          mutinous <lb/>Ingredients of the Animal Frame, and re- <lb/>duce them to an orderly Tone
          and Tem- <lb/>per; eſpecially when they've skirmiſh'd and <lb/>handled one another ill:
          What is this, but the <lb/>Province of <hi rend="italic">Angelick Intelligences</hi>? And
          what <lb/>ſhall we call an Order of Men, thus quali- <lb/>fy'd and employ'd, but God's
          ſpecial <hi rend="italic">Ope- <lb/>rators</hi>, and the Subſitutes of Omnipotence?
          <lb/>Briefly, Madam, whoever would make an <lb/>Eſtimate of the <hi rend="italic"
            >Intrinſick</hi> of both Profeſſions, <lb/>ſhould ask himſelf which is the nobler Sub-
            <pb n="18"/>
          <lb/>ject of the two to practice upon, the Bodies <lb/>of Men, or the Skins of Beaſts. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ja.</hi> This Rhetorick of yours, I muſt <lb/>tell you, may
          tranſport you into Inconveni- <lb/>ences. Let me diſſuade you from purſuing <lb/>the
          Compariſon. Sign your Will before <lb/>you ſay any more of it; and reſerve it for <lb/>the
          laſt Compliment to your Doctor. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi> I ſhall follow your Advice, and turn <lb/>off into
          ſmoother Way. I come now to <lb/>what I may call <hi rend="italic">The Divine Right of the
            <lb/>Phyſician</hi>. If you pleaſe, we'll conſult our <lb/>Bibles upon the Queſtion. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ja.</hi> I don't apprehend you will find <lb/>much there to your
          purpoſe, but what is <lb/>Apochryphal. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi> More, perhaps, than you imagin. The <lb/>Author of Nature
          tells you out of his own <lb/>Mouth, That <q rend="italic">they that are ſick need a
            Phyſician </q>. <lb/>For that is plainly imply'd in the Antithe- <lb/>ſis of thoſe
          Words; <q rend="italic">They that be whole, need <lb/>not a Phyſician, but they that are
            ſick </q>. And the <lb/>Prophet <hi rend="italic">Jeremy</hi> ſpeaks of Health, as a
          natural <lb/>Conſequence of the Phyſician's Attendance <lb/>and Direction; <q
            rend="italic">Is there no Balm in <hi rend="roman">Gilead</hi>? <lb/>Is there no
            Phyſician there? Why then is not the <lb/>Health of the Daughter of my People recover'd? </q>
          <lb/>And I'll venture to ſay, 'twas an Honour de- <lb/>ſign'd the Mechanical and Ordinary
          Means <lb/>which God has provided, of repairing <lb/>Strength, reſtoring Health, and
          preſerving <lb/>Life, that material Applications were ſome- <pb n="19"/>
          <lb/>times us'd in miraculous Cures. The Prophet's <lb/>Plaiſter of Figs, and our
          Saviour's Mixture of <lb/>Clay and Spittle, ſeem to carry this Meaning. <lb/>Juſt as the
          diſtinguiſhing Enſigns or Symbols <lb/>of a Nation's Eminence and Honour, for in-
          <lb/>ſtance, the Red and the White Croſs, are en- <lb/>courag'd and aggrandiz'd by the
          Prince's <lb/>Wearing them. In the next place, if <lb/>you call for the Senſe of Lawgivers
          and <lb/>Senates upon this Matter, you'll find <lb/>they have conferred Reputation and
          Privi- <lb/>lege very liberally upon the Faculty, ſubſcri- <lb/>bed to their Merit, and
          enſcons'd them with <lb/>Sanction. But before I bring the Cauſe in- <lb/>to Court, let's
          enquire what Credit and E- <lb/>ſteem the Profeſſion has ſtood in with Pub- <lb/>lick
          Bodies or Conſiderable Perſons. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ja.</hi> You begin to talk formidably. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi> Perhaps you'll have reaſon to ſay ſo <lb/>preſently. Come
          on then. The <hi rend="italic">Egyptians</hi>
          <lb/>aſſign'd their Phyſicians large Salaries out <lb/>of the Publick Stock. <hi
            rend="italic">Herodotus</hi> tells us, <lb/>the Doctors in this Country were diſtribu-
          <lb/>ted into as many Claſſes as there were known <lb/>Diſtempers; and <hi rend="italic"
            >Plutarch</hi>, that Med'cine <lb/>was ſo much in Vogue among them, that <lb/>they were
          one and all Phyſicians. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ja.</hi> That's what I would have elſe- <lb/>where. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi> Let us be as well qualify'd firſt. I <lb/>proceed. The <hi
            rend="italic">Athenians</hi> had ſuch a Re- <lb/>ſpect for this Profeſſion, that they
          ſuffer'd <pb n="20"/>
          <lb/>no Man to meddle with it, that had not his <lb/>Freedom. The ſame Republick ſet up
            <hi rend="italic">Hip- <lb/>pocrates</hi> a noble Statue in his Life-time. <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Julius Cæſar</hi> Enfranchis'd all Students in <lb/>Phyſick, to keep thoſe
          that were already at <lb/><hi rend="italic">Rome</hi>, from leaving it, and encourage more
          <lb/>to come. <hi rend="italic">Auguſtus</hi>, upon <hi rend="italic">Antonius Muſa'</hi>s
          <lb/>recovering him from a dangerous Fitt of <lb/>Sickneſs, gave the Phyſicians the
          Privilege of <lb/>wearing Gold Rings, which before only Se- <lb/>nators and Knights might
          do. And the <hi rend="italic">Ro- <lb/>mans</hi> honour'd him with a Statue, at the
          <lb/>Side of another of <hi rend="italic">Eſculapius</hi>, in conſide- <lb/>ration of ſo
          great a piece of Service. <hi rend="italic">Darius</hi>
          <lb/>gave <hi rend="italic">Democedes</hi>, a Captive, ſeveral noble <lb/>Mannors for
          curing him, and the Honour <lb/>too of a Place at his Table. The Faculty <lb/>had Penſions
          conferr'd upon them by the <lb/>Emperor <hi rend="italic">Alexander Severus</hi>. <hi
            rend="italic">Ptolemy</hi> made <lb/>a Preſent of a Hundred Talents to <hi rend="italic"
            >Eraſiſtra- <lb/>tus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Ariſtotle</hi>'s Grandſon, for curing his
          <lb/>Father <hi rend="italic">Antiochus</hi>; and <hi rend="italic">Antigonus</hi> gave
          him <lb/>Sixty thouſand <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5) italic" n="*">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* <hi rend="roman">Aureos Philippeos</hi>, each being, according to Dr. <hi
                rend="roman">Ber- <lb/>nard</hi>, in Value 18 s. 4 d. of <hi rend="roman"
                >Engliſh</hi> Money. </p>
          </note>
          <hi rend="italic">Philippean</hi> Guineas for cu- <lb/>ring his Son. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ja.</hi> I find getting Eſtates has been an old <lb/>Affair with
          the Phyſicians. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi> It has ſo; and why not, if they got <lb/>them honeſtly?
          The <hi rend="italic">Caſſii</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Carpitani</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
            >Arun- <lb/>cii</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Albucii</hi>, made their Fortunes this way, and
            <pb n="21"/>
          <lb/>very great ones too, without maiming their <lb/>Characters. <hi rend="italic"
            >Cardan</hi>, in his Panegyrick upon <lb/>Medicine, has more Inſtances to mortify
          <lb/>you. He tells you of <hi rend="italic">Artaxerxes</hi>'s Gene- <lb/>roſity to <hi
            rend="italic">Hippocrates</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Phalaris</hi>'s to <hi rend="italic"
            >Polycletus <lb/>Miſſenius</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Polycrates</hi>'s to <hi
            rend="italic">Democedes</hi>. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Alexander</hi> the Great almoſt
          Buried <hi rend="italic">Critobulus</hi>
          <lb/>in Gold, for keeping him above Ground. <lb/>What think you of one <hi rend="italic"
            >Crinas</hi>, that new <lb/>built all the Fortifications of a City in his
          <lb/>Life-time, and yet left a vaſt Eſtate at his <lb/>Death? </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ja.</hi> 'Tis well if he did not build with <lb/>the Burghers
          Bones. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi> Miſrepreſentations and Aſperſions <lb/>would not ſtick
          upon the Profeſſion in thoſe <lb/>Days. Princes and People of the firſt Rank <lb/>were
          proud to be of the Faculty; inſomuch <lb/>that it was a Sort of <hi rend="italic"
            >Miſpriſion</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Scanda- <lb/>lum Magnatum</hi>, to treat the
          Doctors con- <lb/>temptuouſly. <hi rend="italic">Solomon</hi> was certainly a very
          <lb/>Learned <hi rend="italic">Phyſician</hi>. And ſo probably were <lb/>ſeveral other
          Eaſtern Monarchs; <hi rend="italic">Sabor</hi> and <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ginges</hi>,
          Kings of <hi rend="italic">Media</hi>; <hi rend="italic">Sabiel</hi> of <hi rend="italic"
            >Arabia</hi>; <lb/><hi rend="italic">Mithridates</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Perſia</hi>;
          and <hi rend="italic">Hermes</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Egypt</hi>. <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Meſues</hi>, Grandſon of a King of <hi rend="italic">Damaſcus</hi>; <lb/>and <hi
            rend="italic">Avicenna</hi>, ſuppos'd to be Prince of <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Corduba</hi>, were very eminent this way too. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ja.</hi> Have you no Queens in your Cata- <lb/>logue? </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi> I don't find any. The Sex were <lb/>then afraid of
          Pretendingneſs. But I <pb n="22"/>
          <lb/>come forward to the Recommendations and <lb/>Favours of the Law. Several of the Empe-
          <lb/>rors granted the Faculty many Legal Privile- <lb/>ges. <hi rend="italic"
            >Veſpaſian</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Adrian</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Antonine</hi> con-
          <lb/>firm'd the Immunity and Eminence <hi rend="italic">Julius <lb/>Cæſar</hi> and <hi
            rend="italic">Auguſtus</hi> had given them. <hi rend="italic">Com- <lb/>modus</hi>, <hi
            rend="italic">Severus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Conſtantine</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
            >Valentinian</hi> and <lb/><hi rend="italic">Valens</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
            >Honorius</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Theodoſius</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Julian</hi>,
          <lb/>enacted in their Favour. Theſe Edicts freed <lb/>them from all publick Impoſts and
          Offices of <lb/>Trouble, and not only their Perſons, but their <lb/>Wives, Children, and
          Eſtates too. Agen, <lb/>the Law cover'd them with ſuch an effectual <lb/>Protection, that
          whoever moleſted or injur'd <lb/>them, was to be puniſh'd at the Judge's Diſ-
          <lb/>cretion. Nor had they only Privileges and <lb/>Protection, but likewiſe large
          Salaries <lb/>and Penſions aſſign'd them. 'Tis true in- <lb/>deed, only a certain ſelect
          Number, and <lb/>thoſe to be preferr'd, principally for their <lb/>Morals, and in the
          ſecond regard for their <lb/>Learning, call'd <hi rend="italic">Numeraries</hi>, as the
          reſt were <lb/>call'd <hi rend="italic">Supernumeraries</hi>, had a title to, or
          <lb/>enjoy'd theſe Rights. But then we know <lb/>theſe Honours and Encouragements were
          <lb/>deſign'd the Profeſſion more than the Perſons. <lb/>As for Statute-Law, the 5th of
          the 14th and <lb/>15th of <hi rend="italic">Henry</hi> VIII. diſcharges Phyſicians
          <lb/>from being ſummon'd upon Juries in <hi rend="italic">London</hi>; <lb/>and requires
          an Examination and Licence <lb/>from the College to qualify for Practice. <lb/>And the
          Powers deriv'd to them by Aca- <pb n="23"/>
          <lb/>demical Promotion are too well known to <lb/>be mention'd. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ja.</hi> You ſeem to have weigh'd the <lb/>Strength of the Cauſe
          with uncommon Ap- <lb/>plication and Curioſity. But perhaps you <lb/>have never, or very
          rarely, been under the <lb/>Diſcipline of Anatomical Hands. I fancy, <lb/>if you were to
          feel the Smart of a few Ex- <lb/>periments, you'd abate of your Zeal. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi> And that brings me directly to the o- <lb/>ther Head of
          Diſcourſe; the Phyſician's and <lb/>the Patient's Duty; which I have had Occaſion
          <lb/>more than enough to conſider, before you <lb/>and I came acquainted. I never was a
          Bi- <lb/>got to Pain. And I ſhall not excuſe a Phy- <lb/>ſician's Abuſe of his Power. <q
            rend="diple">To be forc'd </q>
          <lb/>(ſays <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5) italic" n="*">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Carnificis eſt, pendentibus fatis, <hi rend="roman">&amp;c.</hi>
              <hi rend="roman">Alex. Benedi- <lb/>ctus</hi>. <hi rend="roman">De Med. atq; Ægri
                officio Aphoriſm</hi>. c. 1. </p>
          </note> one of them) <q rend="diple quotes">to come to a hard Bar- <lb/>gain for
            Life or Relief; to be kept long in <lb/>Miſery and Suſpence, and perhaps but half
            <lb/>cured at laſt; is enough to make a Man <lb/>think himſelf under the Hands of an
            Exe- <lb/>cutioner, rather than a Doctor. </q> But, not- <lb/>withſtanding this, I
          always thought my Phy- <lb/>ſician and my Surgeon beſt able to judge, <lb/>When Rigorous
          Methods were neceſſary, and <lb/>then I ſubmitted to them. To conſult a <lb/>Man's Eaſe,
          and indulge his Averſions, in <lb/>ſome Circumſtances, is but a kind Way of <lb/>cutting
          his Throat. Inciſion-Knives were <pb n="24"/>
          <lb/>not made for Ceremonie. When the Rule <lb/>requires it, the Phyſician is as much
          bound <lb/>to torture a Man into Health, as a Judge to <lb/>give Sentence. For Cancers and
          Gangreens <lb/>are as Incorrigible, as Harden'd Malefactors. <lb/>Beſides, this Pretence
          of Quarrel concerns <lb/>the Surgeons more than the Phyſicians. The <lb/>Severities of the
          latter are few, and not fre- <lb/>quent; and are generally the Effect, either <lb/>of the
          Patient's Vices, or his Negligence. <lb/>Carduus Cantharides and Mercury ſeem
          <lb/>deſign'd by Providence for Puniſhments as <lb/>well as Preſervatives. And before you
          en- <lb/>ter upon a Miſunderſtanding with the Sur- <lb/>geons, conſider, Madam, they ſtand
          clear <lb/>of your Imputation too. They are not Ag- <lb/>greſſors. The ſharpeſt of their
          Operations <lb/>are extorted, either by the Patient's Raſh- <lb/>neſs, or Misfortune. The
          Part is made Uſe- <lb/>leſs to Itſelf, and Dangerous to the Whole, <lb/>before they come
          to cutting off.—I could <lb/>enlarge upon this Head, but I ſuppoſe you <lb/>ſee how the
          Matter ſtands already. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ja.</hi> I confeſs my Objection was ſtarted <lb/>a little haſtily.
          Let it be withdrawn, if you <lb/>pleaſe, and go on as you propos'd. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi> I begin with the Patient's Part; whom <lb/>it concerns, as
          nearly in Duty as Intereſt, <lb/>to chuſe, where there is more than one <lb/>Phyſician,
          the Man of moſt Skill, Experi- <lb/>ence, and Succeſs. </p>
        <pb n="25"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ja.</hi> I thought you would ſoon run a- <lb/>ground. I have you
          now at Mercy, Ma- <lb/>dam. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi> As how? </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ja.</hi> With your favour, let me underſtand <lb/>how a Phyſician's
          Qualifications and Abilities <lb/>can come under my Cognizance, unleſs I am <lb/>compleat
          Judge of his Principles and Me- <lb/>thods? If you'll allow me to know when he
          <lb/>preſcribes and manages right, this is Con- <lb/>feſſing, I underſtand before-hand,
          what <lb/>Meaſures and Medicines are to be taken, and <lb/>then why ſhould I trouble the
          Doctor? </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi> A good Judge of Painting may be no <lb/>Performer. You may
          make an Eſtimate, <lb/>in ſome meaſure, of a Phyſician's Qualifica- <lb/>tions and
          Conduct, when you know what <lb/>Courſe he deſigns, and for what Reaſons, <lb/>tho' your
          own Capacity could never have <lb/>reach'd either. Second Cauſes, when they're <lb/>once
          diſcover'd, are the moſt Obvious things <lb/>in the World. The <hi rend="italic"
            >Cypher</hi>'s over, after you <lb/>have found the Alphabet. Not that any <lb/>further
          Condeſcenſion of this kind ſhould be <lb/>expected from a Phyſician, than explaining
          <lb/>himſelf in general. And 'tis likely his No- <lb/>tions may be ſo Satisfactory, or ſo
          Diſcou- <lb/>raging, as to determine the Patient. Be- <lb/>ſides; I don't ſuppoſe you caſt
          upon a De- <lb/>ſart Iſland, with Two or Three of the <lb/>Faculty in't, and no Body to
          practice upon but <lb/>themſelves. A Phyſician ſeldom ſettles in an <pb n="26"/>
          <lb/>Unpopulous Place; and tho' you ſhould <lb/>happen to be his <hi rend="italic"
            >Handſel</hi>, you may conclude <lb/>yourſelf ſafe, if he comes well enough re-
          <lb/>commended to expect Welcome and Buſi- <lb/>neſs; which 'tis certainly his Intereſt to
          <lb/>take care of, as well as yours to take care of <lb/>yourſelf. But then, if he has
          reſided ſome <lb/>time in the Town or the Neighbourhood, <lb/>you may eaſily get
          Information of his Abi- <lb/>lities and Succeſs, from People either of <lb/>Sound and
          Superiour Underſtandings, or at <lb/>leaſt of Tender Conſtitutions. Further, if <lb/>he
          carrys Academical Honour, or other Le- <lb/>gal Teſtimonials about him, his Pretenſions
          <lb/>are Valid, and you may depend upon his <lb/>Sufficiency. You ſee, Madam, I have rid
          <lb/>myſelf of your Difficulty. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ja.</hi> You are lucky at Solutions. You <lb/>have always a <hi
            rend="italic">Muſe</hi> facing your <hi rend="italic">Form</hi>. But <lb/>for all your
          Cunning, you may be ſnared by <lb/>and by. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi> Are you ſure I ſhan't loſe your La- <lb/>dyſhip in a Wood
          firſt?—You are ever <lb/>and anon going off the Scent.—The Firſt <lb/>thing, I ſay, a
          Patient or his Friends ſhould <lb/>concern themſelves about, is the Choice of <lb/>the
          Phyſician. As to this, Experience chal- <lb/>lenges a Precedency in the Exerciſe and Uſe
          <lb/>all acquired Accompliſhments are to be put <lb/>to; but moſt of all in the Practice
          of Phy- <lb/>ſick. The Knowledge of the Parts of the <lb/>Body, of the Virtues of Druggs,
          and the <lb/>Strength of their Operations, together with the <pb n="27"/>
          <lb/>Diſtinguiſhing of Symptons and Caſes are <lb/>ſo neceſſary, that 'tis Preſumption ſo
          much <lb/>as to feel a Pulſe without them. And yet <lb/>how faint is the Action of all
          theſe Rays at <lb/>large, in Compariſon of their Force collected, <lb/>if I may ſay ſo, in
          a <hi rend="italic">Focus</hi> of Experience? <lb/>This is that which Warms Opinion and
          Spe- <lb/>culation into Life, Braces the Underſtand- <lb/>ing, and teaches the Mind to
          walk alone. <lb/>'Tis this that finiſhes a <hi rend="italic">Mead</hi> or a <hi
            rend="italic">Radcliffe</hi>. <lb/>'Tis this that puts the laſt Hand to the No-
          <lb/>bleſt Productions of Nature and Art. But <lb/>of the Phyſician's Qualifications I
          ſhall have <lb/>occaſion to ſay more, when I come to ſpeak <lb/>upon his Duty. Further,
          the Sick Man is in <lb/>fault, if he does not look out for Help be- <lb/>times. Not that
          we ſhould imagin every <lb/>little Pain, Qualm, or Stitch, an Admonition <lb/>from
          Providence to ſummon the Doctor. <lb/>The Penances either of our Intemperance <lb/>in the
          Quantity, or our Preſumption in the <lb/>Choice of our Meat and Drink, are no ſur-
          <lb/>prizing or myſterious Diſorders. We need <lb/>not be taught, that in ſuch uſual
          inconveni- <lb/>ent Conſequences as theſe, either of lntempe- <lb/>rance, Lazineſs, or a
          Sedentary Neglect of <lb/>ourſelves, Abſtinence, Exerciſe, and Regu- <lb/>lar Evacuations
          will pacifie injur'd Nature, <lb/>and reconcile our Conſtitutions to us agen.
          <lb/>Sometimes ſuch an Inſtinct comes along with <lb/>an Indiſpoſition, that we know as
          well what <lb/>Phyſick we want, as what Diſh of Meat we <pb n="28"/>
          <lb/>like at another time. And ſuch Suggeſtions as <lb/>theſe, I'll allow to be as ſafe a
          Direction as <lb/>a Doctor's Bill; provided ſome notorious <lb/>Symptom does not beſpeak
          our Caution, and <lb/>make us turn our Backs upon our Inclinati- <lb/>ons. Thus, if a
          Fancy comes upon a Man <lb/>unaccountably, that Smelling to Thyme or <lb/>Sweet-Brier
          would relieve him in the Head- <lb/>Ach, I think he ſhould liſten to the Hint, <lb/>and
          try whether his Imagination dictated <lb/>at Random. But if he deſired Small-Beer,
          <lb/>when his Hands were hot, and his Pulſe in <lb/>a Hurry, I ſhould perſuade him not to
          be <lb/>advis'd altogether by his Fancy. But when <lb/>either an Indiſpoſition attacks us,
          whoſe Ori- <lb/>gin we can't account for; or one which we <lb/>can eaſily gueſs at the
          Cauſe of, keeps its <lb/>hold longer than we had Reaſon to expect; <lb/>When either the
          Diſtemper's Violent in the <lb/>Seizure, or Obſtinate in the Continuance; <lb/>Then there
          muſt be no Time loſt; no Con- <lb/>ſulting of Smatterers; no Anxiouſneſs or <lb/>Debating
          about the Expenſiveneſs of Fees and <lb/>Phyſick. When the Enemy's thus far ad-
          <lb/>vanc'd, Irreſolution's Dangerous, and Secu- <lb/>rity Fatal. 'Tis time to think of
          retiring un- <lb/>der the Canon of the College, and confe- <lb/>derating with Art and
          Science. Then the Son <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Sirach's</hi> Advice is ſeaſonable; <q
            rend="italic">Give place <lb/>to the Phyſician, for the Lord hath created him: <lb/>Let
            him not go from thee, for thou haſt need <lb/>of him. </q> c. 38. <q rend="diple"
           >When any thing ails the <pb n="29"/>
            <lb/>Cattle, </q>ſays <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)" n="*">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Merito hi pœnas delicti dant, cùm ſtatim ad vete- <lb/>rinarios tranſmittant
              jumenta, &amp;c. <hi rend="italic">De Med. &amp; Ægroti <lb/>Munere</hi>. </p>
          </note>
          <hi rend="italic">Botallus</hi>, <q rend="diple">we ſend them to <lb/>the
            Farriers. The Goldſmith has the <lb/>mending of a Lord's Chain, or a Lady's
            <lb/>Bracelet. Diamonds and Precious Stones <lb/>are the ]eweller's Province. And when
            our <lb/>Cloaths want Furbiſhing, we put them <lb/>into the Botcher's Hands. But for
            Life and <lb/>Health, either we don't trouble ourſelves <lb/>about them, or we truſt any
            One with them, <lb/>any confident <hi rend="italic">Jackanapes</hi>, ſooner than a
            <lb/>Phyſician; and it fares with us accord- <lb/>ingly. </q> Agen ſays the ſame Author,
            <q rend="diple">When <lb/>a Man finds himſelf out of order, he may <lb/>preſcribe
            himſelf a Dram or a Cordial, if <lb/>he pleaſes; but for the reſt, he muſt have
            <lb/>Recourſe to the Phyſician. And let him <lb/>conſult not Books, but Men. Med'cine is
            <lb/>always better in Manuſcript, than in Print. </q>
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Benedictus</hi> has a valuable Admonition to the <lb/>ſame Effect.
            <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)" n="†">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>† Nec cuivis præſidium profitenti, valetudinis deſiderio <lb/>ſtatim credatur,
              ſolis medicis occidendi impunitate reli- <lb/>ctà. <hi rend="italic">De Med. atq; Æg.
                Officio Aphoriſm. c. 1.</hi>
            </p>
          </note>
          <q rend="diple">Pain </q>, ſays he, <q rend="diple"> and Sickneſs
            <lb/>are ſtrangely Credulous and Curious, and <lb/>therefore we ſhould take particular
            care <lb/>not to be prevail'd upon by their Importu- <lb/>nities to lay hold of every
            one's Help and <lb/>Advice that offers it, and call in the Phy- <pb n="30"/>
            <lb/>ſician only at laſt, like a Sheriff to an Exe- <lb/>cution. </q> Further; if you
          think there's <lb/>Frugality in ſtaying beyond the Criſis— </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ja.</hi> You'll ſay, I ſhall find myſelf Miſta- <lb/>ken; which I
          can't deny. Some time <lb/>ſince, you know, I was ſadly afflicted with <lb/>the Colick. I
          ſtay'd 'till all the Women <lb/>of Faſhion and Pretence in the Country had <lb/>ſpent the
          Flower of their Cloſets upon me, <lb/>and given me over. At laſt, when the Pain <lb/>had
          foil'd my own Patience and their Medi- <lb/>caments, I made my Complaint to Doctor <lb/>—
          who order'd me two or three Bottles <lb/>of ſomething, that gave me preſent Eaſe, <lb/>and
          reſtor'd me to perfect Health in a <lb/>Week. Now when I had caſt up the Charge <lb/>of
          the Preſents I had ſent to my Doctreſſes, <lb/>and the Viſits I receiv'd from them, I
          found it <lb/>riſe to ten Pound more than the Phyſician's <lb/>Fee, and the Apothecary's
          Bill. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi> Methinks, that might have made a <lb/>Convert of you. But
          to purſue my Advan- <lb/>tage. There's yet another Conſideration <lb/>that ſhould prevail
          with Sick People to make <lb/>uſe of a Phyſician early; becauſe if they ſtay <lb/>ſo long
          that there's little or nothing to be <lb/>done, 'tis odds whether the Phyſician will
          <lb/>venture to be concern'd. One of the Facul- <lb/>tie tells us, <note place="bottom"
            rend="size(0.5)" n="*">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Prudentis Medici eſt inſanabiles ac deſperatos mor- <lb/>bos non curare,
              &amp;c. <hi rend="italic">De Med. atq; Ægri. Offic. Aphor. c. 1.</hi>
            </p>
          </note>
          <q rend="diple">'Tis an lnſtance of a Phyſici- <pb n="31"/>
            <lb/>an's Wiſdom, not to have any thing to do <lb/>with Incurable Diſtempers, and burn
            his <lb/>Fingers with Impoſſibilities: For let Reco- <lb/>very be never ſo
            Impracticable, the Phyſi- <lb/>cian muſt expect to be charg'd with taking <lb/>away
            every Life he does not ſave. If he is <lb/>not a Deliverer, he muſt be a Murderer. </q>
          <lb/>And a Man has yet more Reaſon to be Cau- <lb/>tious and Angry, where a Patient has
          <lb/>been pleas'd to compliment Unqualified <lb/>Undertakers with the beſt Opportunities
          of <lb/>recovering him; for as another Phyſician, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Botallus</hi>,
          obſerves, <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)" n="*">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Intelligite vos Patientes multos, ne dicam forte om- <lb/>nes homines eſſe
              paratos ac liberales in medicis confi<unclear>n</unclear>is <lb/>promendis, &amp;c.
                <hi rend="italic">De Med. &amp; Ægr. Munere</hi>. </p>
          </note>
          <q rend="diple">There are few Peo- <lb/>ple, if any, to be found, but what are
            <lb/>ready with Receipts for the Sick at firſt <lb/>Sight, and throw them into a Courſe
            with- <lb/>out more ado. But when their Skill has <lb/>had its uſual Effect, and they
            know not <lb/>how to manage the Miſchieſs of their own <lb/>making, they'll meddle no
            further, and <lb/>are as humble and unpretending for a lit- <lb/>tle time, as one would
            wiſh. However, </q>
          <lb/>ſays the <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)" n="†">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>† <hi rend="italic">Ubi ſupra</hi>. </p>
          </note> former Author, <q rend="diple">let the Phyſician <lb/>venture where he
            has any Sparks of Hope <lb/>to encourage and direct him. Only the <lb/>Family ought to
            know what the Odds are <lb/>againſt him: Elſe the Blame of a Miſcarri- <lb/>age will
            light upon the Profeſſion, or at <pb n="32"/>
            <lb/>leaſt upon the Man. You'll be believ'd be- <lb/>fore the Defeat, but not eaſily
            after it. <lb/>I know </q>(continues my Author) <q rend="diple">there are
            <lb/>many Advocates for the contrary Opinion, <lb/>that let the Complexion of Affairs be
            ne- <lb/>ver ſo bad, ſomething muſt be try'd; and <lb/>that the beſt Means that can be
            thought <lb/>of, however unpromiſing, are never thrown <lb/>away. </q> Whichever of
          theſe Rules is right, <lb/>you ſee what lamentable Difficulties and <hi rend="italic">Di-
            <lb/>lemmas</hi> are the Conſequence of loſing Time, <lb/>and leaving the Country Open
          and Expos'd <lb/>to the Invader. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ja.</hi> Methinks the Doctor might be ſo kind <lb/>as to come of
          his own accord, and offer his <lb/>Services. This would make him famous <lb/>for his
          Humanity. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi> But not for his Diſcretion. Such For- <lb/>wardneſs is
          forbid by Maxim. <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)" n="*">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Accerſitus adeas, non alias: &amp;c. <hi rend="italic">Botallus, de Med. &amp;
                <lb/>Ægr. Munere</hi>. </p>
          </note>
          <q rend="diple">Come <lb/>to a Patient when you are call'd, ſays a <lb/>Phyſician; Make as
            much haſte as you <lb/>pleaſe then, but not before. When the <lb/>Price of your Wares is
            ſtated and known, <lb/>your Cuſtomers will have the meaner o- <lb/>pinion of them, for
            your bringing them to <lb/>their Doors. </q> And another of them to the <lb/>ſame
          Purpoſe; <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)" n="†">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>† Vitato aſſiduæ conſuetudinis faſtidio, &amp;c. <hi rend="italic">Gabr. à
                <lb/>Fonſeca, Med. OEcon.</hi>
            </p>
          </note>
          <q rend="diple">He that would not make <pb n="33"/>
            <lb/>ſelf cheap, muſt avoid an Exceſs of Con- <lb/>deſcenſion, and keep ſomewhat upon
            the <lb/>Diſtance and the Reſerve. Intruſion and <lb/>Fondneſs for Company is a
            Leſſening <lb/>Infirmity. The way to be reſpected is <lb/>not to be too Forward and
            Familiar. <lb/>And for this Reaſon 'twill be adviſeable <lb/>for a Phyſician not to
            proffer his Service, <lb/>but to ſtay till he has a Summons. 'Tis <lb/>true, it
            diſcovers a noble Benevolence of <lb/>Temper, to lay hold of all Opportunities <lb/>of
            doing Good. But yet good Offices, if <lb/>a Man's Prodigal of them, go a Begging <lb/>at
            laſt; and an Art may be ſo Liberal as to <lb/>make itſelf Contemptible. </q> But to mend
          <lb/>my pace, and keep up with the Argument; <lb/>When the Phyſician's come, 'tis the
          Patient's <lb/>Duty, in the next place, to repreſent his Con- <lb/>dition as diſtinctly
          and fully to him as he can. <lb/>He's neither to let Modeſty, in ſome Caſes, <lb/>nor
          Shame, in others, prevail with him to <lb/>conceal any Circumſtances, or dreſs up the
          <lb/>Diſtemper in falſe and flattering Colours. <lb/>If we fall into noiſome Circumſtances
          by <lb/>Misfortune, or if ſuch is the Nature or Seat <lb/>of the Diſeaſe, that a Baſhful
          Man muſt put <lb/>a Force upon himſelf to mention it; then <lb/>Hiding or Diſguiſing is
          Modeſty no longer, <lb/>but Infirmity. If our own Sin and Folly <lb/>have diſtreſs'd us,
          the Conſciouſneſs of it <lb/>ſhould diſpoſe us indeed to Repentance and <lb/>Reſolutions
          of Reformation, but by no means <pb n="34"/>
          <lb/>to Shyneſs and Neglect of a Cure. <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Sunt etiam qui aliqua clandeſtina libidine flagrant: <lb/>&amp;c. <hi
                rend="italic">Botallus de Med. &amp; Æg. M.</hi>
            </p>
          </note>
          <q rend="diple">One <lb/>Man endeavours to ſmother a Paſſion of <lb/>Love or Luſt, that's
            flaming in his Heart; <lb/>Another ſuppreſſes his Anger, tho' his <lb/>Eyes glow with
            it. One Man's Vitals are <lb/>ſecretly Chill'd with Fear; Another's Wa- <lb/>ſted with
            Care. Now theſe Diſcompoſures <lb/>are either Principals or Seconds in the <lb/>Quarrel;
            and yet that's more perhaps than <lb/>the Doctor knows. But if the Gentle- <lb/>man's
            Caſe muſt not be diſtinctly under- <lb/>ſtood, the Doctor ought to be told at leaſt
            <lb/>in general, what ſhare his Mind has in his <lb/>Malady. For this is more than a
            Circum- <lb/>ſtance; and may make it neceſſary to alter <lb/>his Plan, and change his
            Batteries. </q> The <lb/>ſame Author (for I am now borrowing) <lb/>has a remarkable
          Story to this Purpoſe. <lb/>
          <q rend="diple">
            <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)" n="†">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>† His proximis diebus patientem tractabam, &amp;c. <lb/><hi rend="italic"
                  >Ibid.</hi>
              </p>
            </note> I had a Patient </q>, ſays he, <q rend="diple"> at <hi rend="italic"
              >Paris</hi> t'other <lb/>Day, that thought himſelf in a Feaver, and <lb/>complain'd of
            a great Pain and Op- <lb/>preſſion in his Breaſt. I could find no Fea- <lb/>veriſh
            Symptoms; and I was to take his <lb/>word for t'other. He expreſs'd an Un- <lb/>common
            Impatience, ſigh'd much, and <lb/>reſted little. I purg'd him; I chaff'd his
            <lb/>Breaſt, and ſtroak'd it with comfortable <pb n="35"/>
            <lb/>Liniments; and did what elſe I thought <lb/>moſt likely to relieve him. I forbore
            <lb/>Bleeding, becauſe he did not complain of <lb/>any fixt or conſtant Pain, and he
            breath'd <lb/>freely. Beſides, he was threeſcore Years <lb/>old; and 'twas Winter. This
            paſs'd on <lb/>for four Days. Upon the Fourth Day <lb/>about two a Clock in the
            Afternoon, this <lb/>Unintelligible Diſorder unmask'd, and <lb/>vaniſh'd on a ſudden,
            while I was in the <lb/>Room. The Gentleman's Servant came <lb/>up, and brought him word
            he had carried <lb/>his Cauſe at <hi rend="italic">Lions</hi>. It ſeems 'twas the
            <lb/>Iſſue of a Law-Suit that had made his Heart <lb/>ake, and given him ſuch a racking
            Pain <lb/>thereabouts. The News was ſcarce told, <lb/>when my Patient, who lay the
            Minute <lb/>before, as if he was expiring, mounts up <lb/>in his Bed; Well, now, ſays
            he, the Pain's <lb/>quite gone, and I'm as well this moment <lb/>as ever I was in my
            Life. I find I was <lb/>Sick of Sollicitude; and if I had not been <lb/>Defendant at <hi
              rend="italic">Lions</hi>, I had not been Plan- <lb/>tiff here. </q> To return; This
          Covering and <lb/>Diſguiſing is not only Dangerous, but very <lb/>often Impracticable. A
          Cheat will not ea- <lb/>ſily paſs upon <hi rend="italic">Science</hi>. The Heart is the
          <lb/>only Part of the Body a good Phyſician can't <lb/>ſee into. Some Features and
          Indications of <lb/>Impoſture will be peeping out, and 'ſcape <lb/>Prevention. A
          Diſſembled Caſe lies as o- <lb/>pen to a Profeſſor, as a Counterfeit Coin to <pb n="36"/>
          <lb/>an Antiquarie. And then a Man, beſides <lb/>the Diſgrace of the Diſeaſe, has that of
          the <lb/>Detection too, to diſcompoſe him; which <lb/>is to ſome People the greater
          Mortification <lb/>of the two. And withall he may have Rea- <lb/>ſon to fear the Phyſician
          will revenge Di- <lb/>ſtruſt with Diſcovery; whereas if he had <lb/>been confided in, he
          would not have been <lb/>provok'd to betray. <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)" n="*">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Alienam miſeriam pudoris ſociam indicare nefas eſt, <lb/><hi rend="italic"
                >Alex. Benedictus De Med. atq; Ægri Offic. Aphoriſm. c. 1.</hi>
            </p>
          </note>
          <q rend="diple">In Infamous or <lb/>Diſreputable Caſes, a Man of Honour </q>,
          <lb/>ſays <hi rend="italic">Benedictus</hi> very rightly, <q rend="diple"> will
            keep <lb/>the Secret as carefully as he'll attend the <lb/>Cure. For 'tis barbarous, to
            put a Man <lb/>to Pain in his Character, that has already <lb/>ſo much of it in his
            Bones. </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ja.</hi> Thus far I agree with you. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi> I don't doubt but we ſhall underſtand <lb/>one another by
          and by. — I have two or <lb/>three ſhort Precepts more for the Patient, <lb/>and then I
          come to the Doctor's Duty; which, <lb/>I ſuppoſe, you long to hear. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ja.</hi> I expect Impartiality. You have <lb/>brought the Phyſician
          to the Bedſide; One <lb/>would think you might leave him there. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi> If the Patient be perfectly right in his <lb/>Senſes. But
          the truth is, many Sick People <lb/>are more Lightheaded at the begining of a <lb/>Fit of
          Sickneſs, than afterwards. And this <lb/>is the beſt Defence I can make for thoſe, that
            <pb n="37"/>
          <lb/>when they have conſulted a Doctor, and had <lb/>his Advice, over rule his Directions,
          and <lb/>throw away his Phyſick. You ſhall have a <lb/>Learned Phyſician's Reflections
          upon this <lb/>matter, if you pleaſe. <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)" n="*">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Æger obſequens eſſe debet: &amp;c. <hi rend="italic">Alex. Benedictus,
                <lb/>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
          </note>
          <q rend="diple">The Patient </q>, ſays <lb/>he, <q rend="diple">muſt be
            governable, and reſign to thoſe <lb/>that have the care of him, eſpecially to <lb/>the
            Phyſician: And neither the Sick Man, <lb/>nor they that are about him, may pre-
            <lb/>ſume to impoſe upon the Phyſician, or elude <lb/>his Directions. The Patient's
            Irregulari- <lb/>tie and Impatience light hardeſt upon him- <lb/>ſelf. This ſort of
            Sedition, tho' never ſo <lb/>induſtriouſly conceal'd, always breaks out <lb/>in the
            Conſequences. </q> Another tells us, <lb/>
          <q rend="diple">
            <note n="†" place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>† Certiſſimum experimentum quotidie commonſtrat, <lb/>&amp;c. <hi rend="italic"
                  >Gabr. à Fonſeca, Med. OEcon.</hi>
              </p>
            </note> 'tis Fact, and that daily Obſervation <lb/>proves it ſo, that more Men loſe
            their <lb/>Lives by their own Obſtinacy, than by all <lb/>the Diſtempers in a Bill of
            Mortality put <lb/>together. </q> So ſays <hi rend="italic">Botallus</hi> too; <note
            n="‖" rend="size(0.5)" place="bottom">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>‖ Etſi in multis peccare in ſuo officio poſſit Medicus: <lb/>&amp;c. <hi
                rend="italic">De Med. &amp; Æg. Offic.</hi>
            </p>
          </note>
          <q rend="diple">A <lb/>Phyſician, 'tis true, miſtakes his way ſome- <lb/>times; but where
            one Man dies of the <lb/>Doctor, a hundred miſcarry by their own <lb/>Folly. 'Tis no
            wonder that Ignorant, Neg- <lb/>ligent, Ungovernable, Enterprizing Peo- <lb/>ple ſhould
            not eaſily get over at Fit of Sick- <pb n="38"/>
            <lb/>neſs. </q> And elſewhere he affirms, <note n="*" rend="size(0.5)" place="bottom">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Oportet pro rato habendum facilius poſſe multos æ- <lb/>gros morigeros: &amp;c.
                <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
          </note>
          <q rend="diple">That <lb/>one Phyſician, or even the Unaſſiſted <lb/>Strength of Nature,
            may recover a much <lb/>greater Number of Complying and Order- <lb/>ly Patients, than a
            whole College can of <lb/>perverſe ones, that ſuppreſs their Com- <lb/>plaints, and
            refuſe their Submiſſion. </q> Fur- <lb/>ther, theres Ill Manners as well as Abſurdity
          <lb/>in this Inſtance of Misbehaviour. Not to <lb/>make uſe of a Phyſician is a
          Preſumptuous <lb/>Neglect of ourſelves; But 'tis over and above, <lb/>an Incivility, and a
          Contempt of his Cha- <lb/>racter, to defeat his Care, and proteſt his <lb/>Bills. Beſides,
          this Conduct implys a ſtrange <lb/>Inconſiſtency and Levity. For at laſt, if we
          <lb/>underſtand the matter right, the Doctor's <lb/>Preſcription, in this Caſe, is our own
          at Se- <lb/>cond Hand. If we can't confide in him, <lb/>why do we conſult him? And if we
          can, <lb/>why don't we? </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ja.</hi> Excuſe me, Madam; That Conſe- <lb/>quence has its
          Exceptions. For the purpoſe, <lb/>if I have made Tryal before of the Druggs <lb/>he orders
          me, and found them Abhorrent to <lb/>my Nature; or if I know there's Poiſon in <lb/>the
          Potion; muſt I join my Lips to Death, <lb/>and drench myſelf as meekly as a Diſcarded
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Vizier</hi> would receive the fatal Bowl from <pb n="39"/>
          <lb/>the Hand of an <hi rend="italic">Eunuch</hi>? I never thought <lb/>the Phyſician ſo
          abſolute. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi> The laſt of your Objections, if you <lb/>apply it in
          Earneſt, is not to be imagin'd. <lb/>'Tis out of the Confines of the Queſtion too;
          <lb/>and carrys you to the World in the Moon. <lb/>It affects your Cook, Butler,
          Dairymaid, <lb/>all your Domeſticks, Relations, Neighbours, <lb/>and Acquaintance, as much
          as your Doctor. <lb/>And as for t'other, 'tis plainly a ſtudied one. <lb/>For tho' a
          Phyſician may be a Humoriſt as <lb/>well as another Man; yet is it probable he <lb/>ſhould
          be ſo little concern'd for his own Re- <lb/>putation and Intereſt, as to ask no previous
          <lb/>Queſtions about his Patient's Conſtitution, <lb/>Antipathies, and Management of
          himſelf? <lb/>At leaſt, if a Caution's given him, it can't <lb/>be conceiv'd he ſhould lie
          under any Temp- <lb/>tation to impoſe unneceſſary Severities upon <lb/>his Patient, and
          join the Enemy Himſelf <lb/>with his Auxiliaries. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ja.</hi> What if I follow his Directions, and <lb/>grow worſe? </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi> If you have no other Reaſon to ſuſpect <lb/>his Judgment
          or Integrity, but a longer Con- <lb/>tinuance of the Diſtemper than you expect- <lb/>ed,
          let not That determine you too ſoon to <lb/>his Diſadvantage. For 'tis one Phyſician's
          <lb/>Advice to another, <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)" n="*">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* A recta ratione nonquam <unclear>drſcedendem</unclear> eſt, &amp;c. <hi
                rend="italic">Be- <lb/>nedictus, De Med. <unclear>atq; Ægri. Offic.</unclear></hi>
            </p>
          </note>
          <q rend="diple">to abide obſtinate- <pb n="40"/>
            <lb/>ly by thoſe Means and Meaſures that he's <lb/>ſure are Rational and Well-grounded,
            tho' <lb/>he waits long the good Effects of them; <lb/>and never to purſue a Hazardous
            and <lb/>Uncertain Method, becauſe it has not been <lb/>follow'd long enough to do any
            viſible <lb/>Miſchief; For that Caſualties are ſo ſar <lb/>from being general Rules,
            that they are <lb/>only Exceptions. </q> However 'tis not ſafe <lb/>to be too Implicit
          neither. If you find your <lb/>Champion foil'd; if you don't mend with- <lb/>in any
          reaſonable Time; much more, if you <lb/>grow worſe; you are certainly at Liberty <lb/>to
          take Notice of it to him. And if the Symp- <lb/>toms look formidable, and Danger haſtens
          <lb/>its Approaches, to deſire him to think of <lb/>conferring with a Brother of the
          Facultie, <lb/>and if he refuſes, (which very rarely hap- <lb/>pens) to diſmiſs him, and
          ſeek elſewhere for <lb/>Help. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ja<choice>
              <corr>.</corr>
              <sic/>
            </choice></hi> No doubt on't. In good Time, if <lb/>the Diſtemper's Chronical enough,
          the Houſe <lb/>may be full of Phyſicians. Thoſe ſame <hi rend="italic">Con-
            <lb/>ſults</hi>, I confeſs, are a Maſterpiece! For ei- <lb/>ther the Aſſiſtants will
          agree with the firſt <lb/>Doctor, or differ from him. If they agree, <lb/>then One would
          have done as well as Both. <lb/>If they diſagree, what better Iſſue's to be <lb/>expected
          from the Claſhing Opinions of <lb/>Two or more, than from the Uniform Pro- <lb/>ceedings
          of One? When they have made <lb/>the moſt of their Maxims, the only new <pb n="41"/>
          <lb/>Reſolution you can come to is to truſt your- <lb/>ſelf with a new Doctor, or with
          none. And <lb/>what's a new one to do? Why truly he <lb/>has double work upon his Hands;
          He has <lb/>his Predeceſſor's Errors, as well as his Pati- <lb/>ent's Conſtitution, to
          correct. And at laſt you <lb/>have only the ſame Chance as before, whe- <lb/>ther you
          ſha'nt be left in a Condition a third <lb/>part worſe than he found you in, for others
          <lb/>of the Faculty to take their turn, and carry <lb/>off their Shares of the <hi
            rend="italic">Wreck</hi> too. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi> Soft and fair. Your Speed, I'm ſure, <lb/>has carry'd your
          Ladyſhip on the wrong <lb/>ſide o' th' Poſt. Let's apprehend one another <lb/>right. I
          would not have it quoted for my <lb/>Opinion, that Phyſicians ought to aſſemble <lb/>in as
          Numerous Bodys as General Coun- <lb/>cils. The Circumſtances of Perſons, and <lb/>the Turn
          of Things, are the beſt Rule in <lb/>theſe Difficulties. If the Patient's Life and
          <lb/>Health are of great Importance, either to <lb/>the Family or the Publick, nothing
          ſhould <lb/>be omitted that any Good can be hoped from. <lb/>The whole <hi rend="italic"
            >Poſſe</hi> of Nature and Art ſhould be <lb/>muſter'd. Agen; If there's a Life of leſs
          Con- <lb/>ſequence at ſtake, and if none of the known <lb/>and uſual Expedients have been
          neglect- <lb/>ed; If the Skill of two or three Authoriz'd <lb/>and Careful Phyſicians
          gives way, and the <lb/>Diſeaſe forces all their Intrenchments; I <lb/>will not ſay but
          the Patient's free to gratify <lb/>a Departing Curioſity with the Med'cines <pb n="42"/>
          <lb/>of all the Matrons in the Country. After <lb/>Sentence of Death pronounc'd, he may
          <lb/>make a Bargain of his Body if he pleaſes. <lb/>And, for your Comfort, Madam, you
          <lb/>know ſuch lurking Embers of Life have <lb/>ſometimes ſurviv'd an Execution as have
          <lb/>kindled it up agen. I'll allow you to pleaſe <lb/>yourſelf with juſt ſuch a
          Poſſibility as this, <lb/>when a Conſult of Learned Phyſicians have <lb/>done what they
          can for you, and give you <lb/>over. To do you further Juſtice; It ſeems <lb/>you think it
          abſurd, when one Phyſician has <lb/>done you no Service, to conſult another; <lb/>and your
          Reaſon for it is, becauſe if the laſt <lb/>Comer ſtrikes into the Meaſures of the firſt,
          <lb/>your Purſe may be ſomewhar lighter, but <lb/>you are ſtill where you were; and if he
          does <lb/>not, you are ne'r the nearer a Cure, and <lb/>may be practic'd upon to Death. I
          think <lb/>that's your Argument. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ja.</hi> And what's your Anſwer? </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi> 'Tis this; if they agree, you may be- <lb/>gin to ſuppoſe
          your Condition deſperare, <lb/>or conclude you have not try'd the Courſe <lb/>you are in
          long enough; which laſt will be <lb/>a Cordial however, if it does not end in a <lb/>Cure.
          And if the laſt Phyſician ſees the Mi- <lb/>ſtake of the Firſt, or believes he does, you
          <lb/>may demand his Reaſons without Preſump- <lb/>tion, and 'tis like he may be furniſh'd
          with <lb/>them by an Inſight into the Error of his Bro- <lb/>ther's Method. We have all a
          better Hand <pb n="43"/>
          <lb/>at finding out other People's Miſtakes than <lb/>our own. Thoſe <hi rend="italic"
            >Subtilties</hi> of Nature, which a <lb/>Single Microſcope will not reach, a Double
          <lb/>one diſcovers in a trice to advantage. Ob- <lb/>ſerve agen, how Partial you are
          pleas'd to <lb/>be in your Suppoſals. You Viſit the Sick, <lb/>more like an Ill-boding
          Bird than a Friend. <lb/>Your Meſſage is all to the Purpoſe of Diſap- <lb/>pointment and
          Death. <q rend="diple">What </q>, ſay you, <lb/>
          <q rend="diple">if every new Undertaker ſhould make <lb/>things worſe than he
            found them? Sup- <lb/>poſe their Practices run foul upon one an- <lb/>other, and each of
            them luggs off a Limb <lb/>of you? </q> What's all this but Phantom and <lb/>Chimera?
          Does ſuch a thing happen once <lb/>in a thouſand Inſtances? And then agen, <lb/>ſay I in
          my turn, <q rend="diple">What if a Second or <lb/>a Third prevents or ſtops the Ill Conſe-
            <lb/>quences of a former Miſmanagement, fa- <lb/>ſtens upon the True Cauſe, and
            reinſtates <lb/>you in Health and Vigour? </q> Does this ſo <lb/>rarely happen, Madam,
          that it could not <lb/>enter into your Thoughts? Fallibility will <lb/>always be a Weak
          Argument againſt the uſe <lb/>of Reaſon. And, as one of the Faculty ob- <lb/>ſerves very
          well, <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)" n="*">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Errorem in homine quamvis ſapientiſſimo calum- <lb/>niari, &amp;c. <hi
                rend="italic">Gab. à Fonſeca, Med. OEcon.</hi>
            </p>
          </note>
          <q rend="diple">the Reproaches that <lb/>are thrown upon a Knowing and a Wiſe <lb/>Man for
            the Misfortune of a Miſtake, are <lb/>an Indignity offer'd to the Honour of Man- <pb
              n="44"/>
            <lb/>kind, and ought to be Reſented Univerſal- <lb/>ly. </q> If lmperfection would
          juſtifie Uſe- <lb/>leſſneſs, we might all be Idle upon Principle. <lb/>And he that's
          afraid to uſe his Legs, becauſe <lb/>he may ſtumble, may e'en lie a bed till <lb/>they
          mortifie. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ja.</hi> In earneſt, <hi rend="italic">Olympia</hi>, I'm afraid
          you'll <lb/>never be wean'd from this Weakneſs. I <lb/>ſuppoſe you us'd to have more
          Phyſicians <lb/>about you in your Sickneſs, than other Wo- <lb/>men have Goſſips at their
          Labour. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi> You'll be leſs Severe by and by. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ja.</hi> In the mean time, ſince the Clue of <lb/>the Argument has
          brought us to the Buſi- <lb/>neſs of Conſults, let's know, if you pleaſe, <lb/>how they're
          to be govern'd. This is a Point, <lb/>I ſuppoſe, the Doctors have refin'd upon. <lb/>It
          goes deep in their Affairs, and brings a <lb/>great deal of good Lining into their Poc-
          <lb/>kets. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi> And yet it lies under ſome Reſtricti- <lb/>ons that keep a
          Man upon his Guard, and <lb/>Fetter him with Maxims. You may have a <lb/>Specimen of them
          from the Phyſicians them- <lb/>ſelves, who ſhould beſt underſtand them. <lb/>To begin
          then; 'Tis <hi rend="italic">Botallus</hi>'s Opinion, <lb/>
          <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Medicorum conſilia ſeorſum ab ægris ineunda ſunt, <lb/>&amp;c. <hi
                rend="italic">Ubi ſupra.</hi>
            </p>
          </note>
          <q rend="diple">That no Conſults ought to be held in <lb/>the Patient's Preſence, becauſe
            'tis not fit <lb/>he ſhould know all the Circumſtances of <pb n="45"/>
            <lb/>his Caſe that are neceſſary to be canvaſs'd, <lb/>the bad as well as the good.
            Damps and De- <lb/>ſpair Sett their Teeth where they ſeize; and <lb/>'tis much eaſier to
            keep them off at firſt, than <lb/>to make them quit their hold afterwards. </q> As
          <lb/>to the Time when recourſe ſhould be had to <lb/>them; <note place="bottom"
            rend="size(0.5)" n="*">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Conſultoribus tunc... opus eſt; tum quia &amp;c. <hi rend="italic">Ubi
                <lb/>ſupra.</hi>
            </p>
          </note>
          <q rend="diple">There is a neceſſity </q>, ſays <hi rend="italic">Fonſeca</hi>,
            <q rend="diple"> for <lb/>Conſults, when a Phyſician finds himſelf <lb/>overmatch'd.
            Where much depends up- <lb/>on't, all Parties will ſtrain their Faculties <lb/>for
            Diſcoveries, and one Man obſerve <lb/>what 'ſcapes another. <hi rend="italic"
              >Numbers</hi> are beſt <lb/>at Invention. A <hi rend="italic">Cabinet</hi> of the
            Facultie <lb/>ſees, like <hi rend="italic">Argus</hi>, every way at once. Be-
            <lb/>ſides, as <hi rend="italic">Solomon</hi> ſays, <q rend="italic">Without counſel,
              <lb/>purpoſes are diſappointed: but in the mul- <lb/>titude of counſellers they are
              eſtabliſhed </q>. </q>
          <lb/>And then too, as <hi rend="italic">Fonſeca</hi> further ſuggeſts, <lb/>
          <q rend="diple">a Phyſician's calling-in more Aſſiſtance is <lb/>finding Security for his
            own Reputation. <lb/>It covers him from Cenſure and Miſreport. <lb/>If his Management
            ſhould be queſtion'd, <lb/>his Brethren can do him Juſtice, and ſo the <lb/><hi
              rend="italic">Cataſtrophe</hi> of a Violent Diſtemper won't <lb/>be charg'd upon the
            Doctor's Ignorance or <lb/>Indiſcretion. </q> As to the Number of Per- <lb/>ſons that
          are to be at it, <hi rend="italic">Botallus</hi> is for a few; <lb/>
          <note rend="size(0.5)" place="bottom" n="†">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>† Confundit potius multitudo medicorum <unclear>quim</unclear> ju- <lb/>vet;
              &amp;c. <hi rend="italic">Ubi ſupra.</hi>
            </p>
          </note>
          <q rend="diple">A Numerous Conſult's more likely to <pb n="46"/>
            <lb/>perplex things than to clear them. Two <lb/>or Three good Phyſicians, Honeſt and
            <lb/>Knowing, are enow; and ſeldom leave a <lb/>Fourth matter to work upon. </q> As to
          the <lb/>Quality of them; <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)" n="*">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* .. ſeorſumq; à populo uno auditore, &amp;c. <hi rend="italic">Ubi
                <lb/>ſupra.</hi>
            </p>
          </note>
          <q rend="diple">Admit none </q>(ſays the <lb/>ſame Author) <q rend="diple"
           >but Phyſicians to your Con- <lb/>ferences, or at moſt but one or two Per-
            <lb/>ſons more, a Nurſe, or an Attendant, or <lb/>ſo. Intruders and Interlopers always
            croſs <lb/>upon Men of Knowledge. Either there <lb/>are more or fewer Ingredients in the
            Bill <lb/>than there ſhou'd be! Or if you preferr <lb/>the Wiſdom of the College to
            their tedi- <lb/>ous Impertinence, the whole <hi rend="italic">Regimen's</hi>
            <lb/>abſolutely condemn'd, and your Reputa- <lb/>tion murder'd, if your Med'cine does
            not <lb/>work as quick as a Miracle. Another In- <lb/>convenience is, that if any Party
            in the <lb/>Conſult happens to be Poſitive and Con- <lb/>ceited, the Weakneſs and
            Ignorance of the <lb/>By-ſtanders encourage his Confidence, <lb/>and make him
            inſufferably troubleſome. <lb/>He'll be the Foreman. He knows Thoſe <lb/>that know leaſt
            are always Friends to <lb/>thoſe that talk moſt; and ſo he puſhes his <lb/>Advantage,
            hears no Body, and makes e- <lb/>very Body hear him; cancels a well-con- <lb/>certed
            Scheme, flouriſhes upon his own, <lb/>and perhaps plagues his Brethren at laſt <pb
              n="47"/>
            <lb/>into a Compliance too. </q> To the ſame effect <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fonſeca</hi>;
            <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Conſultationi velut <unclear>rei</unclear> graviſſimæ
                <unclear>nunquam</unclear> aſtantes <lb/>affineſve &amp;c. <hi rend="italic">Ubi
                ſupra.</hi>
            </p>
          </note>
          <q rend="diple">The Debates of Phyſicians <lb/>ought to be as private as
            poſſible. How <lb/>often have they and their Patients far'd <lb/>the worſe, for letting
            People into the Place <lb/>of Conſultation, that had no Buſineſs <lb/>there? They that
            envy Men their Know- <lb/>ledge, as the Ignorant always do, make <lb/>the ſame ill uſe
            of the Diſputes of Phyſi- <lb/>cians, as of thoſe of Divines; turn them to <lb/>the
            Diſparagement, not only of the Diſ- <lb/>putants, but the Profeſſion itſelf<choice>
              <corr>.</corr>
              <sic/>
            </choice> An- <lb/>other Inconvenience, </q> continues my Au- <lb/>thor, <q rend="diple"
            > is this; that Phyſicians, who have <lb/>their Failings in Common with other Men,
            <lb/>may be Poſitive and Dogmatical. Not <lb/>unlikely, their Hypotheſes may claſh, and
            <lb/>and yet every One muſt maintain his own <lb/>vigorouſly, as he values his
            Reputation. <lb/>Tho' he ſhould be made ſecretly ſenſible <lb/>that he's out in his
            Meaſures, yet his Con- <lb/>cern for his Character ſollicits ſtrongly to <lb/>give up
            his Patient rather than his Poſition. <lb/>Whereas if only the Facultie are upon the
            <lb/>Spot, he may acquieſce without Danger <lb/>of any Blemiſh upon his Honour. In
            ſhort, <lb/>a Conſult of Opiniaters ought to be lock'd <lb/>up as cloſe as a Jury.
            They'd certainly come <lb/><pb n="48"/> the ſooner to a right Underſtanding and
            <lb/>Unanimity. </q>
        </p>
        <gap reason="sampling" quantity="44" unit="pages"/>
      </div>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="42"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
