<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - London Physician: The Modern Quack; or, the Physical Impostor,
          Detected</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>London Physician</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">THE Modern QUACK; OR, THE Physical Impostor, DETECTED. In Three
              Parts. I. Exposing their Qualifications and Remedies. II. Proving the Insufficiency of
              the Latter to Answer what is proposed by them. III. Unfolding their Nature and ill
              Consequences. WITH A Supplement, displaying the present Set of Pretenders to
              Clap-curing, giving Judgment upon Urine, &amp;c. in which their Frauds and Abuses are laid
              open; Rules also to know, and Cautions against them. To which [for the farther
              Security of the Sick of any sort] a Catalogue is annexed of all the Members of the
              Royal College of Physicians, residing in and about the Town, with the Places of their
              several Abodes or Habitations. </title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T93454</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T93454"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for J. Roberts near the Oxford Arms in Warwick-Lane, 1718.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1718</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="35"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="156"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="2"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW106849475</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Public welfare and institutional"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="35"/>
    <body>
      <pb n="1"/>
      <figure>
        <figDesc>An ornamental horizontal column, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <head rend="align-center size(1.5) sc">
        <lb/>the <lb/><hi rend="roman size(1.5)">Modern QUACKS. </hi>
      </head>
      <div type="part">
        <figure rend="space">
          <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>PART. I. </head>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Argument</hi>. </head>
        <head rend="italic hanging">
          <lb/>That there can be no Safety in relying upon <lb/>any Remedy left up and down the Town
          to <lb/>ſell at Tradeſmen's Shops, and publiſh'd by <lb/><hi rend="roman">Bills</hi>
          diſperſed for that Purpoſe, or <hi rend="roman">Adver- <lb/>tiſements</hi> in the <hi
            rend="roman">Prints</hi>; the ſame being <lb/>uſually made up by ignorant People, who
          <lb/>themſelves know not their real Uſe; or by <lb/>profeſs'd <hi rend="roman"
          >Quacks</hi>, who for baſe and ſordid <lb/>Lucre only, expoſe and ſet the ſame to Sale. </head>
        <p rend="space"><hi rend="dc(6)">A</hi>S the <hi rend="italic">Medicinal</hi> Profeſſion
          <lb/>upon Account of the Sub- <lb/>ject about which it is em- <lb/>ploy'd, has been at all
          <lb/>times reckon'd the moſt <lb/>uſeful; ſo, by reaſon of the <lb/>profound Judgment, as
          particularly by <lb/>the Diſſection of Humane Bodies, to be <pb n="2"/>
          <lb/>inform'd throughly of the exact Scituation, <lb/>the Nature and Uſes of the ſeveral
          Parts, <lb/>with as diligent an Enquiry into the ſe- <lb/>veral Properties and Vertues, as
          well of <lb/>ſimple as compounded Medicaments, <lb/>alſo the Manner of their Operation
          <lb/>when taken into our Bodies: For theſe <lb/>Reaſons, I ſay, it has been thought too
          <lb/>the moſt difficult of all others to be ac- <lb/>quir'd; and therefore the great
          Profi- <lb/>cients therein, have, by the Learned, <lb/>been uſually, and deſervedly, above
          all <lb/>others, highly honour'd and eſteem'd, <lb/>even deify'd by ſome of the Antients.
          <lb/>Yet notwithſtanding all this, if we ſur- <lb/>vey the Qualifications of ſome
          pretending <lb/>to this noble Profeſſion, a Man would <lb/>be apt to think it the eaſieſt
          of all <lb/>others; or that little elſe was thereto <lb/>wanting but the Name of a
          Diſeaſe, <lb/>without its Definition, and the turning <lb/>over ſome <hi rend="italic"
            >Receipt-Book</hi> to find ſomething <lb/>there enter'd, as a Remedy for the <lb/>ſame. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>That this is now the Foundation of <lb/>ſome Peoples Knowledge who ſtile them-
          <lb/>ſelves Phyſicians, and are vulgarly alſo <lb/>call'd Doctors, is no very difficult
          Matter <lb/>to make appear; from whence I think <lb/>the Conſequence is as eaſy, That
          there <lb/>can be no Safety in taking ſuch Reme- <pb n="3"/>
          <lb/>dies, which they ſet thus to Sale, as other <lb/>ſorts of Merchandize or Trading Com-
          <lb/>modities. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Having made it my Buſineſs to get the <lb/>beſt Intelligence I could, of the Authors
          <lb/>of theſe <hi rend="italic">Medicines</hi>, as well as of the <hi rend="italic">Me-
            <lb/>dicines</hi> themſelves, I found ſome of them <lb/>were profeſs'd <hi rend="italic"
            >Quacks</hi>, or ſorry <hi rend="italic">Chymiſts</hi>, <lb/>both alike ignorant in the
          Practice of Phy- <lb/>ſick. Others ſimple Tradeſmen, and foo- <lb/>liſh but bold Women.
          Others again from <lb/>ſome Family <hi rend="italic">Receipt</hi>, many Years toge-
          <lb/>ther handed down as ſome Sacred Re- <lb/>lique, by way of Tradition, and kept with-
          <lb/>in their own Walls, as they will tell you, <lb/>for many Ages, till at length falling
          to the <lb/>Share of one unwilling the mighty Trea- <lb/>ſure ſhould be longer conceal'd,
          or rather <lb/>for turning the Penny [which is termed <lb/>the publick Good] the ſame is
          expos'd, <lb/>with ſome hard Name, and a large Cata- <lb/>logue of its admirable Virtues.
          Others, <lb/>laſtly, transfer'd from ſome Phyſical <hi rend="italic">Pre- <lb/>ſcript</hi>
          on the Apothecary's File, or borrow- <lb/>ed directly from the <hi rend="italic"
            >Diſpenſatory</hi>, with a <lb/>Foreign Title, that [like other Things, far <lb/>fetch'd
          and dearly paid for] it may pleaſe <lb/>the better. This Charge will be ſtill far-
          <lb/>ther made appear, when I come preſently <lb/>to enquire into the Nature of theſe
          Reme- <lb/>dies; in the mean time I will appeal to <pb n="4"/>
          <lb/>all Perſons of a common Capacity, whe- <lb/>ther it be reaſonable to venture their
          Lives <lb/>[as too many of them do] upon ſo deſpe- <lb/>rate and weak a Bottom. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>If an idle Mechanick, or other Tradeſ- <lb/>man, having run out his Subſtance, and
          <lb/>not caring to Work at his proper Occupa- <lb/>tion, procuring a <hi rend="italic"
            >Diſpenſatory</hi>, or ſome <lb/>other Phyſick Book in his Mother Tongue, <lb/>ſhall
          thereby underſtand, that <hi rend="italic">Gamboge</hi>, <lb/>as it is called, and <hi
            rend="italic">Elaterium</hi>, or the Juice of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Wild
            Cucumber</hi>, are the moſt powerful <lb/>Remedies to cure a <hi rend="italic"
            >Dropſy</hi>; that the Root <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Bryony</hi> will do the ſame; that
            <hi rend="italic">Hellebore</hi>
          <lb/>is good for <hi rend="italic">Melancholy</hi>, or Mad-People; <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Mountain-Flax</hi> for the <hi rend="italic">Gout</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Rheuma-
            <lb/>tiſm</hi>; that <hi rend="italic">Coloquintida</hi>, or the <hi rend="italic"
            >Bitter Apple</hi>
          <lb/>will do mighty Feats for young Women; <lb/>that <hi rend="italic">Mercury</hi> will
          cure the <hi rend="italic">French Pox</hi>; <lb/><hi rend="italic">Opium</hi> give Eaſe;
          and the <hi rend="italic">Glas</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Anti- <lb/>mony</hi> [ſo call'd]
          will Vomit, and the like <lb/>of ſundry others diſpers'd up and down <lb/>in Phyſick
          Books: If, I ſay, ſuch a Per- <lb/>ſon as this ſhall ſet about [as perhaps the <lb/>ſame
          Book may inſtruct him] the making <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Extracts</hi> or <hi
            rend="italic">Electuaries</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Pills</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
            >Tinctures</hi>, <lb/>or <hi rend="italic">Elixirs</hi>, giving each of them ſome
          <lb/>cramp Name, much more if he ſhall <lb/>deliver them out as he buys them <lb/>at the
          Druggiſts Shop, what is it <lb/>that he may not accompliſh! I would <pb n="5"/>
          <lb/>ſay, What Miſchief is he not qualified <lb/>to perpetrate? when, perhaps, the over-
          <lb/>poiſe of the Scale is ſufficient to do Exe- <lb/>cution upon ſome, and a Doſe
          impropor- <lb/>tionate, to kill the ſtouteſt Man in the <lb/>Kingdom. At the beſt, if any
          Good can <lb/>be done [as it may ſometimes happen] <lb/>it is like ten or twenty People's
          falling <lb/>down a <hi rend="italic">Precipice</hi>, where one or two only <lb/>have the
          Luck to eſcape, and that not by <lb/>their own Skill or Foreſight, ſo much as <lb/>ſome
          unforeſeen Incident in their Favour. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>If it be here objected, that you do not <lb/>hear of many ſuch Miſchiefs befalling
          <lb/>thoſe who have bought theſe Remedies? I <lb/>will readily allow the one half of them
          <lb/>to be of ſuch a Nature, as to do you nei- <lb/>ther Harm nor Good; and theſe ſeem
          <lb/>only levell'd at your Pockets; whilſt o- <lb/>thers are often found more dangerous to
          <lb/>the Experimenters thereof. Thus, I ob- <lb/>ſerve, among the Delinquents formerly
          <lb/>call'd to Account, and puniſh'd for ſuch <lb/>like Crimes, one <hi rend="italic">John
            Not, and divers <lb/>others, were Fin'd and Impriſon'd for having <lb/>kill'd ſundry
            Perſons, with one or other of <lb/>the before-mention'd dangerous Medicines</hi>.
          <lb/>Thomaſine Scarlet, <hi rend="italic">with other Women, <lb/>for tampering with
            Mercurial and Antimonial <lb/>Remedies, by which others were miſerably tor- <lb/>mented,
            and many deſtroy'd</hi>. William For- <pb n="6"/>
          <lb/>reſter, <hi rend="italic">a Prieſt</hi>, Simon Foreman, <hi rend="italic">a pre-
            <lb/>tended Aſtrologer, and one <hi rend="roman">Trig</hi> a Shoe- <lb/>maker, but
            deſperate bold Empirick, for the <lb/>like Evil and fatal Practices with ſome Chi-
            <lb/>mical Preparations. Another for giving <hi rend="roman">Co- <lb/>loquintida</hi>,
            another <hi rend="roman">Elaterium</hi>, by which <lb/>ſome Perſons were murther'd as it
            were <lb/>upon the Spot. Another Prieſt, one <hi rend="roman">Evans</hi>
            <lb/>by Name, was Proſecuted and Impriſon'd, <lb/>for that it was proved, inſtead of
            preaching <lb/>the Goſpel, he had run out of his Province <lb/>and kill'd ſeveral
            Perſons with his Antimonial <lb/>Cup</hi>; and leaſt you ſhould think our preſent
          <lb/>Medicine-makers more honeſt, a late Au- <lb/>thor has inform'd us upon his own Know-
          <lb/>ledge, <hi rend="italic">That a great Parcel of the courſeſt and <lb/>fouleſt
            Horſe-Aloes were even ſeen, and had <lb/>been refuſed by ſeveral Farriers for fear of
            <lb/>miſchiefing their Beaſts, was bought up by one <lb/>of theſe wretched People, and
            made into Pills, <lb/>left to ſell at ſeveral Places for the moſt uſe- <lb/>ful Purge
            and ſuited to all Diſeaſes and <lb/>Conſtitutions</hi>: Under the fatal Operation
          <lb/>of ſome of which, I have ſeen my ſelf <lb/>three ſeveral Perſons deſtroy'd miſerably,
          <lb/>and many more, with the utmoſt hazard <lb/>of their Lives, eſcaping. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Indeed, were the Phyſicians Province <lb/>ſo very eaſy as theſe <hi rend="italic"
            >Empirics</hi> would in- <lb/>duce the People to believe, and that <lb/>there was
          nothing more neceſſary than to <pb n="7"/>
          <lb/>find a Name for their Diſtempers, a Re- <lb/>medy [no matter what] call'd now a-
          <lb/>days a <hi rend="italic">Specifick</hi>, is always ready at hand; <lb/>for which,
          inſtead of applying to Phyſi- <lb/>cians, we need but look into the <hi rend="italic"
            >News- <lb/>Papers</hi>, and there we have plenty of all <lb/>ſorts, let the Grievance
          be where it will, <lb/>even from the falling of the Hair on the <lb/>Top of the Head, to
          the Corns upon the <lb/>Soles of our Feet or Toes. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>And thus for the Diſeaſes of the <hi rend="italic">Head</hi>
          <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">Brain</hi>, we have <hi rend="italic">Cephalick Tinctures</hi>
          <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">Head Pills</hi> of divers kinds: <hi rend="italic">Apoplectick
            <lb/>Spirits</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Balſams</hi>; <hi rend="italic">Vapour
            Drops</hi>, and <lb/><hi rend="italic">Drops</hi> for the <hi rend="italic">Palſy</hi>
          and <hi rend="italic">Convulſions</hi>; for <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Eyes</hi>, we have
            <hi rend="italic">Salves</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Waters</hi> with- <lb/>out Number,
          ſome of them as far fetch'd <lb/>as <hi rend="italic">Jeruſalem</hi>, tho' they never
          travell'd per- <lb/>haps a Mile from the <hi rend="italic">Exchange</hi>; not for-
          <lb/>getting the Goody <hi rend="italic">Cater</hi> the Oyſter-Woman's <lb/>moſt excellent
            <hi rend="italic">Oyntment</hi>, reveal'd to her <lb/>Husband's great Grand-father in a
          Dream; <lb/>for the <hi rend="italic">Ears</hi> we have <hi rend="italic">Drops</hi> for
            <hi rend="italic">Deafneſs</hi>; <lb/>for the <hi rend="italic">Tooth-ach</hi>, <hi
            rend="italic">Tinctures</hi>, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> and to <lb/>whiten them <hi
            rend="italic">Dentifrices</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">Powders</hi> from <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Morocco</hi>, <hi rend="italic">China</hi>, and <hi rend="italic"
            >Japan</hi>; for the <hi rend="italic">Mouth</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Gargles</hi>
          and <hi rend="italic">Waſhes</hi>, many; for the whole <lb/><hi rend="italic">Face</hi>
          and <hi rend="italic">Hands</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Chymical Waſhballs</hi>, be-
          <lb/>ſides <hi rend="italic">Pearls</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Cream Balls</hi>, <hi
            rend="italic">White-Pots</hi>, and <lb/><hi rend="italic">Cuſtards</hi>, ſome from <hi
            rend="italic">Rome</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Italy</hi>, o- <lb/>thers from <hi
            rend="italic">Venice</hi>. You ſee how far theſe <pb n="8"/>
          <lb/>good People travel even for Remedies to <lb/>remove <hi rend="italic">Freckles</hi>
          and clean our Faces. <lb/>Come we now to the <hi rend="italic">Breaſt</hi>, and here we
          <lb/>have <hi rend="italic">Lozenges</hi> in every Corner for our <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Coughs</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Colds</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Tinctures</hi> and <hi
            rend="italic">Elixirs</hi> for <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Lungs</hi>; <hi rend="italic"
            >Tinctures</hi> likewiſe to ſweeten <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Breath</hi>, and for the
            <hi rend="italic">Phthiſick</hi>, and <lb/><hi rend="italic">Aſthma</hi>; <hi
            rend="italic">Cordials</hi> of all ſorts for the <hi rend="italic">Heart</hi>, <lb/>and
            <hi rend="italic">Rectificators of our Vitals</hi>, which if <lb/>we believe the <hi
            rend="italic">Quack</hi> Authors Account, <lb/>will ſupply the Place of all other Reme-
          <lb/>dies whatever, being <hi rend="italic">Specifical</hi> to the <lb/>whole Body, as
          well as to particular Parts. <lb/>Shall we deſcend lower, and view the Diſ- <lb/>eaſes of
          the <hi rend="italic">Stomach</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Spleen</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
            >Liver</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Womb</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Kidneys</hi> and <hi
            rend="italic">Bladder</hi>? and here we have <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Elixir Mag.
            Stom.</hi> with ſeveral Re- <lb/>finers thereupon; <hi rend="italic">Pills</hi>, <hi
            rend="italic">Powders</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Tin- <lb/>ctures</hi>, great Variety,
          for all ſorts of Ob- <lb/>ſtructions; to drive away <hi rend="italic">Melancholy</hi> from
          <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Spleen</hi>, we have the <hi rend="italic">Hypo-Drops</hi>; for
          <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Stone</hi>, whether in the <hi rend="italic">Reins</hi> or <hi
            rend="italic">Bladder</hi>, <lb/>we have <hi rend="italic">Powders</hi>, <hi
            rend="italic">Tinctures</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Diſtill'd Wa- <lb/>ters</hi>, <hi
            rend="italic">Volatile Cleanſers</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Diſſolution
          <lb/>Salts</hi>; for <hi rend="italic">Cholick</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Gripes</hi>, <hi
            rend="italic">Spirits</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Tin- <lb/>ctures</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
            >Waters</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Pills</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Elixirs</hi>, and what
          <lb/>not, ſome to eaſe us in a quarter of an <lb/>Hour, others in half a Quarter; but why
          <lb/>ſhould we ſtay ſo long, when others will <lb/>do the Feat in a Minute, eſpecially if
          <lb/>taken with a good round Doſe of <hi rend="italic">Geneva</hi>
          <pb n="9"/>
          <lb/>or of <hi rend="italic">Lovage</hi>, called otherwiſe their <hi rend="italic">Gripe-
            <lb/>Water</hi>; for <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> we have <hi rend="italic">Purging Ta-
            <lb/>blets</hi>, or to tempt the poor Infant, often- <lb/>times to its Deſtruction, the
            <hi rend="italic">Purging <lb/>Sugar Plumbs</hi>: And to compleat this <hi rend="italic"
            >My- <lb/>ſtery of Iniquity</hi>, if we want Heirs to our <lb/>Eſtates, there are <hi
            rend="italic">Vivifying Drops</hi> for <hi rend="italic">Bar- <lb/>renneſs</hi>, not to
          mention ſome other pecu- <lb/>liar Remedies ſuited to the Weakneſſes or <lb/>Infirmities
          of one kind or other, belong- <lb/>ing to the Fair Sex. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But farther, if we take a view of other <lb/>Diſorders, more generally ſuppoſed to
          <lb/>have their Reſidence in our Blood and Hu- <lb/>mours, we are here likewiſe amply fur-
          <lb/>niſh'd. In <hi rend="italic">Acute Diſtempers</hi> we have Re- <lb/>medies for <hi
            rend="italic">Fevers</hi> of other kinds, as well <lb/>as for the <hi rend="italic"
            >Meaſles</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Small-Pox</hi>. For <hi rend="italic">Chro-
            <lb/>nical</hi>, or more tedious ones, as the <hi rend="italic">Scurvy</hi>
          <lb/>[which, by the way is a Name we uſe <lb/>for almoſt all Diſtempers that we know
          <lb/>not what to make of] there are <hi rend="italic">Elixirs</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Spirits</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Waters</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Electuaries</hi>, and
          ſome o- <lb/>thers; for the <hi rend="italic">Gout</hi> [that Diſgrace to Phy-
          <lb/>ſicians] we have a <hi rend="italic">Coal-heaver</hi>'s <hi rend="italic"
            >Decoction</hi>, <lb/>an <hi rend="italic">Old-Woman</hi>'s <hi rend="italic"
            >Plaiſter</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Oyntment</hi>, a <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Tarpaulin</hi>'s <hi rend="italic">Eaſt India Oyl</hi>, beſides the <hi rend="italic"
            >A- <lb/>tyla</hi> of a Quacking Surgeon, and twenty <lb/>of the ſame Goodneſs, <hi
            rend="italic">i. e.</hi> good for no- <lb/>thing but to cheat Men, ſome of their
          <lb/>Money, and others of their Lives; for <pb n="10"/>
          <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Leproſy</hi>, a late <hi rend="italic">Chymical Spirit</hi>,
          firſt <lb/>Coſin to King <hi rend="italic">Atyla</hi> aforeſaid; for the <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Itch</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Waſhes</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
          >Oyntments</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Girdles</hi>, all very <lb/>ſafe, and harmleſs as the
          rankeſt Poyſon, <lb/>which too many, without any Prepara- <lb/>tion of their Bodies,
          running upon Head- <lb/>long, have wofully experienc'd. But to <lb/>proceed; we have <hi
            rend="italic">Conſumptions</hi> of all <lb/>ſorts pluck'd up by the Roots: we have the
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">King's- Evil</hi> cur'd by that eminent <hi rend="italic"
            >Phyſico- <lb/>Chyrurgical</hi> Parſon, the Chaſt, Honeſt, and <lb/>Pious Mr. <hi
            rend="italic">V—s</hi> the C—y-M—n, <lb/>who has told you at leaſt once a Week <lb/>for
          theſe eight or ten Years [leaſt you <lb/>ſhould forget him] that he lives in <hi
            rend="italic">S— <lb/>L—</hi>; laſtly, to bring up the Rear of <lb/>this Raſcally
          Regiment, you have <hi rend="italic">Mother <lb/>Bedlicot</hi>'s <hi rend="italic"
            >Drink</hi> for the <hi rend="italic">Dropſy</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Jaun-
            <lb/>dice</hi>; ſhe, good Woman, uſed to open the <lb/>Pews at St. <hi rend="italic"
            >Sepulchres</hi>, when ſhe could <lb/>ſpare time from viſiting her Patients, and
          <lb/>always took care that upon her Demiſe, <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Secret</hi> ſhould
          deſcend lineally to the <lb/>next Heir, who I am told has the noble <lb/>Legacy now in
          Poſſeſſion. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It would be almoſt endleſs to enume- <lb/>rate the Remedies theſe honeſt Folks have
          <lb/>invented to eaſe us, I ſhould ſay to pick <lb/>our Pockets, and therefore I ſhall
          quit my <lb/>Hands of them for the preſent, after I have <lb/>acquainted you with what is
          very neceſ- <pb n="11"/>
          <lb/>ſary [being a principal part of the Bait] <lb/>that at the Head of each of theſe
          Reme- <lb/>dies, I find ſome very inviting Term, <lb/>ſuch as <hi rend="italic"
            >Angelical</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Royal</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Incomparable</hi>, <hi
            rend="italic">O- <lb/>doriferous</hi>, [tho' that implies no more than <lb/>a <hi
            rend="italic">Sir—ce</hi>] <hi rend="italic">Specifick</hi>, [which is now <lb/>become
          the univerſal Epithet, if it were <lb/>but for a Remedy for broken-winded or
          <lb/>founder'd Horſes; ſo that in a little time <lb/>we ſhall doubleſs have <hi
            rend="italic">Specificks</hi> to kill Rats <lb/>and Mice (about which their Time and
          <lb/>Medicines would be better employ'd) as <lb/>there are already for Lice and Fleas] and
          <lb/>moſt of them <hi rend="italic">Admirable</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Infallible</hi>, or
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Never-failing</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Upon ſumming up this Bill of Fare, I <lb/>found I had left out one of the moſt ma-
          <lb/>terial Diſhes ſerv'd up at this Phyſical <lb/>Banquet, I mean the All-Sovereign or
          <lb/>moſt <hi rend="italic">Famous Anodyne Necklace</hi> for Chil- <lb/>drens Teeth, [you
          ſee the Generoſity of <lb/>theſe good People extends even to our <lb/>Infants as well as
          our ſelves] prepar'd <lb/>out of St. <hi rend="italic">Hugh's Bones</hi>. Now you muſt
          <lb/>know, this St. <hi rend="italic">Hugh</hi> [miſtake me not, <lb/>I do not mean that
          St. <hi rend="italic">Hugh</hi> that lies neg- <lb/>lected up and down in the
          Coblers-Stalls] <lb/><hi rend="italic">was a great Lover of young Children, uſed <lb/>to
            dandle them in his Lap, ſmack his Fingers <lb/>and ſing to them; and finding them pain'd
            <lb/>in their Teeth, he would dip his Finger in <pb n="12"/>
            <lb/>Holy Water, and ſo going gently over their <lb/>Gums nine times, upon removing his
            ſaid <lb/>Finger the laſt time, preſently popt out the <lb/>Tooth; he had, moreover,
            great Virtue in <lb/>the ſame Finger in croſſing the Forehead three <lb/>times</hi> [for
          you muſt know there lies great <lb/>ſtreſs upon an odd Number] <hi rend="italic">to drive
            away <lb/>the Head-ach, and the like upon the Bellies of <lb/>Women in Labour to forward
            their Delivery</hi>. <lb/>Upon all which Conſiderations, after his <lb/>Deceaſe, the
          good Man being Sainted, <lb/>the Women came far and near to worſhip <lb/>at his Tomb, with
          their Children when <lb/>in danger from their Teeth; the great <lb/>Belly'd for an eaſy
          Travel; and the Bar- <lb/>ren [for they had no <hi rend="italic">Vivifying Drops</hi> in
          <lb/>thoſe Days] that they might conceive. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>
          <q rend="diple">Now it happen'd, that a young Lady <lb/>having been long Married to an
            ancient <lb/>Knight [we muſt not tell their Names] <lb/>and without Children, ſitting
            penſively <lb/>one Summer Evening in her Garden, <lb/>this St. <hi rend="italic"
              >Hugh</hi> appears, tells her who he <lb/>was, that he knew her Wants, and that
            <lb/>if ſhe came to Chapel the ſame Even- <lb/>ing, and <hi rend="italic">Veſpers</hi>
            being over, conceal'd her- <lb/>ſelf in ſuch a part thereof till the Peo- <lb/>ple were
            all gone out, he would again <lb/>appear to aſſiſt her; but, by the way, <lb/>ſome ſay
            it was a Roguiſh Fryar that <pb n="13"/>
            <lb/>laid this Stratagem to debauch her; be <lb/>this as it may, to go on with our Le-
            <lb/>gend, the Lady obeys; St. <hi rend="italic">Hugh</hi> comes <lb/>and lies conceal'd
            in ſome other part, <lb/>when the Religious being all gone out, <lb/>and the Chapel
            Doors ſhut up, our <lb/>Saint coming out of his Hole, accoſts <lb/>his Lady, prevails by
            reaſon of his <lb/>Sanctity, firſt telling her he had aſſum'd <lb/>his Body for this
            ſpecial Work, lies <lb/>with her and retires, as does the abuſed <lb/>Lady to her Covert
            till the time of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Mattins</hi>, when Opportunity was given
            <lb/>for their Releaſe. In ſhort, upon this <lb/>Intercourſe with the Holy Father, the
            <lb/>Lady Conceiv'd, went out her time, <lb/>and by coming daily to St. <hi
              rend="italic">Hugh</hi>'s <lb/>Tomb, was deliver'd ſafely of a Son, who, <lb/>at about
            nine Months end, being like <lb/>to die with his Teeth, ſhe had a Dream, <lb/>wherein
            was diſcover'd to her, that if <lb/>ſhe could procure one of St. <hi rend="italic"
              >Hugh</hi>'s Toes <lb/>[whether it was the great or little Toe <lb/>truly I forget,
            but admire it was not <lb/>his Finger that had been uſed to the <lb/>Work] and rub the
            Child's Gums <lb/>therewith, it would recover: Upon <lb/>which, not without great
            Intereſt <lb/>made [ſome ſay by bribing only of <lb/>the Sexton] the Coffin was open'd,
            <lb/>and the Bone brought, when [com- <pb n="14"/>
            <lb/>mend me to the Romancer] no ſooner <lb/>was the ſame apply'd to the Child's
            <lb/>Gum, but up ſtarts two great ſwanking <lb/>Teeth, the Infant preſently ſmiles, and
            <lb/>grew well at the ſame Inſtant; however, <lb/>to prevent danger from any other
            <lb/>Teeth, the holy Relick being carefully <lb/>wrapt up in a Piece of Silk, was hung
            <lb/>about little Maſter's Neck, and he <lb/>thence forwards throve mainly, beyond
            <lb/>all the Children round about the Coun- <lb/>try, cutting the reſt of his Teeth
            with- <lb/>out a Whimper. </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>How it happen'd that theſe Relicks lay <lb/>undiſturb'd ſo many hundred Years [for
          <lb/>it is time out of Mind that this St. <hi rend="italic">Hugh</hi>
          <lb/>flouriſh'd] I know not; but ſo it is, that <lb/>a generous <hi rend="italic">Popiſh
            Prieſt</hi> having got the reſt <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">Skeleton</hi> into his
          Poſſeſſion, has <lb/>brought it over Sea, and [hiring a Turner's <lb/>Garret] work'd the
          ſame into <hi rend="italic">Beads</hi> for <lb/><hi rend="italic">Necklaces</hi> for the
          uſe of the <hi rend="italic">Hereticks</hi> Chil- <lb/>dren, that as they grow up, their
          Faith <lb/>may be ſtrong enough to ſwallow yet <lb/>greater Deluſions intended for them by
          <lb/>him and his Accomplices. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Ah <hi rend="italic">England! England!</hi> that it ever <lb/>ſhould be ſaid of thee,
          that even the <lb/>meaneſt <hi rend="italic">Maſters</hi> of thy Families [ſince <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Popery</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Superſtition</hi> have been baniſh'd <pb
            n="15"/>
          <lb/>hence] ſhould permit, or the <hi rend="italic">Miſtreſſes</hi>
          <lb/>thereof deſire, ſuch Childiſh <hi rend="italic">Trinkets</hi> [fit <lb/>only to amuſe
          Ideots or Fools] to be <lb/>brought in, or hung about their Children's <lb/>Necks, in
          Expectation of Advantage by <lb/>the ſame? That ſome of you who ſcarce <lb/>have Bread to
          feed them, or Cloaths to <lb/>hide their Nakedneſs, ſhould yet find <lb/>Money to purchaſe
          theſe Baubles, theſe <lb/>moſt abſurd and ridiculous Trifles; that <lb/>you ſhould, I ſay,
          be perſwaded, a piece <lb/>of a dry Stick, or other Vegetable, a <lb/>Stone or a Bone [no
          matter which or <lb/>what] <hi rend="italic">ſhould be able to ſend forth ſuch ſa-
            <lb/>lutiferous Emanations, or Steems into the <lb/>Air, which roving up and down in
            queſt of <lb/>ſome proper Object on which to ſettle, but, find- <lb/>ing none elſewhere,
            at length return, and en- <lb/>tering the Mouth or Noſtrils, or ſome more <lb/>ſecret
            Paſſages of the Body, whirl about therein <lb/>with the Blood, find out their Fellows,
            call a <lb/>Council, and muſtering up their Forces, ſtrait <lb/>hasten to relieve the
            beleaguer'd Gum; here <lb/>ſome of them with their Pickaxes break <lb/>Ground and ſap
            the ſame; others lay the Train; <lb/>others blow up the Fortreſs and make way for
            <lb/>the impriſon'd Tooth</hi>; or, if this <hi rend="italic">Allegory</hi> be
          <lb/>thought too Foreign, <hi rend="italic">ſome of them muſt <lb/>rarefy or attenuate,
            others relax and mollify: <lb/>others of them dilate, and, laſtly, others muſt
            <lb/>incide or Cut, by which, immediate Paſſage is <pb n="16"/>
            <lb/>now granted for the Eruption</hi>. This being <lb/>the Story, I muſt ſay, <hi
            rend="italic">Quis credat? cre- <lb/>dat Judæus, Papiſta credat</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Some doubtleſs, and perhaps juſtly too, <lb/>may think I have ſpent too much of my
          <lb/>Reader's Time in this <hi rend="italic">Burleſque</hi>, and that <lb/>there was no
          need of ſo much <hi rend="italic">Drollery</hi>? <lb/>To which I ſhall only reply, that
          Fooleries <lb/>of any kind are ſometimes beſt anſwer'd <lb/>in the <hi rend="italic"
            >Drolling</hi> Way, eſpecially where the <lb/>Argument will not ſuffer very ſerious
          <lb/>handling. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>To ſuch however as have ſerious Scru- <lb/>ples about this Affair, and ſhall retort
          <lb/>Matters of Fact, as they call them, and <lb/>alledge the publick Teſtimonies in <hi
            rend="italic">Ad- <lb/>vertiſements</hi>, which give an Account of <lb/>the great Virtue
          experienced in theſe <lb/><hi rend="italic">Beads</hi>; <hi rend="italic">and the Numbers
            of Children reco- <lb/>ver'd by wearing of the ſame; Women eaſed <lb/>in their Labours;
            others cured of Head-achs, <lb/>Cramps, Convulſions, and the like</hi>; to theſe <lb/>I
          ſay I will now ſeriouſly make anſwer, <lb/>and doubt not in the leaſt to prove them
          <lb/>no other than direct Frauds, and groſs <lb/>Impoſitions upon Ignorant and Credulous
          <lb/>Perſons. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Firſt then I ſay, conſidering the many <lb/>thouſands of theſe <hi rend="italic"
            >Toys</hi> that are ſold, the <lb/>Number is exceeding ſmall, that we hear, <pb n="17"/>
          <lb/>of thoſe who have pretended any ways <lb/>to Benefit thereby; as one perhaps in one
          <lb/>hundred. And, <hi rend="italic">Secondly</hi>, among theſe, <lb/>we find the greater
          part of them miſre- <lb/>preſented; it being Cuſtomary for the <lb/>Cheat, or his
          Accomplice, to draw up <lb/>the Teſtimonial, and the People [ſuch as <lb/>can] are to ſign
          or ſet their Mark, ſome- <lb/>times to they know not what; as I have <lb/>had it from
          their own Mouths. Others <lb/>have given Commiſſions at large to the <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Scout</hi>, or Meſſenger, ſent out to pick up <lb/>Informations; and yet
          the <hi rend="italic">Advertiſement</hi>
          <lb/>has come forth as if unknown to the <hi rend="italic">Neck- <lb/>lace-Merchant</hi>,
          by way of return of <lb/>Thanks, or rather for a return of their <lb/>Money, very likely
          with Intereſt, upon <lb/>Condition of this Liberty of putting <lb/>what they pleaſed into
          the <hi rend="italic">News-Paper</hi>, <lb/>with a Promiſe of vouching it, ſhould
          <lb/>there be any occaſion. But, <hi rend="italic">Thirdly</hi>, I <lb/>find theſe
          Informations have been general- <lb/>ly obtain'd, one way or other, among <lb/>the Meaner,
          and ſome of them Neceſſi- <lb/>tous Perſons; or if of better Faſhion, <lb/>from Families
          where the Mother is much <lb/>addicted to <hi rend="italic">Superſtition</hi> and <hi
            rend="italic">old Wives Fa- <lb/>bles</hi>, and the Father about as Wife, if he
          <lb/>knows any thing of the Matter. <hi rend="italic">Fourth- <lb/>ly</hi>, It is a plain
          Argument of the great Want <lb/>of New and almoſt Dayly <hi rend="italic"
            >Advertiſements</hi>, <pb n="18"/>
          <lb/>[of which they could not ſtand in need, <lb/>if the Thing it ſelf were not in the
          Vul- <lb/>gar Phraſe, a <hi rend="italic">Bite</hi>] for that once in a <lb/>Month,
          ſometimes after three or four, we <lb/>find an old Story trumpt up, as if juſt <lb/>then
          fallen out; among ſome of which, <lb/>finding my ſelf concern'd, I ſhall here de-
          <lb/>liver the Caſe truly. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A poor Woman brought her Child to <lb/>me, then labouring under what we call <lb/>a
            <hi rend="italic">Symptomatic Fever</hi>; looking into its <lb/>Mouth, I found two of
          the upper Gums <lb/>full ſpread, highly inflam'd, and the <lb/>Teeth juſt ready to break
          through; how- <lb/>ever, by reaſon of the Fever and great <lb/>Fluxion, I preſcrib'd,
          among other Re- <lb/>medies, Bleeding, Bliſtering, and above <lb/>all, that they would
          ſend for a Surgeon, <lb/>to cut into the affected Gums, and ſet at <lb/>Liberty the Teeth,
          which gave riſe to <lb/>this Fever, as I had reaſon thus to con- <lb/>jecture: But the
          fooliſhly fond Mother <lb/>being afraid of the Lancet [the beſt and <lb/>ſpeedieſt Remedy
          at ſuch times] neglects <lb/>this latter Part of the Advice, and whe- <lb/>ther the reſt
          was purſued I know not; <lb/>but few Days after, I heard in the Neigh- <lb/>bourhood, that
          ſhe had with the ſimple <lb/>Multitude, purchas'd the famous <hi rend="italic">Anodyne
            <lb/>Necklace</hi>, which had not been worn long, <lb/>before one of the Teeth [juſt
          coming out <pb n="19"/>
          <lb/>as I obſerv'd but now] did cut, ſoon <lb/>after the other, and the Child grew eaſier,
          <lb/>as was to be expected. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This Tale, by a <hi rend="italic">Scout</hi>, was preſently <lb/>got hold of, brought
          in, and dreſt up <lb/>with all the Formality of a wonderful Re- <lb/>covery, partly true,
          and partly falſe; true <lb/>in that the Teeth came out [and ſo they <lb/>had if the <hi
            rend="italic">Necklace</hi> had never been heard <lb/>of]; falſe, in that they had taken
          Advice <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">whole College of Phyſicians</hi>, of whom <lb/>none
          but my ſelf was ever conſulted, <lb/>and mine [as you have heard, in the <lb/>moſt
          material Point, if in any one] not <lb/>follow'd; and all this to magnify the great
          <lb/>Virtue in St. <hi rend="italic">Hugh's Bones</hi>; but obſerve <lb/>now the Sequel of
          this Story. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>When this Tale had been often told, and <lb/>worn as it were Thread-bare [by which I
          <lb/>ſuppoſe their <hi rend="italic">Advertiſements</hi> thereof, were <lb/>well paid for,
          in bringing more Fools to <lb/>their Market] it happen'd ſome Months <lb/>after, as if <hi
            rend="italic">Old Nick</hi> owing them a ſpight <lb/>was now minded as we ſay to pay
          them; <lb/>ſome new Teeth coming out, the Child <lb/>was again brought very low and weak,
          and <lb/>truſting to the <hi rend="italic">Famous Anodyne Necklace</hi>, <lb/>they ſought
          for no other Help, till it was <lb/>too late; when at length, behold, the very <lb/>Day
          the old Story was advertis'd, and <lb/>dreſt up to all the Advantage imaginable, <pb
            n="20"/>
          <lb/>with the Parents return of Thanks, un- <lb/>known to the Author, and ſuch like ful-
          <lb/>ſome Lies, the poor Infant expires with <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Miraculous
            Beads</hi> about its Neck; and <lb/>certainly, unleſs they had not quite aban-
          <lb/>don'd all Modeſty, as well as common <lb/>Honeſty, they would have prudently ſup-
          <lb/>preſs'd this particular <hi rend="italic">Advertiſement</hi> for <lb/>the future; yet
          ſo ſhameleſs and ſcanda- <lb/>lous do I find them, as to continue this <lb/>very Relation
          with an additional Piece of <lb/>fine Wire-drawing, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> That the
          ſaid <lb/>Child, by Means of the <hi rend="italic">Necklace</hi>, is ſo re- <lb/>cover'd
          of all his Weakneſs, that he is <lb/>grown a very fine Boy, ['twas much their <lb/>Hands
          being in, they had not made a <lb/>Man of him] and can run alone; where- <lb/>as, had
          themſelves ſent to enquire, they <lb/>muſt have known he had been Dead <lb/>[and of his
          Teeth as I have told you] <lb/>ſeveral Months paſt. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Many the like Examples I have heard <lb/>of, from Perſons of the greateſt Credit;
          <lb/>ſome of them having curs'd their Credu- <lb/>lity, in ſuffering themſelves to be
          impoſed <lb/>on, and thrown the <hi rend="italic">Popiſh Trumpery</hi> [as <lb/>they then
          call it] into the Fire. But, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Laſtly</hi>, granting all of them to
          be Facts, <lb/>there needs not many Words to prove <lb/>them of no Force for the End
          propoſed; <lb/>it being certain, that moſt Children be- <pb n="21"/>
          <lb/>tween ſeven and twelve Months old, ſoon- <lb/>er or later, muſt cut ſome of their
          Teeth; <lb/>if now when a Child is indiſpos'd there- <lb/>by, a <hi rend="italic"
            >Necklace</hi>, or any other Toy, is put <lb/>on at the time of its breaking forth, or
          <lb/>perhaps two or three Days before, this <lb/>Tooth, I ſay, had inevitably broke thro',
          <lb/>whether the Beads, or other Toy, had <lb/>been left on or off; and if the Parent had
          <lb/>written <hi rend="italic">Hocus Pocus, adſis Dens?</hi> on a piece <lb/>of Paper, in
          the ſtead of the <hi rend="italic">Necklace</hi>, <lb/>take my Word, it would have done
          eve- <lb/>ry jot as much Service, in bringing forth <lb/>the Tooth. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>If they would have the Argument prove <lb/>any Thing, they ſhould prove, that no
          <lb/>Child, [at leaſt the greater Number] e- <lb/>ver wore it but with ſome Advantage;
          <lb/>whereas, on the contrary, there are ſome <lb/>Scores I have ſeen with it for ſeveral
          <lb/>Months, pining and languiſhing to no pur- <lb/>poſe, till a Lancet has been admitted,
          and <lb/>then ſome of them have recover'd. Others <lb/>meerly by Strength of Nature, not
          by <lb/>any Efficacy of theſe Childiſh Amuſe- <lb/>ments, have at laſt weather'd the
          Point, <lb/>whilſt great Numbers die dayly, in ſpight <lb/>of St. <hi rend="italic">Hugh's
            Toes</hi>, or his <hi rend="italic">Teeth</hi> either; <lb/>but if the few having it on,
          ſhall happen <lb/>to cut their Teeth, no Matter, ſays the <lb/>Impoſtor, for the thouſands
          that die with <pb n="22"/>
          <lb/>it on, for you are never ſent of this Er- <lb/>rand to the Parents of the Dead. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>You will ſay, perhaps, the Author has <lb/>ſhow'd himſelf a learned Man, and a
          <lb/>great Philoſopher, proving alſo that many <lb/>ſtrange Feats may be done by <hi
            rend="italic">Sympathy</hi>, or <lb/>by means of <hi rend="italic">inviſible Atoms</hi>,
            <hi rend="italic">Miaſms</hi>, <hi rend="italic">A- <lb/>porrhæas</hi>, <hi
            rend="italic">Effluvias</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Emanations</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
            >Exhalati- <lb/>ons</hi>, with abundance of hard Words; and <lb/>that <hi rend="italic"
            >Paracelſus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Van Helmont</hi> and Sir <hi rend="italic">Kenelm
            <lb/>Dygby</hi> were of the ſame Opinion; and, <hi rend="italic">laſt- <lb/>ly</hi>,
          that he has appeal'd to the <hi rend="italic">Royal Society</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>To all which I ſhall anſwer as ſhortly <lb/>as I can; That I take him, indeed, to be
          <lb/>a very ſhrewd Man, and that he has <lb/>thrown out as good a <hi rend="italic"
            >Bait</hi> for Fools as <lb/>perhaps was ever known in <hi rend="italic">London</hi>,
          and <lb/>proſecutes as likely a Method to carry on <lb/>his Deſign, which yet is not
          ſupported but <lb/>on very large Expence; for no longer than <lb/>he is Piping with his
            <hi rend="italic">Advertiſements</hi>, will <lb/>the Fiſh come to the <hi rend="italic"
            >Bait</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>He has likewiſe given us a great many <lb/>hard Names, and told us ſome wonderful
          <lb/>Stories, ſome True, which prove Little; <lb/>others Falſe, which prove Nothing, un-
          <lb/>leſs that the Author, telling them as Truths, <lb/>is not to be credited in any thing
          he ſays. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Paracelſus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Helmont</hi> were
          both <hi rend="italic">Quacks</hi>, <lb/>as himſelf, yet of much larger Talents in
          <lb/>the Phyſical Science; the former, how- <pb n="23"/>
          <lb/>ever a mad Extravagant, the latter a <lb/>whimſical <hi rend="italic"
          >Enthuſiaſt</hi>, each, notwithſtand- <lb/>ing, of a ſingular and great <hi rend="italic"
            >Genius</hi>; and I <lb/>dare believe in Principle, both Honeſter <lb/>than himſelf. Sir
            <hi rend="italic">Kenelm</hi>, a moſt renown'd <lb/>Perſonage, a very great Naturaliſt,
          but <lb/>no Phyſician; nor has his <hi rend="italic">Sympathetick</hi>
          <lb/>Cure of Wounds any ways vacated or ſu- <lb/>perſeded the Practice of Surgery, [I know
          <lb/>where it has forty times made Work for <lb/>that Profeſſion] any more than this ridi-
          <lb/>culous Bead-roll is like to that of Phy- <lb/>ſic; they having both of them been
          ſuffi- <lb/>ciently prov'd Fallacious and idle Dreams; <lb/>the one however, of an honeſt
          and well- <lb/>meaning <hi rend="italic">Nobleman</hi>, the other [as it is <lb/>credibly
          reported] of a knaviſh and de- <lb/>ſigning <hi rend="italic">Prieſt</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But ſtill you may farther argue, if the <lb/>Project was no better than a Cheat, how
          <lb/>comes it that Dr. <hi rend="italic">Paul Chamberlen</hi> of the <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">College of Phyſicians</hi>, ſhould ſuffer his <lb/>Name to be ſet, as a
          kind of Sanction <lb/>thereunto? To this laſt raiſed Objection I <lb/>ſhall anſwer as
          tenderly as I can. Dr. <lb/><hi rend="italic">P. C.</hi> [who, by the way, was not a Mem-
          <lb/>ber of the College] is now gone to his <lb/>Place, and can't anſwer for himſelf: nor
          <lb/>can I for him, any better than that there <lb/>were more Reaſons than every body
          <lb/>knew, why his Name was uſed to give <pb n="24"/>
          <lb/>Credit, and ſupport this Piece of R—y; <lb/>ſome of them have been already gueſt
          <lb/>at in Print, and his Executors, I dare ſay, <lb/>can tell yet more. I have already
          told <lb/>you he is gone, and can ſay nothing to me, <lb/>and therefore all I ſhall ſay
          more of him <lb/>is this, that when a learned Phyſician of <lb/>my Acquaintance took him
          to Task upon <lb/>this Matter, and endeavoured to make <lb/>him ſenſible of the Scandal to
          himſelf as <lb/>well as to the whole <hi rend="italic">Faculty</hi> of Phyſic; <lb/>he put
          off the Diſcourſe with a Smile, <lb/>ſaying, <q rend="italic">The Thing was harmleſs, and
            ſuited <lb/>to the People's Humours; and that if the <lb/>Children, for want of it,
            could not benefit in <lb/>their Teeth, the Mothers, by the force of <lb/>Fancy, might be
            eaſed in their Deliveries; <lb/>and that laſtly, it had as much Virtue as any <lb/>other
            external Remedy of this Nature, which <lb/>the People ſeem'd extremely fond of </q>;
          which <lb/>was [what all the ſenſible part of Man- <lb/>kind knew before] juſt none at
          all; nor I <lb/>dare ſay [if you will not take my Word <lb/>for it] can you find one
          Gentleman of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Royal Society</hi>, that will not readily acknow-
          <lb/>ledge as much as all I have ſaid amounts <lb/>to. </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="25"/>
      <div type="part">
        <head rend="align-center space size(1.5)">
          <lb/>PART II. </head>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Argument</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="italic hanging">
          <lb/>That, ſuppoſing ſome of theſe Remedies were <lb/>at firſt directed by the moſt
          learned Phyſi- <lb/>cian, and afterwards compounded or pre- <lb/>par'd by an honeſt
          Artiſt, yet in this way of <lb/>their Adminiſtration, it cannot otherwiſe <lb/>fall out,
          but that many more muſt be injur'd <lb/>[at leaſt if they are good for any thing]
          <lb/>than can be benefited thereby. </p>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>His 2d general Propoſition, I ground, <lb/>
          <list rend="italic">
            <item>1. Upon the ſimilitude or likeneſs of <lb/>one Diſeaſe with another; by which,
              Phyſicians <lb/>themſelves, who have had all Opportunities by <lb/>a View of the
              Patient, and ſtrict Enquiry in- <lb/>to all Circumſtances, have, notwithſtanding,
              <lb/>been ſometimes unhappily miſtaken. </item>
            <item>2. Upon <lb/>the differing Conſtitutions, as well as differing <lb/>Circumſtances
              of ſome others, labouring un- <lb/>der the ſame Diſtemper, requiring ſtill a di-
              <lb/>vers Method of Healing. </item>
            <item>3. From the ſame <lb/>Diſeaſe, differently circumſtantiated one Day, <lb/>perhaps
              an Hour from what it is the next, <lb/>and quite altering the firſt Intention. </item>
            <item>4. From <lb/>divers Cauſes giving Riſe to the ſame Di- <lb/>ſtemper, and which are
              always to be reſpected <lb/>carefully by every good Phyſician. </item>
            <item>5. <hi rend="roman">And <pb n="26"/>
                <lb/>laſtly</hi>, From particular Idioſyncraſy's, a hard <lb/>Word I muſt confeſs
              for a common Reader to <lb/>underſtand, and which I know not how to ex- <lb/>preſs
              otherwiſe, than its implying ſomething <lb/>in our Natures, by which one Man naturally
              <lb/>abhors, or loaths, what another is pleaſed <lb/>with, and ſo contrarily. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>From ſome one or more of theſe <lb/>[which are not all I could enumerate, but
          <lb/>enough I think to my Purpoſe] I ſhall <lb/>here, I ſay, undertake to evince that you
          <lb/>run exceeding Hazards, by meddling with <lb/>any Medicine, however good in its kind,
          <lb/>recommended in this way of <hi rend="italic">Advertiſe- <lb/>ment</hi>,
          notwithſtanding the beſt printed <lb/>Directions that can be given therewith. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>And for the clearer Repreſentation of <lb/>this Affair, I ſhall, by way of Demonſtra-
          <lb/>tion, give at leaſt one Example [my in- <lb/>tended Brevity not allowing more] under
          <lb/>each of the foregoing Heads; and I will <lb/>begin with that very common Diſeaſe the
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Cholick</hi>: Now this you all know, is a <lb/>Name by which we
          are apt to ſignify any <lb/>Pain, whether fix'd or moving, in the <lb/>Stomach or Bowels.
          It is indeed a Word <lb/>of Latitude, and contains ſeveral <hi rend="italic">Species</hi>
          <lb/>[if I may be allowed the Expreſſion here] <lb/>under one common <hi rend="italic"
            >Genus</hi>; and thus there <lb/>is a <hi rend="italic">Cholick</hi> [the moſt frequent
          of any <lb/>other] ariſing from <hi rend="italic">Wind</hi> pent up in ſome <pb n="27"/>
          <lb/>part of the Stomach or Guts. There is a <lb/><hi rend="italic">Cholick</hi> from
          Cold, Phlegmatick Humours <lb/>alſo heap'd up and obſtructing the ſame <lb/>Parts. There
          is a <hi rend="italic">Cholick</hi> from what <lb/>Phyſicians properly enough call <hi
            rend="italic">Bile</hi> or <lb/>yellow Choler, hence nam'd a <hi rend="italic">Bilious
            <lb/>Cholick</hi>, ariſing from this Humour fer- <lb/>menting with ſome others in theſe
          Parts <lb/>alſo, and exciting the moſt cruel Tor- <lb/>ments. Again, there is a <hi
            rend="italic">Cholick</hi> proceed- <lb/>ing from an Inflammation of theſe Parts,
          <lb/>attended with very cruel, and often fatal <lb/>Symptoms, as <hi rend="italic"
            >Gangrene</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Mortification</hi>. <lb/>Farther, there is a <hi
            rend="italic">Cholick</hi> from a Hurry <lb/>and Confuſion of the Spirits, ruſhing as
          <lb/>it were impetuouſly upon the Bowels, and <lb/>producing exquiſite Pains in the
          Stomach <lb/>or Guts, with Vomiting ſometimes, as in <lb/>a true <hi rend="italic"
            >Cholick</hi>: At other times the Pain is <lb/>ſeated on the Kidneys and Neck of the
          <lb/>Bladder, which in conſult with that ex- <lb/>cellent Phyſician Dr. <hi rend="italic"
            >Mead</hi>, I was once a <lb/>Witneſs of, occaſioning a total Suppreſſi- <lb/>on of <hi
            rend="italic">Urine</hi>, and putting on the exact <lb/>likeneſs of a <hi rend="italic"
            >Cholick</hi> from the <hi rend="italic">Stone</hi> or <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Gravel</hi>; and this we call an <hi rend="italic">Hyſterick <lb/>Cholick</hi>. There
          is, <hi rend="italic">laſtly</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">Cholick</hi> from <lb/>the ſaid <hi
            rend="italic">Gravel</hi>, which we call the <hi rend="italic">Stone <lb/>Cholick</hi>,
          and which by Conſent of Parts, <lb/>in many Symptoms, reſembles alſo the <lb/>common <hi
            rend="italic">Cholick</hi>. </p>
        <pb n="28"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>You may object, that albeit there may <lb/>be many Cauſes of theſe <hi rend="italic"
            >Cholicks</hi>, yet if <lb/>the ſame Remedy will remove the Com- <lb/>plaint, no matter
          whether he who ſells it, <lb/>can rightly diſtinguiſh theſe ſeveral Cauſes; <lb/>and
          indeed, if this could be made out, I <lb/>would grant due weight to the Objection;
          <lb/>but the contrary is moſt notorious, and by <lb/>this Miſtake, abundance of Patients
          have <lb/>miſcarry'd; for tho' many of the <hi rend="italic">Species</hi>
          <lb/>have ſome common Accident or Symptom, <lb/>ſuch as <hi rend="italic">Pain</hi>, <hi
            rend="italic">Vomiting</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Coſtiveneſs</hi>, with <lb/>ſmall or no
            <hi rend="italic">Fever</hi>; others great <hi rend="italic">Heat</hi>, <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Thirſt</hi>, with <hi rend="italic">Fever</hi> attending; others, as
          <lb/>we ſaid juſt now, with <hi rend="italic">Strangury</hi> or <hi rend="italic">ſtop-
            <lb/>page</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi>; yet theſe ariſing from <lb/>very
          differing Cauſes, and producing alſo <lb/>differing Conſequences, muſt be treated
          <lb/>therefore in a quite differing Method. <lb/>'Tis own'd they all agree in one common
          <lb/>Symptom, I mean <hi rend="italic">Pain</hi>, implying, as it <lb/>might therefore
          ſeem, one common Re- <lb/>medy, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> ſome <hi rend="italic"
            >Opiat</hi> to take off the <lb/>ſame. But he who firſt goes to take off <lb/>this
          Symptom in ſome of them, without <lb/>having an Eye to remove the Cauſe, <lb/>fixes the
          ſame deeper, and ſometimes <lb/>thereby puts it out of the Power of the <lb/>moſt ſuitable
          Remedy afterwards to re- <lb/>lieve the Sick, who had been thus igno- <lb/>rantly treated. </p>
        <pb n="29"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>To explain this Matter a little farther; <lb/>He, who in the Inflammatory, or Bilious
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Cholick</hi>, ſends for any of the common <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Cholick Waters</hi>, [as they are miſchievouſly <lb/>termed] whether the famous <hi
            rend="italic">J— M—rs</hi>, <lb/>the never failing <hi rend="italic">G—s</hi>, which is
          nothing <lb/>elſe but <hi rend="italic">Lovage Water</hi>, the common, and <lb/>now well
          known Remedy of <hi rend="italic">Daffy</hi>; or, <lb/>in a word, a Quartern of <hi
            rend="italic">Geneva</hi> [which <lb/>alone has deſtroy'd more than our thirty
          <lb/>Years War, and will do the Buſineſs as <lb/>well as the beſt of them] not forgetting
          <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">burnt Brandy</hi> prepar'd at home; he, I <lb/>ſay, who takes
          this Method, at this time, is <lb/>little wiſer than one who claps the <lb/>Muzzle of the
          Piſtol into the Patient's Fun- <lb/>dament, and lets fly, in hopes to clear the <lb/>Way
          of all Obſtructions: Pardon the <lb/>Compariſon, but I can aſſure you, the <lb/>one is
          likely near upon with the other, <lb/>to deſtroy the Diſeaſed and the Diſeaſe to-
          <lb/>gether. Again, he who ſhall attempt, <lb/>and give one of the ſtrong Glyſters, much
          <lb/>more the Purges at this time, which are <lb/>cuſtomary in the Cold, Phlegmatick, or
          <lb/>Vitreous <hi rend="italic">Cholick</hi>, will act as wildly; the <lb/>ſame will have
          the like evil Tendency in <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Hyſterick Cholick</hi>, where the
          chief In- <lb/>tention is by ſome of the <hi rend="italic">Fœtid</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
            >Hyſterick</hi>
          <lb/>Remedies, ſo called, mix'd with <hi rend="italic">Opiates</hi>, <lb/>to take off the
          Hurry, and bridle the ex- <pb n="30"/>
          <lb/>orbitant Outrage of the Spirits. Farther, <lb/>He likewiſe who purſues this Courſe
          with <lb/>hot inflaming Spirits, and hot Purges, in <lb/>expectation of eaſing the <hi
            rend="italic">Stone-Cholick</hi>, <lb/>where ſoft, glib, ſlippery, and oyly Me-
          <lb/>dicines, lenient Glyſters, and cooling Pur- <lb/>gatives, with <hi rend="italic"
            >Opiates</hi>, eſpecially in the <lb/>Fit, are indicated, will be as much diſap-
          <lb/>pointed. On the contrary, He who di- <lb/>rects cold Water, Milk and Water, Bar-
          <lb/>ley Water, Almond Milks, and the like, <lb/>in the Cold Phlegmatick <hi rend="italic"
            >Cholick</hi>, [howbeit <lb/>well ſuited to the Bilious and Hot] where <lb/>the hotter
          Carminative Compoſitions, <lb/>warm Glyſters, and brisk Purges, bridled <lb/>however with
          ſome <hi rend="italic">Opiate</hi>, are requiſite, <lb/>will ſhoot alſo as wide of the
          Mark. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Hence I think it will appear ſelf-evi- <lb/>dent, that whoever truſts to any of theſe
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Anticholical</hi> Remedies, ſo denominated and <lb/>ſold about
          the Town, muſt expect to <lb/>riſque his Health, if not his Life, ſince the <lb/>Chance is
          ſo great of its doing more Hurt <lb/>than Good; and if the beſt Phyſicians are
          <lb/>ſometimes puzzled, who attend at the <lb/>Bed-ſide of the Patient, and inform them-
          <lb/>ſelves all they can, yet find, by a peculiar <lb/>Symptom, or accidental Appearance
          af- <lb/>terwards, that they had gone before upon <lb/>a wrong Notion of the Caſe, which
          be- <lb/>ing by this new Diſcovery let into, they <pb n="31"/>
          <lb/>quickly after can relieve the Sick Perſon; <lb/>if this be ſo, as frequently falls
          out, how, <lb/>I ſay, is it to be expected, that any ſingle <lb/>Medicament, made up by a
            <hi rend="italic">Quack</hi> who <lb/>knows nothing of theſe Diſtinctions [or <lb/>if he
          did, could in this way provide for <lb/>the ſame] can anſwer the Expectation. <lb/>You ſee
            <hi rend="italic">it muſt be Hot, and it muſt be Cold; <lb/>it <choice>
              <corr>muſt</corr>
              <sic>moſt</sic>
            </choice> Purge ſtrongly, weakly, and it muſt <lb/>not Purge at all; it muſt cauſe Reſt,
            and <lb/>muſt prevent Sleep</hi>; with ſeveral other very <lb/>oppoſite Qualities, which
          are contradicto- <lb/>ry in the very Terms, and therefore both <lb/>impoſſible and
          impracticable in this pub- <lb/>lick way. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The ſecond Objection I raiſed againſt <lb/>theſe Quack-Remedies ſold at the Shops,
          <lb/>was founded on the differing Conſtitutions, <lb/>and divers Circumſtances otherways
          at- <lb/>tending upon the ſame Patient; and I will <lb/>here inſtance in another popular
          Diſeaſe, <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Scorvy</hi>, which together with that of <lb/>the <hi
            rend="italic">Worms</hi>, father many more Diſtempers <lb/>than they have a juſt right
          to, and by the <lb/>miſtaken Conceptions whereof, many a- <lb/>dult Perſons have ſuffer'd
          by the one, as <lb/>thouſands of Children have done by the <lb/>other. I deny not but they
          are both com- <lb/>mon Diſeaſes, yet I would have no one <lb/>take a Remedy for either,
          till by the Judg- <lb/>ment of ſome able Phyſician, they are <pb n="32"/>
          <lb/>inform'd what Ground they go upon; <lb/>but I haſten to my Buſineſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Scorvy</hi> has been uſually, by all <lb/>good Modern Writers,
          divided into a <lb/><hi rend="italic">Salino Sulphureous</hi>, and a <hi rend="italic"
            >Sulphureo Saline</hi>; <lb/>but theſe being Words not at all intelli- <lb/>gible to
          common Readers, for which this is <lb/>deſigned chiefly, we ſhall diſtinguiſh it <lb/>only
          as <hi rend="italic">Acid</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Salt</hi>, or, if you pleaſe, a
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">cold</hi> and a <hi rend="italic">hot Scorvy</hi>; and indeed
          without <lb/>regard to this ſimple Diviſion, it is impoſ- <lb/>ſible either to conceive a
          true Notion of the <lb/>Diſeaſe, or to adapt Remedies for the <lb/>Cure: Some have made a
          middle <hi rend="italic">Species</hi>, <lb/>and truly with reſpect to ſome Tempe-
          <lb/>raments, lying betwixt the two Extremes, <lb/>not improperly. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Now as the <hi rend="italic">Acid</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Cold Scorvy</hi> will
          <lb/>diſpenſe with ſome of the hot and biting <lb/>Plants, ſuch as <hi rend="italic"
            >Horſe-radiſh</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Arſmart</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Scorvy-graſs</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Wormwood</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Aron-Roots</hi>,
            <hi rend="italic">Win- <lb/>ters-Bark</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Orange-Peel</hi>, and the
          like; with <lb/><hi rend="italic">diſtill'd Waters</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Tinctures</hi>,
            <hi rend="italic">Wines</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Spirits</hi>, <lb/>extracted thence; ſo
          contrarily, the <hi rend="italic">Sul- <lb/>phureo Saline</hi>, or the <hi rend="italic"
            >Hot Scorvy</hi>, requires <lb/>the more cold or temperate; ſuch are <hi rend="italic"
            >En- <lb/>dive</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Dandalyon</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Plantane</hi>,
            <hi rend="italic">Fumitory</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Ci- <lb/>chory</hi>, <hi
            rend="italic">Sorrel</hi>, and ſuch like; either in <hi rend="italic">De-
            <lb/>coctions</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Infuſions</hi>, or the ſimple <hi rend="italic"
            >Juices</hi> cla- <lb/>rified, which exceed all other Forms. The <lb/>middle ſort may
          have them choſen out of <pb n="33"/>
          <lb/>both the foregoing, as may beſt ſuit the <lb/>Patient's Temperament or Conſtitution,
          <lb/>without regard to which, it will be im- <lb/>poſſible any one afflicted with this Di-
          <lb/>ſtemper, can ever receive the Advantage <lb/>that otherwiſe he might, and no won-
          <lb/>der that in over-looking thereof, ſo ma- <lb/>ny People fall under worſe
          Circumſtances <lb/>than before, much heightening the very <lb/>Symptoms, of which they
          thought them- <lb/>ſelves purſuing the Cure; and here I <lb/>think I have a fair
          Opportunity to ac- <lb/>quaint you, that thoſe very common Re- <lb/>medies, with which
          more eſpecially the <lb/>Town is ſtock'd by <hi rend="italic">Quacks</hi> and <hi
            rend="italic">Empiricks</hi>, <lb/>I mean the <hi rend="italic">Spirits of
            Scorvy-graſs</hi> [to thou- <lb/>ſands of whom each has prov'd a very ſcurvy
          <lb/>Spirit] whether plain or purging, have <lb/>been ſome of the moſt pernicious and de-
          <lb/>ſtructive Remedies that were ever adver- <lb/>tis'd in Publick, eſpecially to the <hi
            rend="italic">hot</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">ſaline</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
            >ſqualid</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">emaciated</hi> Habits, whoſe <lb/>Blood has been
          thereby fired to that de- <lb/>gree, and the Diſeaſe ſo aggravated, that <lb/>I have ſeen
          hundreds of them broke out <lb/>with Blotches and Boils, who were clear <lb/>before the
          taking thereof; others have <lb/>become as it were Leprous; others drove <lb/>into
          Hecticks and Conſumptions, and the <lb/>Spots or Eruptions growing ten times <lb/>worſe
          under the expected Remedy. Nor <pb n="34"/>
          <lb/>is it likely it ſhould happen otherwiſe, <lb/>where no regard is had, as I ſaid
          before, <lb/>to theſe three different States, Tempera- <lb/>ments, or Habits of Body, but
          led away <lb/>with the empty Name of <hi rend="italic">Spirits of Scorvy- <lb/>graſs</hi>,
          giving the ſame promiſcuouſly to all <lb/>of them. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>From theſe <hi rend="italic">Spirits</hi> I might paſs to o- <lb/>thers, tho' not of
          the like Nature, yet of <lb/>the ſame Form; particularly the two late <lb/>ones ſet up for
          Sale by ſome of the ſame <lb/>People, I mean the <hi rend="italic">Spirit of
            Ground-Ivy</hi>, <lb/>and the <hi rend="italic">Spirit of Bohea-Tea</hi>, as to which
          <lb/>my time will not allow me to make far- <lb/>ther Remarks, than that they ſeem all of
          <lb/>them to contain much more of the Arti- <lb/>ficial Productions of the Element, made
          <lb/>uſe of to extract them, than the ſimple <lb/>or natural Ones of the Plant they are
          <lb/>drawn from; or, [as an excellent Phyſi- <lb/>cian has well obſerv'd of ſome others]
          <lb/>that they are rather Creatures of the <lb/>Fire, than real or inherent Qualities ex-
          <lb/>iſting before therein; and that notwith- <lb/>ſtanding they may be well enough ſuited
          <lb/>to ſome few Caſes, where the hot and <lb/>ſpirituous <hi rend="italic">Regimen</hi>
          [as Phyſicians call it] <lb/>is allowable, yet, generally ſpeaking, they <lb/>are much
          more hurtful than beneficial; <lb/>and whoever will be at the Pains of infu- <lb/>ſing or
          ſteeping the well-dry'd Plant in hot <pb n="35"/>
          <lb/>Water, as the common Tea is prepar'd, <lb/>or taking the clarify'd Juice from the
          <lb/>Green one, when the Seaſon will admit, <lb/>will have a Remedy infinitely preferable
          <lb/>to theſe fiery Spirits. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>As to the Teas, peculiarly ſo termed, a <lb/>fooliſh Cuſtom has now brought them in-
          <lb/>to ſuch Request among People of all ſorts, <lb/>that to go about the crying them down
          <lb/>were to little purpoſe; nor indeed till we <lb/>know what better Amuſement to intro-
          <lb/>duce [for there is, it ſeems, no Conver- <lb/>ſation that can be upheld without ſome
          <lb/>tipling of one kind or other] in their <lb/>room, would it be expedient. The pre-
          <lb/>ſent have many powerful Advocates on <lb/>their ſide, any one of which might en-
          <lb/>danger the over-ſetting a ſingle Adver- <lb/>ſary; for firſt of all, if theſe Liquors
          <lb/>were diſus'd, the Crown would be robb'd <lb/>of a conſiderable Revenue: the <hi
            rend="italic">E. I.</hi> C. <lb/>put to their Trumps to ſend abroad ſo <lb/>much of our
          Silver, which they barter <lb/>away for theſe dry Leaves, and ſome <lb/>other Toys and
          Trifles, eſpecially the <lb/>Earthen Ware that comes along with them; <lb/>[but ſure it is
          no more than right, that <lb/>thoſe who furniſh the <hi rend="italic">Regalio</hi>, ſhould
          ſend <lb/>us likewiſe the Utenſils with which it is <lb/>diſh'd out]; and laſtly, to name
          no more, <lb/>the Grocer would be at as great a loſs to <pb n="36"/>
          <lb/>get off his Loaf-Sugar; ſo that upon all <lb/>theſe Conſiderations, we will leave it
          <lb/>where we found it, with this farther Ad- <lb/>monition to all thoſe who have a value
          for <lb/>their Gums and Teeth, if nothing elſe, <lb/>that they would leave off thus
          perpetu- <lb/>ally Codling or Parboyling of them, un- <lb/>leſs they intend them, at long
          run, to be <lb/>ſerved up at the ſame Table for a ſecond <lb/>Courſe. In a word, I can't
          think any of <lb/>theſe ſcalding hot Infuſions, fit for any <lb/>other than a Phyſical
          uſe; but if they muſt <lb/>take place, methinks 'tis great pity we <lb/>are oblig'd to
          ſend ſo far for ſomewhat, <lb/>whoſe Place [were we minded to make the <lb/>Enquiry] might
          be as well, if not much <lb/>better, ſupply'd at Home, it being a cer- <lb/>tain Truth,
          that no Man walks a Mile <lb/>from the Town's end, but treads upon <lb/>many a more uſeful
          Plant than this; but to <lb/>return to our Subject, the <hi rend="italic">Scorvy</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>There is, farthermore, ſcarce any thing <lb/>ſo common, as to find this Diſeaſe
          <lb/>complicated with ſome others, requiring <lb/>variety of Preſcriptions and
          Compoſitions <lb/>ſuited to the preſent Indication, that is, <lb/>ſuch other peculiar
          Ingredients in the <hi rend="italic">Anti- <lb/>ſcorbutick</hi> Mixture, as may beſt
          anſwer the <lb/>variety of Symptoms, which are ſo vari- <lb/>ous at ſometimes, that the
          higheſt Pru- <lb/>dence, and great Judgment, is often <pb n="37"/>
          <lb/>wanted to trace out the Original, and to <lb/>know certainly, whether the ſame are
          <lb/>Symptoms only of the <hi rend="italic">Scorvy</hi>, or primary <lb/>and original
          Diſeaſes of themſelves: thus <lb/>to inſtance, In the <hi rend="italic">Head, we have
            often <lb/>Giddineſs and great Pain, like a common <lb/>Head-ach; rotten or putrid Gums
            in the <lb/>Mouth like the Canker</hi>, as the good old <lb/>Women call it; <hi
            rend="italic">in the Breaſt, Palpitation of <lb/>the Heart and Swooning: ſhortneſs of
            the <lb/>Breath, as in the Aſthma; in the Belly, Cho- <lb/>licks and Bloody Fluxes</hi>,
          as from other <lb/>Cauſes; <hi rend="italic">with wandering and flying Pains in <lb/>the
            Limbs like the Rheumatiſm</hi>; together <lb/>with ſundry other intricate Symptoms,
          <lb/>which in adapting our Remedies to the <lb/>Diſeaſe in general, are always moſt heed-
          <lb/>fully to be reſpected; and for which there- <lb/>fore, none of theſe <hi
            rend="italic">Quack</hi> Remedies, how <lb/>carefully ſoever compounded, can make <lb/>a
          neceſſary Proviſion. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>My third Exception againſt theſe <hi rend="italic">Em- <lb/>pirical</hi> Medicines
          publiſh'd in this way, <lb/>was taken from the Conſideration of the <lb/>ſame Diſeaſe
          circumſtantiated differently <lb/>one Day, perhaps one Hour, from what it <lb/>was in that
          before, or may be in the follow- <lb/>ing, and requiring alſo a quite differing
          <lb/>Method in the Cure: And here I ſhall <lb/>give Example in that moſt terrible, but
          <lb/>common Diſtemper, the <hi rend="italic">Gravel</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Stone, <pb
              n="38"/>
            <lb/>which in the Fit requires one Remedy; out of <lb/>it, another; or if too big to
            paſs</hi> [here alſo <lb/>the learned Phyſician can only judge] <hi rend="italic">one
            <lb/>Intention; if paſſing, a ſecond; and if paſſed <lb/>into the Bladder, a third</hi>:
          And here, I <lb/>ſay, the Preſence of an experienc'd Phy- <lb/>ſician is as much wanted as
          any where, <lb/>and a Miſtake herein has often coſt the <lb/>poor tormented Patient his
          Life; torment- <lb/>ed, I ſay, by his Diſeaſe, and ſtill farther <lb/>tormented by a <hi
            rend="italic">Quack</hi> Remedy he had <lb/>raſhly taken; but farther to enlarge up-
          <lb/>on this Subject by way of Explanation. <lb/>When the <hi rend="italic">Stone</hi>
          then is fix'd in the <hi rend="italic">Kid- <lb/>ney</hi>, and too big to paſs [known only
          as <lb/>above by the Scrutiny of an able or expe- <lb/>rienc'd Phyſician] all we can do
          here, is <lb/>rationally to blunt the Pain with <hi rend="italic">Anodyne</hi>
          <lb/>or <hi rend="italic">Opiate</hi> Medicines ſuited thereunto; <lb/>whilſt in the mean
          time we try to ſheath <lb/>the Acrimony of the Humours by proper <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Emulſions</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Almond Milks</hi>, and other ſoft <lb/>or
          Mucilaginous Medicines, as Phyſicians <lb/>call them, having Regard alſo to the
          <lb/>bloody Water that is ſometimes made, <lb/>when the Stone ſhall happen to ſhift its
          <lb/>Place, and with its Points or Angles <lb/>wound ſome of the tender Veſſels. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>When the Stone [being paſſable] is <lb/>moved down into the <hi rend="italic"
            >Ureter</hi> [<hi rend="italic">the Paſſage <lb/>from the Kidney to the Bladder, ſo
            named, <pb n="39"/>
            <lb/>about the bigneſs of a ſmall Gooſe quill, long, <lb/>and ſomewhat diſtorted like
            the letter ſ</hi>] <lb/>we are then, by ſome <hi rend="italic">oyly</hi>, <hi
            rend="italic">glib</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ſoft</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >ſmooth</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">ſlippery</hi> Medicines, as before ob- <lb/>ſerved, <hi
            rend="italic">Turpentine Cliſters</hi>, alſo <hi rend="italic">emollient <lb/>Oyls</hi>
          and <hi rend="italic">Baths</hi> externally, to attempt the <lb/>dilating of theſe narrow
            <hi rend="italic">Pipes</hi>, and make <lb/>way for its deſcent or paſſing on; in the
          <lb/>mean time, directing alſo [as aforeſaid] pro- <lb/>per <hi rend="italic"
            >Anodynes</hi> to appeaſe the Pain, or blunt <lb/>the exquiſite Senſation thereof; and
          believe <lb/>me, whoever ſhall give or take at this Jun- <lb/>cture, either <hi
            rend="italic">Tipping</hi>'s <hi rend="italic">Liquor</hi>, the <hi rend="italic"
            >Volatile <lb/>Cleanſer</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Rogers's Powder</hi>, or any other, e-
          <lb/>ven <hi rend="italic">Honorato Fornello, <hi rend="roman">Gent.</hi> and no
            Phyſician</hi>, <lb/>his <hi rend="italic">Diſſolution Salt</hi>, will run great danger
          <lb/>of encreaſing their Torture, plugging up <lb/>the obſtructing Stone, and miſerably
          de- <lb/>ſtroying you; the mildeſt <hi rend="italic">Diuretic</hi>, or <lb/>Urine-forcer,
          doing, at ſuch times, incre- <lb/>dible Miſchief: And altho' ſome of them <lb/>may be
          after uſeful, together with dilu- <lb/>ting Liquors, to cleanſe the Paſſages, and
          <lb/>waſh the Kidneys; yet the Continuance <lb/>of them unſeaſonably, has ſometimes
          <lb/>both weaken'd the <hi rend="italic">Urinary</hi> Parts, and <lb/>brought more of this
          ſabulous or gravelly <lb/>Matter, together with ſome concreting <lb/>Salts out of the
          Blood, than might other- <lb/>wiſe have fallen down; ſo that upon all <lb/>theſe
          Conſiderations, you muſt ſurely be <pb n="40"/>
          <lb/>apprized how dangerous it will be for you <lb/>to rely upon any of theſe, however
          cele- <lb/>brated Remedies, ſold up and down the <lb/>Town by <hi rend="italic"
            >Quacks</hi>, or ignorant Perſons; <lb/>not one of which either ever was, or can <lb/>be
          ſo contriv'd, as to anſwer all the pro- <lb/>per Intentions, how <hi rend="italic"
            >ſpecifically</hi> ſoever they <lb/>are compounded: Of which farther pre- <lb/>ſently,
          when we enquire into their Na- <lb/>ture. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>My fourth Reaſon for diſſwading you <lb/>againſt theſe Medicines, was taken from
          <lb/>the vaſtly differing Cauſes, giving Riſe <lb/>to the fame Diſtemper, and which are
          al- <lb/>ways carefully to be reſpected, in our <lb/>Phyſical Preſcriptions for the ſame.
          And <lb/>here I ſhall ſet before you, one of the <lb/>moſt common [and which through tam-
          <lb/>pering firſt of all with <hi rend="italic">Quack</hi> Remedies, <lb/>and old Wives
            <hi rend="italic">Receipts</hi>, at leaſt for want <lb/>of timely Application to the
          learned Phy- <lb/>ſician, makes one of the moſt conſiderable <lb/>Numbers in our Bills of
          Mortality] that <lb/>is a <hi rend="italic">Conſumption</hi>, of which, beſides the
          <lb/>general diſtinction of <hi rend="italic">Original</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Sympto-
            <lb/>matical</hi>, we have from one of the beſt <lb/>Writers of this Diſtemper [and who
          knew <lb/>as well as any other how to cure it] the <lb/>following particular ones reckon'd
          up; as <lb/>a <hi rend="italic">Conſumption from great Loſs of Blood, or <lb/>other
            Evacuations, as from Ulcers, Fiſtula's <pb n="41"/>
            <lb/>or Apoſtems; from giving Suck, a Looſeneſs, <lb/>Diabetes, Sweats,
          Salivations</hi>; likewiſe, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Conſumptions from a Dropſy, the
            Kings-Evil, <lb/>Scorvy, Aſthma, Melancholy, Stones in the <lb/>Lungs, the <hi
              rend="roman">French</hi> Pox</hi>: Again, there <lb/>are <hi rend="italic"
            >Conſumptions from the Green-ſickneſs, <lb/>Intermitting Fevers or Agues, Pleuriſies,
            <lb/>Jaundice; from the Gout, Rheumatiſm</hi>, <lb/>with certain others too tedious and
          unne- <lb/>ceſſary farther to take notice of. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Now altho' in each of theſe we have <lb/>one general Aim, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
          the recruiting the <lb/>decay'd Habit; yet not only the Symp- <lb/>toms, ſuch as the <hi
            rend="italic">Cough</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Looſeneſs</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Sweats</hi>, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> afford divers Indications, and <lb/>a
          different Management, but in each of <lb/>them, very ſingular regard is to be had <lb/>to
          the <hi rend="italic">original</hi> Diſeaſe, of which theſe <lb/>Symptons are only
          Conſequents: Thus <lb/>for Example, if we think to cure a <hi rend="italic">Con-
            <lb/>ſumption</hi> from the <hi rend="italic">Evil</hi> with the ſame Re- <lb/>medies we
          ſet upon another from a <hi rend="italic">Dropſy</hi>; <lb/>or if we undertake to cure
          another from <lb/><hi rend="italic">bleeding at the Noſe</hi>, or other parts of the
          <lb/>Body, with thoſe we direct for the Cure <lb/>of one from an <hi rend="italic"
            >Aſthma</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Scorvy</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">Jaun- <lb/>dice</hi>,
          we ſhall find our ſelves very much <lb/>out of the way of obtaining our deſired <lb/>Ends:
          No wiſer is he, who enterprizes <lb/>the Cure of a <hi rend="italic">Pocky Hectic</hi>
          with <hi rend="italic">Antiſcor- <lb/>buticks</hi>, requir'd in the Cure of a <hi
            rend="italic">Conſump- <pb n="42"/>
            <lb/>tion</hi> from the <hi rend="italic">Scorvy</hi>; nay, if he mix not <lb/>the <hi
            rend="italic">Counter-poiſon</hi>, I mean ſome <hi rend="italic">Mercurial</hi>
          <lb/>Preparation, with his <hi rend="italic">Pectoral</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Anti-
            <lb/>phthiſical</hi> Remedies, at leaſt orders them <lb/>not between whiles, he will
          find he is do- <lb/>ing ſomewhat worſe than waſhing the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Æthiopian</hi> White, that is loſing his La- <lb/>bour only, but is acceſſary alſo to
          the <lb/>poor Man's Death, which, in all proba- <lb/>bility, had been prevented by the
          Care of <lb/>a more underſtanding and expert Phyſi- <lb/>cian. In a word, he who fancies
          he can <lb/>cure any one of theſe <hi rend="italic">Conſumptions</hi> we <lb/>have already
          recounted, with the ſame <lb/>Regimen, that may be truly uſeful for <lb/>ſome other of
          them, is upon the ſame level <lb/>of Underſtanding with the Undertaker, <lb/>to fit all
          Bodies with the ſame Suit of <lb/>Apparel; ſince it is manifeſtly apparent, <lb/>that in
          each of them, the Method muſt <lb/>be in ſome Particulars varied, and conſe- <lb/>quently
          many of them thus differing, <lb/>even <hi rend="italic">radically</hi> one from the
          other, there <lb/>can be no radical Cure [according to the <lb/>vain Pretence of one our
          preſent Re- <lb/>ceipt Quacks] by any ſingle Remedy <lb/>whatever, even that very common
          Symp- <lb/>tom attending almoſt all of them, eſpe- <lb/>cially towards the Concluſion, I
          mean the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Cough</hi>, requires the utmoſt of our Caution <lb/>and
          Circumſpection, in endeavouring to <pb n="43"/>
          <lb/>eaſe the Sick herein; for tho' many of <lb/>them bear <hi rend="italic">Opiates</hi>
          well, and that we can <lb/>do little or nothing without them, as in the <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Melancholy</hi> particularly, and ſeveral others <lb/>with a thin <hi
            rend="italic">Catarrh</hi>, or with a dry <hi rend="italic">Convul- <lb/>ſive
            Tickling</hi>, and a tolerable good Breath- <lb/>ing; yet in ſome others, as the <hi
            rend="italic">Scorbutic</hi>
          <lb/>with a <hi rend="italic">tough Phlegm, difficult Expectoration, <lb/>and ſhort
            Breath</hi>; <hi rend="italic">in the Hydropic, and eſpe- <lb/>cially the Aſthmatick,
            half a Grain of Lau- <lb/>danum, given by ſome Quack or Empiric, <lb/>has ſent many of
            theſe People to their long <lb/>Home</hi>; the Authors of whoſe untimely <lb/>Ends [had
          Juſtice taken Place] ought, <lb/>from the Gallows, to have been ſent after <lb/>them. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I come now to my laſt Objection a- <lb/>gainſt theſe Medicines, which I took from
          <lb/>the ſingular and unaccountable <hi rend="italic">Antipathies</hi>
          <lb/>of particular Perſons, againſt ſome parti- <lb/>cular Ingredients in a Compoſition;
          <lb/>which, how mean ſoever it may appear <lb/>to be raiſed here, has always had great
          <lb/>Regard in Phyſic; and the want of Fore- <lb/>ſight or Pre-conſideration thereof, has
          <lb/>been exceedingly pernicious to ſome Pa- <lb/>tients, and has alſo diſgraced the
          Phyſician. <lb/>To inſtance in one or two Examples: <hi rend="italic">Some <lb/>few
            Hyſteric Women there are, who receive a <lb/>very ſingular Relief by a full Doſe of Musk
            <lb/>or Civet, whereas a Grain of either, to the <pb n="44"/>
            <lb/>greater Number of that Sex, is exceedingly <lb/>diſpleaſing, and to ſome of them
            has been al- <lb/>moſt fatal. Again, There are ſome of both <lb/>Sexes who can bear <hi
              rend="roman">Opium</hi> well, and ſleep <lb/>quietly therewith; whilſt others are
            confound- <lb/>ed, and almoſt diſtracted, till the Effects of <lb/>it are worn off. The
            leaſt quantity of <hi rend="roman">Honey</hi>
            <lb/>will purge and ſwell up ſome as if they were <lb/>Poiſon'd: Hence <hi rend="roman"
              >Diaſcordium</hi>, <hi rend="roman">Venice- <lb/>Treacle</hi>, and <hi rend="roman"
              >Mithridate</hi>, not only upon <lb/>this Account, but ſometimes alſo upon ſome
            <lb/>other Secret, or, as we ſay, natural Anti- <lb/>pathy or Averſion, inſtead of being
            Anti- <lb/>dotes, are like Poiſon it ſelf to ſome parti- <lb/>cular Conſtitutions. <hi
              rend="roman">Mint-Water</hi> to one I <lb/>know, is the moſt certain Vomit, tho' it
            ſtops <lb/>that Complaint in almoſt all others. <hi rend="roman">Saffron</hi>, <lb/>a
            Cordial to the generality, I have alſo ob- <lb/>ſerved by the like Secret, Antipathy,
            has cau- <lb/>ſed others to faint away, either by the Smell <lb/>or Taſte. </hi>It were
          too tedious to reckon <lb/>up more of this kind, which the prudent <lb/>Phyſician, by
          converſe with his Patient, <lb/>and Enquiries of this Nature, can eaſily <lb/>obviate and
          provide againſt; but of <lb/>which, in this publick way of purchaſing <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Quack Remedies</hi> [I wiſh I could ſay that <lb/>were all] you muſt run
          the Hazard. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I have given only a ſingle Inſtance un- <lb/>der each Head of theſe Objections, that
          <lb/>I might not ſwell this little Tract beyond <pb n="45"/>
          <lb/>its intended Bounds; and indeed to have <lb/>ſingled out each Diſeaſe, and commented
          <lb/>thereon, would have been to have writ <lb/>a kind of Phyſical Hiſtory for the uſe of
          <lb/>Phyſicians, who know, perhaps, already <lb/>[at leaſt many of them] more than my
          <lb/>ſelf, inſtead of ſome ſhort Hints and In- <lb/>ſtructions, for the uſe of others, and
          for <lb/>whom this preſent Diſquiſition is only in- <lb/>tended; for there is no Diſtemper
          with <lb/>which we are afflicted, but in unfolding <lb/>after the ſame manner, I could
          eaſily <lb/>make it appear, and I hope alſo, convince <lb/>you, that no Remedy for any of
          them, <lb/>this way recommended, can be ſecurely <lb/>rely'd on; that it may poſſibly
          afford <lb/>ſome Benefit, but much more probably <lb/>do you a Miſchief; or in other
          Words, <lb/>that in about twenty, there is one Chance <lb/>for, to nineteen, againſt you.
          Who then <lb/>that has his Senſes would thus act in the <lb/>Dark in an Affair ſo valuable
          as their <lb/>Health? Or who thus <hi rend="italic">throw the Dye, as it <lb/>were, upon
            the Drum-head, for their Life</hi>, if <lb/>they could avoid it? </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Can you now believe it poſſible, in ſo great <lb/>variety of
            Symptoms, appearing under the <lb/>ſame Diſeaſe, ſome of them ſo contradictory to
            <lb/>each other in their Indications or Intentions <lb/>of Healing; ſo great Affinity or
            Likeneſs of <lb/>one Diſeaſe with another in ſome common <pb n="46"/>
            <lb/>Symptoms, yet requiring, as you ſee, a va- <lb/>rious Method, the Miſtakes in which
            have <lb/>been of the higheſt Conſequences; ſuch diver- <lb/>ſity of Habits or
            Conſtitutions likewiſe to be <lb/>carefully reſpected; alſo the ſudden Changes and
            <lb/>Alterations; the different Appearances on Hour <lb/>of the ſame Diſtemper, from
            what it was the <lb/>Hour before, or may be next, and calling for a <lb/>quite different
            Preſcription; the Sympathies and <lb/>Antipathies natural to ſome certain Perſons
            <lb/>likewiſe to be obſerved:</hi> I ſay, if you can be- <lb/>lieve all theſe are to be
          provided for by any <lb/>ſimple <hi rend="italic">Quack Remedy</hi> whatever, left to ſell
          <lb/>at a Tradeſman's Shop, you muſt believe <lb/>at the ſame time, that a <hi
            rend="italic">Taylor</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Shoe- <lb/>maker</hi>, nay, that any <hi
            rend="italic">Old Woman</hi> who <lb/>can neither read nor write, nor yet <lb/>ſpeak
          intelligibly, knows as much of <hi rend="italic">Me- <lb/>dicine</hi> as the beſt of us
          all; or that one <lb/>who never look'd into a Humane Body, <lb/>may be as well acquainted
          with all the <lb/>minuteſt Parts therein, their Scituation <lb/>and Uſe, as the greateſt
          Maſter of <hi rend="italic">Anato- <lb/>my</hi>. But I muſt believe better of the
          <lb/>Generality of my Readers, moſt of which, <lb/>I dare think, have been thus impoſed on
          <lb/>for want of having the Truth ſet in a clear <lb/>Light, and in a Way ſuited to their
          Un- <lb/>derſtandings. </p>
      </div>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="110"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
