<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Lucas: Pharmacomastix</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Charles Lucas</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">Pharmacomastix: or, the office, use, and abuse of Apothecaries
              explained; the present degenerate State of Pharmacy, with its manifold Corruptions and
              Adulterations, considered; and some essays on reforming thereof: Humbly addressed to A
              Member of Parliament, with Intent to shew the necessity of amending and continuing a
              temporary Statute, for preventing Frauds and Abuses committed in the making and
              vending unsound, adulterate, and bad Drugs and Medicines, now near expiring. By the
              Author of the Scheme on which the said Statute was founded.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T62886</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T62886"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Dublin</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Dublin: printed by S. Powell, for Abraham Bradley, at the two Bibles in
                  Dame-Street, MDCCXLI.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1741</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="2"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="80"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW105763661</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Public welfare and institutional"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="2"/>
    <body>
      <pb n="3"/>
      <figure>
        <figDesc>An illustration ... </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">PHARMACOMASTIX: </hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="space">OR, THE </hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5) space"/>OFFICE, USE, and ABUSE <lb/>of APOTHECARIES explained, <hi
          rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
      </head>
      <salute rend="indent italic space">
        <lb/>SIR, </salute>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(4)">S</hi>INCE <hi rend="sc">Physic</hi> alone among all the uſe- <lb/>ful
        ſciences, has at this time the misfortune <lb/>to be <hi rend="italic">unrepreſented</hi> in
        Parliament, and as the <lb/><hi rend="sc">Statute</hi>
        <hi rend="italic">for preventing Frauds and Abuſes <lb/>in the making and vending unſound,
          adulterate, and bad <lb/>Drugs and Medicines</hi>, is now near expiring, I hope <lb/>it
        may not be improper to ſhew the neceſſity of <lb/>continuing that Act, and to offer ſome
        Amendments <lb/>thereto, which the artful evaſions and corruptions of <lb/>mercenary
        artificers have rendered abſolutely neceſ- <lb/>ſary. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Your early acquaintance with the nature and <lb/>conſtitution of Parliaments, your
        weight in our <lb/>national Aſſembly, and your extenſive benevolence, <lb/>have pointed you
        out the fitteſt patron and advocate <lb/>for a Scheme wholely calculated for the public Be-
        <lb/>nefit, to correct the many enormous Abuſes in <lb/><hi rend="sc">Pharmacy</hi>, and
        conſequently to promote the <pb n="4"/>
        <lb/>health and temporal happineſs of a conſiderable part <lb/>of mankind. Therefore I ſhall
        venture, without <lb/>any farther apology, to ſubmit the following lines to <lb/>your
        ſerious conſideration. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There is no well regulated country where the <lb/><hi rend="sc">Legislature</hi> has
        not made ſome proviſion for <lb/>the preſervation of the health of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Body natural</hi>, <lb/>as well as for that of the <hi rend="italic">Body politic</hi>;
        yet pity it is, <lb/>that in moſt, for want of due Information, all the <lb/>Laws hitherto
        enacted in regard to <hi rend="italic">Medicine</hi>, have <lb/>fallen far ſhort of it's
        good intentions. For as an <lb/>Evil whoſe ſource or cauſe is unknown muſt be
        <lb/>remedileſs; ſo is it ſcarce poſſible, that the Frauds <lb/>or Abuſes in any art or
        trade, tho' ever ſo pernicious <lb/>to ſociety, can be prevented or puniſhed by law,
        <lb/>until they are firſt diſcovered and made apparent to <lb/>the law-givers. — If ſome of
        the honeſt artiſts or <lb/>tradeſmen of every occupation, would ingenuouſly <lb/>diſcloſe
        the ſecret corruptions of their reſpective <lb/>callings (without which they may for ever
        eſcape <lb/>the cognizance and cenſure of the <hi rend="sc">Legislature</hi>) <lb/>we might
        then hope for a general reformation. <lb/>But alas! we are too like the <hi rend="italic"
          >Epheſian ſmith</hi> in <lb/>ſcripture, ready upon every attempt to purge us <lb/>from
        iniquity, to cry out with him, <hi rend="italic">The craft is in <lb/>danger</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The natural, fragile ſtructure of the human <lb/>Frame, which has rendered it ſubject
        to ſundry <lb/>inevitable viciſſitudes, from the force of external <lb/>bodies, from the
        alterations of the air, the nature <lb/>of the aliments, and from the very vital actions,
        <lb/>has made the <hi rend="italic">healing art</hi> in general, of all others the <lb/>moſt
        uſeful and neceſſary for the ſupport and well- <lb/>being of mankind, and nearly <hi
          rend="italic">coœval</hi> with the <lb/>Creation <note place="bottom" n="†"
          rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>† Boerh. Inſtit. Medic. Prolegom. </p>
        </note>. So ſenſible were men in all ages of the <lb/>uſefulneſs and dignity of Phyſic, that
        it has ever <lb/>been held in the utmoſt reverence and eſteem. <pb n="5"/>
        <lb/>The inventors or improvers of this noble art were <lb/>by the antients ranked among the
        Gods, and ſtiled <lb/>ſons of Gods, and the hands of Gods. It was a long <lb/>time practiſed
        by heroes only, or the ſons of Gods, <lb/>
        <note place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>† Ælian de. animal. lib. ii. cap. 18. </p>
        </note>
        <lb/>being deemed too ſacred for prophane hands. <lb/>The Heathen, Jews and primitive
        Chriſtians agreed in <lb/>paying the utmoſt reſpect to the healing art, be- <lb/>lieving it
        of divine and heavenly origine <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)" n="‡">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>‡ Cicer. Tuſculao. Quæſt. lib. 3. Hippoc. de priſ. medicina <lb/>S. Aug. de Civit.
            Dei. </p>
        </note>. Hence <lb/>we find the greateſt honors poſſible were conferred <lb/>on the antient
        phyſicians in the moſt wiſe, polite, and <lb/>politic ſtates. They were generally careſſed
        or en- <lb/>vied by kings and princes who deſigned to ſtudy, <lb/>and endeavoured to acquire
        and practice their in- <lb/>eſtimable art. Many natural productions as well as
        <lb/>artificial preparations to this day retain the Name of <lb/>a royal diſcoverer or
        inventor. And two <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)" n="§">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>§ Meſue &amp; Avicen. </p>
        </note> of the <lb/>moſt conſiderable antient phyſical writers whoſe <lb/>works are extant
        at this time, were, one the ſon of <lb/>a king, the other a ſovereign prince. The <hi
          rend="italic">Athenians</hi>
        <lb/>ſo juſtly prized the worth and excellency of the <lb/>divine <hi rend="italic"
          >Hippocrates</hi>, that they initiated him into their <lb/>grand myſteries; they preſented
        him with the free- <lb/>dom of <hi rend="italic">Athens</hi> in a crown, (a royal diadem) to
        <lb/>the value of a thouſand pieces of Gold, and ſet- <lb/>tled a conſiderable ſtipend for
        his maintenance during <lb/>life, at the public expence. — They likewiſe made <lb/>a law
        prohibiting all women, bondſmen, or ſlaves <lb/>meddling with Phyſic: as they did likewiſe
        in Locris, <lb/>which decreed, that diſobedience to the directions or <lb/>preſcriptions of
        Phyſicians ſhould be puniſhed with <lb/>death. <hi rend="italic">Julius Cæſar</hi> made all
        Phyſicians that ſhould <lb/>ſettle in <hi rend="italic">Rome</hi>, freemen and denizens
          <note n="‖" place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>‖ Sueton. </p>
        </note>; and when, <lb/>for ſome reaſons of ſtate, a ſucceeding emperor <lb/>baniſhed the
          <hi rend="italic">Greeks</hi> that city, yet the Phyſicians, <lb/>tho' all <hi
          rend="italic">Greeks</hi>, were exempted. It is alſo obſervable <pb n="6"/>
        <lb/>that the firſt alien known to obtain his freedom of <lb/>that once glorious city was a
        Phyſician <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)" n="*">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Arcagathus. </p>
        </note>. The <lb/>Phyſicians of the college of <hi rend="italic">Milan</hi> are dignified
        <lb/>with an order of knighthood, and wear to this day <lb/>golden Collars <note
          place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)" n="†">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>† John. Bapt. Sylvatic. </p>
        </note>. Innumerable other inſtances <lb/>might be produced, if neceſſary, to ſhew, that
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">medicine</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">medical ſages</hi> were
        ever reſpected <lb/>and eſteemed, admired and encouraged, all <lb/>the World over. See <hi
          rend="italic">Celſus</hi>, Senert. <hi rend="italic">Inſt.</hi>
        <hi rend="italic">Med.</hi>
        <lb/>Moæbii <hi rend="italic">Synopſ. epitom.</hi>
        <hi rend="italic">Inſt. Med.</hi> Le Clerc <hi rend="italic">Hiſt.</hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">de la Medecine.</hi> Friend's <hi rend="italic">Hiſtory of
          Phyſic</hi>. Harris's <lb/><hi rend="italic">Pharmac-anti-empyr.</hi> and <hi
          rend="italic">Prof. to</hi> Fuller's <hi rend="italic">Pharmacop. <lb/>extempor</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If the <hi rend="italic">healing art</hi> was thus honored in the ruder, <lb/>early
        ages, how much does it deſerve our regard <lb/>and attention with the many conſiderable
        improve- <lb/>ment of the moderns, which were to the antients <lb/>utterly unknown? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There can hardly be any one inſenſible of the <lb/>value of <hi rend="sc">Health</hi>
        and <hi rend="sc">Life</hi>, ſince the very firſt <lb/>impulſe of nature prompts every
        creature to uſe all <lb/>ways and means to preſerve them: And nothing <lb/>but an
        uninterrupted enjoyment of health can render <lb/>any man regardleſs of ſo invaluable a
        bleſſing. It <lb/>was the dreadful contagion which raged in <hi rend="italic">Rome</hi>
        <lb/>about the 301ſt year after the building that city, <lb/>'where there were not then
        found Phyſicians enough <lb/>to attend the ſick <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)" n="‡">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>‡ Dion. Halicarnaſ. </p>
        </note>, that firſt made the robuſt <hi rend="italic">Ro- <lb/>mans</hi> ſenſible of the Uſe
        and Excellency of <hi rend="sc">Physic</hi>, <lb/>which they afterwards ſo generouſly
        incouraged, and <lb/>ſo amply rewarded. <hi rend="italic">Salus populi ſuprema lex
        eſto</hi>, is <lb/>a precept which was once religiouſly obſerved, in <lb/>its fulleſt
        extent, by every worthy <hi rend="italic">Roman</hi> ſenator. <lb/>And tho' it might not
        have been originally pro- <lb/>nounced or received in this ſenſe literally, yet I ap-
        <lb/>prehend the application of it merely to the bodily <pb n="7"/>
        <lb/>health of the people, can be no wide deviation from <lb/>the ſenſe of the wiſe author;
        ſince the general well- <lb/>fare of the community depends upon the health of <lb/>it's
        Members. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Physic</hi> or <hi rend="sc">Medicine</hi> is the art by which our
        <lb/>lives and health are preſerved and reſtored. And <lb/>abuſes or mal-adminiſtration in
        any branch thereof <lb/>muſt neceſſarily prejudice or ſubvert the whole. <lb/>This cannot be
        charged upon <hi rend="italic">Phyſic</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Chirurgery</hi>, <lb/>for it
        may in truth be affirmed, that this Kingdom <lb/>was never ſo happily provided in that way,
        as at <lb/>preſent, with men of both profeſſions inferior to <lb/>none in <hi rend="italic"
          >Europe</hi>, in erudition, judgement, and probity. <lb/>But <hi rend="sc">Pharmacy</hi>,
        or the <hi rend="italic">apothecary's art</hi> in parti- <lb/>cular, which miniſters in an
        eſpecial manner to the <lb/>two former branches, namely <hi rend="italic">Phyſic</hi> and
          <hi rend="italic">Chirurgery</hi>; <lb/>tho' the good ſucceſs of both moſt conſiderably
        <lb/>depends thereupon, is left neglected and un- <lb/>cultivated, over-run with <hi
          rend="italic">errors</hi>, <hi rend="italic">abuſes</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
        >frauds</hi>. <lb/>And tho' there are no corruptions in any art ſo per- <lb/>nicious and
        deſtructive to the public, as thoſe of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Apothecaries</hi>, yet
        (melancholly conſideration!) none <lb/>are ſo little liable to diſcovery or puniſhment.
        <lb/>Deceits in moſt trades are perceptible to the gene- <lb/>rality, and are not only in
        ſome ſenſe cognizable <lb/>by law, but as they muſt ſooner or later be diſcover- <lb/>ed by
        the cuſtomers, common policy will direct <lb/>moſt tradeſmen to ſome integrity in their
        callings. <lb/>But as the moſt baneful frauds in <hi rend="italic">Pharmacy</hi>, being
        <lb/>never ſuſpected, are ſeldom or never perceptible to <lb/>the public, tho' often felt,
        (few or none beſides <lb/><hi rend="italic">Phyſicians</hi>,<hi rend="italic"
          >Chirurgeons</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">Apothecaries</hi>, being ſenſible <lb/>of the
        evils in this way,) ſo none tranſgreſſes with <lb/>more eaſe and ſecurity, than the
        diſhoneſt apothe- <lb/>cary. He may deſtroy the reputation of the moſt <lb/>careful and
        judicious phyſicians and chirurgeons, and <lb/>murder thouſands of their patients, his bill
        is never- <lb/>theleſs paid, and he is ſtill unſuſpectedly entertain- <lb/>ed, careſſed and
        employed by the ſurviving Fami- <pb n="8"/>
        <lb/>lies. A little artifice can tinſel or varniſh over the <lb/>moſt vile <hi rend="italic"
          >frauds</hi> or <hi rend="italic">perfidious neglects</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">unjuſt
          <lb/>apothecary</hi>. If he can command a brazen front, <lb/>with an hardened, ſervile
        conſcience, it is enough, <lb/>all is ſafe. For his <hi rend="italic">vaſſal
          apprentices</hi>, who only can <lb/>be privy to his villainy, are huſhed, they are obliged
        to <lb/>keep his <hi rend="italic">ſecrets</hi> without diſtinction. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As <hi rend="sc">Pharmacy</hi> is a moſt uſeful and neceſſary <lb/>art, nay, according
        to one of the fathers of phyſic <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)" n="†">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>† Celsus. See J.D. Horſt. Inſt. pharmac. L. ii. C. i. </p>
        </note>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">the moſt uſeful branch of medicine</hi>, when in a ſtate
        <lb/>of purity and perfection, ſo it is the moſt <hi rend="italic">pernicious</hi>
        <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">deſtructive</hi>, when it is not exerciſed with the <lb/>utmoſt
        integrity, care, fidelity and good under- <lb/>ſtanding. No knave ſo vile, ſo dangerous to
        ſociety <lb/>as a bad apothecary. The rapacious highwayman, <lb/>a profeſſed <hi
          rend="italic">enemy</hi> to mankind, bids the unwary tra- <lb/>veller ſtand and at the
        peril of his life part with his <lb/>money: But the diſhoneſt apothecary, a more ſubtil
        <lb/>kind of robber, pretends a <hi rend="italic">friendſhip</hi> for his Cuſto- <lb/>mer,
        yet takes the ſame opportunity with the former <lb/>(which the love of life and health, and
        dread of <lb/>death that human Nature is poſſeſſed with, amply <lb/>affords him,) and ſo
        robs thouſands of their fortunes, <lb/>giving them only ſome vile, uſeleſs drug in ex-
        <lb/>change; by which their lives are always endan- <lb/>gered and often deſtroyed. And yet
        notwithſtand- <lb/>ing the apothecary is never in the leaſt ſuſpected; ſo <lb/>that the
        orphan may oft pay him for the death of <lb/>his parents, parents for that of their
        children, wi- <lb/>dows for their husbands, and ſo forth: and perhaps <lb/>gratefully
        acknowledge the great care and tenderneſs <lb/>of their <hi rend="italic">worthy
          apothecary</hi>, tho' he might have been <lb/>more inſtrumental to their death than the
        diſeaſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>For theſe reaſons,, the apothecaries have no tem- <lb/>poral advantages in, nor any
        incitements to honeſty <lb/>or integrity in their calling. For while men can <lb/>buy the
        moſt baſe and worſt commodities, and may <pb n="9"/>
        <lb/>without detection, ſubſtitute them for, or ſell them <lb/>at the ſame rate with the
        beſt and moſt genuine, we <lb/>ſhall probably be infeſted with ſuch mercenary <lb/>wretches
        as will prefer their own ill-gotten gain, to <lb/>a clear conſcience and the ſafety and
        welfare of <lb/>their neighbours; <hi rend="italic">the far greater profit ariſing from
          <lb/>illegal trade</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I would not be hereby thought to charge all the <lb/>worthy apothecaries of this
        kingdom, with igno- <lb/>rance, diſingenuity, or diſintegrity; far be it from <lb/>me! I am
        well aſſured that we have ſome, as ju- <lb/>dicious, as ſkilful, and as honeſt in their way,
        as <lb/>any in <hi rend="italic">Europe</hi>. But as it may not be allowable <lb/>to point
        at the indentical guilty perſons, either by <lb/>naming the one, or exempting the other, ſo
        I am <lb/>obliged to make the charge in general againſt the <lb/>whole fraternity, my ſelf
        not excepted. So <hi rend="italic">let him <lb/>whom the cap fits wear it</hi> — <note
          place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)" n="*">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Shakeſpear's Hamlet. </p>
        </note> let <hi rend="italic">the galled jade <lb/>wince.</hi> — It is thro' a real concern
        for the juſt, <lb/>good men, that are indiſcriminately blended with <lb/>the unjuſt, and for
        the ſcandalous diſrepute which <lb/>the excellent art of <hi rend="italic">Pharmacy</hi> is
        fallen into, toge- <lb/>ther with the long train of evils which attend the <lb/>public in
        general, from the baſe craft and corrupti- <lb/>on of avaricious falſifiers of medicines,
        that I am <lb/>urged to this work. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I have a long time had a conflict with myſelf <lb/>about this important undertaking. I
        muſt confeſs I <lb/>ſome time feared the united powers of the wicked a- <lb/>gainſt me,
        having on the like occaſion heretofore, <lb/>fatally experienced the ſtrength of the <hi
          rend="italic">confederate <lb/>Opponents of reformation</hi>: And above all, I avoided
        <lb/>taking upon me a task, to which I am conſcious of, <lb/>and confeſs my inequality. But
        at length laying a- <lb/>ſide all ſelfiſh fear, and finding none of the many <lb/>more
        capable inclined to engage in ſuch a juſt and <lb/>neceſſary <hi rend="italic">warfare</hi>,
        I have at all hazards preſumed <pb n="10"/>
        <lb/>to give you the following informations, and to ſub- <lb/>mit theſe juſt (tho'
        indigeſted) Obſervations to the <lb/>wiſdom of the <hi rend="sc">Legislature</hi>; from
        whoſe pater- <lb/>nal care and benevolence alone, we may expect the <lb/>due encouragement
        of <hi rend="italic">Virtue</hi>, and the ſuppreſſion <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Vice</hi> of
        every kind. If my weak endeavours <lb/>anſwer any uſeful purpoſes, I have my full recom-
        <lb/>pence in being but ever ſo mean an Inſtrument of <lb/>effecting a public good. I hope
        the merits of the <lb/>Cauſe, for which I am but a ſlender advocate, and <lb/>the ſimplicity
        and honeſty of mine intentions, will <lb/>gain your attention, plead for the weakneſs of my
        <lb/>performance, and ſupply the want of <hi rend="italic">Rhetoric</hi> and <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Oratory</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In order to lay this matter properly before you, I <lb/>judge it expedient, </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I. To conſider the riſe and primitive ſtate of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Pharmacy</hi>,
        and from the beſt authority to point out <lb/>the proper <hi rend="italic">Office</hi> and
          <hi rend="italic">Duty</hi> of, and the requiſite <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Qualifications</hi> for an <hi rend="italic">Apothecary</hi>. In which I ſhall
        <lb/>curſorily endeavour to explain the difference between <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Apothecaries</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Druggiſts</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>II. To ſhew the preſent ſtate of <hi rend="italic">Pharmacy</hi>, and <lb/>how far the
        modern deviate from the <hi rend="italic">proper Office</hi>
        <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">Duty</hi>, and fall ſhort of the <hi rend="italic"
          >qualifications</hi> of the <lb/>antient true <hi rend="italic">Apothecaries</hi>; in
        which fatal degeneracy <lb/>it will appear, that it is ſcarcely poſſible for a man <lb/>to
        learn that Art <hi rend="italic">fully</hi>, and then to get an <hi rend="italic"
          >honeſt</hi>
        <lb/>livelihood by that profeſſion <hi rend="italic">ſolely</hi>, let his know- <lb/>ledge
        and underſtanding in it be ever ſo conſider- <lb/>able, unleſs he had the good fortune of an
        extraordi- <lb/>nary genius, which may lead him to ſtudy it properly, <lb/>and of gaining a
        ſet of cuſtomers who pay un- <lb/>common deference to his judgement and integrity. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>III. To lay open ſome of the moſt inconſidera- <lb/>ble and obvious <hi rend="italic"
          >Frauds</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Abuſes</hi> in this way, whe- <lb/>ther thro' <hi
          rend="italic">ignorance</hi> or <hi rend="italic">deſign</hi> of Apothecaries or
        <lb/>Druggiſts; and to point out ſome of the moſt per- <pb n="11"/>
        <lb/>nicious <hi rend="italic">ſophiſtications</hi> of Medicines, with the evil
        <lb/>conſequences thereof. And </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>IV. and laſtly, To offer ſome means to prevent <lb/>ſuch horrid mal-practices for the
        future; whereby <lb/>the <hi rend="sc">King</hi> is not only baſely defrauded in his juſt
        <lb/>Revenue, by which every Subject muſt ſuffer; but <lb/>alſo the <hi rend="sc"
          >Public</hi> is robbed of the chief bleſſing <lb/>of this life, Health, and the means of
        reſtoring it; <lb/>and the fair and honeſt Apothecary is crampt and <lb/>reſtrained in the
        lawful diſcharge of his function; <lb/>being underſold by the fraudulent and diſhoneſt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I. In the pure, primitive ages of the <hi rend="italic">healing Art</hi>, <lb/>the <hi
          rend="italic">phyſician</hi> not only <hi rend="italic">preſcribed</hi>, but <hi
          rend="italic">collected</hi>, <hi rend="italic">pre- <lb/>pared</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
          >diſpenſed</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">adminiſtred medicaments</hi>, as well <lb/>as <hi
          rend="italic">performed chirurgical operations</hi>. For the <hi rend="italic">now</hi>
        <lb/>three diſtinct branches of <hi rend="italic">Medicine</hi>, called <hi rend="italic"
          >Phyfic</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Pharmacy</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Chirurgery</hi>,
        were (till about the time <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Herophilus</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
          >Eraſiſtratus</hi>) managed by one and <lb/>the ſame hand <note place="bottom"
          rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Celſ. Pref. l. i. Le. Clerc. hiſt. de la Med. p. ii. l. <unclear>t</unclear>. c.
            ix. </p>
        </note>. But finding it too laborious and <lb/>burdenſome, and according to a trite aphoriſm
        of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">father</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Phyſic</hi>, <note
          place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)" n="†">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>† Hippoc. Lib. i. Aph. i. </p>
        </note> that <hi rend="italic">the life of man was <lb/>too ſhort to comprehend fully, or to
          compleat the know- <lb/>ledge of that ſublime Art</hi>, it was judged expedient <lb/>to
        divide it into theſe three different parts, that <lb/>having leſs to ſtudy in each, it might
        become leſs <lb/>tedious and prolix, inſomuch that every ſtudent <lb/>may hope to arrive at
        a competent degree of know- <lb/>ledge in that branch which he choſe for his peculiar ſtu-
        <lb/>dy: Whereupon the three diſtinct offices of <hi rend="italic">Phyſician</hi>, <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Apothecary</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Chirurgeon</hi>, were inſtituted. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Phyſicians</hi>, on account of <hi rend="italic">ſeniority</hi>
        and <hi rend="italic">ſuper- <lb/>lative erudition</hi>, are juſtly allowed the <hi
          rend="italic">pre-eminence</hi>
        <lb/>of the two other brethren, which, indeed, I think <lb/>that profeſſion merits of all
        others, divinity only <lb/>excepted. A Phyſician muſt have a moſt liberal edu- <lb/>cation:
        He muſt be well verſed in all the learned <pb n="12"/>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">languages</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">natural hiſtory</hi>, in all
        parts of <hi rend="italic">Phi- <lb/>loſophy</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">Anatomy</hi>, <hi
          rend="italic">the animal Œconomy</hi>, <hi rend="italic">the hiſto- <lb/>ries of
          diſtempers</hi>, <hi rend="italic">their natures</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ſigns</hi>, <hi
          rend="italic">Symptoms</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">cauſes</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
          >diagnoſtics</hi>, <hi rend="italic">prognoſtics</hi>, indications of <hi rend="italic"
          >Cure</hi>, <lb/>&amp;c. He muſt likewiſe be well grounded in <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
          >theories</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Chemic</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Galenic
          pharmacies</hi>
        <lb/>and of <hi rend="italic">chirurgery</hi>. For according to the wiſe <hi rend="italic"
          >author</hi>
        <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">medicine</hi>, <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)" n="*">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Hippoc. lex. </p>
        </note>
        <hi rend="italic">natural endowments</hi>, <hi rend="italic">learning</hi>, <hi
          rend="italic">a proper</hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">place for ſtudy</hi>, <hi rend="italic">education from infancy</hi>,
          <hi rend="italic">induſtry and <lb/>time</hi>, <hi rend="italic">are requiſite to
          conſtitute a phyſician</hi>; in conſe- <lb/>quence of which we find, the education of ſuch
        is <lb/>in ſchools and univerſities, ſeminaries of polite lite- <lb/>rature, where all
        things are learned to compleat the <lb/>phyſician and the gentleman. Thus muſt a <hi
          rend="italic">phyſician</hi>
        <lb/>be qualified before he can undertake the care of the <lb/>ſick in any, the ſlighteſt
        diſorder: And he who <lb/>made the greateſt progreſs in that admirable art, <lb/>even the
          <hi rend="italic">divine ſage</hi>, <note n="†" place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>† Hippoc. Epiſt. ad Democrit. </p>
        </note> is not aſhamed to confeſs, <lb/>that <hi rend="italic">tho' he was now advanced in
          old age, and got to the <lb/>extremity of life, he had not yet arrived at the end of
          <lb/>phyſic</hi>. Whence it follows that phyſic is the deep- <lb/>eſt and moſt extenſive
        ſtudy, and it's practice the <lb/>weightieſt and moſt important charge, that human
        <lb/>nature can poſſibly undertake. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Chirurgery</hi> now <hi rend="italic">uſurps</hi> the ſecond rank; and
        <lb/>tho' it has had a worſe fate than phyſic, in falling <lb/>ſome time into the hands of
        ignorant and illiterate <lb/>men, yet it's knowledge is again happily revived a- <lb/>mong
        us, and all thoſe who make a figure in that <lb/>profeſſion, are not only men of learning
        and erudi- <lb/>tion, but inferior to none in <hi rend="italic">Europe</hi> in judgement and
        <lb/>underſtanding in that excellent art. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>For ſome centuries <hi rend="italic">Chirurgery</hi> 1 as well as <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Pharmacy</hi>, 2 was <hi rend="italic">ſubſervient and miniſterial</hi> to
          <hi rend="sc">Phy- <lb/>sic</hi>. The firſt <hi rend="italic">Chirurgeons</hi>
        <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)" n="†">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>† <unclear>GREEK</unclear> Arist. Polit. L. iii. C. ii. Medicins mainæuvre &amp;
            <lb/>medicins pharmaceatique. Le Clerc. Hiſt. de la Medicine, p. ii. p. 47. </p>
        </note> and <hi rend="italic">Apothecaries</hi> after <pb n="13"/>
        <lb/>the diviſion of <hi rend="italic">Medicine</hi> into theſe three branches, <lb/>being
        taught by the <hi rend="sc">Physicians</hi>, <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)" n="‡">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>‡ <unclear>GREEK</unclear> ou Medicins Architect. ibid. </p>
        </note> were by them <lb/>ſolely directed and conducted in the exerciſe and <lb/>diſcharge
        of their reſpective functions. So that the <lb/><hi rend="italic">then Chirurgeons</hi>
        never bled, opened tumours, <lb/>amputated limbs, nor performed any other opera- <lb/>tion
        in their profeſſion; nor did the <hi rend="italic">Apothecaries</hi>
        <lb/>apply, or adminiſter any medicine, but in con- <lb/>ſultation with or by the advice or
        approbation <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">Phyſicians</hi>. Yet as it is now eſſentially ne-
        <lb/>ceſſary to compleat a <hi rend="italic">Chirurgeon</hi>, that he be a man <lb/>of
        learning, a perfect maſter of anatomy and of <lb/>courſe well acquainted with the animal
        œconomy, and <lb/>his object being one, and his practice being grounded <lb/>on the ſame
        principles and <hi rend="italic">rationale</hi> with Phyſic, <lb/>(with this only
        diſtinction, that one treats the ex- <lb/>ternal, the other the internal diſorders of the
        human <lb/>Body,) it does not ſeem unreaſonable, that <hi rend="italic">ſuch
          <lb/>Chirurgeons</hi> ſhould bleed and perform other opera- <lb/>tions in that way, and
        even preſcribe, eſpecially ex- <lb/>ternal applications, upon their own Judgement
        <lb/>ſolely. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But the caſe is quite otherwiſe with <hi rend="italic">Apothecaries</hi>: <lb/>For
        altho' they ſhould be good ſcholars, and ne- <lb/>ceſſarily converſant with the writings of
        the learn- <lb/>ed who treated on their profeſſion, yet does their <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >requiſite Readings</hi> no where inſtruct them in anato- <lb/>my, or the animal œconomy,
        nor in any of the <lb/>many other neceſſary qualifications of phyſicians, or
        <lb/>chirurgeons, the knowledge of the <hi rend="italic">Materia medica</hi>
        <lb/>only excepted, the apothecary's office, his very <lb/>appellation in all the known
        languages denotes. <lb/>Thus among the antients, <hi rend="italic">Medicus ſellularis</hi>
        <lb/>implied an apothecary or one who prepared and <lb/>diſpenſed medicines. As did likewiſe
          <hi rend="italic">Pharmaceuta</hi>
        <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">Medicamentarius</hi>. In like manner <hi rend="italic"
          >Apothecarius</hi>
        <lb/>an apothecary from <hi rend="italic">Apotheca</hi>, a ſhop, ware-houſe or <pb n="14"/>
        <lb/>repoſitory, or (in the more common acceptation,) <lb/>a place where drugs or medicines
        are kept or ſold; <lb/>and he may be aptly called a <hi rend="italic"
          >Phyſic-Shop-keeper</hi>: <lb/>alſo <hi rend="italic">Pharmacopæus</hi>, a maker, preparer
        or compound- <lb/>er of medicines. And likewiſe <hi rend="italic">Seplaſiarius</hi>, from
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Seplaſia</hi>, a market-place in <hi rend="italic">Capua</hi>, once
        a famed <lb/>mart for drugs and perfumed ointments. And <lb/>the ſole proper buſineſs and
        office of an Apothecary, <lb/>is, to <hi rend="italic">collect</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
          >procure</hi> at due times and ſeaſons, from <lb/>the proper places, <hi rend="italic">the
          ſeveral</hi>, <hi rend="italic">uſual medicinal pro- <lb/>ductions of Nature</hi>, <hi
          rend="italic">the ſimples of the Mineral</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ve- <lb/>getable and
          animal Kingdoms</hi>; <hi rend="italic">to ſelect and prepare</hi>, <lb/>to <hi
          rend="italic">decompound</hi> or <hi rend="italic">compound them according to Art</hi>, by
        <lb/>the directions of <hi rend="italic">Phyſicians</hi>, and by their preſcripti- <lb/>ons
        only, <hi rend="italic">to diſpenſe</hi>, <hi rend="italic">adminiſter</hi>, or <hi
          rend="italic">apply them</hi>. <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)" n="*">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Renod. Inſt. pharmac. c. 2. Geo. Wolf. Wedel Pharmac. <lb/>Proæm. </p>
        </note> To <lb/>qualify him for which undertaking he ſhould be well <lb/>verſed in natural
        hiſtory, as far as it regards <hi rend="italic">Mine- <lb/>ralogy</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
          >Botonalogy</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">Zoology</hi>, and rationally as well as
        <lb/>experimentally grounded in the knowledge of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Galenic</hi> and
          <hi rend="italic">Chemic Pharmacies</hi>; which is a large Field <lb/>for a man to
        exerciſe his talents in learnings and it <lb/>muſt well employ his time every ſeaſon or the
        year <lb/>after, if he intends diſcharging the duty of his office <lb/>ſtrictly and
        faithfully. <hi rend="italic">Pharmacopola</hi> is an injurious <lb/>name, improperly given
        to an Apothecary. The <lb/><hi rend="italic">Pharmacopolæ</hi> of the antients ſeem to have
        been ſuch <lb/>as were employed by artiſts in collecting or procuring <lb/>the ſimples; they
        were mere venders of drugs, and <lb/>pretended to no art or knowledge beyond that; but
        <lb/>as theſe men in time degenerated into knaves or <lb/>quacks, they became hateful to
        ſociety, and the name <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Pharmacopola</hi>, with moſt writers ſince
        implies, a <lb/><hi rend="italic">canting hawker</hi>, <hi rend="italic">a falſe quack</hi>,
        or <hi rend="italic">a deceitful mounte- <lb/>bank</hi>. How applicable this appellation, in
        the <hi rend="italic">worſt <lb/>ſenſe</hi>, may be to ſome <hi rend="italic">dealers</hi>
        in <hi rend="italic">medicine</hi>, who call <lb/>themſelves <hi rend="italic"
          >Druggiſts</hi>, I ſhall not here determine; but <pb n="15"/>
        <lb/>we have the ſatisfaction to obſerve, that that trade is a- <lb/>gain revived; for in
          <hi rend="italic">London</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Marſeilles</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
          >Amſterdam</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Rot- <lb/>terdam</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Leghorn</hi>,
          <hi rend="italic">Hamburgh</hi>, and moſt other regular <lb/>trading cities in <hi
          rend="italic">Europe</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Druggiſt</hi> is none other than <lb/>a
        mere <hi rend="italic">Merchant</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Drugs</hi>, and in the <hi
          rend="italic">beſt fenſe</hi> of the <lb/>word, <hi rend="italic">Pharmacopola</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>So different a profeſſion from <hi rend="italic">Phyſic</hi> was <hi rend="italic"
          >Pharmacy</hi>
        <lb/>deemed, that not above a century paſſed, ſince the <lb/>Grocers Company in <hi
          rend="italic">London</hi> diſpenſed medicines. <lb/>But it was at length found expedient,
        that ſome <lb/>ſhould ſeparate from that body, who ſhould take <lb/>upon them the entire
        management of the medicinal <lb/>part of that trade, that by applying themſelves ſole-
        <lb/>ly to an affair of ſo great importance to the public, <lb/>they might cultivate and
        attain to a competent know- <lb/>ledge in ſo uſeful and neceſſary an art. Whereupon
        <lb/>Pharmacy was revived, and the Apothecaries throw- <lb/>ing off all incumbrances, betook
        them to their pro- <lb/>per profeſſion, in which they ſoon became eminent, <lb/>were taken
        notice of, and encouraged by the learned, <lb/>and grew into ſuch favour with King <hi
          rend="italic">James</hi> the <lb/>Firſt, that he incorporated them by Royal Charter,
        <lb/>and uſed to call them <hi rend="italic">his own company</hi>. Thus they <lb/>became a
        diſtinct ſociety from the grocers. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The illuſtrious college of phyſicians of <hi rend="italic">Augſburgh</hi>, <lb/>which
        was the firſt, that I find, who took the pains of <lb/>compiling, and publiſhed the
        celebrated <hi rend="italic">Auguftane <lb/>Diſpenſatory</hi>, has moſt minutely and juſtly
        laid down <lb/><hi rend="italic">the qualifications for and the office and duty of an Apo-
          <lb/>thecary</hi>, from whom, with ſome few amendments <lb/>from other authentic writers,
        I make the following <lb/>abſtract. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/>As <hi rend="sc">Pharmacy</hi> is a moſt conſiderable branch of the <lb/><hi rend="sc"
          >Healing Art</hi>, being the phyſician's chief agent, ſo <lb/>the apothecary ſhould be a
        juſt good man, and principally <lb/>grounded in the knowledge of his profeſſion. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/>He ſhould in general be untainted in his morals, and of <lb/>a perfect ſound
        underſtanding, endowed with a juſt reve- <lb/>rence for the <hi rend="sc">Supreme
        Being</hi>, and the true principles <pb n="16"/>
        <lb/>of the <hi rend="sc">Christian Religion</hi>; pious and faithful, <lb/>juſt and
        equitable; humane, benign, affable, placable, <lb/>merciful and ready; mild and bountiful to
        the poor and indi- <lb/>gent; ever preferring publick to private gains; vigilant <lb/>and
        regardful of the dangers and neceſſities of the ſick; in <lb/>acts of mercy and charity,
        diligent and unwearied; not <lb/>covetous, penurious, or mercenary; for in buying of drugs,
        he <lb/>is to prefer the teſtimony of a clear conſcience, the good <lb/>of his neighbour,
        and his own credit and reputation, to ill <lb/>gotten riches or lucre. Wherefore, he is to
        procure ge- <lb/>nuine good drugs and medicines at any rate, rather than by <lb/>buying at
        the vileſt, diſpenſe adulterate or bad medicines, <lb/>and deceive his unwary cuſtomer to
        the peril or prejudice <lb/>of his life or health. He ſhould be fober and regular in
        <lb/>all his conduct; no gameſter, ſot, or drunkard; nor prone <lb/>to libidinous
        concupifcence or venery. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Thefe premiſed, his capacity is next to' be conſi- <lb/>dered. <hi rend="italic">He
          muſt not only have a ſtrong natural genius to <lb/>lead him to this art, but he muſt be a
          good ſcholar, to ina- <lb/>ble him to read the ordinary preſcripts of phyſicians and
          <lb/>chirurgeons, which</hi> (from the difficulty of tranſlating <lb/>them with any
        certainty into the vulgar tongues, <lb/>and for other obvious reaſons,) <hi rend="italic"
          >are all over</hi> Europe <lb/><hi rend="italic">wrote in</hi> Latin, <hi rend="italic"
          >and eſpecially, that he may acquire a <lb/>thorough knowledge of his profeſſion, by
          conſulting the <lb/>works of the learned, who treat upon the ſeveral <lb/>branches
          thereof</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Authors recommended, are <hi rend="italic">Dioſcorides</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
          >Galen</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ægineta</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Ætius</hi>, <hi
          rend="italic">Meſue</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Nich. Prœpoſitus</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
          >Myrep- <lb/>ſius</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Pliny</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Corn. Celſus</hi>,
          <hi rend="italic">A. M. Braſavolus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Valer. Cor- <lb/>dus</hi>, <hi
          rend="italic">Anut. Fæſius</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Fuchſius</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
          >Garcias ab Horto</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Nich. <lb/>Monardes</hi>, <hi rend="italic">J.
          B. Sylvaticus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Fernelius</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Joubertus</hi>,
          <hi rend="italic">Re- <lb/>nodœus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Melichius</hi>, <hi
          rend="italic">Coudenbergius</hi>; alſo, <hi rend="italic">Mathiolus</hi>, <hi
          rend="italic">Lo- <lb/>nicerus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Tragus</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
          >Lobelius</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Pæna</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Dodonœus</hi>, <hi
          rend="italic">Taberna- <lb/> montanus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Quercetanus</hi>, <hi
          rend="italic">Joh. Jac. Weckerus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Heurnius</hi>, <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Oſwald. Crollius</hi>, &amp;c. To which muſt now be added <lb/>G. Agricola,
        Fer. Imperatus, B. Cæſius, Worm, <lb/>Caſp. &amp; Joh. Bauhin, Salmaſius, Schroeder,
        Zwelſer, <lb/>Morriſon, Ray, Tournefort, Ang. Sala, J. Hartman, <pb n="17"/>
        <lb/>Mynſicht, the Hoffmans, Cluſius, Piſo, Bontius, <lb/>Marcgravius, Wedelius, Le Mort,
        Dale, Stahl, <lb/>Boerhaave, and many others; beſides the ſeveral col- <lb/>legiate
        diſpenſatories of Augſburgh, London, Brux- <lb/>els, Edinburgh, Paris, Leyden, Hague,
        Ghaunt, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">from theſe the apothecary can beſt learn the medicinal parts <lb/>of
          the mineral, vegetable, and animal kingdoms, with their <lb/>proper names and ſynonyma in
          the </hi>Arabic, Greek, Latin, <lb/><hi rend="italic">and vulgar tongues: Theſe will teach
          him to diſcern the <lb/>good from the bad, and to ſelect the true and genuine, <lb/>from
          the falſe and ſophiſticated: and in ſhort, from them <lb/>he can collect the generic marks
          and characteriſtics of <lb/>the ſimple, with proper inſtructions for preparing, and
          <lb/>neceſſary animadverſions on, the compound medicaments</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/> Having laid theſe ſolid foundations for his future <lb/>practice, his Œconomy comes
        next under conſide- <lb/>ration. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">His ſhop ſhould be ſituate in a convenient, open, <lb/>temperate
          place, not expoſed to damps, winds, duſt, <lb/>ſmoke, or ſtench</hi>. And as it contains
        ſundry diſtilled <lb/>liquors, wines or vinous infuſions, tinctures and ſi- <lb/>rups,
        electuaries, confections and conſerves, which <lb/>too much heat will render vapid or
        mothery, fer- <lb/>ment, ſour, or otherwiſe ſpoil; and which exceſſive <lb/>cold will chill
        add freeze, congeal, cryſtallize, or o- <lb/>therwiſe prejudice: A vintner need hardly
        obſerve <lb/>a greater exactneſs or regularity in adjuſting the <lb/>temperature of his
        cellar or vault, than an Apo- <lb/>thecary ſhould in that of his ſhop or ſtore-room.
        <lb/>Wherefore he ſhould avoid the extreme heat of the <lb/>ſun, which on one hand he is
        expoſed to, all the <lb/>ſummer months, and on the other, the extraordi- <lb/>nary cold of
        the winter: For which reaſons, that <lb/>aſpect is moſt eligible which affords the greateſt
        <lb/>mediocrity. Nor ſhould it be expoſed in any, to <lb/>the many inconveniences and evils
        of open un- <lb/>glaſſed windows and doors, nor made more intem- <lb/>perate by fires made
        on particular occaſions only, <lb/>either in ſummer or winter. </p>
      <pb n="18"/>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/>And that the medicines may he handled cleanly and <lb/>neatly, (thoſe for internal uſe
        more eſpecially, which <lb/>are taken with the greater reluctance and diſdain, the <lb/>more
        ſordidly they are obſerved to be treated) the Apo- <lb/>thecary is to keep his ſhop and
        utenſils ſweet, pure, and <lb/>clean; and with indefatigable diligence, furniſh it with
        <lb/>the uſual commodities at due ſeaſons, and preſerve them <lb/>for future uſe in fit
        receptacles and convenient places. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/>He is not to ſell or adminiſter, nor ſuffer, or cauſe <lb/>to be adminiſtered to any,
        (without the immediate li- <lb/>cence of a Magiſtrate, or the preſcription of a judicious
        <lb/>Phyſician) any ſort of poyſon or poyſonous drugg, <lb/>philtres, provocatives of terms
        or abortion, opium or <lb/>laudanum, ſtrong vomitives or purgatives, nor other <lb/>ſuch
        like powerful medicines, eſpecially the Chemical <lb/>preparations of Mercury and Antimony. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/>He ſhould be ſtrictly juſt and faithful, cautious and <lb/>circumſpect, in the
        diſpenſing and preparing the ordina- <lb/>ry preſcriptions of Phyſicians, as well as the
        officinal <lb/>compoſitions. Nor ſhould he raſhly or conceitedly, ſub- <lb/>ſtitute any one
        thing for another in a medicine, truſt- <lb/>ing to his own judgement or knowledge, nor omit
        the <lb/>leaſt or meaneſt ingredient in any compoſition whatſoever, <lb/>without the advice,
        conſent, or approbation of the pre- <lb/>ſcriber, or ſome other skilful, prudent phyſician.
        But <lb/>with religious fidelity, care and integrity, diſpenſe all <lb/>preſcripts in
        quality and quantity, truly and exactly, <lb/>according to the literal fenſe of ſuch
        preſcript or recipe. <lb/>He is to keep an exact regiſtry of all ſuch recipe's, and the
        <lb/>originals, carefully filed. He is to keep ſuch as are for ſe- <lb/>cret complaints from
        being expoſed. He is to repeat <lb/>no medicine without the direction of the preſcriber. <hi
          rend="roman">
          <lb/>See prolegom</hi>. <hi rend="roman">Iſagog. in</hi> pharmac. Auguſt. <hi rend="roman"
          >Cap. <lb/>i. I. D. Horſtij</hi> Inſt. pharmaceut. <hi rend="roman">Part. i. Cap. ii.
          <lb/>Hoffman</hi>. Clav. pharm. Schroed. <hi rend="roman">p. 29. </hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>So ſenſible were the wiſe ſenate of Augſbourg of <lb/>the uſe and neceſſity of theſe
        rules, that they made <lb/>ſome excellent laws, as well to inforce the obſervati- <lb/>on,
        thereof, as to regulate the practices of phyſic, <pb n="19"/>
        <lb/>pharmacy and chirurgery in every other inſtance: <lb/>And the ſenate of <hi
          rend="italic">Ghaunt</hi> alſo took much the like <lb/>method. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Among other ſtatutes it is enacted, "That no <lb/>apothecary, ſhall ſo far ſwerve from
        his duty, <lb/>as to interfere with the proper office of a phyſi- <lb/>cian or chirurgeon;
        and that none preſumes to <lb/>ſell or adminiſter medicines (ſtrong purgatives <lb/>and
        provocatives eſpecially) without the preſcripti- <lb/>on of a phyſician; leſt by the raſh,
        ill-judged, or un- <lb/>timely uſe of the moſt efficacious remedies, the <lb/>health of the
        public may ſuffer, and the beſt <lb/>medicines fall into contempt and diſrepute; phy-
        <lb/>ſicians only being the proper judges of the fit <lb/>ſubjects and juſt times of
        adminiſtering ſuch <lb/>remedies.<q rend="quotes"> — </q>The apothecaries are obliged to
        <lb/>prepare and compound all their medicines by <lb/>the college diſpenſatory, <note
          place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)" n="*">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* See the King's proclamat. prefixed to the <hi rend="italic">London</hi> diſpnſat.
          </p>
        </note> and to ſell them at <lb/>the rates fixed by the ſenate.<q rend="quotes"> </q>All
        quacks, em- <lb/>pirics, mountebanks, and ſuch like impoſtors and <lb/> pretenders to
        medicine whatſoever, not found le- <lb/>gally qualified, are expelled the ſtate." See the
        <lb/>decrees and ſtatutes of the ſenates of <hi rend="italic">Augsbourg</hi> and <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Ghaunt</hi>, annexed to their ſeveral diſpenſatories. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The apothecaries of <hi rend="italic">Paris</hi> are obliged, not only <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">to conform to the diſpenſatory, ſtrictly and literally</hi>, <lb/>but are
        likewiſe <hi rend="italic">prohibited to vend or adminiſter a- <lb/>ny medicines whatſoever,
          without the preſcription of <lb/>one of the faculty of medicine or one of the King's
          <lb/>phyſicians</hi>. See an arret of parliament prefixed to <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
          >Pariſian</hi> diſpenſatory. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Nothing aſſuredly can contribute more to the im- <lb/>provement and benefit of the
        healing art, than the <lb/>profeſſors of the different branches thereof, applying
        <lb/>themſelves entirely to the ſtudy and practice of their <lb/>reſpective callings. And
        this was certainly the wiſe <lb/>deſign of our predeceſſors in dividing it into thoſe <pb
          n="20"/>
        <lb/>three ſeveral parts; and were it yet further ſubdivided, <lb/>it is probable it might
        be brought to greater certain- <lb/>ty and rendered more generally beneficial to man-
        <lb/>kind, than it can be in an aggregate ſtate; ſince the <lb/>meaneſt branch can
        ſufficiently employ the whole <lb/>attention and underſtanding of a man. We find <lb/>that
        many of the antients were of this opinion <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Herodot. L. ii. S. 84. </p>
        </note>, and <lb/>that it was approved by the late celebrated doctor <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Harris</hi> of <hi rend="italic">London</hi>
        <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)" n="†">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>† Pharmac. Anti-Empiric. p. 217. </p>
        </note>. What conſiderable diſcoveries <lb/>and improvements have already been made in phy-
        <lb/>ſic in general by theſe diviſions, are very obvious to <lb/>all that are converſant
        with the hiſtory of medicine. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Phyſicians</hi> by appointing <hi
          rend="italic">proper agents</hi> for the more <lb/><hi rend="italic">operoſe</hi> and <hi
          rend="italic">mechanic</hi> parts of their profeſſion, threw <lb/>off all incumbrance and
        obtained more time and <lb/>leiſure for ſtudy. <hi rend="italic">Chirurgery</hi> was
        cultivated un- <lb/>der the ſame management and both have arrived <lb/>at the extraordinary
        pitch of eminence we now ſee <lb/>them in, under theſe wiſe Regulations. <hi rend="italic"
          >Pharmacy</hi>
        <lb/>too, while it kept within the proper bounds, ſhone <lb/>and flouriſhed; for it is
        obſervable, that no ſet of men <lb/>made a better figure in their way than the apothe-
        <lb/>caries that retained their integrity and kept within <lb/>the juſt limits of their
        Occupation; which the <lb/>works of many of them amply teſtify. Of theſe <lb/>are <hi
          rend="italic">Ferrantes Imperatus</hi> a <hi rend="italic">Neapolitan</hi>, who wrote a
        <lb/>moſt excellent natural hiſtory, 28 books in <hi rend="italic">folio</hi>; <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">John Parkinſon</hi> of <hi rend="italic">London</hi>, who wrote the <hi
          rend="italic">Theatrum <lb/>Botanicum</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Paradiſus
        Terreſtris</hi>; <hi rend="italic">Thomas Johnſon</hi>
        <lb/>of the ſame, who emaculated and augmented <lb/><hi rend="italic">Gerard</hi>'s <hi
          rend="italic">Herbal</hi>, all in large <hi rend="italic">folio</hi>; <hi rend="italic"
          >Moſes Charas</hi> of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Paris</hi>, who wrote a very uſeful
        diſpenſatory, in large <lb/><hi rend="italic">quarto</hi>; <hi rend="italic">Peter
          Pomet</hi> of the ſame, <hi rend="italic">a mere druggiſt</hi>, <lb/>who wrote a hiſtory
        of drugs in <hi rend="italic">folio</hi>; <hi rend="italic">M. Lemery</hi>, <lb/>who wrote a
        courſe of <hi rend="italic">Chemy</hi> in <hi rend="italic">octavo</hi>, an univerſal
        <lb/>diſpenſatory, and a dictionary of drugs in large <pb n="21"/>
        <hi rend="italic">quarto</hi>; and <hi rend="italic">M. Homberg</hi>, who made many improve-
        <lb/>ments and diſcoveries in the Pharmacies <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)" n="*">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* See Memoires de l'Acad. Roy. de Sciences. </p>
        </note>, who were <lb/>both honoured for their eminence with the degree of <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">doctor of medicine</hi>. At preſent Mr. <hi rend="italic">Joſeph Miller</hi>
        <lb/>and Mr. <hi rend="italic">Iſaac Rand</hi> of <hi rend="italic">London</hi>, deſerve
        honourable <lb/>mention; as do Meſſieurs <hi rend="italic">Bolduc</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
          >Geoffrey</hi> of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Paris</hi>, whoſe worth and merit none can be a
        <lb/>ſtranger to, who reads the memoirs of the <hi rend="italic">Aca- <lb/>demy Royal of
          Sciences</hi>. I have reſerved to bring up <lb/>the rear, the brighteſt ornament of his
        profeſſion, <lb/>the late learned and ingenious Mr. <hi rend="sc">Samuel Dale</hi>,
        <lb/>whoſe excellent <hi rend="italic">Pharmacologia</hi> has rendered him <lb/>well known
        to all the phyſical world. For tho' he <lb/>lived in <hi rend="italic">Brantry</hi> in <hi
          rend="italic">Eſſex</hi>, yet was his merit ſo well <lb/>known to the illuſtrious college
        of phyſicians of <lb/><hi rend="italic">London</hi>, that before he publiſhed the laſt
        edition of <lb/>his works, which he greatly augmented and im- <lb/>proved, he was honored
        with a licence to practiſe <lb/>phyſic. With him let me remember that great and
        <lb/>laborious artiſt and curious naturaliſt, <hi rend="sc">Seba</hi> of <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Amſterdam</hi>; whoſe prodigious <hi rend="italic">Muſœum</hi> with the
        <lb/>hiſtory thereof, five large volumes in <hi rend="italic">folio</hi>, muſt <lb/>render
        his memory famous to lateſt poſterity. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>II. While <hi rend="italic">Pharmacy</hi> was practiſed by ſuch able <lb/>hands as
        thoſe, <hi rend="italic">Phyſic</hi> which has ſo great a depen- <lb/>dence upon it, muſt
        have flouriſhed. But ſuch be- <lb/>came the inſatiable avarice of moſt of the <hi
          rend="italic">apotheca- <lb/>ries</hi>, that they could not long content themſelves
        <lb/>with the ample profit that aroſe upon the ſale of <lb/>their proper commodities and
        manufactures; but <lb/>envious of their elder brethren of the faculty of <lb/>phyſic, they
        now endeavoured to imitate them, as <lb/>the frogs in the fable did the oxen, (and indeed
        <lb/>with much the fame ſucceſs) and ſought after new <lb/>methods of increaſing their
        ſordid gains. This they <lb/>effected by treacherouſly and ſurreptitiouſly invading <lb/>the
        provinces of <hi rend="italic">phyſicians</hi> and <hi rend="italic">chirurgeons</hi>, and
          <pb n="22"/>
        <lb/>alluring the populace under the ſpecious pretence of <lb/>giving <hi rend="italic"
          >advice</hi> in phyſic and chirurgery <hi rend="italic">gratis</hi>. <lb/>Which fatal
        deluſion readily inſnared the ignorant <lb/>vulgar, who could not be ſenſible of their groſs
        ig- <lb/>norance and manifeſt incapacity for ſuch an under- <lb/>taking, nor apprehend that
        theſe very bountiful <lb/>gentry, took care to tax their medicines with their
        <lb/>invaluable advice; ſo that their preſcriptions (of <lb/>which it muſt be confeſſed they
        are always moſt li- <lb/>beral) are now charged infinitely more than their <lb/>real value,
        or what thoſe of phyſicians and chirur- <lb/>geons, (tho' of more intrinſic worth, being
        certainly <lb/>better adapted to particular exigencies, to the con- <lb/>ſtitution and the
        indications of cure,) might be made <lb/>up and ſold for. And thus by iniquitouſly enhancing
        <lb/>the prices of remedies and giving them in unneceſ- <lb/>ſary abundance, they
        clandeſtinely acquired unme- <lb/>rited fees, equal to thoſe juſtly due to the moſt
        <lb/>regularly educated and moſt experienced phyſicians <lb/>or chirurgeons. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That this is the preſent cafe, every intelligent, <lb/>candid apothecary muſt confeſs.
        And theſe fallacies <lb/>might be further evinced beyond diſpute, were the <lb/>generality
        to be made ſenſible of the juſt rates of <lb/>medicines and the moſt monſtrous, extravagant
        <lb/>bills they are frequently charged. To ſee two <lb/>drachms of <hi rend="italic">Sal
          prunel</hi> not worth a penny, diſguiſed <lb/>with ſome inſignificant color, and an
        unintelligible, <lb/>pompous title, and ſold for ſixteen pence, muſt ſurely <lb/>move your
        contempt and indignation! Who with- <lb/>out abhorrence and ſurprize, could ſee ſham <hi
          rend="italic">Gaſgoin</hi>'s <lb/><hi rend="italic">powder</hi>, without a grain of
        bezoar, ſold at five <lb/>ſhilling the drachm, when (by omitting that only <lb/>dear
        ingredient) it could not have coſt the maker <lb/>one penny? Yet theſe and many ſuch like
        impoſi- <lb/>tions are daily practiſed by mercenary quacks, and <lb/>by them judged
        neceſſary and their undoubted <lb/>right, on accompt of <hi rend="italic">their
          extraordinary skill, great <lb/>care, frequent viſits, and trouble in attending and
          pre-</hi>
        <pb n="23"/>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">ſcribing</hi>. I have known a gentleman's bill, who <lb/>ſickened on
          <hi rend="italic">Monday</hi> and died the <hi rend="italic">Wedneſday</hi> follow-
        <lb/>ing, amount to above five pounds, tho' his careful <lb/>apothecary had but a ſtreet's
        breadth to croſs be- <lb/>tween his ſhop and the patient's lodging. It is <lb/>more than
        probable, that if the <hi rend="italic">unhappy ſufferer</hi> took <lb/>to the value of his
        bill in medicines, it was the <lb/>cauſe of his death, and would, tho' he had the moſt
        <lb/>athletic conſtitution; but to acquit his apothecary of <lb/><hi rend="italic">this
          murder</hi>, every one of the profeſſion muſt con- <lb/>feſs, that no man could well
        require or conſume <lb/>medicines to that value in the time. Then what <lb/>phyſician could
        expect ſo much for his attendance in <lb/>the ordinary manner for ſo long? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It muſt be allowed that all artiſts have a juſt <lb/>right to charge upon their wares,
        the neceſſary ex- <lb/>pences and trouble that attend the preparing and <lb/>vending them;
        but thoſe of apothecaries in the ſale <lb/>of their commodities without doors, they have
        <lb/>unneceſſarily and unjuſtly brought upon themſelves, <lb/>for the moſt part; ſo let the
        world judge their me- <lb/>rit, in impoſing ſuch an iniquitous tax upon the <lb/>public. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Some perhaps will in good-nature, urge in favour <lb/>of their worthy apothecary, <hi
          rend="italic">that for a bill of ten <lb/>pounds he is often put off with five or
        fix</hi>. A modeſt, <lb/>humble creature! His merit as well as demerit, is <lb/>beſt known
        to himſelf. — It is true ſome apothe- <lb/>caries may think themſelves well paid with half
        their <lb/>bill, and it is not improbable they often are too <lb/>well. For while they can
        ſwell their accounts to <lb/>what ſize they pleaſe, by the quantities of medicines <lb/>they
        preſcribe, and charging what they will, it is <lb/>likely care will be taken to ſuit the
        bill to the humor <lb/>of the cuſtomer, ſo that if he ſhould pay but a <lb/>fourth part,
        they are ſure to be no loſers. But <lb/>which of them will remit one penny of their bill on
        <lb/>their own accord, be it ever ſo highly rated, to <lb/>ſuch as do not wrangle for it?
        And is not whatſo- <pb n="24"/>
        <lb/>ever they receive over and above the real value of the <lb/>medicines <hi rend="italic"
          >juſtly</hi> diſpoſed of, the moſt baſe and wicked <lb/>extortion? — Such <hi
          rend="italic">apothecaries</hi> would probably <lb/>join in the impious breathings of <hi
          rend="sc">Garth</hi>'s <hi rend="italic">Diaſenna</hi>, <lb/>if they thought their goods
        were too low rated. <lb/>
        <floatingText>
          <body>
            <lb/>
            <p rend="align-center space">Thrice happy were thoſe golden days of old, <lb/>When dear
              as <hi rend="italic">Burgundy</hi> ptiſans were ſold; <lb/>When patients choſe to die
              with better will, <lb/>Than live to pay th' apothecary's bill. <lb/>And cheaper than
              for our aſſiſtance call, <lb/>Might go to <hi rend="italic">Aix</hi> or <hi
                rend="italic">Bourbon</hi> ſpring and fall. </p>
            <signed rend="align-right">
              <hi rend="italic">Diſpenſatory</hi>, Cant. iii. </signed>
          </body>
        </floatingText>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The extraordinary, unlimited gain' ariſing from <lb/>theſe horrid uſurpations, has now
        tempted the apo- <lb/>thecaries utterly to forſake their proper and imme- <lb/>diate office
        and duty. For inſtead of purſuing the <lb/>true means of learning <hi rend="italic"
          >pharmacy</hi>, (reading the <lb/>Works of the celebrated writers upon that ſubject,
        <lb/>ſuch being generally in <hi rend="italic">Greek</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Latin</hi>,
        languages to <lb/>which moſt dealers in drugs are entire ſtrangers,) <lb/>they have totally
        neglected and forſaken it, and in <lb/>the room of ſuch authors furniſhed themſelves with
        <lb/>only ſome vile <hi rend="italic">Engliſh diſpenſatory</hi>, the deſpicable <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">cob-webs</hi> of ſome poor illiterate wretch, who quacked <lb/>for a
        livelihood and ſpun theſe paultry traps for ig- <lb/>norant, unwary <hi rend="italic"
          >Flies</hi>. Such were the memorable <lb/><hi rend="italic">ſtar-mongers</hi> and
        voluminous <hi rend="italic">quacks</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Culpeper</hi> and <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Salmon</hi>, and the erroneous, conceited <hi rend="italic">ſcriblers</hi>,
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Quincy</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Alleyne</hi>; whoſe <hi
          rend="italic">diſpenſatories</hi>, <hi rend="italic">practices <lb/>of phyſic</hi>, and
        other ſuch like fallacious <hi rend="italic">quack-books</hi>, <lb/>(which will not bear
        reading by any that have read <lb/>the originals, being calculated only for ſuch mean,
        <lb/>illiterate reptiles, as addict themſelves to that vile, <lb/>pernicious Trade of
        quacking,) can but prompt a <lb/>man to think he underſtands phyſic, and practiſe it,
        <lb/>when a better education muſt convince him of the <pb n="25"/>
        <lb/>contrary, and make him tremble at the thoughts of <lb/>the ſtupendous task. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Thus has <hi rend="italic">Pharmacy</hi> been <hi rend="italic">perverted</hi> and <hi
          rend="italic">debaſed</hi>. <lb/>For tho' held by the antients <hi rend="italic">in the
          ſecond rank</hi>, yet <lb/>is it now deemed the <hi rend="italic">laſt</hi> and <hi
          rend="italic">meaneſt</hi> of the three <lb/>branches; and indeed under the preſent
        miſmanage- <lb/>ment and depravity, it may of all trades be reckoned <lb/>the vileſt and
        moſt deſpicable; and inſtead of being <lb/>uſeful, it is become apparently deſtructive to
        ſociety. <lb/>A footman or porter may now a-days paſs for an <lb/>apothecary, we fee ſhops
        daily ſerved and attended <lb/>by ſuch, or ignorant women. I have known an <lb/>apothecary's
        ſhop ſerved by a journey-man of a cer- <lb/>tain mean mechanic trade, who knew not a letter
        <lb/>in the alphabet. Nay, a wretch who converſed <lb/>more with brutes than men; the
        ſtable-tender or <lb/>groom of a certain eminent apothecary, has been <lb/>exalted from
        rubbing of horſes heels, to attending <lb/>his maſter's table, and thence to wiping of
        compters <lb/>and pounding mortars; and being tranſlated from <lb/>his maſter's to a ſhop of
        his own, acquired ſo much <lb/>craft as to paſs for an apothecary, lived in repute
        <lb/>among his neighbours for many years, and died not <lb/>long ſince in very conſiderable
        circumſtances. <lb/>Hence the calling is become ſo vile and ſcandalous, <lb/>that few,
        beſides the meaner ſort, put their children <lb/>to learn it, and ſo contemptible are thoſe
        after <lb/>a moſt ſervile and tedious apprenticeſhip, that a <lb/>journeyman taylor, or
        ſhoemaker, or any of the <lb/>meaneſt handy-craft trades, ſhall get better wages <lb/>than a
        journeyman apothecary, of ever ſo good un- <lb/>derſtanding in his profeſſion, the moſt
        ignorant <lb/>being capable of ſerving moſt of our common ſhops, <lb/>which conſiſts chiefly
        in retailing medicines made up <lb/>by a <hi rend="italic">nominal druggiſt</hi>, as
        incapable of preparing, as an <lb/><hi rend="italic">apothecary</hi> of <hi rend="italic"
          >preſcribing</hi> them juſtly, or bought <lb/>from a poor, ignorant herb-gatherer, who
        both <lb/>frequently ſell one thing for another of ever ſo dif- <lb/>ferent qualities, which
        impoſitions are implicitly <pb n="26"/>
        <lb/>over-looked by maſter and man; neither thinking <lb/>the knowledge of ſimple or
        compound medicines <lb/>material, or neceſſary, nor their preparation or <lb/>compoſition
        his proper occupation, they lay them- <lb/>ſelves out for practiſing phyſic and chirurgery;
        for <lb/>which as well as their own profeſſion, the reading a <lb/>falſe <hi rend="italic"
          >Engliſh diſpenſatory</hi> is reckoned a ſufficient qua- <lb/>lification. So, quacking
        being the principal buſineſs <lb/>of a <hi rend="italic">modern apothecary</hi>, he
        generally goes thro' that <lb/>himſelf, therefore needs no judicious <hi rend="italic"
          >emanuenſis</hi>, any <lb/>raw-boy being ſoon made capable of the ordinary <lb/>buſineſs
        of his ſhop; for which reaſon, rather than <lb/>pay journeyman's wages, apprentices are
        multiplied <lb/>at any rate, and at all hazards. Whence we come <lb/>to have more
        apothecaries' <hi rend="italic">ſhops</hi> than any city in <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Europe</hi> in proportion: We are within eight or ten <lb/>equal in number with thoſe of
          <hi rend="italic">Paris</hi>, which I think <lb/>is allowed to be ſix times as populous as
          <hi rend="italic">Dublin</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But this fatal degeneracy has now made ſuch a <lb/>progreſs, that we really forget or
        know not what <lb/>we ſhould be. For regardleſs of the worth and <lb/>dignity of our art and
        of the public benefit, the <lb/>apothecaries have neglected and abandoned it, and <lb/>in
        the vain purſuit of another, (like <hi rend="italic">Æſop</hi>'s dog) <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >quitted the real ſubſtance for an empty ſhadow</hi>; ſo, <lb/>loſing their art, have
        dwindled into vile, fallacious <lb/>quacks, vain and audacious pretenders to phyſic and
        <lb/>chirurgery, and deſtructive hawkers of medicine. <lb/>The very method of educating
        youth in this calling, <lb/>is either quite forgotten, or, ſo far perverted and <lb/>changed
        from what it muſt have been heretofore, <lb/>that it is by great accident if ever we happen
        to fee any <lb/>one of common underſtanding in that profeſſion; <lb/>few having more than
        the undeſerved name of <hi rend="italic">apo- <lb/>thecary</hi>, and that only becauſe he
        lived in ſome <lb/>mean, ſervile ſtation for a time, with one of that <lb/>appellation.
        Theſe pretenders are above the ordinary <lb/>buſineſs and attendance of a ſhop; that with
        them <lb/>is quite out of the queſtion; <hi rend="italic">they fly at higher game</hi>. <pb
          n="27"/>
        <lb/>You may ſee ſome of theſe <hi rend="italic">would-be doctors</hi> in all <lb/>parts of
        the town in queſt of prey. One dreſſed <lb/>with all the formality of a prig, another
        affecting <lb/>a dirty ſlovenly mien, and an unnatural, ſullen grim- <lb/>mace, inſtead of
        the natural gravity which muſt <lb/>neceſſarily poſſeſs men of underſtanding in the
        <lb/>important practice of phyſic. The firſt ſhall aſſume a <lb/>moſt pedantic, dogmatic
        air; the ſecond, an ill- <lb/>feigned, awkward, <hi rend="italic">hippocratic</hi> leer: and
        either ſhall <lb/>ſmell, <hi rend="italic">taſte</hi>, or inſpect excrements, examine the
        <lb/>viſage and tongue, and feel the pulſe with great <lb/>ſolemnity; then, in a long ſpun,
        uncouth jargon of <lb/>ill-choſen, unintelligible, technical words, enough to <lb/>raiſe the
        admiration and puzzle all the nurſe-keepers <lb/>in <hi rend="italic">Chriſtendom</hi>,
        ſhall ask a poor languiſhing patient, <lb/>a ſet of tedious, impertinent, common-place queſ-
        <lb/>tions, which he cannot poſſibly underſtand, and con- <lb/>ſequently cannot anſwer. But
        the wily quack, with <lb/>a ſelf-ſufficient look, and a weighty, revolving <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">humh!</hi> — cries, <hi rend="italic">ſo,</hi> — <hi rend="italic">ay</hi>,
        — <hi rend="italic">very well</hi>, — <hi rend="italic">hemh</hi>, <lb/>— <hi rend="italic"
          >I thought ſo</hi>, — <hi rend="italic">I apprehend you</hi>, and ſo forth. <lb/>Then
        armed with fatal pen, ink, and paper, he pre- <lb/>ſcribes largely, ſome ſtinking, mothered
        waters, <lb/>fermented ſirrups, pernicious burning ſpirits, in- <lb/>grateful, <hi
          rend="italic">medicated brandy-juleps</hi>
        <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)" n="*">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* G. Harvey. </p>
        </note>, or at beſt, <hi rend="italic">unwhol- <lb/>fome and unſavory punch</hi>, which the
        preſcriber (to <lb/>whom indeed their worth is ſolely known) calls <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >ſpecific</hi> or <hi rend="italic">alexipharmic</hi>, and takes care often to
        <lb/>repeat, becauſe he would not have his patient <hi rend="italic">die <lb/>for want of a
          cordial</hi>, (as it is termed) or rather, <lb/>that he may ſell his wares and have an
        opportunity <lb/>of charging for his viſits; tho' he does not know, <lb/>but he hereby in
        effect ſigns the poor <hi rend="italic">ſufferer's</hi>
        <lb/>death-warrant, tho' he meant only to draw a <hi rend="italic">ſmall bill</hi>
        <lb/>in his own favour. Yet ask this mighty <hi rend="italic">ſham-doctor</hi>, <lb/>how the
        meaneſt compoſitions in his ſhop are made? <lb/>whence this or the other ſimple ingredient?
        what <pb n="28"/>
        <lb/>it's diſtinguiſhing marks and characteriſtics ? or the <lb/>like; I will venture to
        anſwer for him rather than <lb/>betray his ignorance, he will confeſs <hi rend="italic">he
          bought them <lb/>from ſome honeſt druggiſt</hi>. No, no; he does not <lb/>ſtoop to ſuch
        mean things, <hi rend="italic">he practiſes phyſic</hi>; like <lb/><hi rend="sc"
        >Garth</hi>'s <hi rend="italic">Colon</hi>, <lb/>
        <floatingText>
          <body>
            <lb/>
            <p rend="align-center space">In trifling ſhew his tinſel talent lies, <lb/>And form the
              want of intellects ſupplies. <lb/>In aſpect grand and goodly he appears, <lb/>Revered
              as patriarchs in primæval years. <lb/>Hourly his learned impertinence affords, <lb/>A
              barren ſuperfluity of words. <lb/>The patients ears remorſeleſs he aſſails,
              <lb/>Murders with jargon where his medicine fails. </p><signed rend="align-right">
                <hi rend="italic">Diſpenſ</hi>. Cant. ii. </signed>
          </body>
        </floatingText>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Let us now take a further view of ſuch an apo- <lb/>thecary and ſee how he can teach
        pharmacy. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The apprentice of <hi rend="italic">ſuch a maſter</hi>, begins with a <lb/>ſmall
        ſmattering of grammar rules, and ſometimes <lb/>none; which he (leaſt <hi rend="italic"
          >Tyro</hi> ſhould ſoon diſcover <lb/>his ignorance and illiterature, or in time out do
        him) <lb/>judges ſufficient. His fund of ſenſe, genius, or o- <lb/>ther abilities, are never
        conſidered, being indeed but <lb/>trifling to a <hi rend="italic">modern Apothecary</hi>,
        for a little acquired <lb/>craft may make a mere block-head, or even an <hi rend="italic">I-
          <lb/>deot</hi>, paſs for an <hi rend="italic">Apothecary</hi>. His apprenticeſhip com-
        <lb/>mences, with the ſervile drudgery of the moſt abject <lb/>ſlave; as for inſtruction of
        any kind he muſt not <lb/>expect it, his maſter, who ſhines among his nurſe- <lb/>keepers
        and co-equals, had none: So that to learn <lb/>his trade, the only proſpectle ft, is to
        follow the good <lb/>example of maſter, which in this inſtance is not at- <lb/>tended with
        much difficulty, and therefore requires <lb/>but few documents. For altho' he deigns to
        ſuffer his <lb/>vaſſal to make up ſome few phyſicians preſcrip- <lb/>tions, (out of pure
        complaiſance to the elder bro- <lb/>thers of the faculty of phyſic, or inſuperable love of
          <pb n="29"/>
        <lb/>pelſ,) yet he never ſullies his own delicate hands <lb/>with any preparation; his
        fingers are made for no- <lb/>bler purpoſes, <hi rend="italic">feeling of pulſes</hi>, (in
        other words) <hi rend="italic">pick- <lb/>ing of pockets</hi>. Nor does he think it needful
        he <lb/>ſhould, when from certain <hi rend="italic">half bred</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
          >mungrel apo- <lb/>thecaries</hi>, falſely called <hi rend="italic">druggiſts</hi>, he can
        buy almoſt <lb/>every preparation or compoſition, or rather <hi rend="italic">ſubſtitutes
          <lb/>for any, cent. per cent.</hi> cheaper than any honeſt man can <lb/>make them; nothing
        need be wanting while there is <lb/>any thing of the ſame or like appearance in the ſhop.
        <lb/>The poor deluded boy is told, that maſter by <lb/>experience knows this or the other
        baſe and foreign <lb/>ſubſtitute to be equal, if not the ſame, with whatever <lb/>he is
        pleaſed to vend it for. Thus is he to learn his <lb/>future occupation! </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>At length the ſlaviſh apprenticeſhip ended, the mi- <lb/>ſerable, unedified drudge of a
        vile quack is now be- <lb/>come a maſter. — Of what? — Why of a ſhop only <lb/>forſooth. —
        See him already by example, if not by <lb/>precept, thorough paced, not only in the little
        mean <lb/>inſinuating artifices and tricks of quacks and ordinary <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >haberdaſhers of drugs</hi>; but likewiſe imbued with the <lb/>baſe penury and ſordid
        craft of pinching on the one <lb/>hand the induſtrious wretch, who for want of better
        <lb/>employment ſeeks a miſerable livelihood, by gather- <lb/>ing the herbs or reptiles of
        the earth, and extorting <lb/>on the other, an exorbitant profit from the pitiful
        <lb/>farthing of the moſt neceſſitous. Having obſerved <lb/>it needful while an apprentice,
        he chiefly ſtudied the <lb/><hi rend="italic">aſtucia medica</hi>, the querks and artifices
        of <hi rend="italic">phyſic- <lb/>jobbers</hi>, rather than the neceſſary qualifications of
        a <lb/><hi rend="italic">good apothecary</hi>, to which he is yet a ſtranger. He
        <lb/>therefore apes ſomething of the dreſs and mien of a <lb/>phyſician, well knowing, <hi
          rend="italic">that eſteem is oftener gained <lb/>by artifice and outward appearance, than
          by real worth <lb/>or merit</hi>; and then by fawning, cringing, diſſimulati- <lb/>on, and
        the like, gains a ſet of acquaintance and <lb/>cuſtomers in low life, by whom he is
        extolled, till, <lb/>by degrees or accident, he riſes a ſtep higher, and ſo <pb n="30"/>
        <lb/>is ſoon (like <hi rend="italic">Moliere</hi>'s faggot-maker, tho' not al- <lb/>ways by
        ſtripes) <hi rend="italic">perſuaded to think himſelf a Doctor</hi>. His <lb/>cuſtomers he
        now calls <hi rend="italic">patients</hi>, in imitation of his <lb/>ſuperiors, and had he
        called them <hi rend="italic">ſufferers</hi>, the appel- <lb/>lation would be ſtill more
        expreſſive and ſignificant. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>His ſole care is now to vend the deſtructive maga- <lb/>zine of periſhable
        ſhop-trumpery, which is not very <lb/>difficult to effect, when the quack has puſhed him-
        <lb/>ſelf into ſome repute with the vulgar, among whom <lb/>he muſt have many <hi
          rend="italic">Jack-calls</hi>, by whom the skilful <lb/>phyſicians and chirurgeons are
        artfully decried and <lb/>falſely vilified, who might by abſtinence, diet, air, <lb/>or
        exerciſe, or by dexterity of hand or bandage, <lb/>perhaps without the uſe of a
        ſhop-medicine, cure <lb/>ſundry maladies, for which the <hi rend="italic"
          >phyſic-ſhopkeeper</hi> bears <lb/>them mortal enmity, as they do not promote his
        <lb/>trade unneceſſarily, with the uſual fallacious inſinua- <lb/>tion of <hi rend="italic"
          >his unparallelled ſkill and judgement in phyſic and <lb/>chirurgery, and his thorough
          acquaintance with the prac- <lb/>tice of both, from the number of recipes, which come in-
          <lb/>to his hands</hi>: but above all, <hi rend="italic">the cheapneſs of his advice
          <lb/>and attendance</hi>; being ſaid <hi rend="italic">to charge no more than <lb/>the
          bare prices of a few neceſſary, cheap Remedies</hi>; which <lb/>is the principal
        recommendation. His character thus <lb/>eſtabliſhed, he has frequent opportunities of
        putting <lb/>off his commodities at any rate, and this he takes <lb/>care to improve by
        raiſing ſo many dangers and dif- <lb/>ficulties, that he keeps his poor <hi rend="italic"
          >ſufferers</hi> in as wretched <lb/>a ſtate of dread and dependence, as the wicked and
        <lb/>ignorant quack <hi rend="italic">Coctier</hi> did the timorous king of <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">France</hi>
        <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)" n="*">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Lewis xi. Mezeray. </p>
        </note>. Theſe abject vaſſals of an <hi rend="italic">uſurping apo- <lb/>thecary</hi>, (to
        palliate, cure, or prevent ſome imaginary <lb/>or fictitious diſtemper,) are never to ceaſe
        taking <lb/>medicines, being perſuaded <hi rend="italic">they cannot live an hour
          <lb/>longer than they are crammed with ſome</hi> unneceſſary <lb/>nauſeous <hi
          rend="italic">part or other of his decaying ſhop-lumber</hi>, till <lb/>after many filthy,
        expenſive drenches, harraſſed nature <pb n="31"/>
        <lb/>ſinks under the oppreſſive weight, or by her own <lb/>ſtrength breaks the bonds, and he
        is pleated to take <lb/>the honor of the cure, and to pronounce them <hi rend="italic">in
          <lb/>ſtatu ſano</hi>. If a bleeding or any chirurgical operati- <lb/>on ſhould be wanting,
        provided it be ſuch as his ig- <lb/>norance and incapacity may not too plainly appear
        <lb/>in, and wherewith he may conſume plenty of <hi rend="italic">Styptics, <lb/>Litus's,
          Balſams, Liniments, Ointments and Plaſters</hi>, <lb/>it is done by the apothecary, <hi
          rend="italic">citó, tutó, &amp; jucundé</hi>, and <lb/>that too without the leaſt help of
        a chirurgeon; which <lb/>the ſick are told to be quite unneceſſary, as phyſicians <lb/>in
        other cafes; the fees of both being pretended to be <lb/>ſaved by the quack. As a thrifty
        ale wife, to avoid <lb/>exciſe, gave her cuſtomers ale <hi rend="italic">gratis</hi>, paying
        two <lb/>pence for the <hi rend="italic">toaſt and nutmeg</hi> put into each quart. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Moreover to confirm the populace in their vain <lb/>notions of their apothecary's
        judgement in phyſic, he <lb/>has generally the artifice to become the baſeſt <hi
          rend="italic">pla- <lb/>giary</hi>. For among the cuſtomers, he uſes on every
        <lb/>occaſion, or rather <hi rend="italic">abuſes</hi>, the preſcriptions, and even
        <lb/>borrows the very words of the family-phyſician. <lb/>Thus he ſteals the doctor from
        himſelf! (if I may <lb/>be allowed the phraſe) inſomuch, that when by force <lb/>he is
        called in and conſulted, it is ten to one the pre- <lb/>judiced patients will fay, <hi
          rend="italic">that the doctor ſaid and di- <lb/>rected the very ſame things which the
          worthy apothe- <lb/>cary did before</hi>, in this or ſome other cafe, which they
        <lb/>think, or perhaps are told, was the fame. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I cannot here overlook that moſt abominable prac- <lb/>tice of <hi rend="italic">ſome
          apothecaries</hi> and <hi rend="italic">druggiſts</hi>, who not only <lb/>perſonate one
        another, by aſſuming the name of <lb/>their neighbouring brethren, in order to ſteal their
        <lb/>cuſtomers, but a certain <hi rend="italic">audacious quack</hi> has been <lb/>known to
        perſonate <hi rend="italic">a late phyſician</hi> of <hi rend="italic">his name</hi>, and
        <lb/>to recommend himſelf after as an <hi rend="italic">apothecary</hi>. Theſe <lb/>baſe
        artifices lead them to make repetitions of <lb/>preſcriptions which they never ſaw, being on
        ano- <lb/>ther's file. How fatal ſuch horrid gueſs-work muſt <lb/>often prove, to the
        patient and preſcriber, is eaſily <pb n="32"/>
        <lb/>judged; and how late a gentleman of figure ſuffer- <lb/>ed by this ſort of <hi
          rend="italic">chicane</hi>, as well as his phyſician, I <lb/>ſhall not ſay, leſt it ſhould
        too far injure a certain <lb/>pert, young quack apothecary, whoſe raſhneſs in this
        <lb/>inſtance, will, I hope, prove a warning to him for <lb/>the future. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Thus admirably equipped with craft and artifice, <lb/>and with impudence and aſſurance,
        (the inſeparable <lb/>attendants of ignorance) this <hi rend="italic">monſtrous, amphibious
          <lb/>animal, this wretched cobler in medicine</hi>, who has not <lb/>in reality a ſingle
        qualification for a <hi rend="italic">phyſician</hi> or <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >chirurgeon</hi>, nor perhaps even for an <hi rend="italic">apothecary</hi>, vainly
        <lb/>pretends to the knowledge of the <hi rend="italic">three</hi>, and ſo <lb/>takes upon
        him the ſole care and management of <lb/>the ſick in all diſtempers and diſorders; <hi
          rend="italic">acute</hi> or <lb/><hi rend="italic">chronic</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
          >phyſical</hi> or <hi rend="italic">chirurgical</hi> cafes are all alike to <lb/>him, well
        knowing that <hi rend="italic">his incapacity is not obvious <lb/>to the unhappy parties
          concerned</hi>! he hardily perſiſts in <lb/>his malpractices, being blinded with <hi
          rend="italic">ignorance</hi>, <lb/>prompted by <hi rend="italic">avarice</hi>, and having
        his conſcience <lb/>hardened by an early contracted habit of <hi rend="italic"
        >iniquity</hi>, <lb/>till he has rendered the unhappy <hi rend="italic">ſufferers</hi>
        immedica- <lb/>ble; and then (ſeldom or never before) permits a <lb/>phyſician or chirurgeon
        to be called in; or rather, <lb/>if he can, brings in ſome <hi rend="italic">poor
          pretender</hi> to, or <hi rend="italic">mercena- <lb/>ry tool</hi> of, either profeſſion,
        to juſtify his apparent <lb/>miſconduct, or to take the honor of giving the tor- <lb/>tured
          <hi rend="italic">ſufferer</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Coup de Grace</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I ſhall beg leave to give one melancholy inſtance <lb/>of this kind out of many. A
        certain unfortunate <lb/>man, who too much confided in the boaſted ſkill <lb/>of a bold
        preſumptuous quack, committed himſelf <lb/>to his care for a certain, ſlight, ſecret
        diſorder: The <lb/>apothecary judging it the only way to make a penny <lb/>of the patient,
        proceeded to adminiſter medicines <lb/><hi rend="italic">by wholeſale</hi>. For within the
        compaſs of three <lb/>months he gave him above forty doſes of mercurial <lb/>phyſic, with
        ſundry other coſtly drenches, which <lb/>brought a conſiderable flux of humors upon the af-
        <lb/>fected part: to which he then made divers unctuous <pb n="33"/>
        <lb/>applications, till at length it became cancerous. <lb/>Laſtly he had recourſe to
        ſalivation, but with no <lb/>better ſucceſs, the patient grew ſenſibly worſe: Yet <lb/>the
        Quack to diſpel the growing doubts and ſuſpici- <lb/>ons of the poor abuſed man, called in a
          <hi rend="italic">reputed phy- <lb/>ſician</hi>, to juſtify his mal-practice, and aſſiſt
        him in <lb/>the cure. The <hi rend="italic">doctor</hi> being unable to ſatisfy the
        <lb/>unhappy ſufferer in his diſtruſt of the <hi rend="italic">quack</hi>, he call- <lb/>ed
        in better aſſiſtance, and had his life with great <lb/>difficulty ſaved, by the amputation
        of the diſtem- <lb/>pered member. Notwithſtanding all this groſs <lb/>abuſe of the miſerable
        patient, this unworthy apo- <lb/>thecary, who may be preſumed to be the principal <lb/>cauſe
        of the greateſt evil attending this cafe, makes <lb/>a moſt extravagant large bill, with a
        charge of <lb/><hi rend="italic">twenty ſhillings</hi> to his coadjutor the doctor, annexed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By theſe and ſuch like unnatural tranſgreſſions, is <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
          >apothecary</hi> led out of the way of his duty, and <lb/>bred an utter ſtranger to all
        parts of his proper <lb/>calling. By this vile craft he gets his bread, no <lb/>wonder then
        he ſhould be firmly attached to it. <lb/>This is all he learns, all he knows, all he
        practiſes, <lb/>all he teaches: And this he finds ſufficient to re- <lb/>commend him : He
        indeed generally takes care to <lb/>ſecure an intereſt in ſome <hi rend="italic">party</hi>
        or <hi rend="italic">club</hi>, whether <lb/><hi rend="italic">religious</hi> or <hi
          rend="italic">politic</hi>, no matter with how little <hi rend="italic">reaſon</hi>,
        <lb/>provided he eſpouſes and defends their principles <lb/>with a good ſtock of <hi
          rend="italic">blind zeal and violence</hi>, he is ſure <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Society's</hi> favour, ſo he may ſecurely neglect <lb/>his <hi rend="italic">true
          profeſſion</hi>. He therefore employs his whole <lb/>time in quacking or ſtroling over the
        town in queſt <lb/>of prey. For to avoid the dangerous imputation of <lb/>having nothing to
        do, <hi rend="italic">no practice</hi>, (as the phraſe is,) <lb/>he muſt never be found at
        home ; not to be ſeen <lb/>in his noiſome ſhop except by accident to preſcribe <lb/>for ſome
        ſudden emergency, or perhaps ſometimes <lb/>to edify by reading over his own <hi
          rend="italic">ill-choſen</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ſtolen re- <lb/>cipe's</hi>, there
        carefully filed more for <hi rend="italic">ſhew</hi> than <hi rend="italic">uſe</hi>:
        <lb/>That done, he muſt hurry forth, and ruſh thro' <pb n="34"/>
        <lb/>the ſtreets as if he had ſo many calls, that he cannot <lb/>tell which firſt to anſwer:
        While the principal part <lb/>of his buſineſs, furniſhing the ſhop and ſerving the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">wretched cuſtomers</hi>, is left to ſome mercenary <hi rend="italic">ſham-
          <lb/>druggiſt, a miſerable herb-gatherer, and a raw appren- <lb/>tice</hi>. The very <hi
          rend="italic">Druggiſt</hi>, who in all other nations <lb/>in <hi rend="italic"
          >Europe</hi> is but <hi rend="italic">Pharmacopola</hi>, a mere drug-mer- <lb/>chant, is
        with us, not only a <hi rend="italic">phyſician and chirurgeon</hi>, <lb/>but alſo <hi
          rend="italic">a Galenic and Chemic apothecary; a ſeller <lb/>of druggs, medicines,
          vernices, oils, paints or colours, <lb/>poyſons</hi>, &amp;c. <hi rend="italic">a Jack of
          all trades</hi>, and in truth, <hi rend="italic">ma- <lb/>ſter of none</hi> — For bad as
        the uſual education of an <lb/>apothecary may be, if it could be yet worſe, he <lb/>may make
        a good modern druggiſt enough. And <lb/>it is demonſtrable, that, among the many who
        <lb/>aſſume that name, there are not above two in <hi rend="italic">Dub- <lb/>lin</hi> that
        have any right to it. Theſe who are, if <lb/>poſſible, worſe quacks than the apothecaries,
        and <lb/>generally worſe qualified in every reſpect, were the <lb/>firſt who introduced that
        blackeſt villainy of ſophi- <lb/>ſticating, and debaſing of medicines to gain fame and
        <lb/>applauſe by underſelling their honeſt brethren; <lb/>and you ſhall now find moſt of
        them ready to make <lb/>up the preſcriptions of phyſicians and chirurgeons, <lb/>brought to
        them by the ignorant vulgar, (who alone <lb/>indeed intruſt them with ſuch,) at any rate
        they are <lb/>offered, even tho' they cannot read them, and tho' <lb/>they may be compoſed
        of ſundry medicaments to <lb/>them utterly unknown. How muſt the unhappy <lb/>patient and
        preſcriber ſuffer, whoſe preſcriptions <lb/>fall into ſuch unworthy hands? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Thus wretchedly is <hi rend="italic">pharmacy</hi> taught and practiſed <lb/>now
        a-days. How foreign to the manner of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">antient, true
          apothecaries</hi>, is, I hope, evident from the <lb/>foregoing ; and how contradictory to
        reaſon, juſtice, <lb/>and common ſenſe, is, I believe, to every rational <lb/>unprejudiced
        man, obvious. Yet, that under the pre- <lb/>ſent fatal miſmanagement, it is, and muſt
        continue ſo, <lb/>is, I think, moſt demonſtrable. Foe a man who <pb n="35"/>
        <lb/>takes the greateſt pains to learn that art, and <lb/>acquires the moſt extraordinary
        knowledge, and all <lb/>the requiſite qualifications therein, and ever ſo ſtrict- <lb/>ly,
        and diligently attends to the <hi rend="italic">regular calls</hi> of his <lb/>profeſſion,
        and diſcharges the <hi rend="italic">duty</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">proper office</hi>
        <lb/>of an <hi rend="italic">apothecary</hi>, if he does not moſt audaciouſly <lb/>and
        adventurouſly, quack in all caſes without diſ- <lb/>tinction, he is ſurely deemed but a <hi
          rend="italic">blockhead</hi>, and <lb/>may remain to the generality unknown, and ſtarve;
        <lb/>or perhaps have the comfort of being reputed, in <lb/>his narrow circle of
        acquaintance, <hi rend="italic">a good, honeſt <lb/>fellow, but no apothecary</hi>; that is
        to fay, <hi rend="italic">no quack</hi>; <lb/>and is therefore deſpiſed, becauſe, he has the
        candor <lb/>and integrity, not to intermeddle with any buſineſs, <lb/>but his own, nor to
        attempt things beyond his <lb/>ſphere. In ſhort it is not ſuch a man that is <hi
          rend="italic">with <lb/>us</hi> deemed an <hi rend="italic">apothecary</hi>, no, it is the
        moſt deſpica- <lb/>ble of all human beings, a wretch ignorant of all <lb/>arts, yet
        pretending to the greateſt; a falſe, diſ- <lb/>ſembling ſycophant, that poor, ſhallow
        mimick, or <lb/>untowardly ape of a phyſician, chirurgeon and apo- <lb/>thecary, the vile,
        deluding quack! Where then is <lb/>the encouragement to excel in this art, when the
        <lb/>moſt ignorant of it, are, by the generality, preferred, <lb/>and moſt eſteemed? </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
