<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Philanthropos: Mr. Ward's practice of physick, as it relates to the
          publick, impartially considered</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Philanthropos</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">Mr. WARD's Practice of Physick, As it Relates to the PUBLICK,
              Impartially Considered. IN A LETTER TO THOMAS CAREW, Esq; Member of Parliament. </title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">N19800</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/N19800"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for J. Roberts, at the Oxford-Arms in Warwick-Lane,
                  MDCCXLI. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1741</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="23"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">National Library of Medicine</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3308191269</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K011766.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Public welfare and institutional"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front> </front>
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_2" n="3"/>
      <head rend="align-center dc(2)"><lb/>MR. <hi rend="italic">WARD</hi>'s <lb/>Practice <hi
          rend="italic">of</hi> Phyſick <lb/><hi rend="italic">Impartially Conſidered.</hi>
      </head>
      <lb/>
      <salute>SIR, </salute>
      <dateline rend="align-right">Minehead, Dec. 14. 1740. </dateline>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(4)">T</hi>HE truly generous, noble, and <lb/>indefatigable
        Spirit you have <lb/>exerted on the Behalf of the <w part="I">Com-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >monwealth</w>, during your ſitting in <lb/>Parliament, has drawn upon you the
        <lb/>Trouble of this Application. You <lb/>have ſhewn, not only Inclination, <lb/>but
        Ability to do real Service to <lb/>your Country, by promoting and <w part="I"
          >car-</w><lb/><w part="F">rying</w> on ſeveral Bills, which will <lb/>greatly contribute
        to the publick Good, <pb xml:id="page_3" n="4"/><lb/>and tranſmit your Name with <w part="I"
          >Ho-</w><lb/><w part="F">nour</w> to Poſterity. You are a true <lb/>Patriot, in the pureſt
        Senſe of the <lb/>Word; and, as ſuch, I don't doubt, <lb/>but you will think the following
        Pages <lb/>highly worthy of your ſerious <w part="I">Con-</w><lb/><w part="F"
        >ſideration</w>; and if you find any Hint <lb/>in them fair, reaſonable, and <w part="I"
          >cal-</w><lb/><w part="F">culated</w> for the Intereſt of your <w part="I">Fel-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">low-ſubjects</w>, you will gladly improve <lb/>it, and readily concur in building
        <lb/>upon it ſuch an wholſome Law as <lb/>may redreſs the Grievance complained <lb/>of. I
        think it will be eaſily granted, <lb/>that the Health of the Body is full as <lb/>valuable
        as the Property of Eſtates. <lb/>How difficult would it be for any <w part="I"
          >Per-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſon</w> to believe, that our Legiſlature is <lb/>of that
        Opinion, who ſhould obſerve, <lb/>that there are ſo many good Laws <w part="I"
          >en-</w><lb/><w part="F">acted</w> by every Parliament for the <w part="I">De-</w><pb
          xml:id="page_4" n="5"/><lb/><w part="F">fence</w> of the one, and ſcarce ever any
        <lb/>Care taken of the Preſervation of the <lb/>other? Indeed, within a long Series <lb/>of
        Years, the Parliament has been <lb/>moſt graciouſly pleaſed to caſt an Eye <lb/>towards the
        Health of the People, by <lb/>an Act impowering Phyſicians to <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ſpect</w> Apothecaries Shops; by an Act <lb/>for preventing the Retailing
        ſpirituous <lb/>Liquors; and by an Act for the <lb/>Encouragement of the Publication of
        <lb/>Mrs. <hi rend="italic">Stephens</hi>'s Remedies. However, <lb/>theſe Inſtances, few as
        they are, prove, <lb/>that the Honourable Houſe does <lb/>not think the Health of the Nation
        <lb/>intirely below their Care and <w part="I">Conſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">deration</w>; and
        therefore we ought to <lb/>ſuppoſe, that the Reaſon why Acts of <lb/>Parliament for the like
        good Purpoſes <lb/>are not more frequent, is, that the <lb/>Houſe is not applied to on ſuch
          <w part="I">Sub-</w><pb xml:id="page_5" n="6"/><lb/><w part="F">jects</w> in a proper
        manner; that the <lb/>Grievances the People labour under <lb/>are not fairly and plainly
        laid before <lb/>the Members, or practical Methods of <lb/>Redreſs are not pointed out. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Health of a People can only <lb/>be preſerved by all the wholſome
        <lb/>Laws the Wiſdom of a Legiſlature can <lb/>contrive, to prevent Luxury, <w part="I"
          >De-</w><lb/><w part="F">bauchery</w>, and every kind of <w part="I">Immora-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">lity</w>, which infallibly produce Diſeaſes, <lb/>or by frequent Inſpections into
        the <lb/>State of Phyſick in their Country, <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">cauſe</w>
        Abuſes will daily creep into <lb/>every Society, or Set of Men, who find <lb/>themſelves
        under no Reſtraint, from <lb/>any Apprehenſions of being called to <lb/>an Account for their
        Method of <w part="I">treat-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> Mankind, in their moſt <w part="I"
          >moment-</w><lb/><w part="F">ous</w> Concernments. Tho' the firſt <pb xml:id="page_6"
          n="7"/><lb/>Part of this general Plan is highly <lb/>worth your Conſideration, yet I ſhall
        <lb/>beg Leave to ſay a few Words to you <lb/>in regard to the latter only. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Reformation of the State of <lb/>Phyſick in general is greatly
        wanting <lb/>in this Nation, and, I believe, moſt <lb/>warmly wiſhed by every honeſt Man,
        <lb/>even of the Faculty itſelf. But tho' <lb/>general Reformations may be as <w part="I"
          >dif-</w><lb/><w part="F">ficult</w> as they are deſireable, yet ſome <lb/>crying
        Enormities may themſelves <lb/>point out the Method of their own <lb/>Redreſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>If we conſider the publick <w part="I">Hu-</w><lb/><w part="F">mour</w>
        of the good People of <hi rend="italic">England</hi>
        <lb/>for theſe laſt Twenty Years, one ſhould <lb/>be apt to conclude, that certain odd
        <lb/>Conjunctions of the heavenly Bodies <pb xml:id="page_7" n="8"/><lb/>brought on
        epidemical Follies, as well <lb/>as Diſeaſes. How have <hi rend="italic">Shakeſpeare,
          <lb/>Johnſon, Otway,</hi> and all the Plays <lb/>capable of delighting the Mind, <w
          part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtructing</w> the Head, or mending the <lb/>Heart, been
        totally neglected, or <w part="I">cold-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> received, while dear <hi
          rend="italic">Harlequin!</hi>
        <lb/>charming Devil! has filled all our <lb/>Affections, triumphed over our <w part="I"
          >Judg-</w><lb/><w part="F">ments</w>, and emptied our Pockets! <lb/>During an Aera like
        this, when ſuch <lb/>crowded Audiences, compoſed of the <lb/>great Vulgar and the ſmall,
        gave <lb/>ſuch plain Demonſtrations of their <lb/>polite Taſte, and profound Wiſdom, <lb/>is
        it to be wonder'd, that there ſhould <lb/>appear, from the malign Influences <lb/>of the
        ſame Stars, Marks of an <w part="I">epi-</w><lb/><w part="F">demical</w> Madneſs in other
        Parts of the <lb/>Town, as well as in the Theatre? <lb/>No; Dr. <hi rend="italic"
          >Fauſtus</hi> will have the <w part="I">Ho-</w><pb xml:id="page_8" n="9"/><lb/><w part="F"
          >nour</w> to be handed down to Poſterity <lb/>as the illuſtrious Contemporary of a
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Mapp,</hi> a <hi rend="italic">Taylor,</hi> and a <hi rend="italic"
          >Ward.</hi> The <lb/>Hiſtorian of our Days will be able to <lb/>inform his Readers, that
        the <w part="I">Infatu-</w><lb/><w part="F">ation</w> was ſo general, that <hi rend="italic"
          >Freind, Mead,</hi>
        <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">Pellet,</hi> were as much eclipſed by <lb/>this bright
        Conſtellation, as <hi rend="italic">Shake-<lb/>ſpeare</hi> then was by a more happy
        <lb/>Genius; a Gentleman, who, with <lb/>ſurprizing Activity, could turn <w part="I"
          >him-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſelf</w> into all Shapes, and appear to be <lb/>any Animal but
        what he really was. <lb/>Such are the irreſiſtible Charms of <lb/>Deluſion! Such the
        Happineſs of <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> deceived, that all our Applauſes
        <lb/>riſe in Proportion to the Artfulneſs <lb/>of the Impoſition, and the Difficulty <lb/>of
        diſcovering the Cheat! </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_9" n="10"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Let Mrs. <hi rend="italic">Mapp</hi>'s Bones reſt in <lb/>Peace, tho'
        ſhe tortur'd ſo many in <lb/>the Days of her Fame. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Let the dexterous Dr. <hi rend="italic">Taylor</hi> be <lb/>able to
        purge the viſual Ray of our <lb/>neighbour Nations, that they may ſee <lb/>their true
        Intereſt to conſiſt in <w part="I">treat-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>
        <hi rend="italic">Great-Britain</hi> with Honour and <lb/>Reſpect. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Ward</hi> is the only medicinal <lb/>Meteor which
        yet continues to ſhine <lb/>amongſt us, whoſe Fame has raiſed <lb/>him to the higheſt Degree
        of Eſteem <lb/>and Admiration with the <hi rend="italic">Gay</hi> and <lb/>the <hi
          rend="italic">Polite,</hi> on whoſe Authority and <lb/>Judgment Thouſands, and Tens of
        <lb/>Thouſands, of the lower Part of <w part="I">Man-</w><lb/><w part="F">kind</w>, ſwallow
        his Medicines with <w part="I">im-</w><lb/><w part="F">plicit</w> Faith, and are ſaid
        thereby to <pb xml:id="page_10" n="11"/><lb/>receive moſt wonderful Cures, in <w part="I"
          >al-</w><lb/><w part="F">moſt</w> incurable Diſtempers. The <w part="I">In-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">fluence</w> of this Gentleman's <w part="I">Reputa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>
        being now become ſo very <w part="I">exten-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſive</w>, his Manner of
        practiſing Phyſick <lb/>cannot be thought a Subject <w part="I">unwor-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >thy</w> the Notice and Conſideration of <lb/>the Legiſlature. I am ſure, Sir, you
        <lb/>will afford it your Attention, for a <lb/>few Minutes, as it is of Importance <lb/>to
        the Service of the Publick, to which <lb/>I well know how much every <w part="I"
          >Mo-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w> of your Time is dedicated. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>I ſhall by no means take upon me <lb/>to determine, whether the
        numberleſs <lb/>Deaths laid to this Gentleman's Charge <lb/>by his Oppoſers, or the
        unparallel'd <lb/>Cures he is ſaid to have performed by <lb/>his Admirers, come neareſt the
        Truth. <lb/>What he owns himſelf, and what all <pb xml:id="page_11" n="12"/><lb/>his Friends
        allow, may, I hope, be <lb/>taken for granted. He confeſſes, with <lb/>great Candour, that
        he is wholly <w part="I">ig-</w><lb/><w part="F">norant</w> of the Hiſtory and Nature of
        <lb/>Diſeaſes; that he underſtands nothing <lb/>of Anatomy, or the animal <w part="I"
          >Oecono-</w><lb/><w part="F">my</w>; and that he only pretends to <lb/>ſome Knowledge in
        Chymiſtry, by <lb/>which Art he has diſcovered a few <lb/>Medicines, of greater Efficacy in
          <w part="I">parti-</w><lb/><w part="F">cular</w> Caſes, than thoſe in common Uſe
        <lb/>among regular Phyſicians. Suppoſe <lb/>then, that what this Gentleman aſſerts <lb/>is
        true, and that he has ſuch powerful <lb/>chymical Secrets in his Poſſeſſion; <lb/>muſt they
        not be capable of doing <lb/>as much Harm, when ignorantly and <lb/>promiſcuouſly
        adminiſtered, as they <lb/>would be of doing Good in the Hands <lb/>of a Perſon duly
        qualified to know in <lb/>what Caſes, how, and when, properly <pb xml:id="page_12" n="13"
        /><lb/>to apply them? Will that noble <w part="I">chri-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtian</w>
        Charity, which from this <w part="I">Gentle-</w><lb/><w part="F">man's</w>
        <hi rend="italic">known moral Character</hi> cannot <lb/>but be believed to be the ſole
        Motive <lb/>of his great Bounty to the Crowds of <lb/>poor People who daily attend him,
        <lb/>make amends for his dealing out theſe <lb/>powerful Medicines ſo <w part="I"
          >indiſcriminate-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> to all who ſhall pay him the <w part="I"
          >Com-</w><lb/><w part="F">pliment</w> of being willing to ſwallow <lb/>them? Do the
        Multitude of Patients <lb/>whom he never ſaw before, or will <lb/>ſee afterwards, want no
        Attendance <lb/>during the violent Operation of their <lb/>Phyſick? No Perſon acquainted
        with <lb/>the Nature of their Medicines, to <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">lieve</w> or
        correct any Accidents, which <lb/>ſo often attend the moſt common and <lb/>gentle Remedies?
        Surely it muſt <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">pear</w>, to every unprejudiced Perſon,
        <lb/>that the moſt uſeful Drugs, under <pb xml:id="page_13" n="14"/><lb/>ſuch Management,
        muſt be a ſore <lb/>Evil, and therefore that nothing can <lb/>be more uncharitable, than
        thus to <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceive</w> and hurt a Multitude under the
        <lb/>ſpecious Pretence of Charity? But <lb/>however faulty this Gentleman's <w part="I"
          >Me-</w><lb/><w part="F">thod</w> of Practice may be, yet his <w part="I">Me-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">dicines</w> may in themſelves, and under <lb/>proper Direction, be extremely
        valuable. <lb/>Let us grant, that they are ſo; Is it <lb/>not then incumbent on thoſe who
        <lb/>have the Good of the People at Heart, <lb/>to endeavour to render theſe valuable
        <lb/>Secrets a publick Benefit, which, <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F">der</w> their
        preſent Circumſtances, are <lb/>ſo great a Calamity? Every Man <lb/>ought to be rewarded for
        his Diſcovery <lb/>of any thing that may be beneficial <lb/>to Society. Mr. <hi
          rend="italic">Ward</hi> ſhould not <lb/>be deſired to part with his Property <lb/>(and his
        Noſtrums are undoubtedly <pb xml:id="page_14" n="15"/><lb/>ſuch) without a reaſonable
        Equivalent. <lb/>The Parliament of <hi rend="italic">Great-Britain</hi> is <lb/>able to
        grant him this Equivalent, and <lb/>they have a <hi rend="italic">Right</hi> to <hi
          rend="italic">demand</hi> the <lb/>Knowledge of his Secrets on juſt and <lb/>equitable
        Terms. An <hi rend="italic">Engliſhman,</hi>
        <lb/>who poſſeſſes a Piece of Ground which <lb/>interrupts the making a River <w part="I"
          >navi-</w><lb/><w part="F">gable</w>, is <hi rend="italic">obliged</hi> to part with his
          <w part="I">Pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">perty</w> for the Good of the <w part="I"
          >Commu-</w><lb/><w part="F">nity</w>: Surely Mr. <hi rend="italic">Ward</hi>'s Property in
        <lb/>his Secrets is not more inviolable, than <lb/>what every Man has in his own Land;
        <lb/>and therefore it cannot be looked <lb/>upon as any Hardſhip, if he ſhould <lb/>be
        forced to part with them on like <lb/>Conditions. Should ſuch a Demand <lb/>be made upon him
        by Parliament; <lb/>ſhould the Reward appointed be ob-<lb/>tainable only by the Proof,
        before <lb/>competent Judges, of his Medicines, <pb xml:id="page_15" n="16"/><lb/>when
        divulged, performing the ſame <lb/>Cures on fair Subjects, which they <lb/>are now ſaid to
        do on his private <w part="I">Pa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tients</w>; and ſhould he refuſe to
        ſtand <lb/>that only Teſt, what could be <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">cluded</w>
        from ſuch a Refuſal, but that <lb/>he did not believe in his own <w part="I">Con-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ſcience</w>, that they would perform <lb/>what he and his Friends do now <w
          part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſuade</w> the World to believe that they <lb/>will do?
        Would not ſuch a Refuſal <lb/>be a juſt and equitable Ground for <lb/>the Parliament to
        forbid his farther <lb/>dealing out theſe Medicines, (of which <lb/>they would have Reaſon
        to believe <lb/>that he had himſelf no Opinion) and <lb/>by a wholſome Law, to prevent his
        <lb/>Majeſty's Subjects from being any <lb/>longer cheated of their Money, if not
        <lb/>robb'd of their Lives. But as this <lb/>Gentleman's great Cures are ſo well<pb
          xml:id="page_16" n="17"/><lb/>atteſted by many Perſons of Faſhion, <lb/>whoſe Knowledge in
        ſuch Matters <lb/>cannot be diſputed, I have no Reaſon <lb/>to fear, that he would at all
        ſuſpect <lb/>the Efficacy of his Medicines, in all <lb/>the deſperate Caſes, which he now ſo
        <lb/>confidently undertakes. He will <w part="I">there-</w><lb/><w part="F">fore</w>
        undoubtedly ſubmit them to an <lb/>impartial Trial with the greateſt <lb/>Chearfulneſs,
        eſpecially as he will, <lb/>over and above the Reward appointed <lb/>by Parliament, be ſure
        of gratifying <lb/>his moſt charitable Diſpoſition in the <lb/>Satisfaction of knowing,
        that, whereas <lb/>before only ſome Thouſands of his <lb/>Countrymen enjoyed the Fruits of
        his <lb/>Labours, then he will become a <w part="I">ge-</w><lb/><w part="F">neral</w> Good
        to Mankind. The <w part="I">ho-</w><lb/><w part="F">nourable</w> Gentlemen who now talk of
        <lb/>his Medicines as divine, and of his <lb/>Cures as little leſs than miraculous, <pb
          xml:id="page_17" n="18"/><lb/>will all moſt heartily join in promoting <lb/>this
        Publication; they will <w part="I">congratu-</w><lb/><w part="F">late</w> their Country on
        the ineſtimable <lb/>Poſſeſſion of theſe Secrets, which, but <lb/>for the Care of our
        Legiſlature, might <lb/>have ſlept in the ſingle Breaſt of their <lb/>Author, and have been
        buried with <lb/>him in Oblivion, to the irreparable <lb/>Loſs of all future Ages! </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>As the Number of Inhabitants is <lb/>the Riches of a Nation, while ſo
        <lb/>many brave Men are loſing their Lives <lb/>abroad in the Service of their <w part="I"
          >Coun-</w><lb/><w part="F">try</w>, let us not ſuffer thoſe who remain <lb/>at home to be
        daily thinned, either <lb/>by the improper Application of Mr. <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Ward</hi>'s Medicines, under his preſent <lb/>Adminiſtration of them, or for want <lb/>of
        their being made more univerſally <lb/>uſeful by a ſpeedy Publication. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_18" n="19"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Gin Act is a glorious Inſtance <lb/>of the tender Care of our
        Parliament <lb/>for the Lives and Healths of our <w part="I">Peo-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ple</w>, to whom that pernicious Liquor<lb/> was promiſcuouſly, and ſometimes <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">charitably,</hi> retailed, by ſuch who <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ferred</w> their own wicked Gains to the <lb/>Welfare of all human Creatures. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Mrs. <hi rend="italic">Stephens</hi>'s Act is a plain Proof <lb/>of the
        true Senſe your honourable <lb/>Houſe has of the great Benefit of <lb/>making any uſeful
        Diſcoveries in <w part="I">Phy-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſick</w>; and it is likewiſe a proper <w
          part="I">Pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">cedent</w> of the Manner in which ſuch <lb/>Publications
        ſhould be made, and of <lb/>the Teſts and Trials ſuch diſcovered <lb/>Medicines muſt undergo
        in order to <lb/>entitle their Authors to their due <w part="I">Re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ward</w>. What may be a reaſonable Sa-<lb/>tisfaction for Mr. <hi rend="italic"
        >Ward</hi>'s doing this <pb xml:id="page_19" n="20"/><lb/>ſignal Service to his Country, I
        cannot <lb/>gueſs at. If his Medicines will <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F">form</w>
        the Cures openly and fairly, which <lb/>are now attributed to them, I think the
        <lb/>Parliament cannot pay too much for <lb/>the Knowledge of them, or Mr. <hi rend="italic"
          >Ward</hi>
        <lb/>receive too great Honours from a <lb/>grateful People. But ſhould this <w part="I"
          >Gen-</w><lb/><w part="F">tleman</w> be ſo blind to his own Intereſt <lb/>as to refuſe to
        become this publick <lb/>Bleſſing, on any Terms, can he expect <lb/>to enjoy the warm
        Affections of his <lb/>Countrymen, to whom he will appear <lb/>ſo charitable, and ſo
        hard-hearted, at <lb/>the ſame time? Should he refuſe to <lb/>comply with the generous
        Deſire of <lb/>the Parliament, could he complain that <lb/>they ſhould exert their juſt
        Authority? <lb/>If he refuſes to ſave Millions, he can-<lb/>not ſurely think himſelf
        ill-treated by <lb/>the Guardians of the Publick, if it <pb xml:id="page_20" n="21"
        /><lb/>ſhould be forbid to deſtroy even his <lb/>Thouſands! </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>But to You, Sir, I humbly ſubmit <lb/>the Conſideration of this <hi
          rend="italic">important</hi>
        <lb/>Point; I call it <hi rend="italic">important;</hi> and what <lb/>concerns the Lives of
        ſo many of the <lb/>Innocent, and the Ignorant, deſerves to<lb/> be ſo called. I ſpeak as a
        Friend to <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Ward,</hi> as well as to my Country. <lb/>I propoſe a
        Method, by which, inſtead <lb/>of being the Idol of a Few, he ſhall <lb/>become the Darling
        of a whole People! <lb/>by which he ſhall remove that huge <lb/>Load of Scandal, which now
        lies upon <lb/>him, to the great Chagrin of his <lb/>Enemies, who ſhall pine with Envy
        <lb/>at the Brightneſs of his Glory. The <lb/>black Liſt of his private Murders, <lb/>which
        is now maliciouſly handed about <lb/>by Phyſicians, and their Emiſſaries, <pb
          xml:id="page_21" n="22"/><lb/>ſhall whiten into a pompous Regiſter <lb/>of publick Cures,
        performed by his <lb/>Medicines, on the miſerable Objects, <lb/>who had been delivered over
        to the <lb/>iron Jaws of Death, by the Ignorance <lb/>or Indolence of thoſe Doctors, falſely
        <lb/>ſo called, who have had no <w part="I">Oppor-</w><lb/><w part="F">tunity</w> of
        underſtanding Phyſick, but <lb/>their having been bred to the <w part="I">Profeſ-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ſion</w>. By this means this worthy <w part="I">Gen-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >tleman</w> ſhall be freed from that <w part="I">La-</w><lb/><w part="F">bour</w> and Toil
        with which he now <lb/>ſerves his Country in his private <w part="I">Ca-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >pacity</w>. He ſhall do even more Good, <lb/>and yet, as is moſt meet and fit, he
        <lb/>ſhall be able to retire from the World, <lb/>full of Days and Honours; he ſhall
        <lb/>ſpend the few laſt Years he has to come <lb/>in Dignity and Eaſe, enjoying the calm
        <lb/>Evening of a well-ſpent Life, converſing <lb/>with Nature in the moſt endearing <w
          part="I">Inti-</w><pb xml:id="page_22" n="23"/><lb/><w part="F">macy</w>, to which he has
        arrived by <w part="I">tor-</w><lb/><w part="F">turing</w> her ten thouſand Ways, till he
        <lb/>made her confeſs thoſe very Secrets, <lb/>which he has now communicated for <lb/>the
        publick Good, and which ſhall <lb/>draw down Bleſſings on him, and his <lb/>Poſterity,
        through all future Ages. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>I beg therefore, Sir, for my Sake, <lb/>as your Fellow-Citizen; for Mr.
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ward</hi>'s Sake, who can do us all ſo <lb/>much Service; and for
        your Country's <lb/>Sake, whoſe Intereſt you have ſo <w part="I">ſin-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >cerely</w> and warmly at Heart, that you <lb/>will think ſeriouſly on this Matter.
        <lb/>What you ſee to be right, I know you <lb/>will vigorouſly purſue; and to your <lb/>good
        Conduct the Whole is ſubmitted, <lb/>by, Sir, </p>
      <signed rend="indent hanging"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Your moſt obedient <lb/>humble
          Servant,</hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Philanthropos</hi>. </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
