<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Royal College of Surgeons of England: The case of the surgeons of
          London</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Royal College of Surgeons of England</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">THE CASE OF THE SURGEONS of London.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T204294</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T204294"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName/>
              </publisher>
              <date>1745</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">2⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="3"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">Bodleian Library, Oxford</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3310323322</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K127472.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Public welfare and institutional"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_1"/>
      <head rend="align-center"><lb/>THE <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">CASE</hi>
        <lb/>OF THE <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">SURGEONS <hi rend="italic">of</hi> London.
        </hi></head>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> 1 Edw. IV. 1461. </note><hi
          rend="dc(3)">T</hi>HE Barbers of the City of <hi rend="italic">London</hi> were
        incorporated by King <lb/><hi rend="italic">Edward</hi> the IVth, in order to promote and
        improve the Science <lb/>and Faculty of Surgery, upon Conſideration of the many <w part="I"
          >pub-</w><lb/><w part="F">lick</w> Miſchiefs which had ariſen from the Ignorance and <w
          part="I">Unſkil-</w><lb/><w part="F">fulness</w> of Perſons practiſing that Art. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>To remedy ſuch Evils for the Time to come, which the Charter recites
        <lb/>to have been owing to the Want of a proper Overſight, Correction, and <lb/>Puniſhment
        of ſuch as were not ſufficiently skilled in the Faculty of <w part="I">Sur-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">gery</w>, the Myſtery and Commonalty of Barbers were created a Body <w part="I"
          >Cor-</w><lb/><w part="F">porate</w>, with Power to make proper Statutes and Ordinances
        for their <lb/>good Government. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>And the Maſters and Governors of that Company were to have the
        <lb/>Overſight, Correction, and Government of all Perſons uſing the Myſtery <lb/>of
        Surgeons, within the City of <hi rend="italic">London,</hi> and Suburbs thereof; and the
        <lb/>Puniſhment of them, for their Offences, in improperly exerciſing and <lb/>practiſing
        their Art; and likewiſe the Overſight and Inſpection of all <lb/>Inſtruments, Plaiſters, and
        other Medicines, by them uſed. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>And, in order to attain the End of their Inſtitution, no Perſons <w
          part="I">what-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſoever</w> were to be admitted or received into their
        Company, except <w part="I">Per-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſons</w> ſufficiently skilled and
        inſtructed in the Art of Surgery. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>This Charter was afterwards confirmed by King <hi rend="italic"
          >Henry</hi> the VIIth, in the <lb/>15th Year of his Reign, and by King <hi rend="italic"
          >Henry</hi> the VIIIth, in the 2d <lb/>Year of his Reign. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>In the 32d Year of <hi rend="italic">Henry</hi> the VIIIth, when Perſons
        of better <w part="I">Educa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, and greater Abilities, began to
        apply themſelves to the Study and <lb/>Practice of Surgery, the Legiſlature thought proper
        to unite this <w part="I">Com-</w><lb/><w part="F">pany</w>, which were ſtill all Surgeons,
        and, by the Terms of their Charter, <lb/>could be compoſed of no other Perſons, with another
        Body of Men, <lb/>likewiſe practiſing Surgery, but not incorporated. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_2" n="2"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Act recites, That there then were, within the City of <hi
          rend="italic">London,</hi> Two <lb/>ſeveral and diſtinct Companies of Surgeons, occupying
        and exerciſing <lb/>the Science and Faculty of Surgery; the one Company called <hi
          rend="italic">The <w part="I">Bar-</w><lb/><w part="F">bers</w> of</hi> London, the other
        called <hi rend="italic">The Surgeons of</hi> London. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>And the End propoſed by the Legiſlature in uniting theſe Two diſtinct
        <lb/>Companies of Surgeons, and making them One Body Corporate, is <w part="I"
          >de-</w><lb/><w part="F">clared</w> to be, That, by their Union and frequent Aſſembly
        together, the <lb/>good and due Order, Exerciſe, and Knowledge in the Science and <w
          part="I">Fa-</w><lb/><w part="F">culty</w> of Surgery, ſhould be, as well in Speculation
        as in Practice, obtained, <lb/>both to themſelves and their Apprentices. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Legiſlature then thought proper likewiſe to Enact, for particular
        <lb/>Reaſons mentioned in the Act, That, for the future, the ſame Perſons <lb/>ſhould not
        practiſe both as Surgeons and Barbers, but that, from <w part="I">thence-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">forth</w>, they ſhould be ſeparated Profeſſions. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Surgeons having, ſince the Making of that Act, been more <w part="I"
          >libe-</w><lb/><w part="F">rally</w> and regularly educated, have directed and applied
        their whole <lb/>Study and Attention towards the Advancement and Improvement of <lb/>their
        Art. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Barbers have ever ſince been engaged in a different Way of
        <lb/>Buſineſs, altogether foreign to the Practice of Surgery. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is evident therefore, that neither the Ends, which the Crown had
        <lb/>in view at the original Incorporation of this Company, or thoſe which <lb/>were
        afterwards propoſed to be attained by the Legiſlature, can be <w part="I">an-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ſwered</w> by their continuing united in the ſame Body. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>As the ſole End of their Incorporation was, that they ſhould overſee
        <lb/>and ſuperintend the Practice of Surgery; and as the Legiſlature <w part="I"
          >pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſed</w>, that, by their Meeting and Aſſembly together, the
        Science of <lb/>Surgery ſhould be promoted, as well in Speculation as in Practice; it is
        <lb/>plain, that their whole Union and Meeting with the Barbers, if it were <lb/>no
        Obſtacle, cannot in the leaſt be any Ways conducive towards <w part="I">attain-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ing</w> thoſe Ends. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>But, if the Surgeons were incorporated, as a diſtinct Body, by <w
          part="I">them-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſelves</w>, they would not then be deprived of the Help
        and Aſſiſtance of <lb/>many ingenious Practiſers of their Profeſſion, who, at preſent,
        decline <lb/>being Members of a Company, the Majority of which, being Strangers <lb/>to
        their Art, cannot be ſuppoſed to have in their Views the <w part="I">Advance-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ment</w> and Improvement of it. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Majority of Perſons practiſing Surgery, would not then be <w
          part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">couraged</w> and prevented, as they now are, from being
        Members of the <lb/>Company, by the Inconveniencies and Expences which neceſſarily attend
        <lb/>the Execution of the ſeveral Offices of the preſent Company, which have <lb/>no
        Relation to the Improvement and Profeſſion of Surgery; by which <pb xml:id="page_3" n="3"
        /><lb/>Means, thoſe who practiſe Surgery are again divided, contrary to the <lb/>Intention
        of the Legiſlature: The Number of theſe, at preſent, who are <lb/>not Members of the
        Company, being almoſt double the Number of <lb/>thoſe who are. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Publick Lectures, Examinations of Surgeons, and other <w part="I"
          >Aſſem-</w><lb/><w part="F">blies</w>, inſtituted for the Advancement of Surgery, would
        not then meet <lb/>with any Interruption from Perſons, only Barbers, inſiſting, as they now
        <lb/>do, that they ſhall always be preſent at ſuch Meetings. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Since therefore, there are diſtinct and peculiar Privileges and Powers
        <lb/>lodged with the Surgeons, which the Barbers ought neither to take Part <lb/>or Trouble
        in; particularly that important Truſt, of examining Surgeons <lb/>for the Royal Navy, which
        they have duly executed with the greateſt <lb/>Chearfulneſs, to the great Advantage, as they
        hope, of the Publick: </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>And, as the deſired Separation is founded upon Reaſons of general
        <lb/>and publick Utility; </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Surgeons of <hi rend="italic">London</hi> humbly pray, To be
        ſeparated from the <lb/>Barbers, as thoſe of other Countries have been, each to be made an
          <w part="I">inde-</w><lb/><w part="F">pendent</w> Corporation, and veſted with the ſame
        Privileges which they <lb/>now enjoy under their preſent Charters. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>And, as all the Members of the preſent Company have an equal
        <lb/>Intereſt in the Property belonging to the ſaid Company; and the original <lb/>Members,
        who firſt acquired that Property, could only be Perſons ſkilled <lb/>in Surgery (thoſe,
        practiſing as Barbers only, not having been Members <lb/>of this Company till the Reign of
        King <hi rend="italic">Henry</hi> the VIIIth); they hope, <lb/>That an equitable and
        proportionable Diviſion and Diſtribution of their <lb/>Property ſhall be made, in ſuch
        Manner as the Legiſlature ſhall think fit. </p>

    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_4"/>
        <p rend="align-center"><lb/>THE <lb/><hi rend="size(1.7)">CASE</hi>
          <lb/>OF THE <lb/><hi rend="sc">Surgeons </hi>of <hi rend="italic">London.</hi>
        </p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
