<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus: Pringle: Observations on the Diseases of the Army </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>John Pringle</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">Observations on the diseases of the army, in camp and garrison. In
              three parts. With and appendix, containing some Papers of Experiments, read at several
              Meetings of the Royal Society. </title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T55665</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T55665"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for A. Millar, and D. Wilson, both in the Strand; and T.
                  Payne, next the Mews-Gate, near St. Martin's Church, MDCCLII.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1752</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="21"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="431"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="66"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW107180721</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Public welfare and institutional"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="21"/>
    <body>
      <pb n="1"/>
      <div type="part">
        <figure rend="space">
          <figDesc>A horizontal double-line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="align-center space size(0.75)">
          <lb/><hi rend="size(2.0)">OBSERVATIONS </hi>
          <lb/>On the <hi rend="sc">Diseases</hi> of the <hi rend="sc">Army</hi> in <lb/><hi
            rend="size(1.5)">CAMP and GARRISON. </hi>
        </head>
        <figure rend="space">
          <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>PART I. </head>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <div type="chapter">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>CHAP. I. </head>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>Of the <hi rend="sc">Air</hi> and <hi rend="sc">Endemic Diseases</hi> of the
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Low Countries</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(4)">T</hi>HE river Lis, riſing in Artois, and <lb/>joining the Scheld,
            at Ghent, divides <lb/>the high and dry part of Flanders <lb/>from the low and wet.
            Between <lb/>this line and the ſea the country is flat, mar- <lb/>ſhy and unhealthful,
            including Dutch Flan- <lb/>ders, with ſome barrier towns belonging to <lb/>the States,
            the French, and Auſtrians: of all <lb/>which, Furnes and Sluys are the moſt ſickly.
            <lb/>But the remaining part of Flanders is higher, <pb n="2"/>
            <lb/>and, with the reſt of the Auſtrian Netherlands, <lb/>is altogether a dry and
            healthful country. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Great part of the United Provinces is like- <lb/>wiſe low and wet, and ſubject to
            the ſame <lb/>diſtempers with Flanders: and Dutch Bra- <lb/>bant being alſo marſhy, from
            Graaf down- <lb/>wards along the Maes, and every where in- <lb/>commoded with water near
            the ſurface, is <lb/>ſubject to the ſame aquatic diſeaſes. But above <lb/>all, Zealand
            ſhares the worſt air; as being <lb/>not only low and watery, but ſurrounded with
            <lb/>the oozy and ſlimy beaches of the eaſtern and <lb/>weſtern Scheld, and the moſt
            marſhy parts of <lb/>the country: ſo that almoſt every wind, ex- <lb/>cept from the
            ocean, muſt add to its native <lb/>moiſt and unwholeſome exhalations. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>All this tract of the Netherlands being <lb/>little higher than the level of the
            ſea, or the <lb/>rivers that paſs through it, was once ſo much <lb/>expoſed to
            inundations from floods and high <lb/>tides, that till dykes and drains were made,
            <lb/>it was no better than a large moraſs; and even <lb/>now, after incredible labour,
            the country is <lb/>ſtill ſubject to be overflowed by extraordinary <lb/>floods, and
            other caſual inlets of water. By <pb n="3"/>
            <lb/>the evaporation of this, as likewiſe of the ca- <lb/>nals and ditches, in all which
            innumerable <lb/>plants and inſects lie and rot, the atmoſphere <lb/>is filled, during
            the latter part of ſummer and <lb/>autumn, with moiſt, putrid and inſalutary
            <lb/>vapours. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>A ſecond, but leſs obvious ſource of hu- <lb/>midity, is from the water under
            ground; <lb/>which is every where ſo near the ſurface, that a <lb/>conſtantly dry ditch,
            the ſure mark of a health- <lb/>ful ſituation, is never ſeen, except in the higher
            <lb/>lands. Now, as the ſoil is light, the moiſture <lb/>eaſily tranſpires, and in
            ſummer loads the air <lb/>with vapour, even where no water is viſible. <lb/>This is the
            condition of moſt of Dutch <lb/>Brabant; the inhabitants of which are leſs <lb/>liable
            to intermittents, in proportion to the <lb/>depth of this ſubterraneous water; ſo that
            <lb/>by looking into their wells, it is eaſy to de- <lb/>termine the comparative health
            of each <lb/>village. Theſe wells being fed by the <lb/>under-ground water, and ſinking
            proportion- <lb/>ally to the droughts of ſummer, are at once <lb/>a proof and meaſure of
            the conſtant exhala- <lb/>tion of this water by the ſun. </p>
          <pb n="4"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In Zealand, and upon the oppoſite coaſt of <lb/>Flanders and Brabant, is obſerved a
            peculiar <lb/>kind of putrid damp, which riſes at low wa- <lb/>ter from a beach covered
            with ſlime and mud, <lb/>more liable to corruption on account of the <lb/>mixture of
            freſh and ſalt-water <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>* Vid. LANCIS. <hi rend="italic">de Nox. Palud. Effluv. lib.</hi> i. p. i. c.
                v. </p>
            </note>. But upon <lb/>an open and ſandy coaſt, as at Oſtend, the <lb/>country is
            refreſhed with wholeſome winds <lb/>from the ſea; while at the ſame time there is
            <lb/>reaſon to believe the exhalations from thence <lb/>are conſiderably leſs than thoſe
            of marſhy <lb/>grounds <note place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>† <hi rend="italic">Hiſt. de l'Acad. R. des Sc.</hi> A. 1741. p. 27. </p>
            </note>, and never putrid. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>But another, and more general cauſe of the <lb/>humidity and corruption of the
            atmoſphere, <lb/>is from an imperfect ventilation. There are <lb/>no hills to receive
            the winds, or to direct them <lb/>in ſtreams upon the lower grounds; hence the <lb/>air
            is ſo apt to ſtagnate; and the more by reaſon of <lb/>large plantations made for
            pleaſure, incloſures, <lb/>or fuel. The farms and ſmaller villages are <lb/>crowded with
            trees, which not only confine <lb/>but moiſten the air, by tranſpiration. But in
            <lb/>towns, where there is leſs of this kind of moi- <pb n="5"/>
            <lb/>ſture, where the houſes and pavements of the <lb/>ſtreets in a great meaſure
            prevent the riſing <lb/>of the damps, and where there are continual <lb/>fires, the
            aquatic diſeaſes are both fewer and <lb/>milder. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>To theſe cauſes of endemics, in flat and <lb/>marſhy countries muſt be added, the
            impurity <lb/>of the common water, which being here <lb/>either collected from rains,
            and preſerved <lb/>in ciſterns, or drawn from wells extremely <lb/>ſhallow, is, in hot
            and dry ſeaſons, ſoon <lb/>corrupted. This being the caſe, the gene- <lb/>ral tendency
            to putrefaction is aggravated by <lb/>the uſe of ſuch water; as well as by meats,
            <lb/>which in a cloſe, hot, and moiſt air, are <lb/>quickly tainted. Everything,
            therefore, con- <lb/>ſpires in ſummer, not only to relax the ſolids, <lb/>but to diſpoſe
            the humours to putrefaction: <lb/>and as the combination of heat and moiſture <lb/>is
            the univerſal cauſe of a ſpeedy corruption <lb/>of all animal ſubſtances, ſo it is
            obſerved, in <lb/>every country, to produce fevers, and other <lb/>diſtempers of a
            putrid kind; exactly the ſame, <lb/>or ſimilar to what occur in the low and mar-
            <lb/>ſhy parts of the Netherlands. </p>
          <pb n="6"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>This is the nature of the climate: but <lb/>according to the various degrees of
            heat, and <lb/>moiſture of the ſeaſon, the epidemics will be- <lb/>gin earlier or later,
            be of longer or ſhorter <lb/>duration, and will be attended with milder <lb/>or more
            alarming ſymptoms. If the heats <lb/>begin ſoon, and continue throughout autumn,
            <lb/>not moderated with winds and rains, the ſea- <lb/>ſon proves extremely ſickly, the
            diſtempers <lb/>appear ſoon, and are dangerous: but if the <lb/>ſummer heats begin late,
            or are tempered with <lb/>frequent ſhowers and winds, or if the autum- <lb/>nal colds
            begin early, then are the diſeaſes <lb/>both late and few, the ſymptoms gentle, and
            <lb/>the cure eaſy <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>* All this is agreeable to a regiſter of the weather and diſ- <lb/>eaſes kept
                for ſeveral years, by Dr. Stocke, phyſician at <lb/>Middelburg. </p>
            </note>. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>And here it will be proper to obſerve, that <lb/>moiſt and rainy ſeaſons differ
            greatly; ſince in <lb/>marſhy countries, intenſe and continued heats <lb/>occaſion a
            moiſture in the atmoſphere, by the <lb/>immenſe exhalation they raiſe; whereas fre-
            <lb/>quent ſhowers during the hot ſeaſon, cool <lb/>the air, check the exceſs of vapour,
            dilute and <lb/>refreſh the corrupted ſtagnating water, and <lb/>precipitate all putrid
            and noxious <hi rend="italic">Effluvia</hi>. <pb n="7"/>
            <lb/>But if heavy rains in the beginning of ſum- <lb/>mer are ſucceeded by great and
            uninterrupted <lb/>heats, theſe rains, by overflowing the mea- <lb/>dows, ſerve only for
            matter of more exhala- <lb/>tion, make the ſeaſon more ſickly, and the <lb/>diſtempers
            more fatal. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Again, it is to be remarked, that the ſick- <lb/>neſs never begins till the heats
            have continued <lb/>ſo long as to give time for the putrefaction <lb/>and evaporation of
            the water. The com- <lb/>mencement, therefore, of the epidemics may <lb/>be dated from
            ſome time in July, or the be- <lb/>ginning of Auguſt, under the canicular heats;
            <lb/>their ſenſible decline about the firſt falling of <lb/>the leaf, and end when the
            froſts begin. For <lb/>the reſt of the year, it is ſafe, and not pecu- <lb/>liarly leſs
            diſpoſed to produce any diſtemper. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It is farther to be obſerved, that tho' in <lb/>the month of September the greateſt
            ardour <lb/>of the ſeaſon is gone, yet the epidemics con- <lb/>tinue, by reaſon of the
            difference of the de- <lb/>gree of heat between the days and nights. <lb/>The days are
            ſtill warm, but the nights <lb/>are cold and often foggy; and it is by <lb/>theſe ſudden
            tranſitions that the perſpira- <lb/>tion is ſtopped, and the more putreſcent <pb n="8"/>
            <lb/>parts of the blood retained, or thrown in the <lb/>form of a putrid and acrid bile
            upon the <lb/>bowels. It muſt alſo be remarked, that the <lb/>ſummers are hotter, and
            the weather more <lb/>conſtant, on the continent, than in the ſame <lb/>latitude in
            Britain: and laſtly, that in the <lb/>Netherlands the heats are more cloſe and
            <lb/>ſtifling, than they are uſually felt in hilly <lb/>countries. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The epidemic of the hot ſeaſon, and great <lb/>endemic of this and other marſhy
            countries, <lb/>is a fever of an intermitting nature, commonly <lb/>of a tertian ſhape,
            but of a bad kind; which, <lb/>in the damper places and worſt ſeaſons, appears <lb/>in
            the form of a double tertian, remittent, con- <lb/>tinued putrid, or even an ardent
            fever <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>* An ardent fever is defined Part III. Ch. iv. § 2. </p>
            </note>. All <lb/>which, however varying in type in different <lb/>conſtitutions and
            other circumſtances, are ne- <lb/>vertheleſs of the ſame nature, and proceed from
            <lb/>like cauſes: as a proof, both the continued and <lb/>ardent fever of that ſeaſon,
            uſually terminate <lb/>in regular intermittents. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In Zealand, where the air is worſt, it is <lb/>called the gall-ſickneſs; and,
            indeed, both the <lb/>ſurcharge and depravation of the bile is ſo re- <pb n="9"/>
            <lb/>markable, wherever theſe fevers prevail, that <lb/>the immediate cauſe has been
            uſually referred to <lb/>the corruption of that humour. But however <lb/>that be, it is
            certain, that the continuance and <lb/>malignity of the diſeaſe is owing in a great mea-
            <lb/>ſure to an increaſed ſecretion and putrefaction <lb/>of the bile, occaſioned by the
            fever. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In proportion to the coolneſs of the ſeaſon, <lb/>to the height and drineſs of the
            grounds, the <lb/>epidemic appears milder, remits or inter- <lb/>mits more freely, and
            recedes farther from <lb/>the nature of a double tertian, a continued <lb/>putrid, or an
            ardent fever. In its worſt ſtate, <lb/>the effects plainly aſcertain the cauſe; as theſe
            <lb/>fevers are attended with intenſe thirſt and <lb/>heat, foulneſs of the tongue,
            bitterneſs of taſte, <lb/>deſire of acids, nauſea and averſion to all ani- <lb/>mal
            food, putrid vomiting, extreme ſenſe of <lb/>oppreſſion about the ſtomach, livid ſpots,
            <lb/>and the like ſtrong indications of a putrid <lb/>bile; if not a corruption of all
            the hu- <lb/>mours. And whereas, with ſuch ſymp- <lb/>toms, the diſeaſe aſſumes an
            intermitting <lb/>or remitting form, it ſhould ſeem, that <lb/>even the more benign
            intermittents of this ſea- <pb n="10"/>
            <lb/>ſon were owing to a leſſer degree of the ſame <lb/>cauſe. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Cholera Morbus</hi>, and dyſentery, tho' <lb/>rarely to be
            called epidemic, are nevertheleſs <lb/>frequent diſeaſes of theſe moiſt countries.
            <lb/>They appear in the ſame ſeaſon with the fe- <lb/>vers, and ſeem to be only
            particular determi- <lb/>nations of the ſame corrupted humours; to <lb/>which, if the
            firſt paſſages give free vent, a <lb/><hi rend="italic">Cholera</hi> or flux enſues; but
            if the vitiated hu- <lb/>mours are retained and aſſumed into the blood, <lb/>they may
            occaſion an intermitting, remitting <lb/>or continued fever. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Both fevers and fluxes are often accompa- <lb/>nied with worms, which are not to be
            deemed <lb/>the cauſe of either; but only a ſign of a <lb/>preceding bad ſtate of the
            bowels, brought <lb/>on by a decay of the natural ſecretions, a ſtag- <lb/>nation and
            corruption of the aliment, and a wea- <lb/>kened tone of the inteſtines; all owing to
            the <lb/>heats and moiſture of the ſeaſon. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Theſe are the acute endemics of the mar- <lb/>ſhy parts of the Netherlands. The
            chief <lb/>chronical diſtemper is a ſpecies of a ſcurvy pe- <lb/>culiar to a moiſt and
            corrupted air; the ſymp- <lb/>toms of which agreeing ſo much with the ſea- <pb n="11"/>
            <lb/>ſcurvy, they may be accounted the ſame diſeaſe. <lb/>The exhalation of the canals
            and marſhes in <lb/>hot weather, acts like the vapour which riſes <lb/>from the
            bildge-water of a ſhip; both are <lb/>moiſt and putrid; and in both the effects of
            <lb/>putrefaction are plainly seen. Here the ſea <lb/>air is leaſt to be blamed; for
            ventilation on <lb/>board a ſhip is no greater preſervative from the <lb/>marine ſcurvy,
            than removing from the mar- <lb/>ſhes to a dry ſea coaſt, or to any other dry and
            <lb/>ſound air, is a cure for the other. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In general, it is the richer ſort, or thoſe who <lb/>can afford to live above the
            common rate, <lb/>who keep freeſt from the diſeaſes of the mar- <lb/>ſhes. For ſuch
            climates require dry houſes, the <lb/>apartments raiſed from the ground, proper
            <lb/>exerciſe, without labour in the ſun or in the <lb/>evening damps, a juſt quantity
            of vinous <lb/>liquors, and victuals of good nouriſhment: <lb/>without ſuch helps, not
            only ſtrangers, but <lb/>the natives themſelves, are extremely ſub- <lb/>ject to
            diſeaſes, after hot and cloſe ſum- <lb/>mers. The hardieſt conſtitutions are not
            <lb/>more exempted than others, and leſs in <lb/>proportion to the drineſs of the parts
            <lb/>from whence they come. And this is the <pb n="12"/>
            <lb/>reaſon Britiſh ſoldiers are ſo liable to bilious <lb/>fevers and fluxes, in the
            wetter parts of the <lb/>Netherlands. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Now tho' in the lower parts of Flanders <lb/>and Holland, the ſummer and autumnal
            diſ- <lb/>tempers appear in the extreme, yet in no <lb/>country, however dry, is there a
            total exemp- <lb/>tion. For the ſummer heats, if great, always <lb/>relax the ſolids,
            and tend to corrupt the juices: <lb/>under which circumſtances, if the body is ex-
            <lb/>poſed to fogs and nocturnal damps, or receives <lb/>improper food, the ſame kind of
            diſtempers, <lb/>tho' leſs characterized and in ſmaller num- <lb/>bers, will be incident
            to dry, as well as to mar- <lb/>ſhy countries. Hence in the drieſt camps, <lb/>after
            great and continued heats, theſe ſum- <lb/>mer and autumnal fevers and fluxes are
            <lb/>conſtant; becauſe in that ſituation, beſides the <lb/>natural moiſture of a tent,
            men muſt either <lb/>by duty or miſconduct be frequently expoſed <lb/>to wet ground, wet
            cloaths, nocturnal damps <lb/>and colds. And the ſubjection to theſe ma- <lb/>ladies is
            the more inevitable, in proportion to <lb/>the more ſenſible and frequent interchanges
            <lb/>of heat and cold in the field, than in quarters. </p>
          <pb n="13"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>But a ſudden ſtoppage of perſpiration com- <lb/>ing upon relaxed fibres, and a
            putreſcent <lb/>ſtate of blood if not timely remedied, is ſure <lb/>to produce a
            remitting fever, dyſentery, or <lb/> the like diſorder: ſo that theſe diſtempers
            <lb/>may be called as properly the endemics of a <lb/>camp, as of a low and marſhy
            country. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>CHAP. II. </head>
          <head rend="italic hanging space">
            <lb/>A general account of the <hi rend="sc">Garrison Diseases</hi>
            <lb/>of the Britiſh troops in Flanders, and the <lb/>cantonments in Germany. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>N the beginning of June ( <note place="bottom" n="*"
              rend="size(0.5)">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>* N.B. The new ſtile is uſed throughout. </p>
            </note>N.S.) 1742, the <lb/>Britiſh troops began to embark for Flan- <lb/>ders. There
            were in all, of foot and cavalry, about <lb/>16,000; the winds were favourable, the ſe-
            <lb/>veral embarkations ſhort, the men landed in <lb/>good health, and went into their
            ſeveral gar- <lb/>riſons. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The head-quarters were at Ghent, with <lb/>moſt of the cavalry, three battalions of
            guards, <pb n="14"/>
            <lb/>
            <note place="margin">1742. </note>one marching regiment, and the train; eight
            <lb/>battalions were quartered at Bruges, two at <lb/>Courtray; a regiment of dragoons
            lay at Ou- <lb/>denarde and another was divided between <lb/>Aloſt and Grammond. At
            Ghent there was <lb/>a general hoſpital; but in the other garriſons <lb/>the care of the
            ſick was committed to the <lb/>ſurgeons of their reſpective regiments. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>During the ſummer and autumn, the wea- <lb/>ther was good, the heats moderate, and
            the <lb/>country, for the ſeaſon and climate, enjoyed <lb/>good health. The Britiſh
            officers ſhared in <lb/>it, but the common men were generally un- <lb/>healthy; and this
            ſeemed to be the reaſon: </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Ghent is ſituated between the high and <lb/>low part of Flanders; one quarter of
            it, call- <lb/>ed St. Peters-hill, ſtands high above the reſt <lb/>of the country, and
            in this the barracks, hav- <lb/>ing drains and free air, were quite dry; ſo <lb/>that
            the men who lay there enjoyed perfect <lb/>health: but the reſt, who were quartered in
            <lb/>the low part of the town, whoſe barracks be- <lb/>ing moſtly the ground-floors of
            waſte houſes, <lb/>without drains, and, of courſe, very damp, <lb/>were all ſickly. The
            battalion of the firſt <lb/>regiment of guards was a remarkable inſtance <pb n="15"/>
            <lb/>of the difference of quarters: two of its com- <note place="margin">1742. </note>
            <lb/>panies lay on St. Peter's hill, the remaining <lb/>eight in the loweſt part of the
            town, in rooms <lb/>ſo very damp, that the men could ſcarce keep <lb/>their ſhoes and
            belts from moulding. In the <lb/>month of July, the ſick of this one batta- <lb/>lion
            amounted to about 140 <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>* A compleat battalion conſiſted of 813; but as commiſ- <lb/>ſioned officers
                are not put in the Returns of the ſick, we are only <lb/>to reckon the full corps at
                780. </p>
            </note>; of which <lb/>number only two men belonged to the companies <lb/>on the hill,
            and all the reſt to thoſe in the <lb/>lower town. But in the middle of Au- <lb/>guſt,
            upon changing the barracks, the ſick- <lb/>neſs ſuddenly abated. The reſt of the garri-
            <lb/>ſon ſuffered much leſs in proportion; the <lb/>higheſt Returns of the foot at no
            time exceed- <lb/>ing 70 in a battalion and 40 in a regiment <lb/>of dragoons <note
              place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>† This conſiſted of three ſquadrons, and each ſquadron of <lb/>158 men, not
                including officers. </p>
            </note>. Now as the Returns include <lb/>all accidents unfitting a ſoldier for duty, and
            <lb/>as theſe numbers are more than triple to <lb/>what ſuch corps commonly have at
            <lb/>home, the ſickneſs in this garriſon was ac- <lb/>counted moderate. The higheſt
            Returns were <lb/>in the month of Auguſt; when the diſtem- <pb n="16"/>
            <lb/>
            <note place="margin">1742. </note>pers were chiefly intermitting and remitting
            <lb/>fevers, diarrhœas, and a few dyſenteries. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>But the ſickneſs was more conſiderable at <lb/>Bruges, a city of the lower diviſion
            of <lb/>Flanders, and moiſter than Ghent. The <lb/>ſoldiers had moreover damper
            barracks, and <lb/>ſuffered accordingly. The remitting and inter- <lb/>mitting fevers
            began in July; but in Auguſt the in- <lb/>termittents were moſt numerous, which conti-
            <lb/>nuing throughout September, diminiſhed in <lb/>October, and ceaſed with the froſts
            in <lb/>November. Theſe fevers were not only of <lb/>a worſe kind than thoſe at Ghent,
            but the <lb/>Returns of the ſick was three times greater, <lb/>and more in proportion
            died. Next to the <lb/>fever, fluxes were moſt frequent; and tho' <lb/>not always with
            blood, were generally of <lb/>the dyſenteric kind. It was then obſerv- <lb/>able, that
            ſuch as lay in the upper ſtories, <lb/>kept their health incomparably better than
            <lb/>thoſe who were below on the ground-floors. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The two battalions at Courtray happened <lb/>to be differently lodged; one had dry
            barracks, <lb/>the other wet, and this laſt had double the <lb/>number of ſick
            throughout the autumn: but <lb/>the higheſt Return did not exceed 70. </p>
          <pb n="17"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Oudenarde is in the higher diviſion of <note place="margin">1742. </note>
            <lb/>Flanders; but the barracks being without <lb/>drains, and damp, and the ſituation
            low, the <lb/>Welch Fuzileers, who lay there, ſuffered as <lb/>much in proportion as the
            garriſon of Bruges. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>But at Aloſt and Grammont, towns in the <lb/>ſame diviſion (where the dragoons were
            bil- <lb/>letted in private houſes) there was ſcarce any <lb/>diſtemper at all; and that
            corps was in ſuch <lb/>health, when the army marched into Ger- <lb/>many, that it left
            not a man behind. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The great number of ſick, and the little <lb/>experience in the cure of diſeaſes
            incident to <lb/>a moiſt climate, were the reaſons that, at this <lb/>time, the fevers
            were perhaps leſs ſucceſsfully <lb/>treated than afterwards. Many of the re-
            <lb/>mittents degenerated into continued fevers, <lb/>often mortal; and the
            intermittents, or <lb/>agues, by being prematurely ſtopped, or not <lb/>ſecured againſt
            relapſes, changed likewiſe <lb/>into continued fevers, or ended in dangerous
            <lb/>obſtructions of the <hi rend="italic">viſcera</hi>. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>After the froſts in November, the inter- <lb/>mittents never appeared, unleſs upon
            catch- <lb/>ing cold; when ſuch as had been ill in au- <lb/>tumn were ſubject to
            relapſe. </p>
          <pb n="18"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>
            <note place="margin">1742. </note>Here the autumnal epidemic ceaſed, and <lb/>the winter
            diſeaſes began; which were colds <lb/>in various ſhapes. The moſt common were <lb/>hard
            coughs, ſtitches, rheumatic pains, <lb/>pleuriſies, inflammations of the lungs, &amp;c.
            <lb/>to all which the ſoldiers, unuſed to duty and <lb/>cold quarters; and unprovided
            with cloaths <lb/>ſuited to the climate, and to the ſeaſon (at this <lb/>time
            particularly ſharp) were extremely liable. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Beſides theſe, there was no general ailment, <lb/>except the itch; which indeed was
            ſo uni- <lb/>verſal, ſoon after landing, that many believ- <lb/>ed, that either the
            ſalt-proviſions at ſea, or <lb/>the change of air, muſt have been the cauſe <lb/>of ſo
            ſudden and extenſive a complaint. But, <lb/>it was ſolely owing to the contagion of a
            few, <lb/>who being infected before the embarkation, <lb/>communicated the diſtemper to
            their com- <lb/>panions on board, or ſoon afterwards in the <lb/>barracks. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Such were the diſeaſes moſt incident to the <lb/>troops, before they marched. The
            leſs fre- <lb/>quent, were dropſies and conſumptions; <lb/>whereof the former were the
            conſequence <lb/>of the autumnal fevers ill cured; and the <lb/>latter, the termination
            of neglected colds. </p>
          <pb n="19"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>But of all, the moſt alarming was a fever <note place="margin">1742. </note>
            <lb/>of a malignant nature, very ſlow, and attend- <lb/>ed with a ſunk pulſe and a
            conſtant <hi rend="italic">Stupor</hi>: <lb/>yet it was more the newneſs and danger,
            than <lb/>the number ſeized, that made it conſidera- <lb/>ble. The cauſe was at firſt
            miſtaken; but <lb/>afterwards, it appeared to ariſe from the <lb/>foul air of ſome of
            the wards crouded with <lb/>ſick; and eſpecially of one room, in which <lb/>a man lay
            with a mortified limb. This <lb/>fever was confined to the hospital; and as it <lb/>has
            generally taken its riſe from thence, it <lb/>ſhall hereafter be diſtinguiſhed by the
            name <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">malignant</hi> or <hi rend="italic">hoſpital
              fever</hi>. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In the beginning of February, the troops <note place="margin">1743. </note>
            <lb/>moved from winter quarters, and marching <lb/>into Germany, were cantoned in the
            country <lb/>of Juliers and Aix-la-Chapelle. Part of the <lb/>cavalry, only, was left at
            Bruſſels; and the <lb/>ſick and weak, to the amount of 600, be- <lb/>ing collected from
            all the garriſons, were put <lb/>into the general hoſpital at Ghent. The wea- <lb/>ther
            was, for the ſeaſon, favourable, and the <lb/>troops entered Germany in good condition.
            <lb/>Soon after the <hi rend="italic">Influenza</hi> paſſed through the <lb/>greateſt
            part of Europe, and was ſenſibly felt <pb n="20"/>
            <lb/>
            <note place="margin">1743. </note>at Bruſſels; tho' but little in the cantonements;
            <lb/>otherwiſe, than that many, who, in the pre- <lb/>ceding autumn had been ſeized with
            agues, <lb/>then relapſed. For other diſeaſes, they were <lb/>the ſame as in garriſon;
            ſuch as coughs, <lb/>pleuriſies and the like, from taking cold in <lb/>a rigorous
            ſeaſon. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>From the arrival of the troops at their can- <lb/>tonements, till the beginning of
            May, the <lb/>weather was extremely cold, with extraordi- <lb/>nary ſnows, which fell
            towards the end of <lb/>March, and continued for ſeventeen days: in <lb/>the midſt of
            which the troops left their quar- <lb/>ters, and croſſed the Rhine. The march was
            <lb/>long, and the roads deep; but as the men came <lb/>every night into warm houſes,
            and had good <lb/>proviſions, ſo few fell ill by the way, that in <lb/>both marches,
            from Ghent to the cantone- <lb/>ments, and from thence to the place of en-
            <lb/>campment, in winter, or in the worſt weather, <lb/>we did not, in all, loſe twenty.
            In the begin- <lb/>ning of May, the weather ſuddenly changed, <lb/>and the troops
            encamped on the 17th, at <lb/>Hoechſt, on the banks of the Maine, in a <lb/>dry, open
            and healthful country. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="21"/>
        <div type="chapter">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>CHAP. III. </head>
          <head rend="italic hanging space">
            <lb/>A general account of the <hi rend="sc">Diseases</hi> of the Bri- <lb/>tiſh troops,
            during the campaign in Germany, <lb/>and the enſuing winter in Flanders. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE ground, tho' naturally good, had <lb/>not had time to dry
            thoroughly ſince <lb/>the late ſnows and rains; and tho' the days <lb/>were now warm,
            the nights were ſtill cold, <lb/>and condenſed the vapours. Theſe ſudden
            <lb/>interchanges of heat and cold, joined to the <lb/>moiſture inſeparable from tents,
            could not but <lb/>affect the health of troops unuſed to the field. <lb/>Many were
            thereupon ſeized with inflam- <lb/>matory diſorders, of ſundry forms. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The flying hoſpital was opened at Nied, a <lb/>village in the neighbourhood of the
            camp, <lb/>which, in three weeks, admitted about 250 <lb/>ſick. When the number was
            thirty leſs, the <lb/>diſtempers were claſſed, and ſtood thus: of <lb/>pleuriſes and
            peripneumonies, 71; rheuma- <lb/>tic pains, with more or leſs of fever, 51; in-
            <lb/>flammatory fevers, without either rheumatic, <lb/>or pleuritic pains, 25;
            intermittents, 30; <pb n="22"/>
            <lb/>
            <note place="margin">1743. </note>hard coughs without fever, 9; old coughs <lb/>and
            conſumptions, 7. The reſt had either <lb/>fluxes, or ſome inflammatory ſymptom dif-
            <lb/>ferent from theſe mentioned; and ſeveral <lb/>ſlighter caſes remained in the camp.
            The <lb/>intermittents and fluxes were alſo accompa- <lb/>nied with a conſiderable
            degree of inflam- <lb/>mation. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>This, with a little variation, is the courſe <lb/>of the firſt camp-diſeaſes; for
            the nights be- <lb/>ing yet cold, and the ground wet, it is eaſily <lb/>conceived in
            what manner men muſt ſuffer, <lb/>who lie in tents, without any covering. Be-
            <lb/>ſides, ſoldiers are frequently expoſed to rain, <lb/>and have not means of drying
            their cloaths; <lb/>at other times, for want of occupation, they <lb/>are apt to lie
            down on the graſs, and fall <lb/>aſleep in the ſun. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Hence, the diſeaſes from the firſt en- <lb/>campment till paſt the ſummer ſolſtice,
            are <lb/>all highly inflammatory. Fluxes, remit- <lb/>ting and intermitting fevers are,
            during this <lb/>period, never general; and ſuch as occur, <lb/>are never without
            inflammation. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The cavalry had not near their proportion <lb/>of ſick, and never have in camps;
            for the care <pb n="23"/>
            <lb/>of the horſes gives the men an eaſy but con- <lb/>ſtant employment, their cloaks
            keep them <lb/>dry in rains, and ſerve for bed-cloaths at <lb/>night. For the officers,
            they enjoyed then <lb/>perfect health, as they always do in the firſt <lb/>part of a
            campaign. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>On the 22d of June, the army marched to <lb/>Aſchaffenburg, where it encamped on a
            dry <lb/>and airy field. In the hoſpital were left 500; <lb/>ſo that in five weeks the
            proportion of the ſick <lb/>to the whole, was about 1 to 29. Before <lb/>this motion of
            the troops, the ſickneſs had <lb/>ſenſibly decreaſed; and it continued ſtill to
            <lb/>decline in the new camp: for, the weakeſt <lb/>were already in the hoſpital, and
            the reſt of <lb/>the men were inured to the field. Add to <lb/>this, that the nights
            were now warm, and <lb/>there had been no rain to wet the men's <lb/>cloaths, or the
            ground on which they lay. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>On the 26th, in the evening, the tents were <lb/>ſtruck; the army marched all
            night, and next <lb/>morning fought at Dettingen. On the night <lb/>following, the men
            lay on the field of battle, <lb/>without tents, expoſed to a heavy rain; and <lb/>next
            day they marched to Hanau, where they <lb/>encamped in an open field, and on good <pb
              n="24"/>
            <lb/>
            <note place="margin">1743. </note>ground, but then wet, and they had no ſtraw <lb/>for
            the firſt night. By theſe accidents, a ſud- <lb/>den change was made in the health of
            the ar- <lb/>my. For, the ſummer had begun early, and <lb/>the heats hitherto had been
            great and con- <lb/>ſtant; but, the free and uninterrupted perſpi- <lb/>ration,
            attending thoſe very heats, had as yet <lb/>prevented them from producing any general
            <lb/>ſickneſs. Now the pores were ſuddenly ſtop- <lb/>ped, the humours became putrid,
            and in that <lb/>condition were turned upon the bowels, oc- <lb/>caſioning an epidemic
            dyſentery; which be- <lb/>gan at this time, and continued for a great part <lb/>of the
            ſeaſon. In the ſpace of eight days af- <lb/>ter the battle, about 500 were ſeized with
            it; <lb/>and in a few weeks more, near half of the <lb/>troops were either ill, or had
            recovered of that <lb/>diſtemper. It was common, tho' not nearly ſo <lb/>frequent, among
            the officers; of whom thoſe <lb/>were firſt ſeized, who happened to lie wet <lb/>at
            Dettingen: the reſt ſuffered by contagion. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The dyſentery, the conſtant and fatal epi- <lb/>demic of camps, appeared ſooner
            this ſea- <lb/>ſon than it did in any ſucceeding cam- <lb/>paign. Now, as its uſual time
            is not before <lb/>the latter end of ſummer, or beginning of <pb n="25"/>
            <lb/>autumn, its cauſe has been unjuſtly imputed <note place="margin">1743. </note>
            <lb/>to eating fruit in exceſs. But, the circum- <lb/>ſtances here contradict that
            opinion; for <lb/>the ſickneſs began and raged before any fruit <lb/>was in ſeaſon,
            except ſtrawberries, (which, <lb/>from the high price, the men never taſted) <lb/>and
            ended about the the time the grapes were <lb/>ripe; which growing in open vineyards were
            <lb/>eat by every body. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>To this add the following inci- <lb/>dent. Three companies of Howard's regi-
            <lb/>ment, which had not joined the army, <lb/>marched with the King's baggage from
            <lb/>Oſtend to Hanau; where arriving a night <lb/>or two before the battle, and having
            orders <lb/>to ſtop, encamped for the firſt time, at a <lb/>ſmall diſtance from the
            ground, that was <lb/>afterwards occupied by the army. Theſe <lb/>men had never been
            expoſed to rain, or lain <lb/>wet; by this ſeparation from the line, they <lb/>were alſo
            removed from the contagion of <lb/>the privies; and having pitched cloſe upon <lb/>the
            river, they had the benefit of a conſtant <lb/>ſtream of air. By means of ſuch favour-
            <lb/>able circumſtances, it was remarkable, that <lb/>while the army ſuffered moſt, this
            little <lb/>camp entirely eſcaped the diſtemper; tho' <pb n="26"/>
            <lb/>
            <note place="margin">1743. </note><choice>
              <corr/>
              <sic>tho' </sic>
            </choice>the men breathed the ſame air, the <lb/>contagious part excepted, eat of the
            ſame <lb/>victuals, and drank of the ſame water. This <lb/>immunity continued for ſix
            weeks, until the <lb/>army removed from Hanau; when theſe <lb/>companies joining the
            main body, and en- <lb/>camping in the line, were at laſt infected; <lb/>but ſuffered
            little, as the flux was then ſo <lb/>much upon the decline. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The dyſentery raged all the month of July <lb/>and part of Auguſt, to which the
            weather con- <lb/>tributed. For, ſoon after the above mentioned <lb/>rains, which had
            cooled the air, the heats <lb/>returned, and continued for ſome weeks ſo <lb/>great,
            that the humours, already too much <lb/>diſpoſed, were farther prepared to receive
            <lb/>the infection. Of this the chief <hi rend="italic">fomes</hi> ſeemed <lb/>to be the
            foul ſtraw and the privies: for, as <lb/>ſoon as we left that ground, the ſickneſs
            <lb/>viſibly abated. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The numbers aggravated the ſymptoms, <lb/>as in the caſe of the ſmall pox, plague,
            and <lb/>every other putrid and infectious diſeaſe. <lb/>But, the flux is particularly
            deſtructive in full <lb/>hoſpitals, where the corrupted ſteams being <lb/>confined and
            accumulated, are raiſed to a <pb n="27"/>
            <lb/>high degree of virulence: of which fact the <note place="margin">1743. </note>
            <lb/>preſent ſickneſs afforded a fatal inſtance. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The village of Feckenheim, about a league <lb/>from the camp, was taken up for an
            hoſpital; <lb/>into which, during the ſtay the army made at <lb/>Hanau (beſides the
            wounded from the field <lb/>of battle) about 1500 ſick were ſent from <lb/>the camp; and
            of that number, the greateſt <lb/>part, ill of the dyſentery. By which means <lb/>the
            air became vitiated to ſuch a degree, that <lb/>not only the reſt of the patients were
            ſeized <lb/>with the flux, but the apothecaries, nurſes, <lb/>and other attendants, with
            moſt of the inha- <lb/>bitants of the village, were alſo infected. To <lb/>this acceded
            a ſtill more formidable diſeaſe, <lb/>namely, the <hi rend="italic">hoſpital</hi> or <hi
              rend="italic">jail-fever</hi>, an inſe- <lb/>parable attendant of foul air from crowds
            <lb/>and animal corruption. Theſe two com- <lb/>bined occaſioned a great mortality:
            while <lb/>on the other hand, ſuch as were ſeized <lb/>with the dyſentery, and not
            removed from <lb/>the camp, tho' wanting many convenien- <lb/>cies, others had in
            hoſpitals, kept free of <lb/>this malignant fever, and commonly did <lb/>well. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>On the 10th of Auguſt, the army decamp- <lb/>ed from Hanau, and came to Wiſbaden;
            where <pb n="28"/>
            <lb/>
            <note place="margin">1743. </note>we lay ſome days, and were joined by four
            <lb/>battalions from England. On the 23d, we <lb/>croſſed the Rhine, and on the 30th of
            the <lb/>ſame month, encamped at Worms, along <lb/>the river; where we continued until
            the <lb/>25th of September. All the encampments <lb/>were on dry ground, and in an open
            coun- <lb/>try. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The month of Auguſt was ſtill warm and <lb/>dry, without fogs; and the reſt of the
            autumn <lb/>was of a piece, allowing for the abatement of <lb/>heat, and the conſtant
            dews of this ſeaſon. In <lb/>the end of Auguſt, tho' the days were ſtill <lb/>hot, the
            nights grew cool; and in the begin- <lb/>ning of October the cold was ſo far advanced,
            <lb/>that the fields were ſometimes covered with <lb/>a hoar-froſt. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>From the time of removing from Hanau, <lb/>there was ſo remarkable a decline of the
            dy- <lb/>ſentery, that the change could be only im- <lb/>puted to the leaving behind the
            infectious <lb/>privies, the foul ſtraw, and filth of a long en- <lb/>campment. When the
            army croſſed the <lb/>Rhine, this diſtemper made but a third of <lb/>all the ſickneſs,
            from having been lately al- <lb/>moſt the only complaint. In a month af- <lb/>ter it was
            ſcarce ſeen, unleſs in a few; who <pb n="29"/>
            <lb/>by reaſon of imperfect cures, colds, or errors <note place="margin">1743. </note>
            <lb/>of diet, chanced to relapſe. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>About the middle of Auguſt, when the <lb/>dyſentery was on the decline, a new
            diſeaſe <lb/>appeared, and which daily increaſed, as <lb/>long as the troops kept the
            field. This was <lb/>a remitting fever; the paroxyſms of which <lb/>came <sic>on the in
              the</sic> evenings, with great heat, <lb/>drought, a violent head-ach, and often a <hi
              rend="italic">deli- <lb/>rium</hi>; all which ſymptoms laſted moſt of <lb/>the night,
            but abated in the morning with <lb/>an imperfect ſweat; and ſometimes with an
            <lb/>hæmorrhage of the noſe, or a looſeneſs. The <lb/>ſtomach was, from the beginning,
            much diſ- <lb/>ordered with a <hi rend="italic">nauſea</hi> and ſenſe of oppreſ-
            <lb/>ſion, frequently with a bilious and putrid <lb/>vomiting. If evacuations were
            either ne- <lb/>glected, or too ſparingly uſed, the patient <lb/>fell into a continued
            fever; and ſometimes <lb/>grew yellow, as in a jaundice. When the <lb/>ſeaſon was far
            advanced, ſo that colds be- <lb/>came frequent, the fever was attended with <lb/>a
            cough, rheumatic pains, and ſizy blood. <lb/>The officers were not ſo ſubject to it as
            the <lb/>common men, being leſs expoſed; and for <lb/>the like reaſon the cavalry, who
            had cloaks <lb/>to keep them warm a-nights, were leſs liable <pb n="30"/>
            <lb/>
            <note place="margin">1743. </note>to fall ill. Others, who belonged to the ar- <lb/>my,
            but lay in quarters, were yet ſel- <lb/>domer ſeized; and the leſs in proportion <lb/>to
            their being little expoſed to heats, night- <lb/>damps, and bad lodgings. This
            diſtemper, <lb/>another conſtant epidemic of an army, ſhall <lb/>hereafter be
            diſtinguiſhed by the name of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">bilious</hi>, or autumnal <hi
              rend="italic">remitting fever</hi>. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In the courſe of the dyſentery, and even of <lb/>this fever, ſeveral voided round
            worms; and <lb/>the ſame ſymptom has occurred in both, <lb/>in every campaign. But we
            are not, there- <lb/>fore, to imagine, that theſe worms are the <lb/>cauſe of the fever
            or flux; but only, that <lb/>when joined to either, they make them <lb/>worſe. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>On the 25th of September, the army, free <lb/>of the dyſentery, but with a daily
            increaſe of <lb/>the remitting fever, marched to Spiers; but <lb/>returned on the 13th
            of October. The <lb/>weather had changed, and it rained much <lb/>during the march;
            which, with the cold- <lb/>neſs of the ſeaſon, cauſed, in that little time, <lb/>ſo much
            ſickneſs, that when the troops <lb/>came back, above 800 more were ſent into <lb/>the
            hoſpital, and almoſt all of them ill of <lb/>this fever. Three days after, the army
            moved <pb n="31"/>
            <lb/>to Biberic, and breaking up camp, on the 25th <note place="margin">1743. </note>
            <lb/>of October, the Britiſh, in different diviſions, <lb/>returned to the Netherlands.
            The weather <lb/>being extremely favourable to the march <lb/>(which continued a month),
            and the men <lb/>coming into warm quarters every night, ſo <lb/>few fell ill, that they
            arrived at their ſeveral <lb/>garriſons with ſcarce the loſs of a man. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>But 3000 ſick were left in Germany; part <lb/>at Feckenheim, near Hanau, and the
            reſt at <lb/>Oſthoven and Bechtheim, two villages in <lb/>the neighbourhood of Worms.
            The ſtate <lb/>of the ſick at Feckenheim has been men- <lb/>tioned: where the malignant
            fever and dyſen- <lb/>tery grew daily worſe. Few eſcaped; for, <lb/>how mild or bad
            ſoever the flux was, (for <lb/>which the perſon was ſent to the hoſpital) <lb/>this
            fever almoſt ſurely ſupervened. The <lb/>petechial ſpots, blotches, parotids, frequent
            <lb/>mortifications, contagiouſneſs, and the great <lb/>mortality ſet forth its
            peſtilential nature. In <lb/>this reſpect it was worſe than the true plague, <lb/>that
            there was no ſecurity againſt a relapſe; <lb/>but, on the contrary, almoſt a certainty
            of it, <lb/>if the perſon continued in the infectious air. <lb/>Of fourteen mates
            employed about the ſick, <lb/>five died; and, excepting one or two, all <pb n="32"/>
            <lb/>
            <note place="margin">1743. </note>the reſt had been ill, and in danger. The
            <lb/>hoſpital loſt near half of the patients; but <lb/>the inhabitants of the village
            having firſt re- <lb/>ceived the flux, and afterwards the fever by <lb/>contagion,
            between the two were almoſt ut- <lb/>terly deſtroyed. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The condition of the two hoſpitals near <lb/>Worms was better; where the ſick had
            more <lb/>ſpace, they had been admitted in a cooler <lb/>ſeaſon, and the diſtempers were
            leſs putrid. <lb/>But, one general hoſpital being to be made <lb/>at Newied, the ſick
            were removed from <lb/>their ſeveral quarters, and carried down the <lb/>Rhine to that
            place: where, by the change <lb/>of air, thoſe from Feckenheim were at firſt
            <lb/>relieved, but the reſt, who were mixed with <lb/>them, caught the infection; which
            the fol- <lb/>lowing circumſtance rendered ſtill more ge- <lb/>neral and fatal. For,
            orders coming ſoon <lb/>after to remove the hoſpital from Germany <lb/>to Flanders, all
            the ſick were embarked in <lb/>bilanders, and conveyed by water to Ghent; <lb/>but where
            they did not arrive till about the <lb/>middle of December. So that, in this tedious
            <lb/>voyage, the fever having acquired new force by <lb/>the confinement of the air,
            mortifications, and <pb n="33"/>
            <lb/>other putrid <hi rend="italic">Effluvia</hi>, it was raiſed to ſuch an <note
              place="margin">1743. </note>
            <lb/>extraordinary pitch of virulence, that above <lb/>half the number died by the way,
            and ſeveral <lb/>more ſoon after their arrival. The reſem- <lb/>blance of this fever to
            a true peſtilence, was <lb/>farther evinced by this remarkable incident. <lb/>A parcel
            of tents were put on board the ſame <lb/>bilanders with the ſick, and which being to be
            <lb/>refitted at Ghent, were put into the hands <lb/>of a tradeſman, who employed
            twenty-three <lb/>journeymen about the work; but thoſe un- <lb/>happy men were quickly
            ſeized with a malig- <lb/>nant fever, and ſeventeen of them died. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The proportion of men left in the hoſpitals <lb/>at the end of the campaign, to
            thoſe who came <lb/>ſafe into winter quarters, was about 3 to 13. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The winter quarters aſſigned the troops, <lb/>were Bruſſels, Ghent, Bruges and
            Oſtend: <lb/>of all which, Bruſſels is the higheſt and <lb/>beſt aired. But in winter,
            as there is little exha- <lb/>lation, and conſequently no dangerous moiſture <lb/>in the
            air, the ſituation of the place is a matter <lb/>of leſs conſequence; ſo that the only
            con- <lb/>cern is only to provide the men in warm and dry <lb/>barracks, with a
            ſufficient allowance for fuel. <lb/>The beſt quarters were at Bruſſels, and accord- <pb
              n="34"/>
            <lb/>
            <note place="margin">1743. </note>ingly the ſickneſs was nothing there, in com-
            <lb/>pariſon of what it was at Ghent and Bruges; <lb/>where the dampneſs of the
            barracks, conſpi- <lb/>ring with ſome remains of the diſeaſes of the <lb/>field,
            occaſioned frequent diſtempers in the <lb/>beginning of winter. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>For, notwithstanding the troops returned to <lb/>Flanders in apparent good health,
            yet, ſoon af- <lb/>ter their arrival, ſeveral were taken ill with re- <lb/>mitting
            fevers, attended with inflammatory <lb/>ſymptoms; whereby it appeared, that the
            <lb/>ſeeds of this fever might lie ſome while la- <lb/>tent in the body, and break out
            upon colds <lb/>caught at any time before the froſts have re- <lb/>covered the tone of
            the bowels, braced the <lb/>fibres, and purified the blood. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In the beginning, therefore, of winter, theſe <lb/>remittents were the prevailing
            diſtemper of the <lb/>garriſons; and there were beſides ſeveral jaun- <lb/>dices without
            any fever. At Bruſſels, where, <lb/>as we obſerved, the barracks were dry and <lb/>warm,
            the fevers were few, and the jaundice <lb/>rare: but at Ghent and Bruges, both were
            <lb/>numerous. Yet the continuance of this <lb/>fever was ſhort, for it diſappeared in
            De- <lb/>cember; nor was ſucceeded by any other <pb n="35"/>
            <lb/>diſtemper, but coughs and inflammations from <note place="margin">1744. </note>
            <lb/>colds; exactly as in the preceding winter. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>No epidemic appeared in the ſpring. The <lb/>only diſeaſe, beſides colds, was the
            malignant <lb/>fever, which came from Germany, and was <lb/>ſtill fatal in the hoſpital
            at Ghent. And ſome <lb/>degree of the ſame diſtemper was alſo felt at <lb/>Bruges, in
            the regimental infirmaries <lb/>were at firſt crouded. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>CHAP. IV. </head>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A general account of the <hi rend="sc">Diseases</hi> of the cam- <lb/>paign in
            Flanders, in the year 1744. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE arms firſt encamped at Anderlecht, <lb/>within a league
            of Bruſſels, on the 13th <lb/>of May. On the 1ſt of June they moved to Ber- <lb/>leghem,
            and lay there till the 31ſt of July; <lb/>when they croſſed the Scheld, encamped at
            <lb/>Anſtain, in the territory of Liſle, where they <lb/>remained almoſt all the reſt of
            the campaign. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The Britiſh took the field with five new <lb/>battalions, and at Berleghem there
            was a re- <lb/>inforcement of five more from England; <lb/>which, with the <hi
              rend="italic">additionals</hi> to the dragoons, <lb/>and recruits, made the national
            troops exceed <pb n="36"/>
            <lb/>
            <note place="margin">1744. </note>in number thoſe of the former campaign, by
            <lb/>upwards of 10000. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The firſt three days of the encampment <lb/>were warm for the ſeaſon, the
            ſucceeding ten <lb/>were cold; but afterwards the weather turn- <lb/>ed very mild, and
            keeping dry without exceſ- <lb/>ſive heat, the ſummer proved in general very
            <lb/>favourable for the field. Before the army paſ- <lb/>ſed the Scheld, there having
            been no hard duty, <lb/>and the forrage being at hand, the men ſuffered <lb/>little by
            wet cloaths or fatigue; hence the ſick- <lb/>neſs was ſo moderate, that during ten weeks
            <lb/>encampment, our troops had ſent little more <lb/>than 600 into the hoſpitals of
            Ghent and Bruſ- <lb/>ſels: which was not above <formula notation="fraction"
              >1/43</formula> part of the whole. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Two thirds of theſe caſes were merely in- <lb/>flammatory, being either pleuriſies,
            peripneu- <lb/>monies, quinſeys, rheumatiſms with fevers, or <lb/>the like. For the
            reſt, they were moſtly ver- <lb/>nal agues, with a few fluxes, and other caſual
            <lb/>diſtempers: and theſe likewiſe with ſome in- <lb/>flammation, as in the beginning
            of the laſt <lb/>campaign. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Now as to the inflammatory diſorders of a <lb/>camp, it may be proper once for all
            to obſerve, <lb/>that upon firſt taking the field, coughs and <pb n="37"/>
            <lb/>ſtitches, with inflammations of the lungs <note place="margin">1744. </note>
            <lb/>and pleura, are the common effects of taking <lb/>cold; but towards the ſummer
            ſolſtice, as the <lb/>weather grows warmer, the breaſt is leſs liable <lb/>to be
            affected, and the colds are rather produc- <lb/>tive of a continued fever, with ſizy
            blood, than <lb/>of any of the above mentioned inflammations. <lb/>Moreover, that this
            fever, with proper ma- <lb/>nagement, may generally be removed in a <lb/>few days; but
            when neglected in the begin- <lb/>ning, by the omitting bleeding, by continuing in
            <lb/>camp, or being carried in waggons to diſtant <lb/>hoſpitals, it becomes at laſt
            very dangerous. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>After the army came into the territory of <lb/>Liſle, an hoſpital was opened at
            Tournay, on <lb/>the 23d of Auguſt; into which were at firſt <lb/>ſent but 50 ſick: and
            theſe being all that were <lb/>taken ill ſince the army croſſed the Scheld, <lb/>were a
            proof how healthful the troups then <lb/>were. But in this ſmall number there appear-
            <lb/>ed a change in the diſtempers, from in- <lb/>flammatory to bilious: moſt of the
            caſes <lb/>were either remitting fevers, or dyſenteries. <lb/>So that now there ſeemed
            only wanting ſome <lb/>alteration of weather, to make the bilious diſ- <lb/>eaſes as
            epidemic as the foregoing cool and <pb n="38"/>
            <lb/>
            <note place="margin">1744. </note>moderate ſummer would allow. Accordingly <lb/>a change
            came; for, from the end of Auguſt <lb/>to the middle of September, there fell a great
            <lb/>deal of rain; and the men who were out on <lb/>forraging parties, were not only
            often wet, but <lb/>the ground whereon the foot encamped, be- <lb/>ing low, retained the
            rain water. Hence, by <lb/>the firſt of October, there were in the hoſpi- <lb/>tal above
            450 ill of the dyſentery; beſides <lb/>ſlighter caſes, that remained in the camp. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>This, however, was the height of the diſ- <lb/>temper; which, conſidering the
            number of <lb/>our troops, was as nothing, compared to its <lb/>frequency in the former
            campaign. The <lb/>reaſon was plain; the laſt ſummer had been <lb/>ſo hot, that by the
            end of June the hu- <lb/>mours had already acquired a high degree of <lb/>acrimony; in
            which ſtate, the rains at Det- <lb/>tingen giving a ſudden and general check to
            <lb/>perſpiration, many were then ſeized at once; <lb/>and from thence ſprung the
            infection, <lb/>which was kept up by hot weather, and <lb/>the privies of a long
            encampment. Where- <lb/>as, by the temperature of this ſummer, the <lb/>dyſentery did
            not appear till very late, and <lb/>then could make no progreſs for want of heat. </p>
          <pb n="39"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The remitting fever of the camp being more <note place="margin">1744. </note>
            <lb/>regular in its appearance than the flux, began <lb/>but a little later than it did
            the year before, <lb/>was frequent in the end of September, but was <lb/>at no time ſo
            general. The ſymptoms were <lb/>alſo more moderate, tho' ſimilar: there was <lb/>rarely
            any yellowneſs, as in the former cam- <lb/>paign; but when the weather grew cold, it
            <lb/>was often joined with a cough, infarction of <lb/>the lungs, or rheumatic pains:
            which ſymp- <lb/>toms, as was ſaid above, did not properly be- <lb/>long to the fever,
            but were only acceſſions to <lb/>it, from extraordinary colds. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The rains were ſucceeded by a tract of fine <lb/>weather, which continued till the
            beginning <lb/>of October; but this again being followed <lb/>with heavy and cold rains,
            the ſickneſs muſt <lb/>have increaſed, had not the campaign ended <lb/>ſoon after. For
            on the 16th of that month, <lb/>ſome of the troops were ſent into winter quar-
            <lb/>ters; and in a few days more, they were fol- <lb/>lowed by all the reſt. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>On breaking up, there were about 1500 <lb/>ſick in the hoſpitals at Tournay, Ghent,
            and <lb/>Bruſſels: which was only the 17th part of all <lb/>that took the field. The
            amount of the deaths <pb n="40"/>
            <lb/>
            <note place="margin">1744. </note>during the campaign, and of thoſe who were left
            <lb/>in hoſpitals at the end thereof, did not exceed <lb/>300. The mildneſs of the
            ſeaſon, the dry en- <lb/>campments, the frequent exerciſe given to the <lb/>troops by
            forraging parties, when the camp <lb/>was fixed at Anſtain, and the early retreat
            <lb/>into winter quarters, all concurred in preſerv- <lb/>ing the health of the army. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The troops returning ſo ſoon and well into <lb/>garriſon, carried with them few
            ſeeds of diſ- <lb/>tempers. The dyſentery had been for ſome <lb/>time on the decline;
            and was but a little re- <lb/>vived by the wet weather. And as half the <lb/>army had
            been hardened by two campaigns, <lb/>the remitting fever was confined in quarters
            <lb/>chiefly to the recruits and new regiments, who <lb/>had encamped this ſummer for
            the firſt time. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The Britiſh returned to the ſame garriſons <lb/>they left. At Bruſſels the general
            hoſpital was <lb/>kept up; but at Bruges and Ghent, none were <lb/>appointed: the
            regimental ſurgeons getting <lb/>barracks for their ſick, with an allowance of
            <lb/>medicines, and all other neceſſaries, at the <lb/>public expence. In each of theſe
            garriſons <lb/>was ſtationed an hoſpital phyſician, to whom <lb/>the ſurgeons were to
            apply occaſionally for aſ- <pb n="41"/>
            <lb/>ſiſtance. Which ſcheme of ſeparate regimen- <note place="margin">1744. </note>
            <lb/>tal infirmaries, tho' only intended to ſave the <lb/>expence of one common and
            great one, an- <lb/>ſwered another purpoſe; which was, that of <lb/>dividing the
            infection, and thereby guarding <lb/>againſt a malignant fever, the common and
            <lb/>fatal conſequence of a large and crouded <lb/>hoſpital. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>At Oſtend remained two battalions, which <lb/>having garriſoned the town during the
            cam- <lb/>paign, had enjoyed good health; with the ex- <lb/>ception of a few autumnal
            agues. The re- <lb/>mitting fever was not known among them; <lb/>and the intermittents,
            with a few gentle fluxes, <lb/>were confined to thoſe ſoldiers only, who by <lb/>reaſon
            of out-guards and night-duty, were <lb/>moſt expoſed to colds and wet. But as a
            <lb/>proof of the healthfulneſs of the place and <lb/>ſeaſon, neither our officers nor
            the inhabitants <lb/>had any diſtemper among them. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="42"/>
        <div type="chapter">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>CHAP. V. </head>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A general account of the <hi rend="sc">Diseases</hi> of the cam- <lb/>paign in
            Flanders, in the year 1745. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">O</hi>n the 25th of April, the Britiſh troops <lb/>
            <note place="margin">1745. </note>took the field, encamping again at An- <lb/>derlecht;
            and on the 9th of May the army <lb/>came up to Briffoel. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The weather being mild, the ſickneſs was <lb/>moderate; but altogether like that of
            former <lb/>campaigns. Inflammatory diſorders were com- <lb/>mon, and, as before, moſtly
            in the ſhape of <lb/>a pleuriſy, or peripneumony: ſeldomer in <lb/>the form of an acute
            rheumatiſm, as the wea- <lb/>ther was yet too cold for tempting the men to <lb/>ſleep on
            the graſs, the common cauſe of the <lb/>diſtemper. The vernal intermittents were alſo
            <lb/>of an inflammatory kind; as were likewiſe <lb/>the few fluxes that appeared: the
            only new <lb/>diſeaſe was the ſmall pox, which came <lb/>from England with the recruits;
            but did not <lb/>ſpread: and at no time have we known <lb/>it of any conſequence in a
            camp. </p>
          <pb n="43"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The battle of Fontenoy was on the 11th, <note place="margin">1745. </note>
            <lb/>on which day the weather was fair, and the <lb/>following night ſo dry and mild,
            that tho' moſt <lb/>of the men lay without cover, and all had <lb/>been extremely
            fatigued, yet no ſickneſs <lb/>enſued. Next day an hoſpital was made at <lb/>Ath, in the
            cazernes of St. Roc, which took in <lb/>about 600 wounded. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>On the 16th of the ſame month the army <lb/>removed from Ath, and encamped at
            Leſſines; <lb/>where it continued till the 30th of June. The <lb/>greateſt part of May
            being dry, and moderate- <lb/>ly warm, was favourable, both to the wound- <lb/>ed, and
            to the men in camp. But June being <lb/>cold and wet, the vernal agues and fluxes re-
            <lb/>turned; and, tho' little affecting the old and <lb/>hardened troops, were ſevere on
            Price's and <lb/>Mordaunt's regiments; which, with the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
              >draughts</hi>, were all new, and had for the <lb/>firſt time encamped at Leſſines. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>From this place the army moved to Gram- <lb/>mont, where it ſtaid ten days: and
            from <lb/>thence marching to Bruſſels, encamped on <lb/>the plain of Dieghem; which
            being a dry, <lb/>open, and elevated field, is reputed the moſt <pb n="44"/>
            <lb/>
            <note place="margin">1745. </note>healthful ground for a camp in the Nether- <lb/>lands.
            From hence, after a month's ſtay, the <lb/>army moved to Vilvorde; where the ſoil be-
            <lb/>ing ſtill dry, the country airy, and the heats <lb/>temperate, the men continued to
            enjoy extraor- <lb/>dinary health. For in the middle of Sep- <lb/>tember, few battalions
            returned above 12 <lb/>ſick altogether; which was as low a number <lb/>as could be
            expected in the beſt quarters. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The temperature of the weather, the dri- <lb/>neſs of the ground, and the little
            fatigue the <lb/>troops underwent, conſpired to make the au- <lb/>tumn, naturally a
            ſickly ſeaſon, extremely <lb/>healthful. The dyſentery had been only fre- <lb/>quent in
            the new regiments, and was eaſily <lb/>cured: neither could the remitting fever
            <lb/>ever be called epidemic. For, tho' it began <lb/>about the end of Auguſt, and was
            the moſt <lb/>frequent diſeaſe through the reſt of the cam- <lb/>paign, yet it was ſo
            inconſiderable, that no bat- <lb/>talion at any time returned above ſeven or <lb/>eight
            ill of that diſtemper; and thoſe with <lb/>milder ſymptoms than had been ſeen in for-
            <lb/>mer campaigns. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It was obſervable, when the troops made <lb/>another ſmall remove, to form a line
            along <pb n="45"/>
            <lb/>the great canal, the ground being low and <note place="margin">1745. </note>
            <lb/>cloſe planted, the effects of moiſture began <lb/>preſently to appear: but upon
            returning to <lb/>the former camp, they were no longer ſeen. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>On the 24th of October, the weather ſtill <lb/>continuing fair and temperate, the
            camp broke <lb/>up, and the troops went into winter quarters. <lb/>Some time before
            this, ten battalions had been <lb/>ſent home; and in the beginning of Novem- <lb/>ber,
            the whole Britiſh infantry, with part of <lb/>the cavalry, being recalled to ſuppreſs
            the re- <lb/>bellion, marched to Willemſtad, and em- <lb/>barked for England. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Thus far an account of the health of the <lb/>main body of our troops: the ſtate of
            the ſe- <lb/>parate corps was as follows. In the end <lb/>of Auguft, Oſtend having
            ſurrendered, the <lb/>garriſon, conſiſting of five Britiſh battalions, <lb/>was
            conducted to Mons; where they ſtaid <lb/>about three weeks. Theſe men had been ſo
            <lb/>healthy, that when they retired upon the ca- <lb/>pitulation, notwithſtanding the
            fatigues of a <lb/>ſiege, they left only ten ſick: but the ſame <lb/>corps being put
            into damp barracks at Mons, <lb/>whilſt the town itſelf was ſurrounded with an
            <lb/>inundation, the autumnal diſeaſes prevailed ſo <pb n="46"/>
            <lb/>
            <note place="margin">1745. </note>much, that in that ſhort time, 250 were ta- <lb/>ken
            ill and left behind, when the reſt march- <lb/>ed to Bruſſels. The caſes were
            dyſenteries, <lb/>remittents, and intermittents; and to theſe <lb/>fevers, as is uſual
            towards the end of autumn, <lb/>coughs, rheumatic pains, and other ſymptoms <lb/>of cold
            were joined: not without ſome mix- <lb/>ture, as it appeared, of the hoſpital fever, ac-
            <lb/>quired by the cloſe and bad accommodation <lb/>they had at Mons. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Handyſide's regiment, another detached <lb/>corps which had come over this ſummer,
            <lb/>was, about the middle of July, ſent into the <lb/>citadel of Antwerp. The air of
            that city is <lb/>moiſt, and the fort is particularly expoſed to <lb/>the damps of the
            neighbouring marſhes. <lb/>The barracks were, moreover, on ground <lb/>floors, and
            extremely damp; in conſequence <lb/>whereof the dyſentery, together with remit-
            <lb/>tents and intermittents, of a bad kind, became <lb/>general. In the beginning of
            October, 163 <lb/>were returned ſick from that battalion only; <lb/>which was five or
            ſix times more than any <lb/>other regiment had in the line. This extraor- <lb/>dinary
            diſproportion may, in part, be imputed <lb/>to the newneſs of the men, but much more <pb
              n="47"/>
            <lb/>to the damps; ſince the other new regiments <note place="margin">1745. </note>
            <lb/>that were then in camp, ſuffered very little: <lb/>and in the town itſelf, fluxes,
            remittents, and <lb/>intermittents, were alſo frequent among the <lb/>inhabitants,
            whilſt the people of Bruſſels en- <lb/>joyed perfect health. When Ghent was ta-
            <lb/>ken, part of Rich's dragoons having eſcaped <lb/>from thence, retired to Antwerp,
            and were <lb/>ſeized with the epidemics of the place; whilſt <lb/>the remainder of that
            regiment, which lay in <lb/>camp, continued entirely free of both fever <lb/>and flux. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Upon the whole, when the campaign end- <lb/>ed, there were left in the ſeveral
            hoſpitals of <lb/>Antwerp, Bruſſels, and Mons, about 1000 <lb/>ſick, including all
            caſes: a very ſmall number, <lb/>conſidering that during this campaign, there <lb/>had
            been at one time in Flanders, beſides the <lb/>cavalry, 29 battalions; whereof ſome had
            ne- <lb/>ver before taken the field. The deaths from <lb/>the beginning to the end of
            the campaign, <lb/>excluſive of thoſe who were killed in battle, <lb/>or died of their
            wounds, did not exceed 200. <lb/>In both this and the laſt ſummer, the heats <lb/>were
            moderate, the troops were little harraſ- <lb/>ſed by fatigues, and, in general, little
            expoſed to <pb n="48"/>
            <lb/>
            <note place="margin">1745. </note>wet cloaths or damps; and the return to win- <lb/>ter
            quarters being early, were ſo many con- <lb/>curring circumſtances to make this, of all,
            <lb/>the moſt healthful campaign. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>CHAP. VI. </head>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A general account of the <hi rend="sc">Diseases</hi> of the cam- <lb/>paign in
            Great Britain, 1745, and 1746. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Little before the end of the campaign <lb/>1745, the three
            battalions of foot <lb/>guards, and ſeven others, embarked in Hol- <lb/>land, and landed
            in the ſouth of England: <lb/>the paſſage was ſhort, and the troops leaving <lb/>the
            field before the nights turned cold, arriv- <lb/>ed in perfect health. The reſt of the
            in- <lb/>fantry having lain longer in camp, embarked <lb/>later in the ſeaſon; and being
            detained long on <lb/>board by contrary winds, arrived ſickly at <lb/>Newcaſtle,
            Holy-iſland and Berwick. For, <lb/>ſome of the men, during the voyage, fell ill <lb/>of
            remitting fevers; which, by the crouds and <lb/>the foul confined air of the hold, were
            ſoon <lb/>converted into a malignant fever of the <lb/>hoſpital. </p>
          <pb n="49"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/> An hoſpital was made at Newcaſtle, in <note place="margin">1745. </note>
            <lb/>which the ſick, as they landed, were lodged; <lb/>and this houſe alſo taking in
            thoſe that fell ill <lb/>in the army under the command of Marſhal <lb/>Wade, the air
            became ſoon corrupted and <lb/>infectious. Not only the nurſes, and thoſe <lb/>who were
            conſtantly in the wards, were there- <lb/>by ſufferers, but alſo the medical attendants,
            <lb/>tho' leſs confined to the putrid air: inſomuch <lb/>that three of the town
            apothecaries, with four <lb/>of their apprentices, and two journeymen, <lb/>were ſeized
            with the contagion, and died. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Ligoniers and Price's regiments landed at <lb/>Holy-iſland. Theſe had embarked in
            perfect <lb/>health, leaving all their ſick behind at Ant- <lb/>werp; but before they
            arrived, were in the <lb/>ſame condition with thoſe that came to New- <lb/>caſtle. The
            diſaſter was unforeſeen, and un- <lb/>provided for. Ninety-ſeven were taken out <lb/>of
            the ſhips ill of the malignant fever, where- <lb/>of 40 died; and the people of the
            place re- <lb/>ceiving the infection, in a ſew weeks buried <lb/>50; which was a ſixth
            part of the inha- <lb/>bitants of that iſland. The ſame fever was <lb/>carried into
            Berwick, by the troops that land- <pb n="50"/>
            <lb/>
            <note place="margin">1745. </note>ed there; but there being fewer ſick, the
            <lb/>diſtemper did not ſpread. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In the beginning of December, a body of <lb/>troops, conſiſting of 12 battalions,
            and 3 regi- <lb/>ments of cavalry, under the command of his <lb/>Royal Highneſs the
            Duke, aſſembled at Litch- <lb/>field. The quakers had made a preſent of <lb/>flannel
            under-waiſtcoats to the men; which <lb/>was a ſeaſonable proviſion for a winter cam-
            <lb/>paign. The march was dry; the army en- <lb/>camped at Packington for three days
            only; at <lb/>Stone, the men lay for one night upon their <lb/>arms: but at all other
            times, being every night <lb/>in quarters, having plenty of ſtraw, fuel and
            <lb/>proviſions, they kept their health as well as <lb/>could be expected in that ſeaſon
            of the year. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Towards the end of December, moſt of the <lb/>infantry were ſent into quarters,
            whilſt the <lb/>cavalry and 1000 foot, advanced to Carliſle. <lb/>The ſick, as they fell
            ill, were left in the towns <lb/>on the road, to the care of the ſurgeons and
            <lb/>apothecaries of the ſeveral places, and were <lb/>well treated. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The troops having ſtaid ſome days at Litch- <lb/>field, a greater number of ſick
            was left in that <lb/>place than in any other; on which account <pb n="51"/>
            <lb/>the work-houſe was fitted up for an hoſpital: <note place="margin">1745. </note>
            <lb/>but there being too many admitted, the com- <lb/>mon fevers became malignant, and
            ſeveral died. <lb/>But in the other towns where the men were <lb/>taken ill, and where
            there was no common <lb/>hoſpital, that fever was unknown: ſo that <lb/>the diſtempers,
            without any malignity, run <lb/>their natural courſe, and generally came to a <lb/>happy
            iſſue. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The autumnal remitting fever, diſguiſed <lb/>with many ſymptoms of cold, could be
            traced <lb/>in the troops which came over from Flan- <lb/>ders, until the froſts in
            December put an end <lb/>to it. But the prevailing diſtempers were <lb/>hard coughs,
            ſtitches, pleuritic and rheumatic <lb/>pains, with a few fluxes, the natural conſe-
            <lb/>quences of expoſition to colds and rains on <lb/>duty, or of wet feet on the march.
            There <lb/>were alſo ſome intermittents; but all with <lb/>ſuch a mixture of coughs and
            infarctions of <lb/>the lungs, as made bleeding the moſt neceſ- <lb/>ſary remedy. In
            general, large and repeat- <lb/>ed bleedings were ſo requiſite, that in every <lb/>town
            through which the troops paſt, and <lb/>where ſick were left behind, the phyſician
            <lb/>of the army believed the ſurgeons and apo- <pb n="52"/>
            <lb/>
            <note place="margin">1745. </note>thecaries of the place more than half inſtruct-
            <lb/>ed about the cure of the patients committed <lb/>to them, when he had inculcated
            the neceſ- <lb/>ſity of large and repeated bleedings: for the <lb/>men were at this time
            well fed, and by the <lb/>colds their blood had become extremely ſizy. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Carliſle was inveſted in the beginning of Ja- <lb/>nuary, and taken in a few days.
            The ſhort- <lb/>neſs of the time, the mildneſs of the weather <lb/>for the ſeaſon, and
            the good cover which the <lb/>troops found near the works, made the ſick- <lb/>neſs ſo
            inconſiderable, that only one died there. <lb/>And during the whole expedition, this
            body <lb/>did not loſe above 40 men; tho' there had <lb/>been in all between 600 and 700
            ſick. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>On the 10th of February the Duke's army <lb/>marched from Edinburgh towards Perth.
            It <lb/>conſiſted of 14 battalions, and three regiments <lb/>of cavalry; which being too
            large a number to <lb/>be all billetted in ſo ſmall a place, two battalions <lb/>were
            quartered in churches. Proviſions were in <lb/>plenty, but the quarters were generally
            cold; ſo <lb/>that a great many fell ill of the common in- <lb/>flammatory diſtempers of
            the winter, and in a <lb/>greater degree than before. The hard coughs <pb n="53"/>
            <lb/>in particular, with inflammations of the pleura <note place="margin">1746. </note>
            <lb/>and lungs were moſt frequent. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In the beginning of March the troops re- <lb/>moved from Perth to Montroſe, and
            from <lb/>thence to Aberdeen, leaving 300 ſick behind <lb/>them; who were all well
            accommodated in <lb/>the corporation halls and private houſes of <lb/>theſe towns. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Till the end of March, the whole infantry <lb/>was quartered in Aberdeen; but
            afterwards <lb/>nine battalions were cantoned at Inverurie and <lb/>Strathbogie: and at
            this time, one battalion <lb/>more landed and joined the army. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The weather being all this time extremely <lb/>ſharp, with froſt and ſnow and
            eaſterly winds, <lb/>the diſtempers continued to be highly in- <lb/>flammatory, tho' of
            the ſame kind with what <lb/>uſually occur in winterquarters. Whilſt the <lb/>men
            ſuffered by cold beds, guards and out- <lb/>duties, or by their own miſmanagement,
            <lb/>neither the ſeaſon nor climate gave inflam- <lb/>matory diſorders to the officers,
            who had warm <lb/>quarters, and were leſs expoſed to cold: but <lb/>in the beginning of
            March, when the wea- <lb/>ther was very ſharp, ſome of them were ſeiz- <lb/>ed with the
            gout. </p>
          <pb n="54"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>
            <note place="margin">1746. </note>The ſick were well lodged in the hoſpital
            <lb/>belonging to the town, and in other large <lb/>houſes; where having a free air,
            they were <lb/>preſerved from the hoſpital fever. Including <lb/>thoſe at Inverurie and
            Strathbogie, about 400 <lb/>ſick were left behind, when the army moved; <lb/>but of this
            number a ſmall proportion died. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>On the 23d of April the army firſt <lb/>encamped at Cullen; the next day it paſſed
            <lb/>the Spey: on the 27th <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>* N. B. The new ſtyle is continued. </p>
            </note> after the battle of <lb/>Culloden, the troops advanced to Inverneſs, <lb/>and
            encamped on the ſouth ſide of the town. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>At Strathbogie and Inverurie the duty had <lb/>been conſtant, to guard againſt a
            ſurprize; one <lb/>day's march had been long and rainy, the en- <lb/>campment early, and
            many colds caught from <lb/>wading the rivers: all theſe circumſtances con- <lb/>curred
            to make the ſickneſs conſiderable. Be- <lb/>fore the army reached Inverneſs, about 60 or
            <lb/>70 men were taken ill, were left in towns <lb/>by the way; and after the encampment
            <lb/>the inflammatory diſtempers daily increaſed. <lb/>Theſe were the more ſevere, as
            the ſeaſon <lb/>was early, the climate cold, and the camp ex- <lb/>poſed in an open
            country to piercing winds. <pb n="55"/>
            <lb/>The pleuriſies and inflammations of the lungs, <note place="margin">1746. </note>
            <lb/>in particular, were violent, and tended quickly <lb/>to ſuppuration; if large and
            repeated bleed- <lb/>ings, and other parts of cure, were not <lb/>ſpeedily uſed. </p>
          <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="9"/>
        </div>
        <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="55"/>
      </div>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="309"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
