<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: Considerations on the Bill of Registers</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">Considerations on the Bill for Obliging all Parishes in this Kingdom
              to keep proper Registers of Births, Deaths, and Marriages: and for Raising therefrom a
              Fund towards the Support of the Hospital for the Maintenance and Education of Exposed
              and Deserted Young Children. </title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T161151</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T161151"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for M. Cooper, at the Globe, in Paternoster-Row,
                  1759.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1759</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="2"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="39"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">John Rylands University Library of Manchester</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW104430263</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Public welfare and institutional"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="2"/>
    <body>
      <pb n=""/>
      <figure>
        <figDesc>An ornamental horizontal column, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <head rend="align-center space">
        <lb/>A <lb/><hi rend="size(2.0) space">LETTER, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </hi>
      </head>
      <salute rend="indent space">
        <lb/>SIR, </salute>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(4)">H</hi>AVING lately wrote you my ſen- <lb/>timents fully, on a project
        of <lb/>giving the <hi rend="italic">Foundling Hoſpital</hi> a <lb/>National Eſtabliſhment,
        with a <lb/>fix'd Revenue by Act of Parliament, I was <lb/>ſomewhat ſurpriſed at your
        inſiſting, in <lb/>conſequence of it, on my making them <lb/>publick; for no man is better
        acquainted <lb/>than yourſelf with my backwardneſs to <lb/>commence Author, even of a
        Pamphlet. <lb/>However, this averſion muſt, at preſent, give <lb/>way to what you are
        pleaſed to urge; that <lb/>it may, in your opinion, be of ſervice to <lb/>my Country, as a
        Bill is daily expected to be <pb n="4"/>
        <lb/>brought into Parliament for that Purpoſe, <lb/>which was attempted laſt Seſſions,
        intitled, <lb/><hi rend="italic">A Bill for obliging all Pariſhes in this King- <lb/>dom to
          keep proper Regiſters of Births, Deaths, <lb/>and Marriages; and for raiſing therefrom a
          <lb/>Fund towards the Support of the Hoſpital, <lb/>for the Maintenance and Education of
          expoſed <lb/>and deſerted young Children</hi>. I ſhall therefore, <lb/>without any
        heſitation, prepare to obey your <lb/>commands, and to do my duty, as an <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Engliſhman</hi>, by laying the ſubſtance of what <lb/>I wrote you before the
        Publick, with the <lb/>ſame freedom and ſincerity which I uſed <lb/>in correſponding with a
        Friend. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But here I muſt beg leave to premiſe, <lb/>that it is impoſſible for me not to be
        ſenſible, <lb/>that I ſhall find many perſons, of good and <lb/>benevolent diſpoſitions,
        prejudiced againſt this <lb/>attempt, as far as it may affect the Hoſpital, <lb/>on account
        of the reverence which they <lb/>implicitly pay to every thing that wears the <lb/>name of a
        Charity. The Virtue of Charity, <lb/>I readily agree with them, is moſt noble and
        <lb/>divine; and the abuſe of it has, perhaps, <pb n="5"/>
        <lb/>added to the proof of its Excellency. <hi rend="italic">Cor- <lb/>ruptio Optimi fit
          Peſſima</hi>, is an Obſervation of <lb/>long experience, and great authority; and, <lb/>as
          <hi rend="italic">England</hi> is a ſoil moſt natural to the ge- <lb/>nuine Plant, the
        hurtful imitation of it, to <lb/>a very pernicious degree, has, from time to <lb/>time, been
        here moſt induſtriouſly planted. <lb/>Our anceſtors, many years ago, ſold their
        <lb/>eſtates, and forſook their wives and children, <lb/>all for the faſhionable Charity of
        thoſe times, <lb/>that of reſcuing the <hi rend="italic">Holy-Land</hi> from the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Saracens</hi>. We know the event of the <hi rend="italic">Cru-
          <lb/>ſado</hi>; in moſt Parts of <hi rend="italic">Europe</hi> the evil of it <lb/>was
        ſeverely felt, but, in <hi rend="italic">England</hi>, where it <lb/>found fuel, in the
        valour and generoſity of <lb/>the People, it became a plague, that threat- <lb/>en'd with
        deſtruction the whole realm, <lb/>from the King to the Freeholder. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To this Charity ſucceeded an univerſal <lb/>and unbounded Zeal, for the eſtabliſhment
        <lb/>of Religious Houſes, under various titles, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Monaſteries</hi>, <hi
          rend="italic">Nunneries</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Abbeys</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
          >Priories</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Chaun- <lb/>tries</hi>, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.
          &amp;c. &amp;c.</hi> Upon which laſt men- <lb/>tioned kind of Charity, I ſhall only
        remark, <pb n="6"/>
        <lb/>that with it reign'd Tyranny, Poverty, and <lb/>Ignorance, and from its ſuppreſſion
        aroſe <lb/>Liberty, Trade, and Learning. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Theſe examples of the effects of ill- <lb/>directed Charity ſufficiently prove, that
        the <lb/>Spirit of it may be fatally exerted; but if <lb/>the general Plan of a <hi
          rend="italic">Foundling-Hoſpital</hi>, of <lb/>the prodigious extent now ſeeming to be
        <lb/>aimed at, were a proper one, it ſhould have <lb/>been adopted, at the time when the
        ſup- <lb/>preſſed Religious Houſes might well have <lb/>been converted into <hi
          rend="italic">Foundling-Hoſpitals</hi>, to <lb/>which ſome ſay, they had a propenſity.
        <lb/>They were certainly ſufficient in number, <lb/>and their revenues a fund already
        eſtabliſhed, <lb/>which, at preſent, will be very difficult to be <lb/>found, unleſs the
        preſent poſſeſſors of them <lb/>ſhould charitably apply to Parliament for a <lb/>power to
        ſurrender thoſe eſtates to this our <lb/>preſent faſhionable Inſtitution: However, it
        <lb/>may be but juſtice here to confeſs, that the <lb/>foundation of a few houſes to ſerve
        for a <lb/>retirement to venerable men, grown old and <lb/>infirm, who had ſpent their youth
        in the <pb n="7"/>
        <lb/>cultivation of Piety and Learning; or, as an <lb/>aſylum for virtuous and devout women,
        re- <lb/>duced by the various accidents of life, does <lb/>not convey a diſpleaſing or
        ridiculous idea; but <lb/>it was the exceſs and abuſe, which occaſioned <lb/>the total
        ſuppreſſion of all Religious Houſes <lb/>whatever; and the ſame cauſes may produce <lb/>the
        like effects, in regard to theſe Hoſpitals, <lb/>ſhould this Bill paſs into a Law. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When this Hoſpital was firſt erected, by <lb/>Charter granted by his Majeſty, under the
        <lb/>Great Seal, bearing date the 17th day of <lb/><hi rend="italic">October</hi>, 1739, it
        was on the ſuggeſtion, <q rend="italic">To <lb/>prevent the frequent Murders committed on
          <lb/>poor miſerable Infants, by their Parents, to hide <lb/>their Shame, and the inhumane
          Cuſtom of expoſing <lb/>new-born young Children to periſh in the <lb/>Streets, or training
          them up in Idleneſs, Beg- <lb/>gary, and Theft. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>So laudable a Deſign ſoon found in this <lb/>opulent city and kingdom, generous and
        <lb/>compaſſionate Minds, who contributed largely <lb/>to an Eſtabliſhment, which they
        judged capa- <lb/>ble of producing ſuch ſalutary and deſirable <lb/>effects; and the Liſts
        of Benefactions, with <pb n="8"/>
        <lb/>the Names of the ſeveral Benefactors of both <lb/>Sexes, hung up in the <hi
          rend="italic">Foundling-Hoſpital</hi>, will <lb/>do laſting honour to the memory of the
        No- <lb/>bility and Gentry of this age and kingdom, <lb/>for their generous Contributions to
        ſo pro- <lb/>miſing an Undertaking. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It was then expected by many, eſpecially <lb/>by Gentlemen who had travelled into
        foreign <lb/>countries, and obſerved the method and <lb/>regulation of the beſt ordered
        Hoſpitals of <lb/>this kind abroad, that the ſame method <lb/>would have been adopted and
        obſerved in <lb/>this Hoſpital, by admitting children by a <lb/>wheel of a proper ſize,
        which, on the ring- <lb/>ing of a bell by the perſon who ſhould bring <lb/>the child to the
        Hoſpital, might be turned <lb/>round by the porter or ſervant attending on <lb/>behalf of
        the Hoſpital, and the child brought <lb/>in be taken care of, without aſking any
        <lb/>queſtion whatſoever of the perſon who brought <lb/>it, or making any inquiry after
        them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Had this method been ſtrictly purſued, it <lb/>would not only have effectually anſwered
        the <lb/>good ends propoſed, of covering the mother's <pb n="9"/>
        <lb/>ſhame, and preventing the murder of an in- <lb/>fant, which might, in time, have been
        of <lb/>uſe to the publick; but it is highly probable, <lb/>that the children, brought in
        this manner to <lb/>the Hoſpital, would not have proved very <lb/>numerous; and,
        conſequently, the liberal <lb/>contributions of the Nobility and Gentry, <lb/>made ſoon
        after the eſtabliſhment, would have <lb/>been fully ſufficient to have provided for <lb/>all
        the objects of Charity thus brought. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From what motives a method ſo rea- <lb/>ſonable, ſo obvious, and ſo conformable to
        <lb/>the tenor of the Charter, was laid aſide, I <lb/>ſhall not inquire. It is enough to
        obſerve, <lb/>that the quitting this plain and eaſy method, <lb/>and taking in children, at
        firſt by way of <lb/>advertiſement and balloting, in numbers <lb/>of thirty or forty at a
        time (when uſually <lb/>many more appeared than could be taken <lb/>in) at firſt to two
        months old, and after- <lb/>wards proceeding to a twelvemonth old; <lb/>and from taking in
        thirty or forty at <lb/>a time, to taking in as many as ſhould <lb/>be offered from time to
        time, has ſwelled <pb n="10"/>
        <lb/>the expences of this undertaking to ſuch <lb/>an enormous degree, that it now requires,
        <lb/>over and above their private Revenues, an <lb/>additional aid from Parliament of fifty
        <lb/>thouſand pounds a year to maintain it, <lb/>which muſt continually increaſe every year,
        <lb/>ſo long as this extenſive Scheme is purſued, <lb/>though it is already not much ſhort
        of the <lb/>intereſt of a million and half of mo- <lb/>ney raiſed for the ſervice of the
        pub- <lb/>lick; and this, at a time when we are <lb/>obliged, for our neceſſary defence in a
        juſt <lb/>war, againſt our ancient and perfidious <lb/>enemy, to raiſe for the current
        ſervice of <lb/>the year more money, by ſeveral millions <lb/>than was ever raiſed in one
        year in any former <lb/>war. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Hitherto, indeed, the Governors of this <lb/>Hoſpital have been contented to apply to
        <lb/>Parliament for annual ſupplies, to provide <lb/>for the great expences they are at.
        They <lb/>now apply to Parliament for a fixed and <lb/>perpetual revenue to be ſettled for
        the uſe <lb/>of this Hoſpital: What it may amount to, <pb n="11"/>
        <lb/>if this Bill ſhould paſs into a law, is at <lb/>preſent very uncertain. The higheſt
        eſtima- <lb/>tion which I have heard of it, has not <lb/>amounted to above 10,000<hi
          rend="italic">l.</hi> a year, which <lb/>can, by no means, be ſuppoſed a revenue
        <lb/>equivalent to the expences, which they muſt <lb/>needs be at, in the proſecution of
        this ex- <lb/>tenſive Plan. It would ſeem therefore, that <lb/>the chief view of the
        promoters of this <lb/>Bill is to get their plan approved, and adopted <lb/>at any rate;
        and, when they have obtained <lb/>ſuch a Parliamentary Sanction, they will <lb/>think
        themſelves ſecure of not being aban- <lb/>doned, and, in the end, gain the point <lb/>which
        they propoſe, to wit, to lay the <lb/>enormous charge of this Hoſpital on the <lb/>publick,
        and to engage the Parliament to <lb/>provide for it, how immenſe ſoever the <lb/>expence may
        prove; which, in time, may <lb/>probably ſwell what was at firſt propoſed as <lb/>a
        voluntary Charity, into a Corporation of the <lb/>greateſt revenue of any in the kingdom. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By the accounts delivered into Parliament <lb/>laſt Seſſion, it appears, that the
        Receipts <pb n="12"/>
        <lb/>for accompt of the Hoſpital, from its Com- <lb/>mencement to <hi rend="italic"
          >December</hi> the 31ſt, 1757, have <lb/>amounted to upwards of the Sum of 166,000<hi
          rend="italic">l.</hi>
        <lb/>and that, in all that time, no more than 105 <lb/>children have been put out, <hi
          rend="italic">viz.</hi> 62 boys, <lb/>and 43 girls, which is an expence, for all <lb/>the
        children put out to that time, which <lb/>amounts to upwards of 1500<hi rend="italic"
          >l.</hi> for every <lb/>child ſo put out, to that time. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Whoever peruſes the Bill, as laſt printed, <lb/>by order of the Houſe of Commons, will
        find <lb/>Objections, which may be made almoſt to <lb/>every Clauſe, as it now ſtands,
        which, it is <lb/>hoped, will either be clear'd up, or altered, <lb/>as it may paſs through
        the Committee. In <lb/>the mean time, I ſhall beg leave to make <lb/>ſuch Obſervations as
        have occurred to me, <lb/>which I ſubmit to your better judgment. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As to the firſt and ſecond Clauſes, it does <lb/>not appear that any complaints have
        ever <lb/>been made, that the preſent method of regi- <lb/>ſtering Births, Deaths, and
        Marriages, has <lb/>been found liable to great inconveniences, <lb/>though, perhaps, in ſome
        particulars, there <pb n="13"/>
        <lb/>might be alterations and amendments made <lb/>by which thoſe of Births and Burials
        might <lb/>be rendered more exact and uſeful; but, <lb/>ſurely, by the late Marriage Act,
        ſufficient <lb/>care was taken, not only for the duly ſolem- <lb/>nizing, but the punctual
        regiſtering of all <lb/>marriages whatſoever ſo ſolemnized; but, why <lb/>may not this be
        done, by an Act preſcribing <lb/>thoſe amendments to the miniſters and clerks <lb/>of every
        Pariſh, full as effectually, and at a much <lb/>cheaper rate, than by erecting this General
        <lb/>Regiſter Office, in ſo very expenſive and <lb/>extraordinary a manner, which, at beſt,
        can <lb/>only contain the Duplicates of what is con- <lb/>tained in the original Pariſh
        Regiſter Book, <lb/>which muſt always be of greater authority, <lb/>than any Duplicate or
        Copy taken from them? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>And, as for the application of the produce <lb/>of this tax, for the benefit of the <hi
          rend="italic">Foundling- <lb/>Hoſpital</hi>, by the third Clauſe, there ſeems to <lb/>be
        no more reaſon for giving this extraordinary <lb/>aſſiſtance to that Charity in particular,
        than <lb/>to any other Charity eſtabliſhed in the <lb/>kingdom. </p>
      <pb n="14"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By the fourth Clauſe, a Regiſter General <lb/>is to be appointed by the Governors and
        <lb/>Guardians of the Hoſpital, who, together <lb/>with a competent number of clerks, are to
        <lb/>have ſufficient ſalaries appointed to them, <lb/>and the Regiſter General is to provide
        a ſuffi- <lb/>cient quantity of books and paper, properly <lb/>ruled and titled, to be
        divided into ſeveral <lb/>columns, for which he is to be paid at the <lb/>rate of one penny
        for each folio, or two <lb/>pence for every ſheet of paper ſo ruled and <lb/>titled, by the
        Churchwardens of every Pariſh <lb/>in the kingdom; and to ſupply all the ſaid <lb/>ſeveral
        Pariſhes with the like books and paper <lb/>at the ſame rate, from time to time, as often
        <lb/>as there ſhall be occaſion; which ſeems to <lb/>be a prodigious perquiſite deſigned to
        the <lb/>Regiſter General, for providing ſuch books <lb/>and paper to a perpetuity. And,
        whereas, <lb/>by the late Marriage Act, the new books for <lb/>the regiſter of Marriages,
        ordered to be <lb/>provided by each Pariſh, were allowed to <lb/>be provided by the
        Churchwardens of each <lb/>Pariſh, wherever they thought fit, this <pb n="15"/>
        <lb/>Bill makes the providing ſuch books and <lb/>paper a perpetual monopoly, in favour of
        the <lb/>Regiſter General. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the fifth Clauſe, preſcribing the manner <lb/>of regiſtering Deaths; the ſecond
        column, <lb/>directed to contain the names, profeſſions, or <lb/>additions of the parents
        deceaſed, will be, in <lb/>a number of caſe of the deaths of old people, <lb/>impoſſible to
        be complied with: And, though, <lb/>in the eleventh Clauſe, the occupier of the <lb/>houſe,
        in which any perſon ſhall die, is <lb/>obliged to give notice in writing of thoſe
        <lb/>ſeveral particulars only, ſo far as the ſame <lb/>can be known, or conveniently
        obtained, <lb/>yet this fifth Clauſe poſitively enjoins the <lb/>officiating miniſter to
        enter the regiſter of <lb/>the Death, in the manner above-mentioned. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The ſixth Clauſe, relating to the regiſter- <lb/>ing of Marriages, which were ſo
        thoroughly <lb/>well provided for by the late Marriage Act, <lb/>ſeems wholly needleſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The ſeventh and eighth Clauſes ſeem <lb/>deſigned to ſecure this good job, for the
        <lb/>Regiſter General, by providing the books and <pb n="16"/>
        <lb/>paper for Duplicates, as has been before <lb/>obſerved. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By the ninth Clauſe it appears very difficult <lb/>to oblige ſuch perſons to pay, who
        either <lb/>do not chuſe to chriſten their children, or <lb/>Anabaptiſts, who do not baptize
        children, <lb/>till grown up to maturity, or Quakers, who <lb/>do not baptize at all; nor is
        any method <lb/>preſcribed how to deal with either Ana- <lb/>baptiſts, or Quakers, who do
        not give due <lb/>notice of their child being named, ſo as to <lb/>enforce them to pay
        according to this Act. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By the 10th Clauſe, a very extraordinary <lb/>favour is done to the parents of
        illegitimate <lb/>children, who are exempted from giving any <lb/>notice of the birth of the
        child, but may <lb/>have the child publickly baptized, named, <lb/>and regiſtered, as
        illegitimate, at the charge <lb/>of the pariſh; and whereas, hitherto, the <lb/>bringing a
        baſtard into the world has always <lb/>been deemed an action deſerving ſome puniſh-
        <lb/>ment, or diſcouragement, at leaſt, it is now <lb/>rewarded. </p>
      <pb n="17"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The twelfth, thirteenth, fourteenth, and <lb/>fifteenth Clauſes, oblige the married
        couple <lb/>to give notice of their Marriage in writing <lb/>to the Pariſh-Clerk, though he
        is preſent at <lb/>the wedding, and the Clerk to give the ſaid <lb/>notice to the
        officiating Miniſter, who is <lb/>obliged, immediately after the ſame is delivered <lb/>to
        him, to enter the ſame three times over, <lb/>to wit, once by virtue of the Marriage Act,
        <lb/>and twice by virtue of this Act, as well as <lb/>to file the notices in order; the
        Pariſh-Clerk <lb/>is likewiſe obliged to give immediate notice <lb/>to the Churchwardens, or
        one of them, that <lb/>they may forthwith demand and receive the <lb/>rates herein aſſeſſed,
        which will oblige one <lb/>of the Churchwardens to be preſent at every <lb/>wedding. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By the ſixteenth Clauſe, the rate for a <lb/>Baptiſm and Burial is aſſeſſed at
        eight-pence <lb/>each, and is the ſame for the greateſt peer <lb/>or the meaneſt commoner. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By the ſeventeenth Clauſe, the rates on <lb/>Marriages are ſomewhat varied, <hi
          rend="italic">viz.</hi> 10<hi rend="italic">s.</hi> on <lb/>Marriages by prerogative
        licence, 2<hi rend="italic">s.</hi> for Mar- <pb n="18"/>
        <lb/>riages by common licence, and 6<hi rend="italic">d.</hi> on Mar- <lb/>riages by banns. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By the eighteenth Clauſe, the Poor's <lb/>Rate is made chargeable only for theſe ſeve-
        <lb/>ral rates for ſuch poor as ſtand on the Poor's <lb/>Books already; and by the tenth
        Clauſe, for <lb/>illegitimate children, brought to be baptized <lb/>and regiſtered. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By the nineteenth Clauſe, in the begin- <lb/>ning, it is only ſaid, that the
        Churchwarden <lb/>or Churchwardens, Chapelwarden or Chapel- <lb/>wardens, Overſeer or
        Overſeers, of the Poor, <lb/>ſhall meet to compare the regiſters and <lb/>duplicates, with
        the ſeveral notices required <lb/>to be given; but the latter part of the ſaid <lb/>Clauſe
        directs, that the ſaid Miniſter, as well <lb/>as the Churchwarden or Churchwardens,
        <lb/>Chapelwarden or Chapelwardens, Overſeer or <lb/>Overſeers, ſhall ſign the regiſter and
        dupli- <lb/>cate, or duplicates, and enter thereon the <lb/>time when the ſame were ſo
        ſigned. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Byt the 20th Clauſe, it is made felony, <lb/>(ſuppoſed, without benefit of the clergy)
        <lb/>wilfully to deface any ſuch regiſter or <pb n="19"/>
        <lb/>duplicate, which is adding to the miſchief <lb/>of making capital offences too
        numerous. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By the twenty-firſt and twenty-ſecond <lb/>Clauſes, the method is preſcribed of
        recover- <lb/>ing the penalties from offenders againſt this <lb/>Act, in a ſummary way,
        before a Juſtice of <lb/>peace, of the diſtrict wherein ſuch perſon <lb/>ſhall reſide; the
        one half of which is to go <lb/>to the informer, and the other to the <hi rend="italic"
          >Found- <lb/>ling-Hoſpital</hi>, which is ſomething very ex- <lb/>traordinary, that the
        penalty for breach of <lb/>a law ſhould be made payable to a particular <lb/>Corporation, as
        well as the method of en- <lb/>forcing it in ſo ſummary a manner, by one <lb/>Juſtice of
        peace, eſpecially, when it is con- <lb/>ſidered, that any ſuch ſuppoſed offender is <lb/>to
        contend with a Corporation, that has an <lb/>income of 50,000<hi rend="italic">l.</hi> a
        Year. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The twenty-third Clauſe only obliges the <lb/>Churchwardens, Chapelwardens, or
        Overſeers <lb/>of the Poor, to deliver to the Collectors of <lb/>the Land-tax the ſaid
        duplicates, and to <lb/>pay to them the money which ſhall appear <lb/>to be due for the
        ſame. </p>
      <pb n="20"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By the twenty-fourth, twenty-fifth, twen- <lb/>ty-ſixth, twenty-eighth, and
        twenty-ninth <lb/>Clauſes there is an allowance of 5<hi rend="italic">s.</hi> in the
        <lb/>pound to be paid to the officiating Miniſter, <lb/>for his trouble in making the ſaid
        entries in <lb/>the ſaid regiſters, and duplicates, and com- <lb/>paring, correcting and
        ſigning the ſame; 1<hi rend="italic">s.</hi>6<hi rend="italic">d.</hi>
        <lb/>in the pound to the Pariſh-Clerk, for his <lb/>receiving the ſaid notices; 3<hi
          rend="italic">d.</hi> in the pound <lb/>to the Collector of the Land-tax, for recei-
        <lb/>ving the money, and paying it to the Re- <lb/>ceiver-General; and 3<hi rend="italic"
          >d.</hi> in the pound to the <lb/>Receiver-General, for paying the ſame to <lb/>the
        Treaſurer of the <hi rend="italic">Foundling-Hoſpital</hi> for <lb/>the time being: All
        which is excluſive of <lb/>the charge of purchaſing, or erecting the <lb/>General Regiſter
        Office in <hi rend="italic">London</hi>, and the <lb/>payment of the ſalaries to the
        Regiſter Ge- <lb/>neral, and the Clerks employed by him, for <lb/>their attendance in the
        ſaid Office; where- <lb/>upon I beg leave to obſerve, </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I. That there is no inſtance of any other <lb/>Act of Parliament, where poundage out of
        a <lb/>tax raiſed is given to a Miniſter, in conſider- <lb/>ation of his doing his duty. </p>
      <pb n="21"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>II. It is very doubtful whether any offici- <lb/>ating Miniſter will think himſelf
        ſufficiently <lb/>paid by this, for his extraordinary trouble <lb/>in entering ſo many
        regiſters, for moſt of <lb/>which he will have but two-pence, and for <lb/>many, no more
        than three half-pence apiece. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>III. Suppoſing divers officiating Miniſters <lb/>to have been employed in the courſe of
        a <lb/>year, in performing the offices of Chriſten- <lb/>ings, Burials or Marriages, and
        making the <lb/>entries directed, which of them is to receive <lb/>the gratuity or allowance
        of 5<hi rend="italic">s.</hi> in the pound, <lb/>on the money collected by virtue of this
        Act? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>IV. That the payment of the produce of <lb/>any tax whatſoever, to any Corporation, by
        <lb/>the Receiver General of any county, without <lb/>firſt paſſing thro' the <hi
          rend="italic">Exchequer</hi>, is unconſti- <lb/>tutional. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>V. That the charge of erecting or pur- <lb/>chaſing an office for the Regiſter General,
        <lb/>together with the payment of ſalaries to him, <lb/>and Clerks employed by him, and
        other in- <lb/>cident charges, may be reaſonably ſuppoſed <lb/>to amount to 3<hi
          rend="italic">s.</hi> in the pound more, on all <pb n="22"/>
        <lb/>the money raiſed by this Act, which added <lb/>to the other 7<hi rend="italic">s.</hi>
        will make 10<hi rend="italic">s.</hi> in the pound, <lb/>or one half of the money raiſed,
        which is <lb/>ſuppoſed to be much more chargeable than <lb/>the raiſing any other tax
        whatſoever, and <lb/>ought the leſs to be allowed, as this Office <lb/>will interfere both
        with the Regiſter Office <lb/>of each Dioceſe, as alſo with the Heralds <lb/>Office, who
        have both of them a prior right <lb/>to an Office of this ſort, to the <hi rend="italic"
          >Foundling- <lb/>Hoſpital</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The embarraſſment of Burials, by the Pro- <lb/>hibition in the 27th Clauſe to remove a
        dead <lb/>corpſe into another pariſh, before a certificate <lb/>is obtained from the Clerk
        of the Pariſh where <lb/>the death happens, of the delivery of due <lb/>notice, of the
        regiſtry being made, and the <lb/>money being paid, to with the ſum of 8<hi rend="italic"
          >d.</hi>
        <lb/>may be attended with exceeding bad conſe- <lb/>quences, when any death happens by an
        in- <lb/>fectious diſeaſe, if either the Occupier of the <lb/>houſe, or the Miniſter, or the
        Clerk of the <lb/>Pariſh, or the Churchwarden, be out of the <lb/>way; for the notice muſt
        firſt be given by <pb n="23"/>
        <lb/>the Occupier of the houſe to the Clerk, who <lb/>muſt deliver it to the officiating
        Miniſter, and <lb/>likewiſe acquaint the Churchwardens; the <lb/>Miniſter muſt enter it
        twice over, and file the <lb/>Notice, and the money muſt be paid to the <lb/>Churchwarden,
        and a Certificate of its being <lb/>paid muſt be given; and all this muſt be <lb/>done
        before the Body can be removed, for <lb/>the ſecurity of 8<hi rend="italic">d.</hi> And it
        being ſo common <lb/>a practice in <hi rend="italic">London</hi>, and other great towns,
        <lb/>to remove Bodies to ſome Hall, or other <lb/>publick place, aſſoon as conveniently may
        be <lb/>done, for the eaſe of all the Living in the <lb/>houſe, where the Death has
        happened, this <lb/>ſtrict prohibition to remove the dead Body, <lb/>before ſuch Certificate
        obtained, cannot but <lb/>frequently occaſion great delays and inconve- <lb/>niences, and
        may poſſibly ſometimes commu- <lb/>nicate infection. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By the 30th Clauſe it is enacted, that the <lb/>Copies of any ſuch Entry in any
        Duplicates <lb/>being examined, and atteſted by the ſaid <lb/>Regiſter General or his
        Deputy, ſhall be re- <lb/>ceived as evidence, in any Court of Record <pb n="24"/>
        <lb/>or <hi rend="italic">Niſi-prius</hi>, or any other place whatſoever; <lb/>which gives
        greater authority to a Copy of <lb/>a Duplicate (which Duplicate is but a Copy <lb/>of the
        original Regiſter) than has hitherto <lb/>been given by the Law to a Certificate of the
        <lb/>Clerk of a Pariſh, from an original Entry <lb/>faithfully kept in the Pariſh Regiſter. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By the 31ſt and 32d Clauſes, Abſtracts <lb/>from theſe Duplicates are to be made, and
        <lb/>annually laid before the Parliament by the <lb/>ſaid Regiſter, and Copies thereof
        annually <lb/>delivered to the Lords of Trade and Planta- <lb/>tions, to the end that the
        Sum collected and <lb/>raiſed by this Act may be known, as alſo <lb/>the number of Births,
        Deaths, and Marri- <lb/>ages, which are regiſtered therein; but it <lb/>does not appear to
        what purpoſe theſe Liſts <lb/>are to be prepared, and laid, with ſo much <lb/>parade and
        expence, before the Parliament, <lb/>and the Lords of Trade and Plantations, <lb/>when, by a
        very ſhort Act to oblige all <lb/>Miniſters and Pariſh-Clerks to be exact in <lb/>their
        regiſters of Births and Deaths, ſuch <lb/>a Liſt could be eaſily procured, as it has <pb
          n="25"/>
        <lb/>been hitherto, from the Pariſh-Clerks, within <lb/>the Bills of mortality; and it will
        hardly be <lb/>pretended, but that effectual care has been <lb/>taken by the late Marriage
        Act, to have all <lb/>Marriages exactly regiſtered; and an ac- <lb/>count of all Births,
        Deaths, and Marriages, <lb/>might eaſily be tranſmitted from every Pariſh <lb/>to the
        Regiſter Office of the Biſhop of each <lb/>dioceſe, without occaſioning ſuch an immenſe
        <lb/>expence and trouble, and ſubjecting the <lb/>people to the many inconveniencies and
        <lb/>penalties, which may be occaſioned by this <lb/>Bill, if it ſhould paſs into an Act. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The 33d and 34th Clauſes oblige the <lb/>Pariſh-Clerks, as well in their individual
        <lb/>capacity, as in that of a company, to lay <lb/>weekly, and yearly, ſeveral accounts, as
        <lb/>mentioned, before his Majeſty, and the Lord- <lb/>Mayor of <hi rend="italic"
          >London</hi>; and, by the 35th, it is <lb/>provided, that nothing in this Act ſhall take
        <lb/>away or alter Miniſters fees, or hinder a <lb/>Regiſter being kept of Births, Burials,
        or <lb/>Marriages, within this kingdom, by the Mi- <lb/>niſter of any Pariſh in <hi
          rend="italic">England</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Wales</hi>, or <pb n="26"/>
        <lb/>Town of <hi rend="italic">Berwick upon Tweed</hi>, or a Tran- <lb/>ſcript thereof being
        ſent to the Regiſtry of <lb/>the dioceſe, wherein ſuch Pariſh is ſituated, <lb/>according to
        any Proviſions, ſubſiſting for <lb/>that purpoſe; ſo that, notwithſtanding the <lb/>great
        additional trouble, laid by this Bill, on <lb/>the officiating Miniſters, and Clerks of Pa-
        <lb/>riſhes, nothing is abated to them of their <lb/>former duty. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By the 36th Clauſe, a Copy of this Act, <lb/>as ſoon as it ſhall be printed, is to be
        ſent <lb/>by the Clerk of the peace, in every County, <lb/>City, Riding, or Diviſion, in <hi
          rend="italic">England</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Wales</hi>, and Town of <hi
          rend="italic">Berwick upon Tweed</hi>, <lb/>to the Pariſh Officers of each Pariſh, for
        <lb/>which is to be paid to the ſaid Clerk of the <lb/>peace, by each Pariſh, 3<hi
          rend="italic">s.</hi> which will make <lb/>a pretty perquiſite to the Clerks of the peace,
        <lb/>when the Churchwardens of each Pariſh <lb/>might provide a Copy of the Act for 6<hi
          rend="italic">d.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The laſt Clauſe, being the 37th, enacts <lb/>a Penalty of 5<hi rend="italic">l.</hi> on
        ſuch Churchwardens as <lb/>ſhall refuſe or neglect to buy ſuch books and <lb/>paper, at the
        times directed, and is a ſuffi- <pb n="27"/>
        <lb/>cient penalty to enforce an obedience to that <lb/>part of the Act. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Upon the whole, there is no ſpecial ap- <lb/>propriation of this money, ſo to be
        raiſed, <lb/>to what uſes it is to be applied by the Go- <lb/>vernors and Guardians of the
          <hi rend="italic">Foundling- <lb/>Hoſpital</hi>, or how they are to account for it <lb/>to
        Parliament, or elſewhere. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Laſtly</hi>, The Bill, being a money Bill, is <lb/>capable of no
        amendment by the Lords, but <lb/>muſt be abſolutely paſſed, or rejected, tho'
        <lb/>containing regulations, which affect every <lb/>Pariſh in <hi rend="italic"
          >England</hi>, and interfering very much <lb/>with the management of eccleſiaſtical duties
        <lb/>and perſons. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Having gone through the ſeveral Clauſes, <lb/>I leave it to every unprejudiced man, who
        <lb/>conſiders the whole tenor of the Bill, whether <lb/>it does not appear, that thereby a
        freſh train <lb/>of embarraſſments, difficulties and diſcou- <lb/>ragements, will be heaped
        on the <choice>
          <corr>ſacerdotal</corr>
          <sic>facerdotal</sic>
        </choice>
        <lb/>Order; that a tax is, in effect, to be laid on <lb/>Baptiſm, which, as a Sacrament,
        ought cer- <lb/>tainly to be liable to none; and by that on <pb n="28"/>
        <lb/>Funerals, the grief of perſons in low life, <lb/>on the loſs of their chief ſupport, by
        the <lb/>death of a parent, is, at leaſt, very unſeaſona- <lb/>bly aggravated; and the
        difficulties on Mar- <lb/>riages greatly increaſed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mankind, as much as they are raiſed by <lb/>the dignity of their nature above other
        <lb/>animals, are likewiſe diſtinguiſhed from them <lb/>by Providence, in its particular
        care of their <lb/>Propagation and Increaſe, which is not left <lb/>to a fortuitous
        congreſs, nor to a ſhort ſo- <lb/>ciety of a year or a few months; but in <lb/>the beginning
        GOD made them male and <lb/>female, and ordained marriage as a perpe- <lb/>tual ſociety
        between them for life, which <lb/>(as <hi rend="italic">Milton</hi> finely expreſſes it) <q
          rend="italic indentall">
          <lb/>— — — — — — — requires <lb/>Collateral Love and deareſt Amity </q>, <lb/>for the
        mutual comfort of each other, and <lb/>for rearing an offspring to the ſtate of man-
        <lb/>hood, which demands the joint care of both <lb/>parents for many years, and is a
        perpetual <lb/>ſource of the moſt amiable and the moſt <lb/>uſeful connections in life. </p>
      <pb n="29"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Nor does the obligation then ceaſe, for, as <lb/>the parents grow old, if they have
        done their <lb/>duty by their children, the children have a <lb/>reciprocal duty to perform
        to them to the day <lb/>of their death, and are equally obliged, by <lb/>the ties of nature
        to ſupport the parents in <lb/>age, if they come to want it, as the parents <lb/>were to
        take care of their offspring, when <lb/>young, which requires a mutual ſociety, not
        <lb/>only between the man and his wife, but <lb/>between the parents and their children,
        <lb/>during their whole life. How convenient, <lb/>how beautiful, and how fitly adapted to
        the <lb/>welfare of ſociety is this Order of Providence! <lb/>and how juſtly has it been
        always eſteemed <lb/>and admired among the wiſeſt nations! </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Accordingly, we find that they have al- <lb/>ways given the greaſeſt encouragement to
        <lb/>Marriage, and the <hi rend="italic">Romans</hi> paſſed a law, giving <lb/>ſpecial
        privileges to the Fathers of three <lb/>Children, called the <hi rend="italic">Jus trium
          liberorum</hi>, <lb/>which law continued in force in great part <lb/>of <hi rend="italic"
          >Europe</hi>, for many centuries, and is ſtill, <lb/>tho' with ſome alterations, in force,
        in divers <pb n="30"/>
        <lb/>parts of <hi rend="italic">Italy</hi>: And the welfare of the child <lb/>has been
        always deemed the beſt pledge, and <lb/>ſtrongeſt ſecurity, for the fidelity and loyalty
        <lb/>of the parent. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>And in how great eſteem and veneration <lb/>the parental authority has always been held
        <lb/>amongſt the beſt and wiſeſt of nations, <lb/>Hiſtory will ſhew. Holy writ informs us,
        <lb/>that for many ages it was the foundation of <lb/>all government among the <hi
          rend="italic">Jews</hi>, from <hi rend="italic">Abra- <lb/>ham</hi> to <hi rend="italic"
          >Moſes</hi>; and that it was afterwards, of <lb/>the very eſſence of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Jewiſh</hi> polity. The <lb/>honour therefore to be paid to their parents <lb/>was made
        the firſt commandment of the <lb/>ſecond Table of the Decalogue, which com- <lb/>prehends
        the whole duty to ſociety. The <lb/><hi rend="italic">Egyptians</hi> claim the next place,
        on all ac- <lb/>counts; of their veneration to their parents, <lb/>we have the moſt ample
        proofs, and they <lb/>even preſerved, for ages, this piety to their <lb/>remains. I muſt not
        omit, that they en- <lb/>joined the ſon to be inſtructed in the trade <lb/>of his father.
        How far this was neceſſary, <lb/>I ſhall not pretend to ſay, but they appear <pb n="31"/>
        <lb/>to be the firſt people who carried on commerce <lb/>with glory and advantage; and of
        their great <lb/>proficiency in mechanicks, we have ſtupen- <lb/>dous monuments to this day.
        Not to expatiate <lb/>on this ſubject too widely in the vaſt field <lb/>of hiſtory, it may
        be obſerv'd, that the <hi rend="italic">Gre- <lb/>cian</hi> Legiſlators took their maxims of
        govern- <lb/>ment and morality from the <hi rend="italic">Egyptians</hi>, and <lb/>the <hi
          rend="italic">Romans</hi> deduced theirs from the <hi rend="italic">Greeks</hi>; <lb/>that
        famous republick, in every reſpect the <lb/>beſt regulated ſtate, and the niceſt cenſor of
        <lb/>manners, was ſo jealous of infringing on the <lb/>parental juriſdiction, that they, at
        no age, <lb/>and in no circumſtance of life, intirely <lb/>emancipated a ſon from the
        authority of his <lb/>father. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The next, who make a figure in hiſtory, <lb/>are thoſe great Northern conquerors, the
          <hi rend="italic">Suevi</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Goths</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
          >Alans</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Vandals</hi>, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> all of whom,
        tho' <lb/>tenacious of liberty, to the utmoſt extent of <lb/>the idea, in regard to their
        princes, rigorouſly <lb/>preſerved, in their private families, the ſub- <lb/>miſſion of
        children to their parents, wiſely <lb/>judging, that the preſervation of their publick <pb
          n="32"/>
        <lb/>freedom depended on that œconomy: For, <lb/>in all human ſocieties, there muſt be an
        <lb/>authority lodged ſomewhere; they are happieſt <lb/>where it reſides in the parent, to
        direct and <lb/>inſtruct their youth, and in laws made and <lb/>executed by themſelves to
        regulate their <lb/>manhood. This plan of our conſtitution <lb/>was firſt derived from theſe
        Northern Heroes, <lb/>from whom we boaſt of our origin. From <lb/>them we inherit a well
        regulated ſpirit of <lb/>liberty, and a reverence and ſubmiſſion to <lb/>parents. Theſe are,
        to this day, the univer- <lb/>ſally acknowledged characteriſticks of <hi rend="italic"
          >Engliſh- <lb/>men</hi>, the beſt and happieſt people upon earth; <lb/>long may they
        continue ſo: but that con- <lb/>tinuance muſt depend, in great meaſure, on <lb/>our
        adherence to thoſe principles, which <lb/>have hitherto made us great, and preſerved <lb/>us
        free. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I cannot quit this part of my ſubject <lb/>without mentioning the inſtance of the brave
        <lb/>black Prince, as he was called, Son of <hi rend="italic">Ed- <lb/>ward</hi> III. who,
        as <hi rend="italic">Rapin</hi> relates, after the <lb/>battle of <hi rend="italic"
          >Creſſy</hi> was over, cloſed the atchieve- <pb n="33"/>
        <lb/>ments of that glorious day, by modeſtly and <lb/>dutifully kneeling down, at the
        approach of <lb/>his father, to aſk him bleſſing: <hi rend="italic">Selon la Coutume
          <lb/>d'Angleterre</hi>. This picture excites no idea <lb/>in our minds, that can make us
        aſhamed of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Coutume d'Angleterre</hi>; nor ſhall we look on
        <lb/>our renowned Anceſtors with ſuch Ingrati- <lb/>tude, as tot be any ways the occaſion,
        that, <lb/>inſtead of an honourable Progeny lawfully <lb/>deſcending from them, a debauched,
        ſpurious, <lb/>perhaps an inceſtuous Race, may become the <lb/>future Lords of this Iſland. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This conſequence is what may, well, be <lb/>apprehended in time, if this Bill ſhould
        paſs <lb/>into a law, and the prodigious extenſion of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
          >Foundling-Hoſpital</hi>, now aimed at, be car- <lb/>ried into execution; which does not
        admit, <lb/>only, children in danger of being murdered, <lb/>to hide the ſhame of their
        parents; but is, <lb/>in a manner, a publick encouragement to all <lb/>parents, who do not
        chuſe to maintain their <lb/>own children, to abandon them before they <lb/>are a
        twelve-month old; whereby, not- <lb/>withſtanding experience hitherto has ſhewn, <pb n="34"/>
        <lb/>that the children have died in very great <lb/>numbers, yet as there are like to be
        more <lb/>and more brought every year into the Hoſ- <lb/>pital, this method muſt, in time,
        bring an <lb/>immenſe number, of which no judgment <lb/>can ſtrictly be formed; although the
        ingeni- <lb/>ous Mr. <hi rend="italic">Maſſie</hi>, in ſome ſhrewd Obſervations, <lb/>which
        he has made of the conſequences of <lb/>the extenſion of this Hoſpital, ſuppoſes, that,
        <lb/>in fifty years time, there will not be leſs than <lb/>50,000 of them, <note
          place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* See Mr. <hi rend="italic">Maſſie</hi>'s Obſervations on the <hi rend="italic"
              >Foundling-Hoſpital</hi>, <lb/>in his Pamphlet lately publiſhed, about Pariſh Poor,
            Page 45 <lb/>to 48, and 145 to 146. </p>
        </note> all of which will be <lb/>deemed Illegitimate and Foundlings, though, <lb/>perhaps,
        five-ſixths, or nine-tenths of them <lb/>be children born in lawful matrimony, but
        <lb/>abandoned by their own parents. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Illegitimate children, who happen to be <lb/>born of parents that take the beſt care of
        <lb/>them, ſeldom eſcape contempt and diſregard <lb/>from their equals; but much worſe is
        the caſe <lb/>of theſe Foundlings, who have no parent to <lb/>foſter them in their
        childhood, or to adviſe <pb n="35"/>
        <lb/>them in their youth; no brothers or ſiſters <lb/>to grow up as friends, to aſſiſt them
        in going <lb/>thro' life, nor any connection with any re- <lb/>lation whatever. Is this
        condition to be com- <lb/>pared to that of legitimate children in a fa- <lb/>mily? No
        ſurely. Why then is it endea- <lb/>vour'd to be extended to ſo enormous a de- <lb/>gree? Are
        theſe Foundlings, when they grow <lb/>up to manhood, to be the men to fight in <lb/>defence
        of their country? Alas! what coun- <lb/>try have they, who have no relations? who <lb/>have
        been abandon'd in their infancy by their <lb/>own parents, and have known nothing of the
        <lb/>effect of natural affection exerciſed towards <lb/>themſelves. How ſhall they love
        their coun- <lb/>try, who have never had any love ſhewed <lb/>them by parents or relations?
          <q rend="indentall space">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Non his Juventus orta Parentibus <lb/>Infecit æquor ſanguine.</hi>—
          <lb/>'Twas not by ſuch a motley Brood, <lb/>The Seas were dyed with hoſtile Blood, <space
            dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"> </space>
        </q>
        <lb/>either at the time of the Deſtruction of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Spaniſh</hi>
        Armada, or in the <hi rend="italic">Dutch</hi> and <hi rend="italic">French</hi>
        <lb/>Wars which have happen'd ſince. </p>
      <pb n="36"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>And, as their connections are not likely to <lb/>excite them to fight for their
        country, ſo <lb/>neither will their Education qualify them for <lb/>a Life of hardſhip and
        fatigue, like the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ruſticorum maſcula militum Proles</hi> of <hi
          rend="italic">Horace</hi>, <lb/>or the hardy Offsping of our <hi rend="italic"
          >Engliſh</hi> La- <lb/>bourers, who, being early inured to bear hun- <lb/>ger and cold,
        and bred to hard labour, have <lb/>ſo often and ſo ſucceſsfully, under the con- <lb/>duct of
        expert and valiant Leaders, made the <lb/>power of <hi rend="italic">France</hi> tremble;
        whereas the chil- <lb/>dren educated in this Hoſpital, being well <lb/>ſupplied with all
        neceſſaries, will feel none of <lb/>theſe hardſhips, and, till they are put out ap-
        <lb/>prentices, will have no employment but to <lb/>make purſes, or ſpin twine, to pray, and
        to <lb/>play. Nor, indeed, would it be poſſible for <lb/>the Governors of any Hoſpital,
        without the <lb/>imputation of barbarity, to uſe children to <lb/>the hardſhips, which many
        of thoſe, of the <lb/>poorer ſort, patiently ſubmit to, and even <lb/>thrive under, when
        bred with their parents, <lb/>who, they are very ſenſible, can do no better <lb/>for them. </p>
      <pb n="37"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>They may indeed, when grown up to <lb/>manhood, be qualified to ſerve in any arbi-
        <lb/>trary deſigns; as we find, in countries, where <lb/>deſpotiſm is carried to the higheſt
        pitch, <lb/>every thing begins and ends in the abſolute <lb/>Will of a Tyrant, inforced by
        mercenary <lb/>homicides, who have no connection with <lb/>the other Inhabitants. Thus, in
          <hi rend="italic">Turkey</hi>, it <lb/>is ſupported by the <hi rend="italic"
          >Janizaries</hi>, who are Found- <lb/>lings, brought up in Colleges, or Hoſpitals,
        <lb/>and tho' no wiſe intitled, by birth, to one <lb/>foot of ground, yet, at their Maſter's
        com- <lb/>mand, annul all private ſucceſſion, and butcher, <lb/>without mercy, whomſoever he
        is pleaſed <lb/>to mark out for deſtruction, and at laſt, for <lb/>want of other game, often
        deſtroy the royal <lb/>Hunter himſelf. The <hi rend="italic">Mamalukes</hi>, next to the
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Janizaries</hi>, were the moſt illuſtrious body of <lb/>Foundlings
        in hiſtory, if in one inſtance they <lb/>did not exceed them; I mean, their bold ſtroke
        <lb/>of placing one of their number on the throne, <lb/>and then by a Law rendering all but
        Found- <lb/>lings incapable of it. </p>
      <pb n="38"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Upon the whole, Sir, I muſt now ſub- <lb/>mit it to your conſideration, whether it does
        <lb/>not appear, that the prodigious extenſion of <lb/>this Charity, by taking in all
        children what- <lb/>ſoever that ſhall be offered, under a twelve- <lb/>month old, is a real
        and extraordinary devi- <lb/>ation from the original deſign of the Char- <lb/>ter; that the
        method of raiſing this tax will <lb/>be very prejudicial, and tend to the diſpa-
        <lb/>ragement and neglect of the ſacred ordi- <lb/>nance of Baptiſm, will unreaſonably
        afflict <lb/>the relations of all dying perſons, and will <lb/>greatly diſcourage Matrimony,
        and tend to <lb/>corrupt the morals of the people; that, in <lb/>ſtead of being a proviſion
        for expoſed and <lb/>deſerted young children, it will prove a <lb/>ſtrong temptation and
        encouragement to <lb/>many parents to abandon their own legiti- <lb/>mate children, for whom
        they are well able <lb/>to provide; and that ſo great a number of <lb/>perſons, brought up
        without any connections <lb/>or relations, will grow into a body quite <lb/>different and
        diſtinct from all others in this <lb/>kingdom, but who will neither by their <pb n="39"/>
        <lb/>education or conſtitutions ſerve ſo well <lb/>either for ſoldiers, day-labourers, or
        manu- <lb/>facturers, or for any other office of life, as <lb/>the children of ploughmen and
        day- <lb/>labourers, bred under the eye of their <lb/>own parents, and early inured to that
        kind <lb/>of life, the number of which uſeful peo- <lb/>ple will be greatly decreaſed by the
        increaſe <lb/>and extenſion of this deſign; the Overſeers <lb/>of the Poor in country
        pariſhes having already <lb/>fallen into the practice of ſending children <lb/>up to the
        Hoſpitals, in waggons, to the no <lb/>ſmall riſque of their lives; and therefore <lb/>that
        it will be far more eligible to reduce <lb/>this Hoſpital again, in time, within its
        <lb/>original bounds of a voluntary Charity, than <lb/>to extend it to that enormous degree,
        which <lb/>would be the conſequence of this Bill. </p>
      <q rend="italic indentall">
        <lb/>Eſt Modus in Rebus, ſunt certi denique fines, <lb/>Quos ultra, citraque nequit
        conſiſtere Rectum. </q>
      <signed rend="space indent">
        <lb/>I am, with the greateſt Eſteem, </signed>
      <salute rend="align-center">
        <lb/>SIR, </salute>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <dateline rend="italic size(0.5) hanging">
        <lb/>Feb. 5. <lb/>1759. </dateline>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <signed rend="italic align-right">
        <lb/>Your moſt affectionate Friend, <lb/>and humble Servant. </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
