<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: Animadversions on the Constitution of Physick</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">Animadversions on the constitution of physick in this kingdom,
              especially in the metropolis; interspersed with reflections on the conduct of the
              College of Physicians: to which is subjoined, an exact copy of the original charter,
              and an abridgement of the statutes or by-laws of the said college. Inscribed to the
              new Parliament. </title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC"> N15011</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/N15011"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for S. Bladon, in Pater-Noster-Row, MDCCLXVIII.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1768</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="3"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="76"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">John Rylands University Library of Manchester</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108620182</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Public welfare and institutionals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="3"/>
    <body>
      <pb n=""/>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>A horizontal double-line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <figDesc>A horizontal double-line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <head rend="size(1.5) align-center space">
        <lb/>ANIMADVERSIONS, &amp;c. </head>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="3"> </space>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Houſe divided againſt itſelf</hi>, ſays the
        ſcripture, <hi rend="italic">cannot <lb/>ſtand</hi>. Whether this be applicable to the
        preſent ſtate <lb/>of the College of Phyſicians, time will determine. <lb/>But we know,
        that, from a fortuitous concurrence of cir- <lb/>cumſtances, great revolutions have often
        been the ultimate <lb/>effect of a very trivial firſt cauſe: yet, be that firſt, that re-
        <lb/>mote-cauſe, whatſoever it may, the conſtitution of the times <lb/>is the principal
        cauſe of moſt revolutions. Our forefathers <lb/>were, doubtleſs, wiſe enough in their
        generation; never- <lb/>theleſs, the natural reſult of experience, or the different com-
        <lb/>plexion of the age, frequently oblige us to diſregard their <lb/>precepts, reverſe
        their decrees, and repeal their laws. But <lb/>mankind are naturally ſo attached to cuſtom,
        that they ſel- <lb/>dom attempt reformation, till the abſurdity or burthen of <lb/>their
        yoke becomes flagrant or intolerable. </p>
      <pb n="2"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Be not alarmed, my good reader, I have no treaſonable <lb/>intention. I have nothing to
        do with the revolutions of <lb/>kingdoms. They are below my notice; for, though they be
        <lb/>ſometimes of importance to individuals, to nations their <lb/>conſequence is generally
        trivial. If life and health be our <lb/>prime bleſſings, and pain and diſſblution our
        greateit evils, <lb/>the date, whoſe conſtitution I am about to conſider, con- <lb/>cerns us
        much more than that by which we are governed, <lb/><hi rend="italic">taxed</hi>, and
        protected. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Anno 1511, previous to the charter of our eighth Harry, of <lb/>pious memory, by which
        the phyſicians of London were made <lb/>a body corporate, there paſſed an act of parliament
        ordain- <lb/>ing, that no perſon ſhould practiſe phyſick, but ſuch as had <lb/>been examined
        by the Biſhop of London or the Dean of St. <lb/>Paul's: and the reafons aſſigned for paſſing
        this act were <lb/>theſe: "Foraſmuch as the ſcience and cunning of phyſic is <lb/>daily
        within this realm exerciſed by a great number of igno- <lb/>rant perſons, of whom the
        greater part have no manner of <lb/>inſight in the ſame, nor in any other kind of learning;
        ſome <lb/>alſo can read no letters on the book, ſo far forth, that com- <lb/>mon artificers,
        as ſmiths, weavers, and women boldly and <lb/>accuſtomably take upon them great cures, and
        things of great <lb/>difficulty, in which they partly uſe ſorcery and witchcraft,
        <lb/>partly apply ſuch medicines as be very noious, and nothing <lb/>meet therefore, to the
        high diſpleaſure of God, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>" This <lb/>preamble is a ſtriking
        picture of the ignorance and barbariſm <lb/>of the people of thoſe times; legiſlators not
        excepted. </p>
      <pb n="3"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the 10th year of the ſame reign, the College of Phyſi- <lb/>cians obtained their
        charter, the principal articles of which I <lb/>ſhall beg leave to conſider. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Art. 6. <hi rend="italic">Doctoribus Joan. Chambre, Thomæ Linacre, Fer- <lb/>dinando de
          Victoria, medicis noſtris, Nicholao Halſewell, Jo- <lb/>anni Franciſco, &amp; Rob. Yaxley,
          medicis, conceſſimus, quod ipſi, <lb/>omneſque homines ejuſdem facultatis, de et in
          civitate predicta, <lb/>ſint in re &amp; nomine unum corpus &amp; communitas perpetua ſive
          <lb/>collegium perpetuum.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From this article it appears, that, not only thoſe whoſe <lb/>names are expreſſed, but
        all the phyſicians then in London, <lb/>were, by this act, conſtituted members of the
        College, <lb/>which College was thus rendered perpetual. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In Art. 7. they are impowered to elect annually a Preſident, <lb/><hi rend="italic">ad
          ſupervidend', recognoſcend', &amp; gubernand'</hi>, their community. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Art. 8. grants the College a common ſeal. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By Art. 12. they and their ſucceſſors are authorized to hold <lb/>lawſul meetings, and
        to make ſtatutes for the government <lb/>and correction, not only of their own community,
        but of <lb/>every perſon exerciſing the ſame faculty in the city of Lon- <lb/>don, and
        within ſeven miles diſtance. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In Art. 13. all perſons are prohibited from exerciſing the <lb/>ſaid faculty in London,
        or within ſeven miles thereof, with- <lb/>out a licence, under the ſeal of the College, on a
        penalty of <lb/>five pounds for every month; half to the King, and the other <lb/>half to
        the College. </p>
      <pb n="4"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Art. 14. impowers them to elect annually four Cenſors, <lb/>who are inveſted with very
        extenſive authority to fine or im- <lb/>priſon thoſe who offend againſt the above laws. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In a ſubſequent act of parliament, in the ſame reign, their <lb/>charter is confirmed,
        and it is farther ordained that no perſon <lb/>be ſuffered to exerciſe or practiſe phyſic in
        any part of Eng- <lb/>land, until ſuch time as he be examined, at London, by the
        <lb/>Preſident of the College, and three Elects, and ſhall have <lb/>obtained letters
        teſtimonial of their approbation, except he <lb/>be a graduate of Oxford or Cambridge. By
        this act alſo, <lb/>eight Elects are eſtabliſhed, who have the ſole power of <lb/>chuſing
        one of their own number annually for a Preſident, <lb/>and of chuſing freſh Elects as often
        as a vacancy ſhall happen. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Theſe then are the pillars which ſupport the College of <lb/>Phyſicians; and certainly
        very ſtrong pillars they are. Their <lb/>power, in general, is great, but not abſolute. We
        have ſeen, <lb/>in Article 12. that they are authorized to make private ſta- <lb/>tutes, <hi
          rend="italic">&amp; ordonationes pro ſalubri gubernatione, ſuperviſu, &amp;
          <lb/>correctione collegii ſeu communitatis præd', &amp; omnium homi- <lb/>num eandem
          facultatem indicta civitate, ſeu per ſeptem milli- <lb/>aria in circuitu ejuſdem civitatis
          exercend' ſecundum neceſſi- <lb/>tatis exigentiam quoties, &amp; quando opus fuerit,
          &amp;c.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Conſidering this article, a queſtion naturally ariſes, name- <lb/>ly, To what degree
        this privilege of making by-laws may be <lb/>legally extended? Was it intended, by this
        clauſe, to give <lb/>the College a power of making whatfoever lawſ they pleaſed, <pb n="5"/>
        <lb/>in favour of whatſoever univerſities they ſhould think proper, <lb/>though ever ſo
        apparently injurious to the practice of phyſic <lb/>and diſcouraging to men of real
        abilities? The clauſe ex- <lb/>preſsly ſays, <hi rend="italic">pro ſalubri
        gubernatione</hi>. This <hi rend="italic">ſalubri</hi>is a ſtrong <lb/>word, as it clearly
        explains the intention of the legiſlature. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If upon an impartial enquiry into the matter, it ſhould ap- <lb/>pear, that thoſe
        members of the College, who have con- <lb/>ſtantly had the power of making the excluſive
        ſtatutes, have <lb/>been invariably partial to the univerſities where they received
        <lb/>their education; and if it ſhould farther appear, that theſe <lb/>univerſities, from a
        defect in their conſtitution, are incapable <lb/>of beſtowing a medical education; if, I
        ſay, this ſhould <lb/>really be the caſe, will it not naturally follow, that it is high
        <lb/>time for the legiſlative power to interpoſe? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>With regard to the univerſities of Oxford, Cambridge, <lb/>and Dublin, nothing can be
        more certain than that they are, <lb/>at preſent, by no means ſchools of phyſic. This is a
        fact, <lb/>which thoſe, who are at all acquainted with the matter, <lb/>muſt neceſſarily
        acknowledge. I do not deny that a ſtudious <lb/>young man may in any univerſity, or in any
        village in the <lb/>kingdom, by aſſiduous application, make himſelf acquainted <lb/>with the
        general theory of any ſcience; but in the ſtudy of <lb/>phyſic this is by no means
        ſufficient. In the abovementioned <lb/>univerſities the neceſſary means of acquiring medical
        know- <lb/>ledge are wanting. The lectures in every branch of medi- <lb/>cine are infinitely
        too ſhort and ſuperficial, and delivered by <lb/>men, though perhaps of ſufficient
        erudition, yet utterly in- <pb n="6"/>
        <lb/>capable of illuſtrating their theory by practical obſervation. <lb/>Beſides, many of
        the eſſentials are not taught at tall. No <lb/>patients, no clinical lectures, which are the
          <hi rend="italic">ſine qua non</hi> of <lb/>a medical education. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Probably it will be urged, that, on patriotic conſidera- <lb/>tions, our Engliſh
        univerſities ſhould be favoured. <hi rend="italic">Cæteris <lb/>paribus</hi>, this may he
        right; but patriotiſm, where the ad- <lb/>vancement of knowledge and the conſequent welfare
        of the <lb/>people are concerned, is only a ſecondary conſideration. In <lb/>matters of this
        importance, we ought to act as citizens of the <lb/>world, and, ſo far from confining our
        medical ſtudents to <lb/>any particular mode of education in our own country, it <lb/>were
        inſinitely more rational to encourage their reſidence in <lb/>thoſe univerſities where
        medical erudition is moſt effectually <lb/>to be acquired. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The rectitude of this reaſoning will appear incontro- <lb/>vertible, if the opinion of
        every individual be allowed to be <lb/>that of the whole community; for, ſuppoſe we aſk any
        ſick <lb/>perſon, at what univerſity he chuſes his phyſician ſhould have <lb/>taken his
        degree, will he not anſwer, That it is a matter of <lb/>indifference, provided he be a man
        of ſkill in his profeſſion? <lb/>The moſt deſirable univerſity, therefore, is that where
        moſt <lb/>knowledge may be acquired. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But, leſt I ſhould be miſapprehended, I repeat, that where <lb/>two univerſities are
        upon an equal footing, as ſchools of me- <lb/>dicine, thoſe of our own country, that is,
        thoſe of England, <lb/>Scotland and Ireland, ought certainly to be preferred; but <pb n="7"/>
        <lb/>if medical knowledge were known to flouriſh eminently in <lb/>any other part of the
        world, a Britiſh ſubject educated in <lb/>ſuch a univerſity, were it even in China, ought to
        meet with <lb/>every poſſible ennouragement on his return to England. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Such, I preſume; are the principles, by which men of ſci- <lb/>ence ſhould be
        influenced. Patriotiſm is undoubtedly a <lb/>virtue; but true patriotiſm will conſider the
        end rather than <lb/>the means. The firſt object of a real patriot is the well- <lb/>being
        of the people, and the firſt part of that object is <lb/>their health. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Let us now aſk whether the Statutes of the College of <lb/>Phyſicians were dictated by
        thoſe liberal principles, and that <lb/>true regard to ſcience, by which, we are of opinion,
        they ought <lb/>to have been influenced? An impartial retroſpection will, I <lb/>preſume,
        convince us, that they rather breathe that ſelfish <lb/>ſpirit of commerce, which is no
        friend to ſcience. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But, before we loſe ſight of Oxford and Cambridge, it <lb/>may not be amiſs to ſatisfy
        thoſe who aſk, how it happens <lb/>that theſe ſerminaries of learning are incapable of
        affording a <lb/>ſufficient medical education? for though, in the preſent diſ- <lb/>pute, it
        were enough to have proved the fact, yet it is not <lb/>entirely foreign to our purpoſe to
        aſſign the cauſe. Firſt, <lb/>then, let it be remembered, that the means inſtituted for that
        <lb/>purpoſe, had their foundation at a time when all knowledge <lb/>was at a low ebb; it is
        no wonder therefore that, in: the pre- <lb/>ſent ſtate of things, they ſhould be
        inſuſſicient to the end for <lb/>which they were deſigned. But the fixed ſtipends of the <pb
          n="8"/>
        <lb/>profeſſors is the chief obſtacle. The preſent flouriſhing <lb/>ſtate of thoſe
        univerſities where the emolument of the pro- <lb/>feſſors depends ſolely on the number of
        their pupils, is a ſuf- <lb/>ficient proof of the truth of this obſervation. In ſhort, the
        <lb/>entire conſtitution of our Engliſh univerſities is ſo ill adapted <lb/>to the preſent
        times, that nothing but a total reformation <lb/>can ſave them from univerſal neglect and
        ruin. I confeſs <lb/>that ſuch a reformation would be a moſt arduous undertaking, <lb/>yet,
        I am convinced, that it will not be long before the uni- <lb/>verſities themſelves will
        ſolicit the attempt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Before we proceed, I muſt requeſt the reader to caſt his <lb/>eye once more on the
        above-recited articles of the charter. <lb/>He will there find no other degrees or
        diſtinction of perſons, <lb/>than thoſe of <hi rend="italic">President</hi>, <hi
          rend="italic">Cenſors</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Elects</hi>; thoſe there- <lb/>fore of
          <hi rend="italic">Fellows</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Candidates</hi>, and <hi rend="italic"
          >Licentiates</hi>, are diſtinctions <lb/>founded ſolely on the authority of the College
        itſelf. By <lb/>the charter it evidently appears, that no diſtinctions <lb/>were intended
        but thoſe therein ſpecified; and that the <lb/>founders of the College were of this opinion,
        is plainly ſeen <lb/>from their not daring even to increaſe the number of their <lb/>Elects,
        without the authority of a ſubſequent act of par- <lb/>liament. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After mature conſideration of this matter, it ſeems pretty <lb/>evident, that in their
        excluſive ſtatutes, the College have <lb/>acted not only with unjuſtifiable partiality, but
        illegally: if <lb/>ſo, the Licentiates will probably be redreſſed; eſpecially if <lb/>it
        ſhould appear, that many of our molt eminent perſo- <pb n="9"/>
        <lb/>nages in the practice of medicine, are thus excluded from <lb/>the honours which were
        certainly intended for men of ſhining <lb/>abilities, of whatſoever ſchool. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Royal Society in England, the Academy of Sciences <lb/>at Paris, and every
        inſtitution of the like nature in other parts <lb/>of Europe, know no ſuch diſtinctions as
        thoſe of ſchool or <lb/>country. Their founders were actuated by more enlarged, <lb/>more
        liberal principles. They conſidered ſcience as a native <lb/>of the univerſe, and have made
        no private ſtatutes that <lb/>would exclude even an inhabitant of Mercury or Saturn, if
        <lb/>he were a man of diſtinguiſhed abilities. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Let us now ſuppoſe, that an inhabitant of either of theſe, <lb/>or any other planet,
        were to pay us a viſit. Let us farther <lb/>imagine him infinitely more learned, and in
        every reſpect <lb/>more enlightened, particularly in the ſcience of medicine, <lb/>than any
        inhabitant of Earth. He determines to ſpend ſome <lb/>time with us, and to viſit patients in
        the city of London. <lb/>The College of Phyſicians, being informed of his proceed-
        <lb/>ings, order him to appear before them, and, with their uſual <lb/>ſolemnity and
        ſagacity, proceed to examine him in what they <lb/>have learned at Oxford or Cambridge to
        call the fundamentals <lb/>of the art of healing. Can any ſcene be imagined more ridi-
        <lb/>culous? After all, they grant him a licence to practiſe, but <lb/>it is impoſſible to
        admit him <hi rend="italic">fellow</hi> of the College, becauſe <lb/>he is not a graduate of
        an Engliſh or Iriſh univerſity. Let <lb/>not this be condemned as a ludicrous repreſentation
        of the <lb/>caſe. The colouring, though ſomewhat ſtrong, is yet real, <pb n="10"/>
        <lb/>and is, I think, a pertinent illuſtration of the arguments I <lb/>have advanced to
        prove, that the London College is built up- <lb/>on a narrow baſis. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>We will now proceed to conſider that Statute of the <lb/>College which regards the
        admiſſion of Licentiates; and, <lb/>that our reaſoning, on this ſubject, may be ſully under-
        <lb/>ſtood, we ſhall tranſcribe the preamble of the Statute it- <lb/>ſelf. </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/>Quoniam complures, in hac Civitate Medicinam faciunt, <lb/>quos inidoneos omino
        cenſemus, ut in numerum Sociorum aut <lb/>Candidatorum adoptentur, vel quod natione non ſint
        Britanni, <lb/>vel Doctoratus gradum non adepti fuerint, vel non ſatis docti, <lb/>aut ætate
        &amp; gravitate provecti ſint, vel alias conſimiles ob cau- <lb/>ſas, &amp; tamen Reipublicæ
        inſervire ſaluti hominum prodeſſe <lb/>poſſint, ſaltem in nonnullis curationibus. De his
        ordinamus &amp; <lb/>ſtatuimus, ut poſt debitas examinationes, &amp; approbationem Præ-
        <lb/>ſidis &amp; Cenſorum permittantur ad praxin, quandiu ſe bene geſ- <lb/>ſerint. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As ſome may think themſelves intereſted in this ſubject, <lb/>who are not acquainted
        with the Latin language, I ſhall tranſ- <lb/>late the above paragraph. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>"Becauſe many in this city practiſe phyſic, whom we <lb/>deem quite improper to be
        adopted Fellows or Candidates, <lb/>either becauſe they are not Britons, not admitted
        Doctors, <lb/>are not ſufficiently learned, are too young, or for ſome ſuch <lb/>like
        cauſes, and nevertheleſs may be of ſervice to the public, <lb/>and the health of mankind, at
        leaſt in ſome caſes. Con- <pb n="11"/>
        <lb/>cerning theſe we ordain and appoint, that after proper exa- <lb/>minations, and the
        approbation of the Preſident and Cen- <lb/>ſors, they be permitted to practife, ſo long as
        they behave <lb/>well." </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Who can read this declaration without being ſtruck with <lb/>its extreme arrogance and
        ignorance? What are the particular <lb/>caſes in which an unlearned man may be of ſervice?
        Why are <lb/>not nurſes and old women licenſed to practiſe for the ſame rea- <lb/>ſons?
        Could any thing have been contrived more humiliating, <lb/>more ſhocking to the Licentiates,
        among whom the greateſt <lb/>number are Britons, of age ſufficient, and Doctors of Phyſic,
        <lb/>who therefore are thus ſtigmatized with the want of that learn- <lb/>ing which many of
        them poſſeſs in a more eminent degree <lb/>than any of thoſe by whom they are examined? Can
        it there- <lb/>fore ſeem wonderſul that the Licentiates ſhould be offended at <lb/>ſuch
        irrational partiality, ſuch monopolizing principles? Is it <lb/>not rather ſurpriſing, that
        any Phyſician, who had already un- <lb/>dergone a ſevere examination by the heads of the
        univerſity <lb/>where he took his degree, ſhould ever have ſubmitted to ac- <lb/>cept a
        licence upon ſuch wretched conſiderations? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But, ſince we are obliged to acknowledge that the College <lb/>of Phyſicians have ſome
        ſanction from the legiſlature, let us <lb/>enquire a little into the manner in which they
        have exerted <lb/>their power. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The reaſons aſſigned for granting them this power were, <lb/>to prevent illiterate and
        ignorant people from practiſing phy- <lb/>ſic. Have they acted accordingly? Have they
        impartially <pb n="12"/>
        <lb/>perſecuted thoſe whom they knew to be illiterate and igno- <lb/>rant? Have they not, on
        the contrary, conſtantly ſuffered a <lb/>number of profeſſed Quacks to practiſe phyſic
        without the <lb/>leaſt moleſtation? Have they not permitted hundreds of Phy- <lb/>ſicians,
        all over the kingdom, to practiſe without a licence, <lb/>though their power extends equally
        to every part of the <lb/>kingdom? Have they not exerted their authority entirely
        <lb/>againſt thoſe who might interfere with their own practice in <lb/>the metropolis? And
        do they not conſtantly diſregard thoſe, <lb/>who, from a different mode of practice, take no
        fees, and <lb/>conſequently do not immediately injure them, I mean the <lb/>Apothecaries? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Such hath been of late years the conduct of the College of <lb/>Phyſicians. Totally
        forgetful of the reaſons aſſigned for their <lb/>inſtitution, they have ſuffered conſummate
        ignorance and <lb/>quackery to ride in ſtate-coaches triumphant through the <lb/>ſtreets, to
        the eternal reproach of that body corporate, which <lb/>obtained its charter on purpoſe to
        ſuppreſs thoſe peſts of ſo- <lb/>ciety. I ſay <hi rend="italic">on purpoſe</hi>, for that
        was the ſole motive for <lb/>granting ſuch power to any ſet of Phyſicians. But Quacks,
        <lb/>it ſeems, are a harmleſs, or rather beneficial tribe of people, <lb/>in regard to the
        intereſt of Phyſicians; therefore they are not <lb/>moleſted. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As to that conſequential body of <hi rend="italic">literati</hi>, called Apothe-
        <lb/>caries, let us ſee in what light they were conſidered by the <lb/>College of Phyſicians
        in the laſt century. </p>
      <pb n="13"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Having in a former ſtatute forbid all its members to uſe <lb/>thoſe Apothecaries who
        themſelves practiſed phyſic, the Col- <lb/>lege in the year 1687 farther ordained, that </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/>Quoniam experientia compertum eſt, Pharmacopolas ex Me- <lb/>dicorum præſcriptis,
        ſpeciem quandam, &amp; umbram falſæ ſci- <lb/>entiæ conſectari, quâ ſe paſſim venditantes,
        non ſine ali- <lb/>orum periculo ad ſuum compendium abutuntur; ſtatuimus, &amp;
        <lb/>ordinamus, ne quis in poſterum Collega, ſive Socius, ſive Can- <lb/>didatus, ſive
        permiſſus, præſcriptis ſuis, ſeu ſchedulis medi- <lb/>cinalibus, directiones (quas vocant)
        adjiciant (præterquam in <lb/>noſocomiis) ſed eas apud ægrum ipſe relinquet, aut ſaltem pri-
        <lb/>us obſignatas ad ejus domum transferendas curabit; medica- <lb/>menta interim in
        ſchedulis præſcripta, jubeat ſolummodoò ut ti- <lb/>tulis quibuſdam congruentibus, aut notis
        ad eorum diſtinctionem <lb/>aptis ſignentur, nempè ut quantum in nobis eſt, nihil quisquam
        <lb/>hujuſmodi Medicaſtris ſuboleat quo conſilio, quà ve intentione, <lb/>aut in quos uſus
        remedia præſcribantur: mulctentur autem ſin- <lb/>guli viginti ſolidis in uſum Collegii
        quoties in hac parte deli- <lb/>querit. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That is, </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>"It being found by experience, that Apothecaries, from <lb/>the preſcriptions of
        Phyſicians, acquire ſome ſhadow of falſe <lb/>knowledge, of which they every where boaſt to
        ſick people, <lb/>and miſuſe, for their own advantage, and not without danger <lb/>to
        others; we will and ordain that, for the future, no mem- <lb/>ber of the College, whether
        Fellow, Candidate or Licen- <lb/>tiate, do add directions to their preſcriptions (except in
        hoſ- <pb n="14"/>
        <lb/>pitals) but that they leave ſuch directions with the ſick, or <lb/>ſend them ſigned to
        their houſes, ordering the medicines only <lb/>to be diſtinguiſhed with proper titles, to
        the intent that, as <lb/>much as in us lies, theſe <hi rend="italic">Medicaſters</hi> may be
        prevented from <lb/>diſcovering with what intention the medicines are preſcribed. <lb/>As
        often as any one ſhall offend in this particular, let him be <lb/>fined twenty ſhillings for
        the uſe of the College." </p>
      <p rend="indent italic">
        <lb/>Nullus Socius, Candidatus aut Permiſſus, Pharmacopolæ <lb/>opera utatur, quem in
        comitiis majoribus (quibus ut interſint <lb/>omnes omnium ordinum Collegæ præmoniti ſunt)
        Præſes renun- <lb/>ciaverit, aut medicine praxin exercere, aut ea de cauſa bis <lb/>citatum,
        ut ſe ſiſteret coram Præſide, &amp; Cenſoribus nondum <lb/>comparuiſſe, ſub pœna quadraginta
        ſolidorum prima vice, ſe- <lb/>cunda quinque librarum, &amp; tertia expulſionis è Collegio.
        Præ- <lb/>ſidis autem &amp; Cenſorum eſto hujuſmodi cauſas cognoſcere, mo- <lb/>menta
        expendere, &amp; definire, quis praxeos teneatur, &amp; quem <lb/>illi, aut major pars eorum
        judicaverit, eum nos Pharmacopo- <lb/>lam practicantem eſſe, ſtatuimus &amp; appellari
        volumus. De- <lb/>nique Sociis, cæteriſque Collegis omnibus, precipimus &amp; manda-
        <lb/>mus, ut ſepoſito omni affectu &amp; reſpectu perſonarum, ejuſmodi <lb/>Pharmacopæos
        quoſcunque praxin exercuiſſe deprehenderint, <lb/>eorum nomina Præſidi, &amp; Cenſoribus
        deferant, idque ſub pæ- <lb/>na violate ſidei Collegio præſtitæ. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That is, </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>"No Fellow, Candidate or Licentiate, ſhall make uſe of <lb/>an Apothecary, whom in the
        greater meetings (at which all <lb/>the members are required to attend) the Preſident hath
        re- <pb n="15"/>
        <lb/>nounced, or declared to practiſe phyſic, or hath on that ac- <lb/>count been twice
        ſummoned to appear before the Preſident <lb/>and Cenſors, yet hath not appeared, under the
        penalty of <lb/>forty ſhillings for the firſt offence; for the ſecond five <lb/>pounds; and
        for the third, expulſion. Let it be the buſi- <lb/>neſs of the Preſident and Cenſors to take
        cogniſance of theſe <lb/>matters, to weigh and determine who are guilty of practiſing
        <lb/>phyſic, and whomſoever they ſhall condemn, we do pro- <lb/>nounce to be practiſing
        Apothecaries. Laſtly, we command <lb/>the Fellows, and every other Member of the College,
        that <lb/>without partiality or reſpect of perſons, as often as they de- <lb/>tect any of
        theſe Apothecaries practiſing phyſic, they bring <lb/>their names to the Preſident or
        Cenſors, under pain of be- <lb/>ing cenſured for breach of faith to the College." </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>So that in the year 1687 the Co1lege were of opinion, that <lb/>theſe <hi rend="italic"
          >Medicaſters</hi> of Apothecaries, deriving their knowledge <lb/>ſolely from the
        preſcriptions of Phyſicians, were too ignorant <lb/>and illiterate to be ſuffered to
        practice Phyſic. They conſi- <lb/>dered, that from the mere peruſal of preſcriptions,
        nothing <lb/>could poſſibly be acquired, but, as they themſelves expreſs <lb/>it, a ſhadow
        of falſe knowledge, ever dangerous to the pa- <lb/>tient. They conſidered the art of mixing
        a bolus as having <lb/>not the leaſt connection with the art of healing; and that a <lb/>man
        might beat in a mortar to eternity, without acquiring <lb/>thence the leaſt knowledge of
        diſeaſes. They conſidered <lb/>that an Apothecary could have no more pretenſions to ſkill in
        <lb/>phyſic, than any other mechanic; for that, if ſuch pre- <pb n="16"/>
        <lb/>tenſions were founded on their dealing in drugs, it might <lb/>with equal juſtice be
        extended to the druggiſt and the herb- <lb/>woman. They conſidered medicines as the
        inſtruments of <lb/>their art, and that it was as abſurd to expect medical know- <lb/>ledge
        in the makers of ſuch inſtruments, as that the maker <lb/>of a fiddle ſhould be an expert
        muſician. But they conſi- <lb/>dered theſe inſtruments, like thoſe uſed by ſurgeons, as
        ſharp- <lb/>edged inſtruments, which could never be intruſted in the <lb/>hands of ignorant
        men, without great danger to the patient. <lb/>And, laſtly, they conſidered, that even
        ſuppoſing the Worſhip- <lb/>ſul Company of Apothecaries, as the peculiar favourites of
        <lb/>heaven, to be inſpired with medical knowledge and ſagacity, <lb/>yet that they were of
        all men the moſt improper to be in- <lb/>truſted with the power of viſiting the ſick and
        diſpenſing <lb/>their own medicines, becauſe their judgment, if they had <lb/>any, would be
        conſtantly biaſſed by their intereſt. It re- <lb/>quires very little medical knowledge to
        comprehend, that effi- <lb/>cacious medicines can never be matters of indifference; that
        <lb/>there can be very few caſes in which ſuch medicines will not <lb/>either do good or
        harm. Be the caſe however what it will, <lb/>the patient muſt take phyſic, becauſe the
        Apothecary has <lb/>no other method of paying himſelf for his attendance. So <lb/>that the
        patient not only runs the riſque of the miſappli- <lb/>cation of medicines, but of being
        obliged to ſwallow a quan- <lb/>tity of ſtuff, in caſes where all medicine whatſoever muſt
        be <lb/>hurtful. </p>
      <pb n="17"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From theſe conſiderations then the College of Phyſicians <lb/>of the laſt century
        thought themſelves obliged to endeavour <lb/>to ſuppreſs an abuſe ſo highly and peculiarly
        injurious to the <lb/>inhabitants of this kingdom. I ſay <hi rend="italic">peculiarly</hi>,
        becauſe it is <lb/>an abuſe which never gained footing in any other part of <lb/>the world;
        the Apothecaries of no other kingdom having <lb/>ever attempted to interfere with Phyſicians
        in the practice <lb/>of phyſic. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>What now ſhall we ſay to the ſupine negligence of the <lb/>preſent College in this
        matter? Is it becauſe they think more <lb/>favourably of Apothecaries? Certainly not. It is
        becauſe, <lb/>from a very unjuſtifiable neglect of their own ſtatutes, they <lb/>have
        ſuffered this numerous body of men to eſtabliſh them- <lb/>ſelves in the opinion of the
        unreaſoning multitude, and by that <lb/>means to render themſelves in ſome degree
        formidable. That <lb/>being the caſe, no one has reſolution enough to hang the bell
        <lb/>about the cat's neck. By neglecting to ſuppreſs the evil in <lb/>its infancy, they have
        rendered themſelves in ſome meaſure <lb/>dependent on Apothecaries. In the preſent
        conſtitution of <lb/>things, it is generally in the power of an Apothecary to in-
        <lb/>troduce his favoured Phyſician into the families he attends, <lb/>and if a Phyſician be
        intruded upon him againſt his inclina- <lb/>tion, it is always in his power to diſappoint
        his expectations, <lb/>by omitting, or ſubſtituting one ingredient for another in the
        <lb/>compoſition of his medicines. This were indeed conſum- <lb/>mate villainy; but there
        are raſcals in all profeſſions. </p>
      <pb n="18"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Let not the Apothecaries imagine themſelves hardly dealt <lb/>with upon this occaſion,
        or that I mean the leaſt reflection <lb/>upon them as men, or to accuſe them of any peculiar
        want of <lb/>underſtanding. I have really no ſuch intention; but unleſs <lb/>I were to
        allow, that they are born with abilities ſuperior to <lb/>the reſt of mankind, I muſt inſiſt
        on their total ignorance of <lb/>a ſcience which, from the nature of their education, they
        <lb/>have had no opportunities to learn. The Apothecaries, I <lb/>know, will be very
        unwilling to allow the impoſſibility of <lb/>their being ſkilful practitioners; but to
        convince them that <lb/>I do not mean to inſinuate that their natural talents are leſs
        <lb/>than thoſe of other men, I declare it to be my opinion, that <lb/>if the greateſt
        Phyſician in Europe had had no other educa- <lb/>tion than that of an apothecary's fhop, he
        would have known <lb/>no more of phyſic than any other mechanic. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But, ſay the Apothecaries, if we are really as ignorant as <lb/>you are pleaſed to
        repreſent us, how comes it that the <lb/>people of this kingdom ſo generally employ us, not
        as Apo- <lb/>thecaries, but as Phyſicians? Do they not ſuffer us to judge <lb/>of their
        diſorders, and to ſend them what phyſic we think <lb/>proper? Is there, in ſhort, any
        difference between our em- <lb/>ployment and that of the moſt learned Phyſician of you all?
        <lb/>I confeſs there is none. But the conduct of the good people <lb/>of England is no
        argument in favour of your medical know- <lb/>ledge; becauſe it is impoſſible for them to
        judge of your <lb/>ſkill, unleſs they themſelves were Phyſicians. </p>
      <pb n="19"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But whilſt I aſſert, that Apothecaries have, from their <lb/>trade, no more reaſon to
        ſuppoſe themlelves Phyſicians, than <lb/>a weaver or any other perſon, I am not forgetful
        that there <lb/>may have been ſome few examples of Apothecaries changing <lb/>their
        profeſſion, and becoming very eminent phyſicians. We <lb/>are told alſo of a blackſmith
        becoming a great painter. Such <lb/>inſtances however are ſo very extraordinary, that
        nothing in <lb/>favour of Apothecaries can be thence concluded. Men of <lb/>uncommon genius
        and application will diſtinguiſh themſelves <lb/>in whatever art or ſcience they happen to
        purſue, in ſpite of <lb/>every diſadvantage of their early education. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But the ſtrongeſt argument in favour of what I have en- <lb/>deavoured to prove, is,
        that the contrary would lead us into <lb/>a manifeſt abſurdity; namely, that the moſt
        difficult of all <lb/>ſciences may be acquired without inſtruction, method, ſtudy <lb/>or
        application, and conſequently, that a regular medical edu- <lb/>cation is entirely
        unneceſſary; and we may then proceed far- <lb/>ther and ſay, that every attorney is a
        lawyer, every cobler a <lb/>ſhoemaker, every botcher a taylor, <hi rend="italic"
          >&amp;c.</hi> But this, though a <lb/>natural concluſion, mankind will hardly allow,
        becauſe rai- <lb/>ment and property are of more importance than health <lb/>and life. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Before I quit this ſubject, I cannot avoid taking notice of <lb/>the frequent fatal
        conſequence to the patient of the cuſtom <lb/>of employing Apothecaries out of their
        profeſſion. Thoſe <lb/>who are well acquainted with the nature and progreſs of diſ-
        <lb/>eaſes, will inform you, that moſt of thoſe which are called <pb n="20"/>
        <lb/>acute, generally become fatal, if improperly treated in the <lb/>beginning; that the
        firſt ſymptoms of ſome diſorders are ſo <lb/>equivocal, as to require much ſagacity,
        penetration, expe- <lb/>rience, and mature recollection of the obſervations of an-
        <lb/>cient writers, to diſtinguiſh them from each other; and that <lb/>theſe maladies, ſo
        very ſimilar in appearance, require a treat- <lb/>ment as different as can poſſibly be
        imagined. But this treat- <lb/>ment conſiſts not only in the medicines to be taken, but in
        <lb/>regimen, temperature of the room, bleeding or not bleeding, <lb/>together with many
        other circumſtances of infinite importance <lb/>to the ſafety of the patient, and which only
        can be deter- <lb/>mined by a proper idea of the diſeaſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Nevertheleſs, by the cuſtom of England, at this important <lb/>period of all diſorders,
        the firſt perſon applied to is a ſhop- <lb/>keeper, a medicine-monger, who differs in no
        reſpect from <lb/>his neighbour the fiſhmonger, or ironmonger, except in the
        <lb/>circumference of his perriwig. ſtrange infatuation l Thus the <lb/>malady is either
        ſuffered to gather ſtrength from neglect, or, <lb/>by injudicious treatment, rendered
        incurable. The Phyſician <lb/>is called in, and the Patient dies. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Let thoſe who doubt the truth of what I ſay, conſult any <lb/>experienced Phyſician,
        whoſe judgment and integrity they <lb/>have no reaſon to queſtion; let them deſire him to
        lay his <lb/>hand upon his heart, and declare upon his honour, whether <lb/>what I have ſaid
        be not a true repreſentation of the matter? <lb/>whether he has not loſt many a patient by
        the ignorance and <lb/>ſelf-ſufficient trifling of an Apothecary? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If this then be the real opinion of all Phyſicians; if it be <lb/>the unanimous opinion
        of the College themſelves, what ſhall <lb/>we think of their unaccountable neglect to exert
        that power <lb/>with which they are ſo amply inveſted. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As to thoſe who employ Apothecaries in the room of Phy- <lb/>ſicians, they urge, in
        excuſe for their conduct, that it is <lb/>owing to the exorbitant fees of the latter; and
        particularly <lb/>that thoſe of the middle, or lower rank, cannot poſſibly af- <lb/>ford ſo
        great an expence. There ſeems indeed ſome weight <lb/>in this argument; but a very little
        reflection will be ſuffi- <lb/>cient to convince us of its fallacy. Apothecaries in general
        <lb/>are as well paid for their trouble of attendance as Phyſicians; <lb/>they differ only
        in the manner of receiving their money: the <lb/>one takes it immediately; the other at the
        end of the year. <lb/>But I will venture to affirm, that in ſlight diſeaſes, according
        <lb/>to the preſent faſhion of being doctored by a ſhopkeeper, <lb/>the patient is generally
        at more expence than if a Phyſician <lb/>had been firſt ſent for; and that, in all diſeaſes,
        if Phyſicians <lb/>were rendered independent of Apothecaries, and intruſted <lb/>with the
        ſole care of the patient from the beginning, the ex- <lb/>pence to the patient would be much
        leſs than it now is. <lb/>This, therefore, is an argument on the other ſide of the
        <lb/>queſtion. Beſides, if we have reaſoned juſtly on this ſubject, <lb/>depending on an
        Apothecary is a dangerous dependance, and <lb/>conſequently worſe than no dependance at all.
        If a ſick per- <lb/>ſon cannot afford to ſend for a Phyſician, he had much better
        <lb/>commit himſelf to the care of an old woman, who, with equal <pb n="22"/>
        <lb/>ſkill, will be under no temptation to ſend him phyſic, in or- <lb/>der to pay herſelf
        for her trouble. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is eaſy to foreſee, that this conſequential body of men <lb/>will be highly offended
        with my having expreſſed myſelf ſo <lb/>unreſervedly concerning their medical abilities. But
        though <lb/>I may be ſingular in thus declaring my ſentiments, they may <lb/>be well
        aſſured, that I have done nothing more than expreſs <lb/>the ſentiments of every Phyſician
        who deſerves that name; <lb/>for, however ſome may, on lucrative conſiderations, demean
        <lb/>themſelves ſo far as to flatter Apothecaries into a belief of their <lb/>being really
        poſſeſſed of ſome medical knowledge, they may <lb/>be well aſſured, that, whenever they open
        their lips concern- <lb/>ing their <hi rend="italic">patients</hi>, they are heard, by the
        Phyſician, with <lb/>contempt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Thoſe who, by long ſtudy and laborious application, have <lb/>become well acquainted
        with the ſcience of phyſic, know it <lb/>to be in its nature ſo very extenſive, and
        inveloped in ſuch <lb/>a cloud of difficulties, that all the advantages of a regular
        <lb/>and learned education are ſcarce ſufficient to conduct them <lb/>through the labyrinth.
        The diſeaſes of the human body are <lb/>lo wonderfully numerous, and their ſpecies
        diſtinguiſhed by <lb/>ſuch variety of minute circumſtances, that the ableſt Phy- <lb/>ſician
        with all his experience, aſſiſted by that of all thoſe <lb/>who have gone before him, from
        the great Hippocrates to <lb/>the preſent time, finds himſelf frequently in doubt, and
        <lb/>obliged to deliberate maturely before he proceeds. To this <lb/>difficulty of judging
        properly of diſeaſes, let us add that of <pb n="23"/>
        <lb/>the falſe properties commonly aſcribed to many of the medi- <lb/>cines in general uſe.
        The medical properties of bodies are <lb/>diſcovered only by a perfect knowledge of their
        chemical pro- <lb/>perties; by frequent experiments on animal bodies, and dili- <lb/>gent
        obſervation of their effects, not only on healthy ſub- <lb/>jects, but in every ſtage of
        every diſeaſe, in every conſtitution. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The ancient Greeks were ſo perfectly ſenſible of the great <lb/>difficulty of attaining
        a competent knowledge in medicine, <lb/>that a Phyſician was obliged to ſpend the greateſt
        part of his <lb/>life in ſtudy and experiment, before he was allowed to prac- <lb/>tiſe. But
        if any one be deſirous of forming a juft idea of the <lb/>many requiſites to a thorough
        knowledge of the medical art, <lb/>let him conſult the celebrated Boerhaave's <hi
          rend="italic">Methodus Studii <lb/>Medici</hi>, where he will find, beſides the books
        commonly ſup- <lb/>poſed neceſſary to be ſtudied, that almoſt every branch of <lb/>learning
        was thought, by that great man, to conſtitute a <lb/>part of a Phyſician's erudition. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Can it then be matter of ſurprize, that a Phyſician who <lb/>views the art of medicine
        in its full extent, and who recol- <lb/>lects the labour and difficulty with which his
        knowledge hath <lb/>been acquired; is it, I ſay, at all wonderſul, that ſuch a
        <lb/>Phyſician ſhould behold with indignation, a moſt ignorant, <lb/>illiterate ſet of
        people, audaciouſly viſiting the ſick, pretend- <lb/>ing to judge of their diſeaſes, and
        adminiſtering medicines, <lb/>witht the ſame confidence as if they were poſſeſſed of all the
        <lb/>advantages that a learned and regular education could ſupply? <lb/>Can he, without
        compaſſion, contemplate the inconceivable folly <pb n="24"/>
        <lb/>of mankind in truſting their lives to the care of ſuch men? <lb/>Can he, without
        amazement, conſider the negligence of his <lb/>brethren at the College who ſuffer this
        abuſe, to the great <lb/>ſcandal of phyſic, and the deſtruction of mankind? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This neglect to confine theſe practiſing Apothecaries with- <lb/>in their proper
        ſphere, is the more unpardonable in the Col- <lb/>lege of Phyſicians, becauſe the means are
        ſo obvious and eaſy. <lb/>They might, indeed, with great juſtice, be proſecuted for
        <lb/>practiſing without a licence, and fined according to the ſta- <lb/>tute; for there is
        hardly a man in England ſo ignorant as not <lb/>to know, that there is no difference between
        the general em- <lb/>ployment of an Apothecary and that of a Phyſician. But <lb/>this mode
        of proceeding were too troubleſome and tedious. <lb/>The moſt eaſy and effectual method
        would be, for the Col- <lb/>lege to require a promiſe, from all their members, upon their
        <lb/>honour, not to ſuffer any of their preſcriptions to be made <lb/>up by a practiſing, or
        viſiting Apothecary. This determina- <lb/>tion firmly adhered to, would in a very ſhort time
        put an end <lb/>to ſo deſtructive an innovation. I ſay <hi rend="italic">deſtructive</hi>,
        for I do <lb/>poſitively afirm from long experience, and very accurate ob- <lb/>ſervation,
        that the preſent faſhion of conſulting Apothe- <lb/>caries, is the moſt fatal evil with
        which this nation is afflicted. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But it is urged, in favour of Apothecaries, that many of <lb/>them, from their
        extenſive practice, muſt neceſſarily have <lb/>gained great experience, which is allowed to
        be of vaſt im- <lb/>portance in the medical art. To this I anſwer, that expe- <lb/>rience
        without theory, and not founded on the experience of <pb n="25"/>
        <lb/>former ages, will produce no better qualification than that <lb/>of an old nurſe.
        Beſides, though this experience may be <lb/>urged in favour of Apothecaries, it is evident
        that mankind <lb/>are, in fact, of another opinion; elſe why do they call in a
        <lb/>Phyſician, when they imagine themſelves in real danger? If <lb/>they are ſincere in
        their opinion of the ſkill of their Apothe- <lb/>cary, why do they not truſt to it entirely?
        No; for, ſay <lb/>they, though we thought him ſufficient at the beginning of <lb/>the
        diſeaſe, we look for better advice when the caſe becomes <lb/>dangerous. But I have told
        you, that in the beginning of diſ- <lb/>eaſes the ſymptoms are moſt equivocal, and
        conſequently that <lb/>an Apothecary might be truſted with more ſafety when the
        <lb/>diſorder is confirmed, and the ſymptoms leſs doubtſul, and <lb/>that, in many caſes,
        the fate of the patient is determined ir- <lb/>recoverably by the conduct of the Apothecary
        in the firſt <lb/>twenty-four hours. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In ſhort, the more we contemplate this matter, the leſs we <lb/>are inclined to excuſe
        the conduct of the College; for there <lb/>is not a man of them all who is not, in his
        heart, convinced <lb/>of the truth of all I have ſaid. Their neglect therefore can- <lb/>not
        be attributed to ignorance; nor can it juſtly be aſcribed <lb/>to indolence, for we have
        ſeen them, of late, particularly <lb/>attentive to young Phyſicians, from whom, in
        conſequence <lb/>of their private ſtatutes, they could exact conſiderable ſums <lb/>of
        money. By perſecuting lthe Apothecaries, that is, by re- <lb/>ſolving not to have their
        preſcriptions made up by thoſe that <lb/>viſit patients, the College would add nothing to
        its wealth; <pb n="26"/>
        <lb/>but by obliging a young Phyſician to buy a licence, the Col- <lb/>lege receives fifty
        pounds. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I wiſh it were in my power to vindicate the College in this <lb/>particular; but it is
        impoſſible. Their partiality is too fla- <lb/>grant to admit of any excuſe. They perſecute a
        man whom <lb/>they know to have had a regular and expenſive education, <lb/>and to whom
        fifty pounds, at his firſt ſetting out in life, <lb/>may be no inconſiderable ſum, whilſt
        they ſuffer a ſet of ig- <lb/>norant men, who have had no education at all, to practiſe
        <lb/>with impunity; and all this under a pretence of preſerving <lb/>the people from the
        danger of employing ignorant <hi rend="italic">medicaſters</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Can it be ſuppoſed, that the Legiſlature, in giving a char- <lb/>ter to the College of
        Phyſicians, ever intended to give them <lb/>a power to oblige regular Doctors of Phyſic to
        purchaſe a li- <lb/>cence to practiſe, at a conſiderable expence? Certainly not. <lb/>The
        ſole deſign of that charter was to prevent the people from <lb/>being impoſed upon by
        ignorant pretenders to medical know- <lb/>ledge. How much the College hath regarded this
        ſole end <lb/>of their inſtitution, by perſecuting Quacks and practiſing <lb/>Apothecaries,
        is well known. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>So long therefore as the College continue to neglect Quacks <lb/>and Apothecaries,
        their calling upon regular Phyſicians can- <lb/>not, by any means, be attributed to their
        regard for the public <lb/>welfare; but, on the contrary, to a motive, of which, as gen-
        <lb/>tlemen, they ought to be aſhamed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When I ſpeak of regular Phyſicians, I do not mean Gra- <lb/>duates of Oxford or
        Cambridge only; nor do I mean to in- <pb n="27"/>
        <lb/>clude thoſe Doctors of Phyſic who are poſſeſſed of a <hi rend="italic">diploma</hi>
        <lb/>from any univerſity which confers degrees without examina- <lb/>tion, medical exerciſe,
        or reſidence. Such degrees are in <lb/>their nature ſcandalous, becauſe they can be no
        teſtimony of <lb/>the graduate's abilities, and becauſe they are never accepted <lb/>by
        thoſe who can obtain one that is more honourable. Such <lb/>Doctors, I confeſs, cannot be
        too ſtrictly examined by the Col- <lb/>lege; or rather, they ought to be abſolutely
        interdicted, ex- <lb/>cept in ſome very few inſtances, where a man's abilities are
        <lb/>univerſally known and acknowledged. If indeed the Legiſla- <lb/>ture were properly
        attentive to the well-being of the people, <lb/>the Scottiſh univerſities, which thus confer
        degrees on perſons <lb/>whom they have never ſeen, ought to be deprived of a power <lb/>ſo
        dangerous to mankind; or, as I have laid before, the <lb/>College of Phyſicians ought not to
        ſuffer any ſuch Doctors to <lb/>practiſe within their juriſdiction. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>With regard to thoſe who have had a regular education, <lb/>who, in conſequence of
        ſufficient reſidence at a creditable <lb/>univerſity, proper exerciſes, and ſevere
        examination, have <lb/>obtained a <hi rend="italic">diploma</hi>, authorizing them to
        practiſe phyſic in any <lb/>part of the world; with regard to ſuch, I ſay, a re-exarni-
        <lb/>nation by any College of Phyſicians muſt be deemed not only <lb/>ſuperfluous, but
        highly inſulting, both to the Phyſician ex- <lb/>amined, and to the Univerſity under whoſe
        great ſeal he is <lb/>declared <hi rend="italic">Doctor</hi>, and worthy to be intruſted
        with the cure of <lb/>diſeaſes. </p>
      <pb n="28"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I have often wondered, how the Preſident and Cenſors of <lb/>a private College of
        Phyſicians could poſſibly arrogate to <lb/>themſelves the unjuſtifiable power of calling to
        examination, <lb/>like ſchool-boys, perſons whoſe medical education they knew <lb/>to be
        ſuperior, and whoſe rank in phyſic was equal to their <lb/>own. It is indeed wonderful they
        ſhould not recollect, that <lb/>when a man has once obtained the degree of Doctor, in the
        <lb/>regular manner above mentioned, he has paſſed the time of <lb/>examination, and that a
        ſecond examination, even by a <lb/>whole Univerſity, could not be propoſed to him without
        in- <lb/>dignity. Strange! that theſe Fellows ſhould be unmindful <lb/>of the rank to which
        they were raiſed when they were cre- <lb/>ated <hi rend="italic">Doctors</hi>: a degree
        which, in civil ſociety, lifts them <lb/>very high, and without which, as Fellows, they have
        no <lb/>rank at all. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By what infatuation then have theſe Fellows been led to <lb/>inſult their equals, by
        commanding them ſervilely to appear <lb/>before them, and, like children, repeat their
        medical cate- <lb/>chiſm. I confeſs, and am heartily ſorry for it, that I myſelf <lb/>did
        ſubmit to be thus catechiſed by this high court of inqui- <lb/>ſition; though, in the
        Republic of Medicine, I was equal in <lb/>rank to the higheſt of my inquiſitors. They were
        pleaſed <lb/>to be ſatiſfied with my anſwers to their <hi rend="italic">important</hi>
        queſtions, <lb/>and I was accordingly dignified with the title of Licentiate: <lb/>that is,
        they did me the honour to write my name in the liſt <lb/>of thoſe blockheads, whom they deem
          <hi rend="italic">omnino inidoneos ut in</hi>
        <pb n="29"/>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">numerum Sociorum aut Candidatorum adoptentur, quod non ſa- <lb/>tis
          docti sunt</hi>, "but who nevertheleſs may poſſibly be of ſome <lb/>ſervice to the public,
        at leaſt in ſome few caſes." </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Is it poſſible that any Licentiate can read this without bluſh- <lb/>ing?' For my own
        part, I wiſh had gone to practiſe phyſic <lb/>at the Cape of Good-Hope, rather than have
        ſubmitted to <lb/>ſtoop ſo far beneath the dignity of my rank, as to anſwer <lb/>their
        impertinent queſtions, and accept their licence on ſuch <lb/>wretched, ſuch contemptible
        conſiderations. As to the mo- <lb/>ney I paid them, they are welcome to it; but I ſhall
        always <lb/>conſider it as a ſum to which they had no more equitable <lb/>right, than they
        have to my whole fortune, which, though <lb/>I am no Fellow, but a <hi rend="italic"
          >licenſed blockhead</hi>, the public hath been <lb/>pleaſed to render conſiderable. But as
        often as I recollect <lb/>my tame ſubmiſſion to be interrogated by a ſet of men who
        <lb/>poſſeſſed no ſhadow of claim to a ſuperiority over me in point <lb/>of medical rank, I
        own that I am diſſatisfied with that want <lb/>of ſpirit, which I ought to have exerted. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Poſſibly I ſhould have had ſome difficulties to encounter; <lb/>but theſe difficulties,
        I am of opinion, would have been leſs <lb/>formidable than is generally imagined. Happily,
        we live in <lb/>an age, and nation, in which remonſtrances againſt flagrant <lb/>abuſes are
        graciouſly received and attended to. If it ſhould <lb/>evidently appear that a body of men,
        to whom the govern- <lb/>ment granted certain powers, had uniformly miſtaken and
        <lb/>miſapplied thoſe powers, ſo as to countenance thoſe whom <lb/>they ought to perſecute,
        and oppreſs thoſe whom they ought <pb n="30"/>
        <lb/>to protect; if, in ſhort, it ſhould appear that the College <lb/>of Phyſicians had ſo
        intirely forgotten the reaſons aſſigned <lb/>for their inſtitution, as to ſuffer an
        innumerable ſwarm of <lb/>moſt illiterate, ignorant Quacks and Apothecaries to practiſe
        <lb/>phyſic all over the kingdom, and particularly in the metro- <lb/>polis, under their own
        eyes. If it ſhould farther appear, <lb/>that the College made a practice of ſelling licences
        at an ex- <lb/>orbitant price, and of obliging regular Doctors of Phyſic to <lb/>ſubmit to
        an ignominious examination. If theſe be facts, <lb/>and theſe facts be deemed acts of
        partiality and oppreſſion, <lb/>can it be doubted that, on a proper repreſentation, the com-
        <lb/>plainants would not be redreſſed? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Suppoſe a Doctor of Phyſic, appearing before the Preſi- <lb/>dent and Cenſors in order
        to be examined, were to addreſs <lb/>them in the following words. "Gentlemen, I have obeyed
        <lb/>your ſummons, becauſe, notwithſtanding the ungenteel man- <lb/>ner in which it was
        expreſſed, I was willing to conſider it as <lb/>an invitation to meet my equals upon
        buſineſs of importance. <lb/>If with an intention to be informed of the preſent improved
        <lb/>ſtate of medicine in the univerſity where I took my degree, <lb/>you chuſe, as matter
        of converſation, to aſk me any parti- <lb/>cular queſtions, I ſhall give you the beſt
        account I am able; <lb/>but you will pleaſe to remember that, conſiſtent with the
        <lb/>honour of that Univerſity, and my own dignity as Doctor of <lb/>Phyſic, I cannot
        poſſible ſubmit to anſwer any queſtions cal- <lb/>culated only to ſatisfy you of my medical
        abilities, of which <lb/>this <hi rend="italic">Diploma</hi> in my hand, together with this
          <hi rend="italic">Theſis</hi>, which I <pb n="31"/>
        <lb/>have Written and publickly defended, are undoubted teſti- <lb/>monies. Surely I need
        not inform you, that having obtained <lb/>the degree of Doctor, by ſuch means, at ſuch an
        univerſity, <lb/>I am already in poſſeſſion of the higheſt honour that phyſic <lb/>can
        confer. As therefore it is not in your power to raiſe me <lb/>higher, there can be no reaſon
        for obliging me to ſubmit to <lb/>any examination; it being a known maxim, that all exami-
        <lb/>nations are made with an intention to advance the perſon exa- <lb/>mined. If you urge
        in excuſe for your method of proceed- <lb/>ing, that your motive is to prevent ignorant
        people from <lb/>practiſing, I muſt tell you, that Doctors of Phyſic, who <lb/>have obtained
        their degree in a regular and reputable man- <lb/>ner, are the laſt perſons you ought to
        ſuſpect, and whom <lb/>therefore you have no right to ſummon, till you have entirely
        <lb/>ſuppreſſed all thoſe whom you know to be moſt ignorant. <lb/>Who theſe are, I need not
        inform you: Quacks and Apotheca- <lb/>ries ſtare you every where in the face, and convince
        the world, <lb/>that your pretence of conſulting only the ſafety and welfare of <lb/>your
        fellow-ſubjects is a mere farce. I am indeed forry, Gen- <lb/>tlemen, to be thus explicit
        with you; but I conſider myſelf <lb/>as ſpeaking to my brethren, and not to my ſuperiors in
        any <lb/>reſpect; beſides, you have continually offered ſuch flagrant <lb/>indignities to
        Doctors of Phyſic, that I am not ſorry for the <lb/>opportunity of vindicating the honour of
        ſo reſpectable a body <lb/>of men, againſt the outrages of an improper authority. I
        <lb/>have read your charter, and conſidered it with much attention, <lb/>and I am perfectly
        convinced, that you are thereby impow- <pb n="32"/>
        <lb/>ered to ſuppreſs malpractice, and not to be oppreſſive to <lb/>men of approved
        abilities." </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>What would the College of Phyſicians reply to ſuch a <lb/>ſpeech? They would call him
        an impertinent fellow, deem <lb/>him refractory, and would proceed againſt him according to
        <lb/>law. But are ſuch oppreſſive proceedings conſiſtent with the <lb/>liberal ſentiments
        which ought to diſtinguiſh men of ſcience? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A College of Phyſicians, on a proper foundation, might <lb/>certainly be rendered a
        ſalutary inſtitution; but I humbly <lb/>conceive, that it ought to be eſtabliſhed on a
        foundation to- <lb/>tally different from any that could poſſibly be erected in the
        <lb/>reign of Harry the Eighth. I have mentioned before, that <lb/>the ſtatutes of all other
        learned ſocieties, as well in England, <lb/>as in other parts of Europe, have been conceived
        by men of <lb/>liberal ideas, regardleſs of the narrow limits of country or <lb/>ſchool; men
        who wiſely conſidered, that to admit none but <lb/>members of their own univerſities, would
        be the moſt ef- <lb/>fectual method to impede the progreſs of ſcience, as by that <lb/>means
        they would deprive themſelves of every improvement <lb/>made by foreigners. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If ſuch unreſtrictive principles were thought neceſſary to- <lb/>wards the improvement
        of leſs eſſential arts and ſciences, how <lb/>much more indiſpenſible are they not to the
        improvement of <lb/>medical knowledge? A College of Phyſicians, ſo far from
        <lb/>endeavouring to confine the ſtudents of medicine to the uni- <lb/>verſities of their
        own country, ought, on the contrary, to do <lb/>all in their power to encourage them to
        ſtudy in foreign coun- <pb n="33"/>
        <lb/>tries, whereſoever the moſt eminent Profeſſors of medicine are <lb/>to be found. As to
        any arguments againſt this liberal plan, <lb/>from political conſiderations, they are too
        fooliſh to deſerve <lb/>an anſwer. A few pounds ſterling that might be thus car- <lb/>ried
        out of the kingdom, is an object too inconſiderable to <lb/>merit a moment's attention;
        eſpecially when compared to <lb/>the advantage of importing medical knowledge in exchange.
        <lb/>Beſides, men thus inſtructed would, in time, become emi- <lb/>nent Profeſſors in our
        own country, and the neceſſity of tra- <lb/>velling grow every day leſs and leſs, which,
        with the aſſiſt- <lb/>ance of new regulations at Oxford and Cambridge, would be <lb/>a means
        of retrieving their character as ſchools of phyſic: for <lb/>if I have reaſoned juſtly, the
        very means which were intended <lb/>by the College of Phyſicians to ſupport thoſe
        univerlities, hath <lb/>been one great cauſe of their decline; a natural effect of il-
        <lb/>liberal notions. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As to the terms of admiſſion, they ought to be ſuch as a <lb/>Gentleman, and Doctor of
        Phyſic, might accept with honour. <lb/>Examinations are ignominious for the reaſons above
        recited; <lb/>they are ineffectual, becauſe the queſtions propoſed are ſuch <lb/>as any
        young ſtudent of medicine may eaſily anſwer; and <lb/>they are ſuperfluous, becauſe thoſe
        who have obtained an ho- <lb/>nourable degree, have already given ſufficient teſtimony of
        their <lb/>knowledge, and the reſt ought not to be admitted on any <lb/>terms whatſoever. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Let it be the buſineſs of the College to enquire into the <lb/>preſent ſtate of
        medicine in every univerſity in Europe. Let <pb n="34"/>
        <lb/>them particularly inform themſelves in what manner ſuch uni- <lb/>verſities are wont to
        confer degrees in phyſic. Let them, in <lb/>conſequence of ſuch enquiry, make a liſt of
        thoſe univer- <lb/>ſities whoſe degrees are truly reſpectable. Let them form a <lb/>ſtatute
        impowering them to admit every Doctor of Phyſic of <lb/>ſuch univerſities, a member of the
        College, under the deno- <lb/>mination of Licentiate, on producing his <hi rend="italic"
          >Thesis</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Diploma</hi>, <lb/>and paying certain ſmall fees
        towards defraying the neceſſary <lb/>expences, which from their nature muſt be very
        inconſidera- <lb/>ble. Let him continue a Licentiate for the ſpace of four <lb/>years;
        during which term let his fee be fixed at half the uſual <lb/>ſum, or whatever moderate ſum
        the College may think pro- <lb/>per; but be that ſum what it may, let him be engaged, upon
        <lb/>his honour, never to refuſe attending the ſick on such mode- <lb/>rate terms, within a
        certain diſtance. Such a regulation would <lb/>not only enable the lower claſs of people to
        ſend for proper <lb/>aſſiſtance, but would give great opportunities of practice to
        <lb/>young Phyſicians. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The four years being expired, let him then be admitted <lb/>Fellow of the College, and
        be thence entitled to receive the <lb/>uſual fees. Thus we might expect to ſee Fellows of
        the Col- <lb/>lege men of learning and experience, and the diſeaſed might <lb/>rationally
        expect the beſt aſſiſtance that phyſic can adminiſter. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Theſe hints are to be conſidered merely as the outlines of <lb/>a plan which might
        eaſily be formed for the purpoſes above <lb/>mentioned. Pride, ſelf-intereſt, and an
        obſtinate adherence <lb/>to old cuſtoms, will, I make no doubt, be conſiderable ob- <pb
          n="35"/>
        <lb/>ſtacles in the way; but they are obſtacles which, I think, <lb/>may be removed without
        difficulty, if the great and powerful <lb/>can, by any means, be perſuaded to think the
        ſubject of ſuffi- <lb/>cient importance for their conſideration. It is indeed a ſub-
        <lb/>ject which people in general ſuppoſe to concern the Faculty <lb/>only; but they are
        much miſtaken. It is a matter which <lb/>ought not, on any account, to be entruſted entirely
        with the <lb/>Faculty. The health of the people is ſo far from being an <lb/>object beneath
        the attention of the Legiſlature, that it would <lb/>not be very difficult to prove it
        deſerving their firſt and moſt <lb/>mature conſideration. Certain it is, that the practice
        of phy- <lb/>ſic is, at preſent, upon a moſt wretched footing; and that if <lb/>the people
        had a proper regard for their own welfare, every <lb/>individual would exert himſelf to the
        utmoſt of his abilities <lb/>to redreſs the evil. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If I were to be aſked, what would be the moſt effectual <lb/>means to procure redreſs,
        I ſhould adviſe an addreſs to Par- <lb/>liament, in order to procure a proper enquiry into
        the ſtate <lb/>of phyſic in this kingdom, praying that a committee might <lb/>be appointed
        for that purpoſe. Such a committee, without <lb/>any ſkill in medicine, might eaſily be made
        to underſtand the <lb/>nature and foundation of the grievances complained of, and <lb/>the
        means of redreſs, by a new eſtabliſhment, would evidently <lb/>appear. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I declare ſolemnly, that I am not actuated by the leaſt ſpark <lb/>of rancor or
        reſentment to any particular Fellow of the Col- <lb/>lege: on the contrary, I reſpect many
        of them for their <pb n="36"/>
        <lb/>learning and medical abilities; but I condemn their inſtitu- <lb/>tion as illiberal,
        obſolete, and oppreſſive; and I blame their <lb/>flagrant partiality and neglect of the moſt
        ſalutary of their <lb/>own ſtatutes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Patriotiſm, I confeſs, is a word which hath heen ſo often <lb/>proſtituted, that a man
        who pretends to have no other mo- <lb/>tive in what he ſays or does, than the good of his
        country, <lb/>is, not unjuſtly, ſuſpected of hypocrify. Nevertheleſs, if it <lb/>be evident,
        from my age and ſituation, that I cannot poſſibly <lb/>have any other end in view, thoſe who
        know me will acquit <lb/>me of any ſiniſter intention. I expect not, however, to com-
        <lb/>mand attention on this account. All I deſire is, that thoſe <lb/>who deem theſe ſheets
        worth their peruſal, will conſider what <lb/>I have written with impartiality, and determine
        according to <lb/>the weight or fallacy of my arguments. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>For the farther information of thoſe who have no oppor- <lb/>tunity of conſulting the
        Archives of the College of Phyſicians, <lb/>I ſhall here ſubjoin an abridgment of their
        Statutes or By- <lb/>laws, to which I ſhall prefix their Charter of Incorpo- <lb/>ration. </p>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="39"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
