<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Aikin: Thoughts on Hospitals</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>John Aikin</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">Thoughts on Hospitals</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T50198</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T50198"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for Joseph Johnson, No. 72, St. Paul's Church-Yard, MDCCLXXI. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1771</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="4"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="98"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW107855776</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Public welfare and institutional"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="4"/>
    <body>
      <pb n="5"/>
      <head rend="space align-center">
        <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">THOUGHTS </hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="space">ON </hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5) space">HOSPITALS. </hi>
      </head>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="3"> </space>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">T</hi>O counterbalance the various <lb/>evils and miſeries of life,
        Provi- <lb/>dence has planted in our na- <lb/>tures a benevolent principle, which,
        <lb/>without waiting for duty to incite, or <lb/>reaſon to approve, inclines us by an in-
        <lb/>voluntary emotion to relieve the diſtreſſes <lb/>of our fellow-creatures, and gives us
        the <lb/>pureſt and moſt ſenſible pleaſure for our <lb/>reward. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Never</hi> were the rights of humanity <lb/>better underſtood, nor the
        feelings of <pb n="6"/>
        <lb/>compaſſion more indulged than in our <lb/>age and country. Of this we have a
        <lb/>pleaſing proof in the rapid ſucceſs at- <lb/>tending every charitable inſtitution. We
        <lb/>have ſeen, within leſs than half a cen- <lb/>tury, numerous edifices ariſe throughout
        <lb/>the kingdom, dedicated to the ſupport of <lb/>the poor under the ſevere afflictions of
        <lb/>diſeaſe and want—we have ſeen theſe <lb/>amply maintained, carefully inſpected,
        <lb/>and diligently attended; and all this <lb/>without any interference of the civil
        <lb/>powers, merely by the generous and diſ- <lb/>intereſted zeal of individuals. In the
        <lb/>Metropolis many new deſigns have been <lb/>ſet on foot for the relief of particular
        <lb/>diſeaſes and calamities; in the country <lb/>general Infirmaries have been eſtabliſh-
        <lb/>ed at almoſt every conſiderable town, <lb/>upon the moſt liberal and extenſive prin-
        <lb/>ciples. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Amidst</hi> the univerſal diffuſion of this <lb/>amiable ſpirit, one
        thing alone appears <lb/>wanting to compleat the wiſhes of hu- <lb/>manity; and this is,
        that a proper di- <pb n="7"/>
        <lb/>rection of the means, ſhould accompany <lb/>the well-meant intentions of doing good.
        <lb/>Without a due regard to this object the <lb/>moſt benevolent deſigns may be fruſ-
        <lb/>trated, and inſtead of a bleſſing, prove an <lb/>additional misfortune to the
        afflicted. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Having</hi> turned my thoughts ſome- <lb/>what particularly to this
        ſubject, ſeveral <lb/>reflections occurred to me which appear- <lb/>ed of importance enough
        to be commu- <lb/>nicated to the public; and in any at- <lb/>tempts to rectify errors or
        ſuggeſt im- <lb/>provements, I have no doubt of being <lb/>favourably heard, by all who can
        diſ- <lb/>cern a good intention even where they <lb/>cannot agree with the opinion. And if
        <lb/>in this little piece they ſhall meet with <lb/>a freedom of cenſure in points which
        <lb/>they may have regarded rather as objects <lb/>of applauſe, they will not I hope, con-
        <lb/>ſider the Author's profeſſion as having <lb/>influenced him to inculcate opinions
        <lb/>with an intereſted view. It is well <lb/>known to the world, and with a conſci-
        <lb/>ous pride I repeat it, that no profeſſion <pb n="8"/>
        <lb/>or ſet of men have ſhown themſelves ſo <lb/>ready to offer their aſſiſtance to the
        poor, <lb/>or ſo diſintereſted in promoting improve- <lb/>ments in their art for the benefit
        of man- <lb/>kind, as the medical faculty. Their vo- <lb/>luntary unpaid attendance on the
        nume- <lb/>rous ſick at Hoſpitals, their readineſs to <lb/>give advice to the poor at home,
        amply <lb/>prove the former; their ſpirited patro- <lb/>nage of inoculation, with every
        other <lb/>means of prevention againſt diſeaſes, their <lb/>union into ſocieties for the
        free commu- <lb/>nication of knowledge and improvement, <lb/>ſufficiently declare the
        latter. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Whoever</hi> has frequented the miſera- <lb/>ble habitations of the
        loweſt claſs of poor, <lb/>and has ſeen diſeaſe aggravated by a total <lb/>want of every
        comfort ariſing from ſuit- <lb/>able diet, cleanlineſs and medicine, muſt <lb/>be ſtruck
        with pleaſure at the change on <lb/>their admiſſion into a Hoſpital where <lb/>theſe wants
        are abundantly ſupplied, and <lb/>where a number of ſkilful perſons are co- <lb/>operating
        for their relief. On the other <lb/>hand, when he walks through the long <pb n="9"/>
        <lb/>wards of a crowded Hoſpital, and ſur- <lb/>veys the languid countenances of the pa-
        <lb/>tients, when he feels the peculiarly noi- <lb/>ſome effluvia ſo unfriendly to every vi-
        <lb/>gorous principle of life, and compares <lb/>their tranſient effect upon him, with that
        <lb/>to be expected by thoſe who are con- <lb/>ſtantly breathing them and imbibing <lb/>them
        at every pore, he will be apt to <lb/>look upon a Hoſpital as a diſmal priſon, <lb/>where
        the ſick are ſhut up from the reſt <lb/>of mankind to periſh by mutual conta- <lb/>gion. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">These</hi> obvious and ſimple ideas an- <lb/>ſwer in fact to the real
        ſtate of advan- <lb/>tages and diſadvantages in hoſpitals. As <lb/>far as diet, nurſing, and
        medical aſſiſt- <lb/>ance are concerned, they are of eminent <lb/>uſe and comfort to the
        poor; but the <lb/>grand neceſſary of life, air, is never to <lb/>be had in a ſalutary
        degree of purity, <lb/>frequently is vitiated ſo as to become a <lb/>poiſon. Every hoſpital,
        I fear, with- <lb/>out exception, may in ſome meaſure be <lb/>conſidered as a Lazaretto,
        having its own <pb n="10"/>
        <lb/>peculiar diſeaſe within it. That dread- <lb/>ful diſtemper, little leſs malignant than
        <lb/>the plague itſelf, diſtinguiſhed by the <lb/>title of the jail or hoſpital fever, has
        long <lb/>been known as the inbred peſtilence of <lb/>crowded receptacles for the ſick, and
        <lb/>has thinned our fleets and armies more <lb/>than the ſword of the enemy. Sir John
        <lb/>Pringle, the great obſervator of military <lb/>diſeaſes, expreſſes in the ſtrongeſt
        terms <lb/>his dread of this fatal diſtemper, and his <lb/>diſapprobation of ſuch a
        diſpoſition of the <lb/>ſick in large general hoſpitals as is almoſt <lb/>certain to produce
        it. When the ſame <lb/>cauſes act in ſo inferior a degree, as not <lb/>to occaſion ſuch
        alarming conſequences, <lb/>they are ſtill far from being innocent. <lb/>I am intimately
        acquainted with a coun- <lb/>try Infirmary remarkable for neatneſs, <lb/>and excellence of
        conſtruction, and I <lb/>have even there very frequently ſeen a <lb/>ſlow depreſſing fever,
        the offspring of <lb/>putridity, creep over the patients other <lb/>complaint, become the
        principal diſor- <lb/>der, and reſiſt every remedy that could <pb n="11"/>
        <lb/>be thought of, till diſmiſſion from the <lb/>houſe produced a ſpontaneous cure. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">My</hi> deſign in offering to view facts of <lb/>this kind, is not to
        inculcate a general <lb/>and undiſtinguiſhing prepoſſeſſion againſt <lb/>theſe charitable
        inſtitutions, but merely <lb/>to ſhow that there is a real neceſſity for <lb/>extraordinary
        caution in their manage- <lb/>ment; and that the preſent faſhion of <lb/>indiſcriminately
        hurrying the poor ſick <lb/>into hoſpitals, and being buſied with a <lb/>benevolent zeal to
        fill them as full as poſ- <lb/>ſible, may be productive of conſequences <lb/>which are quite
        oppoſite to the kind in- <lb/>tentions of humanity. I have no manner <lb/>of doubt that they
        may be rendered emi- <lb/>nently uſeful, and that the greateſt part <lb/>of their
        inconveniences may be avoided; <lb/>and it is upon this conviction that I ven- <lb/>ture to
        offer to the public the reſult of <lb/>ſome ſtudy and obſervation concerning <lb/>them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">I Shall</hi> begin with ſome general re- <lb/>marks on ſome circumſtances
        with re- <lb/>gard to the uſual conſtruction of hoſpitals <pb n="12"/>
        <lb/>which have a conſiderable influence over <lb/>the ſalubrity of the air; and ſhall then
        <lb/>proceed to the conſideration of ſeveral <lb/>particular diſeaſes with reſpect to the
        pro- <lb/>priety of their admiſſion into a hoſpital. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> various cauſes of vitiation of the <lb/>air have been pointed
        out with great <lb/>preciſion, and means of prevention ſug- <lb/>geſted in particular caſes
        by many of the <lb/>improvers of modern practice. The <lb/>great character ſeveral of their
        works <lb/>have deſervedly acquired gives reaſon to <lb/>preſume, that every medical reader
        muſt <lb/>be acquainted with them; a recapulati- <lb/>on therefore of their general doctrine
        <lb/>would be uſeleſs, eſpecially as many <lb/>parts of it are not applicable to our ſub-
        <lb/>ject. It is not to be ſuppoſed that any <lb/>important miſtakes can be committed, in
        <lb/>a thing ſo well known and ſo much in <lb/>our power, as the choice of a proper ſitu-
        <lb/>ation and expoſure of a hoſpital with re- <lb/>gard to the ſtate of the air, as
        depending <lb/>upon heat and cold, dryneſs and moiſ- <pb n="13"/>
        <lb/>ture, and the like external circumſtances. <lb/>It is in the laying out of the
        building, <lb/>and the internal conduct of the houſe <lb/>that we are to look for the ſource
        of thoſe <lb/>errors which may prove ſo fatal. In <lb/>planning the building, two quite
        oppoſite <lb/>and incompatible views are found to in- <lb/>terfere. The architect conſiders
        it as <lb/>his buſineſs to manage his room and <lb/>materials in ſuch a manner, as to accom-
        <lb/>modate the greateſt number of people in <lb/>the leaſt poſſible ſpace. The phyſician
        <lb/>on the contrary would leave as much <lb/>vacant ſpace, occupied by the freſh air
        <lb/>alone circulating freely, as was in any <lb/>degree compatible with uſe and conve-
        <lb/>nience. It is to the prevalence of the <lb/>former above the latter that all our com-
        <lb/>plaints are owing. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> moſt common plan of a hoſpital <lb/>is a quadrangle, the ground
        floor of <lb/>which is appropriated to offices, and the <lb/>ſtores above to lodging the
        ſick, which <lb/>are for that purpoſe diſpoſed into long <lb/>rooms running the whole length
        of the <pb n="14"/>
        <lb/>ſides, and containing, according to the <lb/>ſize of the building, perhaps from twenty
        <lb/>to fifty beds ranging along the oppoſite <lb/>walls. There are uſually two common
        <lb/>ſtories, and an attic ſtory divided in this <lb/>manner. The long wards ſeldom run
        <lb/>along the four ſides of the quadrangle, <lb/>but only two or three of them. The
        <lb/>reſt is taken up with ſtair-caſes and ſmall- <lb/>er rooms for particular occaſions. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> firſt fault to be obſerved in this <lb/>plan, is the
        quadrangular form of the <lb/>whole building, which prevents an ef- <lb/>fectual thorough
        ventilation, and cauſes <lb/>a collection of ſtagnating air, tainted by <lb/>a variety of
        noxious effluvia, in the cen- <lb/>tral ſpace, which continually returns <lb/>upon the rooms
        through the windows <lb/>looking that way. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> diſpoſition of the lodging rooms <lb/>into long wards, is
        another, and a much <lb/>more pernicious fault, inſomuch that I <lb/>would aſſign it as the
        principal cauſe of <lb/>bad air in hoſpitals; and it is evident <lb/>that this muſt be the
        caſe, from the very <lb/>reaſon which led to the contrivance, viz. <pb n="15"/>
        <lb/>that a large number might be lodged in <lb/>a ſmall ſpace. Every perſon, even in
        <lb/>health, by his breath and the effluvia <lb/>ariſing from his body vitiates a quantity
        <lb/>of air around him; and the only reaſon <lb/>why we do not in general perceive any
        <lb/>bad effects from the poiſon generated by <lb/>this vitiation, is, that it is uſually
        diluted <lb/>with a large quantity of freſh air, and <lb/>carried off by a free circulation.
        If the <lb/>quantity of air be leſſened, or its circu- <lb/>lation impeded, noxious effects
        will be <lb/>proportionally ſhown. The degree to <lb/>which this may be done without pro-
        <lb/>ducing any injury of conſequence cannot <lb/>be exactly aſcertained; but there is no
        <lb/>doubt that it muſt become hurtful, when <lb/>ſuch a number as from twenty to fifty
        <lb/>perſons, many of them afflicted with <lb/>ulcers and other diſeaſes which tend to
        <lb/>aggravate the putreſency of the fluids, <lb/>are conſtantly confined together in a room
        <lb/>juſt large enough to hold their beds. The <lb/>circumſtance of continuing through the
        <lb/>day in the room where they ſlept, is a <pb n="16"/>
        <lb/>conſiderable aggravation of the evil. <lb/>The bed-cloaths acquire a ſtrong im-
        <lb/>pregnation from the perſpired vapours <lb/>of the night, as is evident on firſt enter-
        <lb/>ing the bed-chamber of a ſingle perſon <lb/>in health, and their ſoft porous texture
        <lb/>renders them extremely tenacious of <lb/>every kind of effluvia. It would there-
        <lb/>fore be a good regulation in every hoſpi- <lb/>tal, eſpecially ſuch as are in any
        degree <lb/>crowded, that all the patients who are <lb/>capable of ſitting up, ſhould remain
        <lb/>through the day in large airy halls, and <lb/>that their wards and bedding ſhould in
        <lb/>the mean time be as much as poſſible <lb/>expoſed to ventilation. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Still</hi> however I am perſuaded, that <lb/>every precaution and
        contrivance to ſweet- <lb/><sic>een</sic> the air will be only palliative while <lb/>the
        great ſources of contagion, large <lb/>crowded wards, remain in uſe. Sir John <lb/>Pringle,
        indeed, recommends large <lb/>wards for the military hoſpitals, but it <lb/>is evident that
        he does it upon the ſup- <lb/>poſition, that more proportionable void <pb n="17"/>
        <lb/>ſpace will be left in them than in ſmall <lb/>ones; for he lays it down as a rule, that
        <lb/>ſo few patients ſhould be admitted into <lb/>each ward, that one unacquainted with
        <lb/>the danger of bad air might imagine <lb/>there was room for double or triple the
        <lb/>number: a precaution I will venture <lb/>to ſay, obſerved in none of our hoſpi-
        <lb/>tals, ſince it would totally overthrow <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">oeconomical</hi> plan
        upon which they are <lb/>built. It is true the firſt appearance of <lb/>a large ward ſtrikes
        us with an idea of <lb/>ſomewhat very ſpacious and airy; but if <lb/>we conceive for a
        moment in imaginati- <lb/>on, that it was partitioned into as many <lb/>ſeparate diviſions
        as there are patients, <lb/>we ſhall be ſenſible how narrow a ſpace <lb/>is allotted to
        each. It is a farther objec- <lb/>tion to large wards, that if a particular <lb/>cauſe of
        contagion prevails, it is by their <lb/>means communicated to greater num- <lb/>bers than it
        otherwiſe would be. The <lb/>illuſtrious author above-mentioned re- <lb/>lates an inſtance
        of the malignant hoſ- <lb/>pital fever beginning in a ward, from no <pb n="18"/>
        <lb/>other cauſe than a mortified limb of one <lb/>of the patients. The contagion thus
        <lb/>raiſed would probably go no farther than <lb/>that particular ward—by its being ſmall
        <lb/>therefore the number infected would have <lb/>been leſs. Various other circumſtances,
        <lb/>ſuch as the mutual diſturbance and terror <lb/>ariſing among the ſick from the ſhocking
        <lb/>view of each other's ſufferings, their ago- <lb/>nies, raving and dying groans, all
        plead <lb/>ſtrongly with humanity againſt theſe diſ- <lb/>mal lodging places. I am at a loſs
        for <lb/>terms ſtrong enough to cenſure a practice <lb/>which, I verily believe, when
        followed <lb/>to its full extent in a large and crowded <lb/>hoſpital, is the ſource of more
        fatal con- <lb/>ſequences than the original diſeaſes of <lb/>the patients. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">A want</hi> of due height in the wards <lb/>is an additional cauſe of
        vitiated air, and <lb/>is occaſioned by the ſame plan of mak- <lb/>ing the moſt of the room
        and materials. <lb/>The attic ſtory is built for this purpoſe, <lb/>which by its
        diſproportionate lowneſs is <lb/>totally uſeleſs in itſelf and cramps the <pb n="19"/>
        <lb/>ſubjacent ſtories of their proper height. <lb/>I could point out ſeveral expenſive hoſ-
        <lb/>pitals much injured by this circumſtance, <lb/>and, if ever they happen to be thorough-
        <lb/>ly filled, the miſchievous conſequences <lb/>will probably be ſeverely felt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">I am</hi> aware that a different plan of <lb/>conſtructing hoſpitals,
        eſpecially in large <lb/>cities, would be attended with a great <lb/>increaſe of expence and
        loſs of room; <lb/>but this ought not to be an object when <lb/>a point is under
        conſideration, which is <lb/>to determine whether or no theſe inſti- <lb/>tutions be of any
        real public utility. <lb/>There cannot ſurely be a greater contra- <lb/>diction in the
        nature of things than a <lb/>diſeaſe produced by a hoſpital; and that <lb/>ſuch a diſeaſe is
        really known, that it <lb/>has proved fatal to thouſands, and in <lb/>ſome meaſure prevails
        in every hoſpital, <lb/>is a too certain and deplorable proof of <lb/>important miſtakes in
        their conſtruction <lb/>and management. If the utility of them <lb/>in their preſent ſtate
        upon the whole <lb/>really preponderate, it is ſtill placing <pb n="20"/>
        <lb/>them in the rank of neceſſary evils, when <lb/>one would hope they might be rendered
        <lb/>unmixed and undoubted benefits. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> does not belong to my profeſſion <lb/>to lay down an
        architectural plan for one <lb/>of theſe buildings, nor do I conceive it <lb/>neceſſary. By
        pointing out what to a- <lb/>void, we in effect give rules what to <lb/>aim at. The danger
        of corrupted air in <lb/>crowded cloſe apartments will ſuggeſt <lb/>the neceſſity of having
        them lofty, well <lb/>ventilated, and thinly peopled. In ge- <lb/>neral, the beſt plan would
        ſeem to be, <lb/>a range of cells or ſmall rooms opening <lb/>into a wide airy gallery,
        having a briſk <lb/>circulation of air through it. Greenwich <lb/>Hoſpital will give a good
        idea of this <lb/>diſpoſition, though in reſpect to loftineſs <lb/>and ſpaciouſneſs of the
        apartments it is <lb/>unequal to what would be requiſite for <lb/>ſick people. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">I now</hi> proceed to offer ſome remarks <lb/>concerning thoſe means of
        advancing the <lb/>utility of Hoſpitals, and avoiding their <pb n="21"/>
        <lb/>uſual inconveniences which depend up- <lb/>on the ſelection of ſuch patients as from
        <lb/>the nature of their caſes are the moſt <lb/>proper objects for admiſſion. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> judging of diſeaſes with regard to <lb/>the propriety of their
        reception into hoſ- <lb/>pitals, the following general circum- <lb/>ſtances are to be
        conſidered. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>1. <hi rend="sc">Whether</hi> they be capable of <lb/>ſpeedy relief; becauſe as it is
        the inten- <lb/>tion of charity to relieve as great a num- <lb/>ber as poſſible, a quick
        change of objects <lb/>is to be wiſhed; and alſo becauſe the <lb/>inbred diſeaſe of
        hoſpitals will almoſt <lb/>inevitably creep in ſome degree upon <lb/>one who continues a
        long time in them, <lb/>but will rarely attack one whoſe ſtay is <lb/>ſhort. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>2. <hi rend="sc">Whether</hi> they require in a par- <lb/>ticular manner the
        ſuperintendance of <lb/>ſkilful perſons, either on account of their <lb/>acute and dangerous
        nature, or any ſin- <lb/>gularity or intricacy attending them, or <pb n="22"/>
        <lb/>erroneous opinions prevailing among the <lb/>common people concerning their treat-
        <lb/>ment—It is evident that in general the <lb/>moſt important good effects will ariſe
        <lb/>from admitting theſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>3. <hi rend="sc">Whether</hi> they be contagious, or <lb/>ſubject in a peculiar degree
        to corrupt <lb/>the air and generate peſtilential diſeaſes— <lb/>the danger of their
        admiſſion to the other <lb/>patients is obvious. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>4. <hi rend="sc">Whether</hi> a freſh and pure air be <lb/>peculiarly requiſite for
        their cure, and <lb/>they be remarkably injured by any viti- <lb/>ation of it—I fear it will
        be impoſſible <lb/>with every improvement to render a <lb/>hoſpital a fit reſidence for
        perſons affect- <lb/>ed with ſuch diſeaſes. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">We</hi> ſhall apply theſe conſiderations to <lb/>various particular
        caſes, and from weigh- <lb/>ing the comparative importance of each, <lb/>ſhall endeavour to
        deduce ſome firm <lb/>practical concluſions. </p>
      <pb n="23"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">There</hi> are no diſorders in which the <lb/>benefit of hoſpitals ſeems
        more clearly <lb/>apparent, than thoſe which ariſe from <lb/>external injury in a ſound
        body. They <lb/>ſtrongly concur in the important circum- <lb/>ſtances of requiring, and at
        the ſame <lb/>time being capable of ſpeedy aſſiſtance. <lb/>From their violence and the
        ſuddenneſs <lb/>of their attack they are peculiarly diſ- <lb/>treſſing and terrifying, and a
        poor man's <lb/>habitation is uſually very ill provided <lb/>with the conveniences neceſſary
        for their <lb/>treatment. Unaſſiſted nature will fre- <lb/>quently get the better of other
        diſeaſes, <lb/>and they may become leſs formidable by <lb/>bearing up boldly againſt them;
        but a <lb/>wound, a fractured or diſlocated bone, <lb/>are diſorders immediately felt in
        their <lb/>utmoſt ſeverity, and compel the moſt <lb/>reluctant to ſeek the aſſiſtance of
        art. It <lb/>is therefore a very humane and proper <lb/>regulation in every hoſpital that
        all ſuch <lb/>caſes ſhould be admitted upon ſight <lb/>without the formality of a recommend-
        <lb/>ation. </p>
      <pb n="24"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Of</hi> accidental injuries, ſome anſwer <lb/>perfectly well the other
        circumſtances <lb/>favourable to admiſſion, of being little <lb/>ſubject either to cauſe
        corrupted air or <lb/>to be affected by it; others on the con- <lb/>trary are liable to
        great objection on <lb/>theſe articles. This difference in gene- <lb/>ral turns upon the
        degree of inflamma- <lb/>tion, and conſequently of fever, and <lb/>ſucceeding ſuppuration,
        and mortifica- <lb/>tion, excited; and upon the ſenſibility <lb/>and irritability of the
        parts injured and <lb/>expoſed to the air. Thus, fleſh wounds, <lb/>ſimple fractures and
        diſlocations, may be <lb/>cured with almoſt equal eaſe in any ſitu- <lb/>ation, while
        violent contuſions and burns, <lb/>wounds of nervous and membraneous <lb/>parts, compound
        fractures, and the like, <lb/>are rendered peculiarly dangerous and <lb/>difficult of cure
        by the contaminated air <lb/>of a hoſpital. The military and naval <lb/>Surgeons know from
        unhappy experi- <lb/>ence, the fatal effects of bad gun ſhot <lb/>wounds in their hoſpitals.
        They ſee the <lb/>inefficacy of every attempt to ſave a ſhat- <pb n="25"/>
        <lb/>tered limb, and are driven with reluct- <lb/>ance to the frequent uſe of that diſagree-
        <lb/>able, and in theſe caſes, hazardous re- <lb/>medy, amputation. Nor do theſe mor-
        <lb/>tifications fall to their ſhare alone. Every <lb/>Surgeon attending a large and crowded
        <lb/>hoſpital, knows the very great difficulty <lb/>of curing a compound fracture in them.
        <lb/>This is ſo univerſally acknowledged, that <lb/>the moſt humane and judicious of them
        <lb/>have been obliged to comply with that <lb/>dreadful rule of practice, immediate am-
        <lb/>putation in every compound fracture. <lb/>Mr. Pott, than whom there is not in <lb/>the
        whole profeſſion a more unprejudiced <lb/>patron of improvement, or a warmer ad- <lb/>vocate
        for humanity, has recommended <lb/>this general rule upon the grounds of ac- <lb/>curate and
        impartial obſervation. Yet, <lb/>that it is not founded upon the nature of <lb/>the caſe,
        but upon the added malignancy <lb/>of hoſpital air, is evident from the dif- <lb/>ferent
        ſucceſs in private practice and the <lb/>country infirmaries. The reader may <lb/>ſee this
        point ſet in a very ſtriking light <pb n="26"/>
        <lb/>by Mr. Kirkland, in his <hi rend="italic">Letters on <lb/>Fractures and
          Diſlocations</hi>, occaſioned by <lb/>Mr. Pott's Remarks on the ſame ſubject. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> danger of bad air in fractures of <lb/>the ſkull, is a
        particular obſervation of <lb/>antient date. Theſe have not only the <lb/>general
        unfavourable circumſtances of <lb/>compound fractures, but the aggravated <lb/>evil of a
        diſordered brain and nerves. <lb/>The fatality of this accident in private <lb/>practice is
        melancholy, but to a much <lb/>greater degree in hoſpitals. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">All</hi> injuries producing in the firſt in- <lb/>ſtance a great
        deſtruction and mortifica- <lb/>tion of ſubſtance, and in conſequence <lb/>an abundant
        ſuppuration, are extremely <lb/>liable both to occaſion and to be affected <lb/>by corrupted
        air. The ſeparation of <lb/>ſphacelated parts when the powers of <lb/>nature are vigorous
        and the ſurrounding <lb/>air is freſh and reviving, will generally <lb/>be affected without
        communicating a <lb/>contagion to the ſubjacent ſound parts; <lb/>but when the ſolids are
        relaxed, and the <lb/>fluids vitiated by ſteeping in a morbid <pb n="27"/>
        <lb/>atmoſphere, the whole body will be- <lb/>come in ſome meaſure aſſimilated to the
        <lb/>putrefactive ferment in the mortified <lb/>parts, and will readily imbibe and ſpread
        <lb/>its contagion. The prevalence of laxity <lb/>and a putrid tendency will alſo render
        <lb/>the ſuppuration from wounds and ulcers <lb/>ſuperabundant and ill conditioned; the
        <lb/>reabſorption of the matter and its recep- <lb/>tion into the lungs by effluvia will
        keep <lb/>up this diſpoſition, till at length the pa- <lb/>tient is worn away by a conſuming
        <lb/>hectic. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">All</hi> theſe conſiderations will exactly <lb/>apply to the wounds made
        by the ſur- <lb/>geon in his operations. How apt the <lb/>patient is to ſink under the
        ſymptoma- <lb/>tic fever, and abundant ſuppuration con- <lb/>ſequent upon them, when
        breathing the <lb/>corrupt air of a crowded hoſpital, I re- <lb/>fer to univerſal experience
        to teſtify. <lb/>This fatal event has been ſo frequent in <lb/>military practice, as to
        furniſh a plauſi- <lb/>ble argument for the total abolition of <lb/>the amputation of limbs.
        When on the <pb n="28"/>
        <lb/>other hand, the rule before mentioned <lb/>relative to compound fractures is con-
        <lb/>ſidered, the poor ſufferers under this un- <lb/>happy accident ſeem to be given up to
        <lb/>inevitable deſtruction. Preſerve the <lb/>limb—they die of the inflammation and
        <lb/>gangrene; take it off—they are waſted <lb/>by the ſuppuration and a putrid hectic.
        <lb/>A terrible dilemma, if it were unavoida- <lb/>ble from the nature of the caſe. It is
        <lb/>certain, that the number ſacrificed after <lb/>ſurgical operations to hoſpital
        peſtilence <lb/>is an evil of important magnitude. This <lb/>is out of all proportion ſo
        much greater <lb/>in the crowded London Hoſpitals than <lb/>in private practice, and country
        infirma- <lb/>ries, as plainly to ſhow that the ſingle <lb/>circumſtance of purity of the
        air is of <lb/>greater conſequence than any other to <lb/>the ſucceſs of an operation; and
        that <lb/>even increaſed ſkill and knowledge in <lb/>the profeſſion will not counterbalance
        <lb/>the want of it. This is ſtill more con- <lb/>ſpicuous in French practice than our own.
        <lb/>Every ſurgeon in France aims at ſtriking <pb n="29"/>
        <lb/>out ſome petty mechanical improvement <lb/>in the operative part of the art; at the
        <lb/>ſame time it may be ſafely aſſerted, that <lb/>they are uſually too inattentive in
        matters <lb/>of more fundamental importance to the <lb/>general utility of the profeſſion.
        With <lb/>a mixture of ſhame and indignation, I <lb/>have read ſuch paſſages as the
        following, <lb/>in their authors. After propoſing ſome <lb/>new improvement in a common
        opera- <lb/>tion, they relate a caſe in which it was <lb/>adopted; and purſuing it in the
        way of <lb/>a journal, coolly tell you that on ſuch a <lb/>day the patient died; but as his
        death <lb/>was only cauſed by the uſual conſequen- <lb/>ces of the operation, the credit of
        their <lb/>particular method is not at all affected <lb/>by it. Miſerable ſupineneſs and
        deluſi- <lb/>on! To go on in the daily practice of a <lb/>fatal operation, ſatisfied with
        the ſelf- <lb/>flattery of having invented an ingenious <lb/>method of performing it—as if
        the ob- <lb/>ject of a noble and moſt uſeful profeſſion <lb/>was to pleaſe and ſurpriſe by a
        ſhew of <pb n="30"/>
        <lb/>dexterity, rather than to advance the <lb/>welfare of mankind. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> is certainly from bad ſucceſs in <lb/>hoſpital practice, that Mr.
        Sharp and <lb/>others have given a dreadful idea of ſo <lb/>ſimple an operation as that for
        the Hy- <lb/>drocele. In private practice and a coun- <lb/>try infirmary, I have frequently
        ſeen it <lb/>performed without a ſingle dangerous <lb/>ſymptom. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">What</hi> concluſion with regard to the <lb/>admiſſion of patients into
        hoſpitals, are <lb/>we to deduce from the ſtate of facts thus <lb/>laid down? plainly this,
        that ſince ex- <lb/>ternal injuries and the diſeaſes requiring <lb/>ſurgical operations in a
        very particular <lb/>manner need the relief of hoſpitals, we <lb/>are to endeavour by every
        poſſible pre- <lb/>caution to render theſe ſuitable recepta- <lb/>cles for them, rather than
        deny aſſiſtance <lb/>to ſuch afflictions as moſt forcibly de- <lb/>mand it, and are moſt
        capable of receiv- <lb/>ing it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">If</hi> the plan for conſtructing hoſpitals <lb/>which has here been
        briefly pointed out, <pb n="31"/>
        <lb/>were followed, in all probability the fa- <lb/>tal conſequences of theſe caſes would
        <lb/>not take place, unleſs the number of <lb/>patients were inordinately large; a cir-
        <lb/>cumſtance that, I imagine, will render <lb/>it impoſſible with every contrivance to
        <lb/>preſerve the air quite pure and untaint- <lb/>ed. To obviate this inconvenience, it
        <lb/>might be proper in a very large city to <lb/>have ſeveral ſmall hoſpitals interſperſed
        <lb/>through it, ſolely appropriated to the <lb/>reception of accidental injuries; which
        <lb/>would alſo have this farther good effect; <lb/>that aſſiſtance would be nearer at hand,
        <lb/>and the pain and danger of conveying <lb/>ſuch patients to a diſtance would be a-
        <lb/>voided. This laſt conſideration has, we <lb/>ſee, been thought of ſo much impor-
        <lb/>tance in London, that ſome of the hoſpi- <lb/>tals have on that account been placed in
        <lb/>the very heart of the city. It unfor- <lb/>tunately happens that theſe are alſo ſome
        <lb/>of the largeſt, and thereby a double cauſe <lb/>of bad air is allowed to operate. By
        <lb/>much the moſt hurtful of theſe is how- <pb n="32"/>
        <lb/>ever the largeneſs and bad conſtruction <lb/>of the building; for although the air
        <lb/>in the middle of a populous city muſt <lb/>doubtleſs be rendered very impure from
        <lb/>the vaſt variety of impregnations it un- <lb/>dergoes, yet theſe impurities are not in
        <lb/>general of the putrefactive kind, nay <lb/>upon the whole may perhaps have the
        <lb/>effect of antiſeptics, as in ſome inſtances <lb/>has appeared to be the caſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Many</hi> hoſpitals, however faulty in <lb/>general conſtruction, are
        provided with <lb/>ſmall rooms for the reception of thoſe <lb/>who have undergone
        operations; and <lb/>where the number of patients is ſmall <lb/>theſe are uſually ſufficient
        to contain all <lb/>caſes of this kind; which is an addi- <lb/>tional reaſon why the country
        hoſpitals do <lb/>not feel in ſo alarming a degree the bad <lb/>effects of hoſpital air upon
        ſuch patients. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> ſecond and more numerous claſs <lb/>of diſeaſes which come under
        the ſur- <lb/>geon's province, is of ſuch as ariſe from <lb/>ſome peculiar virus or cachexy
        infect- <lb/>ing the whole habit of body, and ap- <pb n="33"/>
        <lb/>pearing in a variety of external morbid <lb/>affections. If we examine theſe by the
        <lb/>general conſiderations before laid down <lb/>concerning the admiſſion of patients, we
        <lb/>ſhall find, for the moſt part, that they <lb/>poſſeſs in an inferior degree the
        favoura- <lb/>ble circumſtances of being capable of <lb/>ſpeedy relief and requiring
        particular at- <lb/>tention; and that they are liable in a <lb/>greater degree to the
        diſadvantage of <lb/>cauſing and being injured by vitiated air. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">No</hi> diſeaſe fills our hoſpitals, eſpeci- <lb/>ally in ſome parts of
        the kingdom, with <lb/>ſo many ſurgical caſes as the ſcrophula, <lb/>and none is in general
        more improper <lb/>for admiſſion. When this virus has once <lb/>infected the conſtitution it
        is continually <lb/>ſhowing itſelf in numberleſs different <lb/>appearances from the
        ſlighteſt glandular <lb/>tumour to the moſt inveterate pulmonary <lb/>conſumption and white
        ſwelling of the <lb/>joints. In all it is conſtantly manifeſted <lb/>by the ſame ſluggiſh
        obſtinate diſpoſiti- <lb/>on, reſiſting almoſt every attempt of art, <pb n="34"/>
        <lb/>either from medicine or the hand of the <lb/>Surgeon. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Nothing</hi> can be more deplorable <lb/>than the condition of a poor
        ſufferer <lb/>under this diſeaſe in its worſt ſtate. I <lb/>have ſeen numbers of theſe
        miſerable <lb/>creatures, covered over with ulcers, diſ- <lb/>abled in their limbs, and
        emaciated by <lb/>ſuppurations and pulmonary obſtructi- <lb/>ons, applying for addmittance
        into a <lb/>hoſpital, and received merely from the <lb/>forcible commiſeration which their
        <lb/>wretchedneſs excited. The conſequence <lb/>was always uniformly the ſame. Pent <lb/>up
        amidſt the morbid effluvia from their <lb/>own bodies and thoſe of other patients <lb/>in
        the ſame condition, their cough and <lb/>hectic increaſed, the diſcharge from their
        <lb/>ulcers became more abundant and ill- <lb/>conditioned, and they either ſunk under
        <lb/>their complaints in the hoſpital, or ob- <lb/>tained a ſhort reprieve by returning home
        <lb/>to the country air. When the effects of <lb/>this diſeaſe are leſs terrible, nature
        will <lb/>often relieve herſelf; eſpecially when <pb n="35"/>
        <lb/>the fibres acquire vigour and firmneſs by <lb/>the progreſs from infancy to puberty.
        <lb/>Medical aſſiſtance directed to this inten- <lb/>tion may uſefully ſecond the efforts of
        <lb/>nature; but the manual and operative <lb/>part of ſurgery is in general very little
        <lb/>required, and every thing relating to in- <lb/>ternal medicine or external application
        <lb/>may be as well adminiſtered out of a <lb/>hoſpital as in it. In this diſeaſe there
        <lb/>ſeem to be no reaſons for admiſſion into <lb/>a hoſpital ſufficient to counterbalance
        <lb/>thoſe againſt it, except where amputa- <lb/>tion is neceſſary on account of a joint
        <lb/>ſwelling, or in a few caſes which render <lb/>ſome other operation adviſeable. Even
        <lb/>in theſe I have frequently ſeen inſtances, <lb/>where the complete cure of a ſtump or
        <lb/>the wound made by opening an abceſs, <lb/>could not be accompliſhed without diſ-
        <lb/>miſſion from the houſe to a purer at- <lb/>moſphere. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> is more difficult to determine on <lb/>the propriety of admitting
        perſons in- <lb/>fected with the venereal virus. Very <pb n="36"/>
        <lb/>few, I imagine, in this age are of that <lb/>rigid ſeverity in principle, as to
        with-hold <lb/>relief from real afflictions becauſe they <lb/>are occaſioned by the folly
        and vice of <lb/>the ſufferers. Charity would be ſolely <lb/>employed in mitigating the
        diſtreſſes of <lb/>mankind, without attempting to diſtin- <lb/>guiſh the chaſtiſing hand of
        heaven from <lb/>the ordinary operation of natural laws. <lb/>I therefore wave all
        conſiderations of this <lb/>ſort, and ſuppoſe theſe patients to claim <lb/>an equal right of
        admiſſion for relief <lb/>with any others, under the rules form- <lb/>erly laid down. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">There</hi> is no inſtance in which the <lb/>power of the healing art is
        more diſtinct- <lb/>ly ſhown than in the treatment of the <lb/>venereal diſeaſe, which,
        alarming and <lb/>dreadful as its effects are when left to <lb/>unaſſiſted nature, will in
        its moſt inve- <lb/>terate ſtate admit of a complete cure. It <lb/>is one of thoſe very few
        diſorders for <lb/>which medicine affords a ſpecific that is <lb/>able with certainty to
        overcome it, by <lb/>an action not referable to general laws, <pb n="37"/>
        <lb/>but peculiar to itſelf. This circumſtance <lb/>in favour of receiving venereal patients
        <lb/>into hoſpitals is reinforced by the great <lb/>advantage, and in many caſes the neceſ-
        <lb/>ſity, of a particular ſuperintendence du- <lb/>ring the treatment. The adminiſtering
        <lb/>of mercurials to a conſiderable quantity <lb/>requires a cloſe attention and numerous
        <lb/>precautions; and when it is conſidered <lb/>that the perſons moſt liable to receive
        <lb/>this diſeaſe are ſuch as are leaſt accuſ- <lb/>tomed to regulate themſelves with pru-
        <lb/>dence, it will appear that the confine- <lb/>ment and rules of a hoſpital cannot be
        <lb/>more uſefully employed than upon them. <lb/>On the other hand it muſt be confeſſed
        <lb/>that the nature of the diſeaſe itſelf in <lb/>many caſes, and the operation of mer-
        <lb/>cury, diſpoſe the body to emit putrefac- <lb/>tive effluvia which ſtrongly tend to cor-
        <lb/>rupt the ſurrounding air. This circum- <lb/>ſtance has occaſioned the total rejection
        <lb/>of theſe patients from ſome hoſpitals; <lb/>and where they are admitted, it is a ge-
        <lb/>neral rule to keep them together in a <pb n="38"/>
        <lb/>part of the houſe remote from the reſt. <lb/>Where this is exactly followed, and they
        <lb/>can be lodged in ſuch a manner that no <lb/>vitiated air can eſcape from them to the
        <lb/>other patients, no objection can, I think, <lb/>be made to their admiſſion, and it
        would <lb/>be difficult to ſupply their places with <lb/>thoſe who would receive more
        benefit <lb/>from ſuch inſtitutions. This, however, <lb/>in a large and crowded hoſpital is
        almoſt <lb/>impracticable; and in ſome of the Lon- <lb/>don hoſpitals the communication of
        bad <lb/>air from the venereal wards is very per- <lb/>ceptible; ſo that in a great city
        where <lb/>the number of theſe patients is conſide- <lb/>rable, it will always be beſt to
        appro- <lb/>priate buildings for the reception of them <lb/>ſolely. In theſe, although the
        contact <lb/>of freſh external air, ſo ſalutary in moſt <lb/>diſeaſes, is hurtful to
        patients undergo- <lb/>ing a high mercurial proceſs, yet every <lb/>contrivance to prevent a
        putrid atmoſ- <lb/>phere, conſiſtent with neceſſary warmth, <lb/>ſhould be adopted. </p>
      <pb n="39"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> is a rule in ſome hoſpitals to com- <lb/>promiſe this matter by
        admitting vene- <lb/>real patients as out-patients only. Where <lb/>this has been done, I
        have never known <lb/>any but the ſlighteſt caſes treated with <lb/>advantage; and it were
        to be wiſhed that <lb/>no others were undertaken, ſince the o- <lb/>peration of mercury is
        by much too de- <lb/>licate a thing to be truſted far out of the <lb/>preſcriber's ſight,
        and it may be highly <lb/>improper for patients under this proceſs <lb/>to attend at the
        ſtated times for advice <lb/>and medicine. It may be farther added <lb/>that palliation in
        this diſeaſe is worſe to <lb/>the community than abſolute neglect, <lb/>ſince the imprudent
        ſufferers deluded by <lb/>a ſuppoſed cure go on to ſpread the con- <lb/>tagion, and entail
        it in its moſt dreadful <lb/>conſequences upon a future generation. <lb/>On this account
        every empirical noſtrum <lb/>vended for this diſeaſe is highly perni- <lb/>cious: for
        allowing that, properly ad- <lb/>miniſtered, it be capable of producing a <lb/>cure, (as in
        fact is the caſe with almoſt <lb/>every mercurial preparation) yet it is <pb n="40"/>
        <lb/>abſolutely impoſſible by any general di- <lb/>rections to render a perſon, who is un-
        <lb/>acquainted with the nature of theſe me- <lb/>dicines, a proper judge of their exhibi-
        <lb/>tion; and it will always happen either <lb/>that they injure their conſtitutions by
        <lb/>over-doſing, or that they remain ſhort <lb/>of a cure; or very probably both theſe
        <lb/>circumſtances may take place. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Little</hi> needs be ſaid concerning that <lb/>terrible diſeaſe, the
        cancer. There is ſo <lb/>ſmall a probability of curing it by any <lb/>means hitherto
        diſcovered, and it is ſo <lb/>loathſome an object to the ſenſes, that <lb/>unleſs the
        removal of the part affected by <lb/>an operation be practicable and adviſeable, <lb/>it can
        with no degree of propriety be re- <lb/>ceived into a hoſpital. If the attention <lb/>of art
        be directed to palliate ſome of the <lb/>moſt grievous ſymptoms, any means for <lb/>this
        purpoſe may be employed with equal <lb/>advantage by the patient at home. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Those</hi> habitual ulcers proceeding from <lb/>that conſtitutional
        indiſpoſition called the <lb/>ſcorbutic, are uſually more dependent <pb n="41"/>
        <lb/>upon internal medicine and diet for their <lb/>effectual cure, than upon topical appli-
        <lb/>cation and the ſurgeon's hand. Ulcers <lb/>of the legs have been thought ſo far an
        <lb/>exception, that a ſtrict obſervance of reſt <lb/>and a reclined poſture, which can
        ſcarcely <lb/>be truſted to without hoſpital confine- <lb/>ment, was imagined the moſt
        neceſſary <lb/>circumſtance in their treatment. Some <lb/>late obſervations would ſeem to
        over- <lb/>throw this ſurgical maxim; and certain- <lb/>ly if the cure can as well be
        accompliſh- <lb/>ed in a different method, it will on ſe- <lb/>veral accounts be preferable.
        It muſt be <lb/>confeſſed that although the ulcers are <lb/>brought to heal by the common
        hoſpital <lb/>treatment, the cure generally only ſtands <lb/>good while the confinement
        laſts. Then <lb/>every ſymptom by which this habit of <lb/>body is diſcovered, and every
        indication <lb/>of cure, ſtrongly points out the tenden- <lb/>cy of putrid air to aggravate
        the origi- <lb/>nal cauſe of the complaint; and where <lb/>this prevails in a great degree
        in a <lb/>crowded hoſpital, it is no unuſual thing <pb n="42"/>
        <lb/>to find theſe ulcers rebellious againſt e- <lb/>very means of art, and gradually
        putting <lb/>on a more alarming appearance, till it <lb/>has been neceſſary to ſend them
        away in <lb/>a worſe condition than they entered. If <lb/>therefore theſe caſes can be
        treated with <lb/>tolerable ſucceſs out of a hoſpital, it <lb/>will certainly be better to
        favour the ge- <lb/>neral health by pure air and ſuitable <lb/>diet and medicines, than to
        incur the <lb/>danger of ſuch a depravation of the <lb/>fluids as may injure the
        conſtitution, and <lb/>perhaps aggravate the topical diſeaſe. <lb/>However as this matter
        may be conſider- <lb/>ed ſtill <hi rend="italic">ſub judice</hi>, and from my own ob-
        <lb/>ſervation I am by no means convinced <lb/>that abſolute reſt and a reclined poſture
        <lb/>are not in many caſes neceſſary, I would <lb/>not chooſe to ſpeak poſitively concern-
        <lb/>ing it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">I proceed</hi> to conſider <hi rend="italic">internal diſeaſes</hi>
        <lb/>with regard to the propriety of their re- <lb/>ception into hoſpitals, which I ſhall
        <lb/>only attempt to do in ſuch a brief and <lb/>general manner as may ſerve to direct <pb
          n="43"/>
        <lb/>the judgment of perſons, not belonging <lb/>to the medical faculty, in the benevolent
        <lb/>employment of ſelecting proper objects <lb/>for theſe charities. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> diviſion of diſeaſes into <hi rend="italic">acute</hi> and
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">chronic</hi>, though not ſufficiently accurate <lb/>and
        comprehenſive for the purpoſes of <lb/>ſcience, is the moſt uſeful in our view <lb/>of the
        ſubject, ſince it turns in general <lb/>upon thoſe properties of diſeaſes, which
        <lb/>determine the circumſtances formerly <lb/>pointed out as the great objects of conſi-
        <lb/>deration in admitting or rejecting them. <lb/>Though it is difficult preciſely to
        diſtin- <lb/>guiſh theſe claſſes, on account of the <lb/>gradation by which they fall into
        each <lb/>others limits, yet it is eaſily underſtood <lb/>that the <hi rend="italic"
          >acute</hi> are thoſe which are violent <lb/>in their attack and rapid in their courſe,
        <lb/>ſoon terminating in death or recovery, <lb/>and which proceed rather from occaſio-
        <lb/>nal and accidental cauſes than a regular <lb/>determination of the conſtitution—that
        <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">chronic</hi> are the contrary of all this; <lb/>ſlow in their
        progreſs, incomplete in <pb n="44"/>
        <lb/>their terminations, and frequent in their <lb/>returns, as proceeding from cauſes con-
        <lb/>ſtantly exiſting in the ſyſtem. This <lb/>ſlight ſketch of their character will at
        <lb/>once ſhow, that the acute have many ad- <lb/>vantages over the chronic in their plea
        <lb/>for admiſſion into hoſpitals. The cauſes <lb/>from which they proceed being acci-
        <lb/>dental, and their progreſs hazardous and <lb/>rapid, they at the ſame time are likely
        <lb/>to receive ſpeedy relief from the ſkill <lb/>and attention of the phyſician, and
        <lb/>particularly ſtand in need of his ſuper- <lb/>intendance. The chronic, on the other
        <lb/>hand, give little hopes of a radical cure, <lb/>and muſt uſually be treated by ſuch re-
        <lb/>medies as do not produce a ſudden <lb/>change, and conſequently do not re- <lb/>quire a
        frequent attention to their ef- <lb/>fects. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Fever</hi> either as a ſymptom or an ori- <lb/>ginal complaint, is the
        principal object <lb/>in acute diſeaſes. There are almoſt in- <lb/>finite diverſities in the
        ſtate of this diſ- <lb/>order; in all its varieties the reaſons for <pb n="45"/>
        <lb/>admitting it to the relief of a hoſpital <lb/>are very ſtrong; the reaſons againſt its
        <lb/>admiſſion vary in degree greatly. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Every</hi> fever, it is true, is liable to <lb/>contract a malignancy
        from the bad air of <lb/>a hoſpital, which alſo becomes commu- <lb/>nicable; but in many of
        them, ſuch as <lb/>the intermitting fever or ague, the in- <lb/>flammatory continued fever,
        the pleuri- <lb/>tic, nephritic, rheumatic, and all of the <lb/>like nature, this
        diſpoſition is in ſo in- <lb/>ferior a degree, that, unleſs the hoſpi- <lb/>tal be in ſo
        wretched a ſtate as to deſerve <lb/>the name of a Peſt-houſe rather than an <lb/>Infirmary,
        there need be no ſcruple in <lb/>admitting them. As was before obſerv- <lb/>ed concerning
        compound fractures and <lb/>other accidental injuries, the neceſſity <lb/>of affording
        relief to ſuch diſorders is ſo <lb/>ſtriking, that theſe inſtitutions do not at <lb/>all
        anſwer their end unleſs they are ren- <lb/>dered ſuitable for them; and this may <lb/>be
        conſidered as the teſt of their utility. <lb/>Many more doubts may be raiſed re- <pb n="46"/>
        <lb/>ſpecting thoſe fevers which are peculi- <lb/>arly termed <hi rend="italic"
          >contagious</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Contagion</hi> is diſtinguiſhable into <lb/>two kinds, and it is of
        importance to <lb/>our ſubject to make this diſtinction. <lb/>The contagion of ſome
        diſeaſes, ſuch as <lb/>the ſmall-pox and meaſles, is of a ſpe- <lb/>cific nature, always
        producing its own <lb/>diſeaſe, infecting by the ſmalleſt con- <lb/>ceivable particles of
        its matter, and <lb/>giving no indication of itſelf by a ſenſi- <lb/>ble vitiation of the
        ſurrounding air, ex- <lb/>cept when accumulated in large quantity. <lb/>The contagion from
        putrid and malig- <lb/>nant diſeaſes, on the other hand, is very <lb/>ſimilar in all caſes;
        is communicated in <lb/>proportion to its quantity, which is per- <lb/>ceptible by ſenſible
        effects on the air; <lb/>and is nearly, if not entirely of the ſame <lb/>nature with that
        corruption of the air <lb/>always proceeding from the putrid efflu- <lb/>via of a number of
        perſons crowded into <lb/>a ſmall ſpace. This may therefore be <lb/>ſo diluted and
        counteracted by various <lb/>precautions, as, in great meaſure, to loſe <pb n="47"/>
        <lb/>its infectious quality; the former never <lb/>can; hence a neceſſary and invariable
        <lb/>rule of excluding it from a general hoſ- <lb/>pital. But it ſo happens that of all the
        <lb/>diſeaſes which prevail in this country, <lb/>and indeed in the greateſt part of Europe,
        <lb/>a ſpecifically contagious one, the ſmall- <lb/>pox, is the moſt frequent, and carries
        <lb/>off the greateſt number of people. It <lb/>would therefore be a great check upon
        <lb/>the utility of hoſpitals, if ſo fatal and <lb/>common a diſtemper could meet with
        <lb/>no relief from them; eſpecially as in its <lb/>dangerous ſtate it requires in a very
        par- <lb/>ticular manner the cloſe attention of me- <lb/>dical ſkill; and from ſome late
        improve- <lb/>ments in practice, there is reaſon to be- <lb/>lieve that many lives might be
        ſaved <lb/>which are daily ſacrificed to ancient er- <lb/>rors in the method of treatment. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">A very</hi> happy peculiarity alſo attends <lb/>this diſeaſe, that by a
        certain method of <lb/>communicating it, its violence is leſſen- <lb/>ed in ſo great a
        degree as to render it al- <lb/>moſt a different diſtemper, in which a <pb n="48"/>
        <lb/>fatal event is abſolutely rare and uncom- <lb/>mon. There is not in the whole annals
        <lb/>of the healing art any diſcovery nearly <lb/>ſo beneficial to mankind (excepting per-
        <lb/>haps the uſe of mercury for the venereal <lb/>diſeaſe) as this practice of inoculation;
        <lb/>it is therefore highly intereſting to the <lb/>wiſhes of humanity that it ſhould
        prevail <lb/>as generally as poſſible. On theſe ac- <lb/>counts particular hoſpitals have
        been for <lb/>ſome time paſt erected in the Metropolis <lb/>for the ſmall-pox, both in the
        natural <lb/>and artificial way of receiving it, and <lb/>their public utility has been ſo
        great, <lb/>that it is pity they are hitherto confined <lb/>to London. The frequency of this
        diſ- <lb/>eaſe would always give a ſupply of pa- <lb/>tients in moſt of our large towns, in
        the <lb/>natural way; and if, what is a moſt de- <lb/>ſirable object, the practice of
        inoculation <lb/>was to become general, and all children <lb/>at a certain age were to
        undergo it, there <lb/>never could be wanting a conſtant and <lb/>regular ſucceſſion of
        ſubjects. So flat- <lb/>tering a proſpect of public good, moves <pb n="49"/>
        <lb/>me moſt warmly and heartily to propoſe <lb/>this addition to the charitable inſtituti-
        <lb/>ons in all the cities and towns where a <lb/>general hoſpital is already, or may in fu-
        <lb/>ture, be founded. A moderate ſized <lb/>building, either diſtinct, or forming a
        <lb/>wing to the general infirmary, would <lb/>ſerve this purpoſe. It ſhould be con-
        <lb/>ſtructed with every poſſible contrivance <lb/>for pure air, which is ſo remarkably
        <lb/>ſalutary in this diſeaſe; and might ſerve <lb/>indifferently for the reception of the
        <lb/>natural or inoculated ſmall pox, though <lb/>it would be proper to ſeparate them
        <lb/>into different rooms. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">I would</hi> wiſh the benevolent patrons <lb/>of theſe charities to
        reflect, that, till <lb/>this ſcheme is executed, a large propor- <lb/>tion of the diſeaſed
        poor muſt be un- <lb/>provided with ſuitable relief, and a moſt <lb/>dangerous diſtemper
        will be continually <lb/>making its ravages unchecked by thoſe <lb/>improvements in practice
        which have <lb/>been made ſo much to the benefit of <lb/>mankind. </p>
      <pb n="50"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">With</hi> reſpect to thoſe diſeaſes which <lb/>are contagious on account
        of the degree <lb/>of putrefactive malignance attending <lb/>them, the danger from them is
        to be <lb/>eſtimated in the ſame manner as that <lb/>from the uſual cauſes of putrid air. If
        <lb/>the conſtruction of the hoſpital be ſuch <lb/>as <unclear>f</unclear>ully to guard
        againſt the generation <lb/>and communication of corrupted air, it <lb/>may be ſafe and
        proper to admit patients <lb/>in theſe diſtempers, which univerſally <lb/>demand great
        medical care and attenti- <lb/>on; but it will certainly be wrong for <lb/>their ſakes to
        expoſe a number of other <lb/>patients to any conſiderable hazard of a <lb/>dreadful
        diſeaſe. Beſides, ſince one of <lb/>the very worſt of theſe diſeaſes takes its <lb/>riſe
        from crowded hoſpitals, it cannot <lb/>be imagined that a place where even the <lb/>leaſt
        degree of the ſame cauſe prevails <lb/>can be a proper receptacle for them; <lb/>for this
        reaſon, as moſt of our hoſpitals <lb/>are at preſent circumſtanced, they ought <lb/>as much
        as poſſible to avoid admitting <lb/>them. The fatal neceſſity of receiving <pb n="51"/>
        <lb/>malignant fevers, into the military hoſ- <lb/>pitals has been too often experienced,
        <lb/>but no ſuch neceſſity takes place in com- <lb/>mon practice. It muſt be left to the
        <lb/>judgment of the hoſpital phyſician, to <lb/>balance the poſitive and negative reaſons,
        <lb/>and to determine as he thinks will con- <lb/>duce moſt to the public good. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">All</hi> diſeaſes affecting the lungs, are, <lb/>I fear, of that kind
        which can never <lb/>receive benefit from even the ſweeteſt <lb/>and beſt contrived
        hoſpital. The direct <lb/>application of the air to the affected part <lb/>renders its
        purity a matter of the higheſt <lb/>conſequence; and indeed it is not enough <lb/>that it be
        merely innoxious, it ought to <lb/>be medicinally ſoft and pure, ſince it is <lb/>frequently
        the only remedy in which we <lb/>can put any confidence. Excluſive of <lb/>any peculiar
        contamination of hoſpital <lb/>air, the circumſtance of their being ſitu- <lb/>ated in large
        towns is a ſufficient objec- <lb/>tion to their receiving theſe diſeaſes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">With</hi> reſpect to chronic diſorders, <lb/>it will be needleſs to go
        through an <pb n="52"/>
        <lb/>enumeration of them for the purpoſe of <lb/>determining the propriety of their ad-
        <lb/>miſſion into hoſpitals. The general con- <lb/>ſiderations formerly laid down muſt de-
        <lb/>termine in each particular caſe, always <lb/>remembring that admitting a patient
        <lb/>cannot be a thing indifferent, but both <lb/>on his own account and that of the other
        <lb/>patients, if no peculiar advantage is ex- <lb/>pected from his being taken into the
        <lb/>houſe, he ſhould remain out. Inſtead <lb/>of ſtudying to fill a hoſpital, we ought
        <lb/>to conſider how it may be emptied, ſince <lb/>every improper object admitted is a
        <lb/>burthen upon the whole houſe; and <lb/>every vacancy, a general relief. I would
        <lb/>wiſh to enforce as much as poſſible the <lb/>idea of a hoſpital being a place deſigned
        <lb/>for the <hi rend="italic">cure of the ſick</hi>, and not an <hi rend="italic">alms
          <lb/>houſe</hi> for the ſupport of the indigent and <lb/>decrepid. I have very frequently
        known <lb/>this matter become the ſubject of diſ- <lb/>pute, and humane perſons ſwayed by
        <lb/>the latter conſideration to recommend <lb/>improper objects for hoſpital relief. Yet
          <pb n="53"/>
        <lb/>nothing is more evident than that the <lb/>ſame inſtitution cannot be calculated
        <lb/>for both intentions, and that it is an <lb/>injury to burthen an infirmary, which
        <lb/>is ſupported by the private charity of <lb/>individuals, with ſuch objects of relief
        <lb/>as are provided for by the public. It is <lb/>not poverty, but ſickneſs, that demands
        <lb/>the aſſiſtance of a hoſpital, and when <lb/>diet and lodging are joined to medical
        <lb/>relief, it is only that the end of curing <lb/>a diſeaſe may be better accompliſhed.
        <lb/>On this account, though the number of <lb/>in-patients ſhould be reſtricted within
        <lb/>confined limits, the out-patient liſt ſhould <lb/>be upon the moſt comprehenſive plan
        <lb/>poſſible; and I would wiſh it to be un- <lb/>derſtood that wherever I have ſpoken
        <lb/>of the impropriety of admitting patients <lb/>into a hoſpital, I meant to leave it en-
        <lb/>tirely free and open to them for relief as <lb/>out-patients. I believe this object is
        in <lb/>general too much neglected. Where it <lb/>is kept up with proper ſpirit and atten-
        <lb/>tion, and a habit of regularity in attend- <pb n="54"/>
        <lb/>ance and obedience to orders is formed <lb/>among the patients, very great and ex-
        <lb/>tenſive good may be done by diſpenſing <lb/>advice and medicines to the poor in ſuch
        <lb/>caſes as do not require admiſſion into a <lb/>hoſpital. There is uſually great neglect
        <lb/>and miſmanagement in the treatment of <lb/>thoſe poor ſick who are paid for by a
        <lb/>pariſh. The Apothecary who contracts <lb/>for them at a fixed annual ſtipend, will
        <lb/>be tempted to conſider it as a job which <lb/>he is to do in the cheapeſt manner poſſi-
        <lb/>ble; and to afford them only ſuch at- <lb/>tendance and medicine as is juſt neceſſa-
        <lb/>ry to preſerve himſelf in office. Indeed <lb/>the ſhamefully ſcanty pittance by which
        <lb/>he is recompenſed may generally be plead- <lb/>ed in his excuſe. There is no temptation
        <lb/>to uſe the out-patients of a hoſpital in <lb/>this manner; and the expence of medi-
        <lb/>cines is ſo trifling in proportion to that <lb/>of the various incidents in houſe-keep-
        <lb/>ing, that there need be very little ap- <lb/>prehenſion of wanting a fund to extend
        <lb/>this branch of charity to all who offer. </p>
      <pb n="55"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">I have</hi> taken occaſion in ſeveral in- <lb/>ſtances to cenſure that
        ſpirit of penuri- <lb/>ous œconomy which makes charity to <lb/>appear ſo unlike itſelf, and
        often defeats <lb/>its benevolent intentions. A reflection <lb/>of this kind occurs to me,
        which I can- <lb/>not more properly introduce than in this <lb/>place. It is the cuſtom in
        many hoſpi- <lb/>tals to require a cautionary ſum to be <lb/>depoſited on admiſſion, with
        the deſign <lb/>of ſecuring the charity from any expence <lb/>for the patient's funeral, in
        caſe of death. <lb/>In the lateſt book of hoſpital rules which <lb/>I have ſeen, that
        compiled for the Lei- <lb/>ceſter Infirmary, it is calculated that the <lb/>ſum of twelve
        ſhillings is ſufficient for <lb/>this purpoſe, which is accordingly de- <lb/>manded on the
        admiſſion of each pa- <lb/>tient. Now this ſum, though apparent- <lb/>ly ſo trifling, is
        ſuch as would diſtreſs <lb/>many poor families to raiſe; and this <lb/>difficulty would, in
        a much greater de- <lb/>gree than can readily be imagined, check <lb/>the utility of
        hoſpitals to that claſs of <lb/>perſons who moſt ſtand in need of them. <pb n="56"/>
        <lb/>The natural propenſity that mankind in <lb/>general has to pay the laſt duties to a
        <lb/>relation, and the horror of ſuch violati- <lb/>ons of the dead as are always ſuſpected
        <lb/>in hoſpitals, will incite all but the moſt <lb/>wretched to take this charge upon them-
        <lb/>ſelves. Such a rule is therefore calcu- <lb/>lated to guard againſt thoſe only whoſe
        <lb/>miſery moſt ſtrongly ſolicits relief; and <lb/>in proportion as the fatality of a
        diſeaſe <lb/>rendered medical aſſiſtance neceſſary, they <lb/>would find a greater
        difficulty in procu- <lb/>ring a friend to depoſite the ſum requi- <lb/>red. In the
        Mancheſter Infirmary, where <lb/>no ſuch demand is made, the expences <lb/>for funerals,
        which is calculated at thir- <lb/>teen or fourteen ſhillings each, has for <lb/>ten years
        paſt amounted to no more than <lb/>eight ſhillings per ann. Had it been <lb/>ten times
        greater it would have been a <lb/>pitiful object to ſtand in competition <lb/>with the
        rights of humanity. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Having</hi> already treated of appropri- <lb/>ating hoſpitals to ſome
        particular diſeaſes, <pb n="57"/>
        <lb/>I ſhall now purſue this ſubject with re- <lb/>gard to another caſe or two. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">There</hi> are no inſtances in which hu- <lb/>manity appears ſo amiable
        as in its relief <lb/>of the diſtreſſes to which the weaker and <lb/>ſofter ſex are
        peculiarly liable. Nature <lb/>has given them a particular claim to our <lb/>tender
        protection, and it is a diſtinguiſh- <lb/>ing mark of civilized manners that they <lb/>add
        force to this natural principle: thus, <lb/>nothing more ſtrongly ſtamps the cha-
        <lb/>racter of <hi rend="italic">Gentleman</hi> than a quick ſenſibi- <lb/>lity and delicate
        attention to this point. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> ſtate of pregnancy and parturiti- <lb/>on moſt eſpecially calls
        forth this regard <lb/>to the ſex, and no age or nation has ever <lb/>been ſo barbarous as
        to be entirely in- <lb/>ſenſible of it. It was therefore an ex- <lb/>tremely natural and
        amiable turn of the <lb/>charitable ſpirit ſo prevalent in this age, <lb/>to inſtitute
        hoſpitals for the reception of <lb/>poor lying-in women; and the ſcheme <lb/>has been
        accordingly honoured by the <lb/>patronage of perſons of the higheſt rank <lb/>and
        character. I ſhould on every ac- <pb n="58"/>
        <lb/>count be unwilling to expreſs any diſap- <lb/>probation of a ſpecies of charity appa-
        <lb/>rently ſo very laudable, did not a real <lb/>concern for the welfare of its objects
        <lb/>overbalance other conſiderations. In- <lb/>fluenced by this motive I know no fear
        <lb/>of public disfavour, and ſhall with free- <lb/>dom give my ſentiments on the ſubject. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> chief ſource of error in the treat- <lb/>ment of puerperal women
        has been con- <lb/>ſidering the ſtate of parturition too much <lb/>a diſeaſe, rather than a
        regular operati- <lb/>on of nature. From hence has proceed- <lb/>ed that numerous train of
        arbitrary rules <lb/>and cuſtoms relating to diet, confine- <lb/>ment, and nurſing, which
        are applied <lb/>indiſcriminately to all perſons without <lb/>regard to their particular
        ſtate or conſti- <lb/>tution. It is a fact for which I refer to <lb/>all intelligent
        practitioners in midwifery, <lb/>that fatal conſequences after delivery, <lb/>happen much
        more frequently in that <lb/>claſs of women who are enabled to com- <lb/>ply with all the
        forms and precautions <lb/>of the moſt delicate practice, than among <pb n="59"/>
        <lb/>thoſe who are in want of every conveni- <lb/>ency, and many things uſually thought
        <lb/>neceſſary in their condition; and are <lb/>forced from every indulgence of reſt and
        <lb/>retirement. Hence ariſes a convincing <lb/>argument that there is ſomething fun-
        <lb/>damentally wrong in the common me- <lb/>thod of treatment, and that the ſo much
        <lb/>dreaded diſeaſes of child-bed are rather <lb/>artificial than natural. On this ſubject
        <lb/>a great deal remains to be ſaid, and it <lb/>is with pleaſure that I can refer to a
        <lb/>treatiſe concerning puerperal fevers, and <lb/>the management of women during this
        <lb/>period, which will ſpeedily be publiſhed <lb/>by a gentleman fully qualified from ex-
        <lb/>tenſive experience and an enlarged free- <lb/>dom of thinking, to make the moſt
        <lb/>uſeful improvements in this part of <lb/>practice. My intimacy with him al- <lb/>lows
        me to borrow a few obſervations <lb/>which are applicable to the preſent pur- <lb/>poſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> ſtate of parturition not being a <lb/>diſeaſe, but a regular
        proceſs of nature, <pb n="60"/>
        <lb/>appears at firſt ſight not to be a fit ſub- <lb/>ject for a hoſpital, which is properly
        <lb/>a receptacle for the ſick. Manual aſſiſt- <lb/>ance in delivery is very rarely
        requiſite; <lb/>and when it is, may eaſily be had by the <lb/>pooreſt perſon from the very
        numerous <lb/>practitioners in this branch. Medicines <lb/>and medical ſuperintendence are
        alſo in <lb/>common caſes totally unneceſſary. Nurſ- <lb/>ing, confinement, and unaccuſtomed
        di- <lb/>et, are much oftener carried to a perni- <lb/>cious exceſs, than deficient in a
        hurtful <lb/>degree to the very loweſt claſs of women. <lb/>Nature rather chooſes to be
        confined <lb/>within mere neceſſaries, than burthened <lb/>with ſuperfluities, and though
        theſe may <lb/>ſeem to contribute to the eaſe and com- <lb/>fort of patients, they ſcarcely
        will to <lb/>their ſafety. Theſe remarks may ſerve <lb/>to ſhow that the puerperal ſtate
        does not <lb/>ſtrongly require the aſſiſtance of hoſpi- <lb/>tals; let us next examine
        whether theſe <lb/>receptacles are not peculiarly improper <lb/>and dangerous to women in
        this condi- <lb/>tion. </p>
      <pb n="61"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Though</hi>, this ſtate is not, as I before <lb/>obſerved, of itſelf a
        diſeaſe, yet it is a vio- <lb/>lent effort of the ſyſtem, which renders <lb/>it particularly
        liable to diſarrangement <lb/>from accidental cauſes. The puerperal <lb/>fever is well
        known, and juſtly dreaded; <lb/>and various are the cauſes to which it has <lb/>been
        attributed. I think myſelf ſuffici- <lb/>ently warranted by the authority before <lb/>cited
        to conſider it in general as the ar- <lb/>tificial product of cloſe vitiated air, too
        <lb/>great warmth, and heating medicines <lb/>and diet. As it is manifeſtly a fever of
        <lb/>the putrid tendency, there can be no <lb/>doubt that every thing diſpoſing to pu-
        <lb/>trefaction muſt firſt act as an occaſional <lb/>cauſe, and during its progreſs as an
        ag- <lb/>gravating circumſtance conducing to a <lb/>fatal termination. Hoſpital peſtilence
        in <lb/>the ſlighteſt degree muſt therefore be <lb/>peculiarly dangerous to lying-in wo-
        <lb/>men; and I wiſh it did not appear too <lb/>plainly from fact, that theſe inſtitutions
        <lb/>as they are at preſent conducted, do not <lb/>anſwer the benevolent deſigns with which
          <pb n="62"/>
        <lb/>they were erected, but rather give di- <lb/>ſeaſes where there were none before, than
        <lb/>prevent or cure them. Within theſe two <lb/>or three years puerperal fevers have been
        <lb/>uncommonly frequent and fatal in Lon- <lb/>don, and have proved extremely diſtreſſ-
        <lb/>ing to practitioners, who have been as <lb/>much at a loſs for the general cauſe, as
        <lb/>the remedy. Whatever this was, I have <lb/>been aſſured from the beſt authority that
        <lb/>they have proportionally raged much <lb/>more in the lying-in hoſpitals, than in
        <lb/>private practice; which is a ſtrong argu- <lb/>ment both of their putreſcent nature,
        <lb/>and of the tendency of theſe hoſpitals to <lb/>produce them. <note place="bottom"
          n="(a)" rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">(a)</hi>
            <hi rend="sc">A remarkable</hi> fact of this kind appears in the <lb/>account of an
            epidemic diſeaſe among the lying-in wo- <lb/>men at Paris, in the year 1746, given in
            the Memoirs <lb/>of the Academy of Sciences; where, after obſerving in <lb/>general that
            the diſeaſe was more fatal to the women de- <lb/>livered at the Hotel Dieu, than to
            thoſe delivered at <lb/>their own houſes, it is remarked that out of twenty of
            <lb/>theſe patients at the Hotel Dieu, ſcarcely one recovered. <lb/>A fatality equal to
            that of the moſt malignant fever ever <lb/>known! </p>
        </note>
      </p>
      <pb n="63"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">On</hi> making a calculation from the <lb/>printed account in the year
        1769, of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Britiſh lying-in hoſpital</hi> (which is con-
        <lb/>ducted by perſons eminent for their ſkill, <lb/>and extremely attentive to every
        circum- <lb/>ſtance that can influence the health of <lb/>their patients) I find the average
        propor- <lb/>tion of deaths from the firſt inſtitution <lb/>has been very nearly one in
        fifty one. <lb/>This mortality can never be ſuppoſed the <lb/>natural conſequence of child
        bearing; <lb/>and from many obſervations in my own <lb/>practice, and that of others, I am
        certain <lb/>that private practice is uſually much <lb/>more ſucceſsful. The publiſhers of
        that <lb/>account ſeem aware that the number of <lb/>deaths is alarming, and in ſome meaſure
        <lb/>endeavour to apologize for it, by ſaying, <lb/>that moſt of thoſe who died were
        afflict- <lb/>ed with dangerous diſtempers at their <lb/>admiſſion; but I do not ſee that a
        larger <lb/>allowance of ſuch caſes ought to be made <lb/>for hoſpital patients than for an
        equal <lb/>number of other poor; and it is to be <pb n="64"/>
        <lb/>conſidered that the private practitioner <lb/>who is never called to the poor but in
        <lb/>caſes of difficulty and danger, has a great <lb/>diſadvantage in this reſpect, which
        hoſ- <lb/>pitals that receive patients indiſcrimi- <lb/>nately, are exempt from. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">I should</hi> be extremely unwilling to <lb/>check the progreſs of any
        charitable in- <lb/>ſtitution, which in the main appears <lb/>calculated to promote the
        public good; <lb/>I therefore beg it may be underſtood, <lb/>that my remarks on lying-in
        hoſpitals <lb/>are chiefly calculated for thoſe now in <lb/>being, not ſuch as may hereafter
        be e- <lb/>rected upon an improved plan. Theſe <lb/>I doubt not might be rendered a great
        <lb/>comfort to the poor, without giving riſe <lb/>to any peculiar danger as hoſpitals; and
        <lb/>if nature has in general ſo amply provi- <lb/>ded for the <hi rend="italic">ſafety</hi>
        of women in this con- <lb/>dition, as to render hoſpitals unneceſſary <lb/>with regard to
        their uſual purpoſe of <lb/><hi rend="italic">curing a diſeaſe</hi>, ſtill they may be very
          <pb n="65"/>
        <lb/>uſeful and laudable inſtitutions, conſi- <lb/>dered in the light of <hi rend="italic"
          >common charity</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">There</hi> is another benevolent deſign <lb/>now carried on in London for
        the de- <lb/>livery of poor women at their own hou- <lb/>ſes; in which the attendance of a
        ſkilful <lb/>practitioner, intruſted with a power of <lb/>diſtributing ſupplies as he finds
        requiſite, <lb/>muſt be productive of the kindeſt and <lb/>happieſt effects, and cannot be
        liable to <lb/>a ſingle objection, if faithfully and ju- <lb/>diciouſly managed. Such a
        deſign merits <lb/>the warmeſt encouragement, and I <lb/>heartily wiſh it ſucceſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> laſt diſeaſe to which particular <lb/>hoſpitals have been
        appropriated, that I <lb/>ſhall mention, is Lunacy. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> caſe of the unhappy objects af- <lb/>flicted with this diſorder
        is in a peculiar <lb/>manner diſtreſsful, ſince beſides their <lb/>own ſufferings, they are
        rendered a nu- <lb/>ſance and terror to others; and are not <lb/>only themſelves loſt to
        ſociety, but take <lb/>up the whole time and attention of <pb n="66"/>
        <lb/>others. By placing a number of them <lb/>in a common receptacle, they may be <lb/>taken
        care of by a much ſmaller number <lb/>of attendants; at the ſame time they are <lb/>removed
        from the public eye to which <lb/>they were multiplied objects of alarm, <lb/>and the
        miſchiefs they are liable to do <lb/>to themſelves and others, are with much <lb/>greater
        certainty prevented. It is a me- <lb/>lancholy circumſtance of this diſeaſe that <lb/>it
        very ſeldom admits of a perfect cure; <lb/>ſo that there is a probability of its re-
        <lb/>quiring almoſt during life the care and <lb/>ſuperintendence of ſkilful perſons. As
        <lb/>its ſeat appears to be rather in the mind <lb/>than the body, the attention of art muſt
        <lb/>be chiefly directed to acquire a proper <lb/>government over the temper and paſſi-
        <lb/>ons, by means of contrary affections of <lb/>the mind; a taſk which neceſſarily ſup-
        <lb/>poſes conſtant obſervation and great ex- <lb/>perience in theſe particular caſes, to-
        <lb/>gether with that firmneſs and total <pb n="67"/>
        <lb/>abſence of terror which can only be <lb/>gained by habit. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">From</hi> all theſe conſiderations it has <lb/>long been the cuſtom to
        confine theſe <lb/>patients in houſes appropriated for their <lb/>reception, and provided
        with perſons <lb/>experienced in their management. In- <lb/>ſtitutions of this kind,
        undertaken by <lb/>private perſons for their own emolu- <lb/>ment, are ſufficiently
        numerous; but the <lb/>poor in this kingdom have hitherto been <lb/>but indifferently
        provided with public <lb/>hoſpitals for the relief of Lunatics. Be- <lb/>ſides the two in
        London, there is not <lb/>throughout the kingdom one that de- <lb/>ſerves the name of a
        Lunatic hoſpital, <lb/>except a lately erected one at Mancheſ- <lb/>ter. From an account of
        this laſt lately <lb/>publiſhed, I ſhall quote ſome conſidera- <lb/>tions which induced the
        promoters of <lb/>charity in that place to ſet on foot ſo <lb/>benevolent a deſign. </p>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="15"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
