<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Bromehead: An oration on the utility of public infirmaries</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Joseph Bromehead</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">AN ORATION ON THE UTILITY OF PUBLIC INFIRMARIES. OCCASIONED BY THE
              Opening of the RADCLIFFE Infirmary at Oxford. </title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T111999</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T111999"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: sold by J. and F. Rivington, in St. Paul's Church-Yard; and D.
                  Prince, in Oxford, MDCCLXXII.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1772</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="2"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="24"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3306592925</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K089699.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Public welfare and institutional"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_2"/>
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>ADVERTISEMENT. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>THE following little Piece was haſtily drawn <lb/>up in the Year 1769,
          when the Heads of the <lb/>Univerſity announced their Intention of <w part="I"
            >open-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> the <hi rend="italic">Radcliffe</hi> Infirmary with
          an Encœnia. <lb/>They afterwards dropped this Deſign. But <lb/>the Author having lately
          employed a leiſure <lb/>Hour in correcting and ſomewhat enlarging his <lb/><hi rend="sc"
            >Oration</hi>, now begs Leave to lay it before the <lb/>Public. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_3"/>
      <head rend="align-center"><lb/>AN <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">ORATION</hi>
        <lb/>ON THE UTILITY OF <lb/><hi rend="size(1.7)">PUBLIC INFIRMARIES. </hi></head>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>F we cloſely examine the moral Qualities, which
        are <lb/>denominated Virtues, and which Mankind have agreed <lb/>to honour with Applauſe, we
        ſhall find that almoſt all <lb/>regard Man, as he is a ſocial Being, born to do good
        <lb/>Offices to others. Upon this Principle it is found likewiſe, <lb/>that our Approbation
        of virtuous Actions, is uſually <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">portioned</w> to the
        Extent of their Influence and Utility. <lb/>Thus a Legiſlator and a Patriot muſt ever be
        more admired <lb/>than a Man of Prudence, Wiſdom, and Integrity, exerted <lb/>only in the
        contracted Sphere of private Life. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">But</hi> of all the ſocial Qualities, Benevolence is the
        moſt <lb/>immediately uſeful. It is indeed the Source of all the reſt, <pb xml:id="page_4"
          n="6"/><lb/>and naturally induces that great End and Cement of Society, <lb/>mutual
        Beneficence. This Virtue too, like all others, <lb/>becomes more illuſtrious in Proportion
        as its Conſequences <lb/>are more extended. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">To</hi> the ſtrong and univerſal Prevalence of this
        amiable <lb/>Quality it is owing, that the Magiſtrates and Legiſlators, <lb/>in moſt
        Countries, have inſtituted ſome Proviſion to <w part="I">alle-</w><lb/><w part="F">viate</w>
        the Miſeries of the Indigent and Helpleſs. This alſo, <lb/>in the opulent, the liberal, and
        the ingenuous, has <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">duced</w> the undertaking of Works
        of the preſent Kind, of <lb/>Hoſpitals, Infirmaries, and Receptacles for the Relief of
        <lb/>various Diſtreſſes. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Indeed</hi> the Goods of Fortune, the Means of Health and
        <lb/>Felicity, which come to the Rich by Inheritance or <w part="I">Acquiſi-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">tion</w>, are not their ſole excluſive Property. The Poor have <lb/>a Claim of
        Right for their Share. And the Relation that <lb/>ſubſiſts between them and the Rich,
        certainly obliges the <lb/>latter to aſſiſt them under Diſeaſes, Caſualties, and heavy
        <lb/>Calamities. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_5" n="7"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> perhaps may not be unneceſſary to remind the Sons
        of <lb/>Eaſe and Affluence, that the laborious Poor not only form <lb/>the Bulk of the
        Nation, but are likewiſe the Part on which <lb/>the Strength, the Proſperity, and even the
        Exiſtence of the<lb/>Whole depends. To them, as diſtributed through the <lb/>humbler and
        more toilſome Offices of Society, we owe all <lb/>the Neceſſaries of Life, and all its
        Conveniencies. The <lb/>Labour of the Husbandman, the Manufacturer, and <w part="I"
          >Me-</w><lb/><w part="F">chanic</w>, is confeſſedly eſſential to the Welfare of the
        <lb/>Community; and yet a preſent Subſiſtence for themſelves <lb/>and their Families is
        their only Recompence. Every Sun <lb/>riſes to light them to their fatiguing Labour, which
        often <lb/>ends not with the cloſing Day. They contentedly toil on <lb/>from Youth to Age,
        and while they perhaps repoſe their <lb/>weary Limbs in the Hut of Poverty, ſee their Sons
        entering <lb/>upon the ſame Courſe of unnoticed Hardſhips and <w part="I">unre-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">warded</w> Induſtry. Surely then their Lot at the beſt is not to <lb/>be envied.
        But what a deplorable Change muſt they feel, <lb/>ſhould they be attacked by any one of that
        Hoſt of Diſeaſes <lb/>which make ſuch Havock amongſt the human Race? That <lb/>Strength
        which ſupported them in their daily Toil, now <pb xml:id="page_6" n="8"/><lb/>fails them;
        that Health of Body and Eaſe of Mind which <lb/>lightened the Burthen of Poverty, are now no
        more. <lb/>Sickneſs, by diſabling them from earning a Subſiſtence, occaſions Want, and Want
        excludes the Means of <w part="I">Reco-</w><lb/><w part="F">very</w> from Sickneſs. The two
        greateſt of natural Evils <lb/>united, double each other's Weight, and accumulate
        <lb/>Diſtreſs. Thus, in more ſultry Climes, the ſcorching Sun <lb/>every where oppreſſes the
        fainting Traveller with his <lb/>Beams, but ſhould they be reflected from the Declivity of
        <lb/>ſome barren Mountain, the Heat becomes intolerable, the <lb/>very Air is tainted, and
        all Nature ſickens. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Without</hi> Health, without the Means of recovering
        <lb/>it, or even of ſubſiſting, whither then muſt theſe abandoned <lb/>Sons of Affliction
        look for Relief? To the caſual <w part="I">Munifi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cence</w> of private
        Benefactors? Uncertain, hopeleſs Proſpect! <lb/>To their own Friends or Kindred? Alas! their
        Pity is all <lb/>they have to beſtow. To their Children (ſince ſome of them <lb/>no doubt
        are Fathers of Families)?—But here the Scene is <lb/>truly calamitous. The little Mourners
        ſtand round the ſick <lb/>Bed of their Parent, and while they feel, deeply feel for his <pb
          xml:id="page_7" n="9"/><lb/>Sufferings, cannot be inſenſible to their own. He turns
        <lb/>an hopeleſs Eye towards them, perceives them in Want of <lb/>that Bread which he had
        hitherto provided for them by his <lb/>Labour, perceives them foretaſting thoſe Diſtreſſes
        which, <lb/>at his Death, are to be their ſad Inheritance. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">But</hi> waving theſe peculiar Circumſtances of Miſery,
        let <lb/>us only reflect on that Variety of Diſtempers to which <lb/>Poverty is expoſed,
        without the Means of Relief. And in <lb/>this View, what Objects of Compaſſion preſent
        themſelves <lb/>before us? Objects which muſt awe the Pride of Man, and <lb/>awaken his
        Tenderneſs. </p>
      <q rend="quotes size(0.5)"><lb/><l>Numbers of all diſeas'd, all Maladies, </l>
        <lb/><l>Of ghaſtly Spaſm, or racking Torture, Qualms </l>
        <lb/><l>Of heart-ſick Agony, all feverous Kinds, </l>
        <lb/><l>Convulſions, Epilepſies, fierce Catarrhs, </l>
        <lb/><l>Inteſtine Stone and Ulcer, Colic Pangs, </l>
        <lb/><l>Demoniac Phrenzy, moping Melancholy, </l>
        <lb/><l>And Moon-ſtruck Madneſs, pining Atrophy, </l>
        <lb/><l>Maraſmus, and wide-waſting Peſtilence, </l>
        <lb/><l>Dropſies and Aſthmas, and joint-racking Rheums. </l></q>
      <pb xml:id="page_8" n="10"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">What</hi> a Group of human Miſeries! All various, yet all
        <lb/>languid, deformed, and loathſome. A benevolent Mind <lb/>ſhudders at their very Names.
        But could you have the <lb/>wretched Sufferers before your Sight, could you mark the
        <lb/>dire toſſing of reſtleſs Anguiſh, and liſten to the deep <lb/>Groans of Deſpair, ſurely
        every Eye would drop a <w part="I">ſympa-</w><lb/><w part="F">thizing</w> Tear, and every
        gentle Heart would bleed. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> may juſtly be a Matter of Wonder that our civil
        <lb/>Police has made none, or at leaſt no adequate Proviſion <lb/>for the Poor when
        labouring under theſe Calamities. They <lb/>are the Servants of the Public, and therefore
        entitled to its <lb/>Protection. Beſides, a ſtronger Tye ſubſiſts. They <lb/>whoſe
        Diſtreſſes thus loudly implore our Compaſſion, what <lb/>are they? Want, indeed, and
        Misfortunes have much <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">guiſed</w> them, and Miſery hath
        worn them to the Bone. <lb/>Yet they have the ſame Nature, and except a few accidental
        <lb/>variable Diſtinctions, are the ſame with us. They have an <lb/>Original alike divine, a
        Mind alike intelligent. To be a <lb/>Man, and to be miſerable, is a ſufficient Claim on the
        <lb/>generous and humane. Shall we then leave thoſe to periſh, <lb/>whom it is the Intereſt
        of their Country, and the Duty of <pb xml:id="page_9" n="11"/><lb/>all Mankind to aſſiſt and
        preſerve? Medicine, and every <lb/>other Relief in the Calamity of bodily Diſeaſes, are
        natural <lb/>Proviſions for the preſent indigent and infirm State of the <lb/>Sons of Men.
        In Spite, indeed, of all theſe Aſſiſtances, <lb/>Sickneſs will ſtill ſlay its Thouſands, and
        thin the World b<lb/>y its deſtroying Sword. But nothing ſurely can more <lb/>contradict the
        Order of Nature and the Will of Providence, <lb/>than that Numbers ſhould fall Victims, not
        ſo much to the <lb/>Fury of Diſeaſe, as to the Neglect and Cruelty of thoſe <lb/>who ought
        to ſupply them with the Means of Recovery. <lb/>Yet how many of our ſick and diſabled Poor
        muſt be left to <lb/>this unhappy Lot, if no public Infirmaries are eſtabliſhed <lb/>to
        receive them? </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">These</hi>, indeed, open their friendly Doors for ſuch
        poor <lb/>deſerted Wretches, theſe bind up their Wounds, and exert <lb/>all the Power of
        Medicine to heal their Diſeaſes. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Where</hi> no charitable Aſylums of this Kind are erected,
        <lb/>it is a common Reſource with our ſick Poor, though a fatal <lb/>one, to apply to
        mercenary and pernicious Empirics, <lb/>whoſe Ignorance either immediately deprives them of
        their <pb xml:id="page_10" n="12"/><lb/>Lives, or injures their Healths beyond Reparation.
        But <lb/>in theſe Houſes of Charity they are ſure to find able <w part="I">Phyſi-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">cians</w>, and every Thing provided for their Conveniency <lb/>and Cure that Art
        can ſuggeſt or Munificence ſupply. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Public</hi> Infirmaries are not only the beſt, but the
        only <lb/>Means by which the neceſſitous can procure the ſeveral <lb/>Kinds of Aſſiſtance
        which their various bodily Diſeaſes <lb/>require. In large commercial Towns, what other
        Proviſion <lb/>can be made againſt thoſe Caſualties which ſo frequently <lb/>happen to the
        poor labouring Part of the Inhabitants, or <lb/>to the ſtill more unfortunate Stranger? </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Here</hi> give me leave to add to theſe general <w
          part="I">Advan-</w><lb/><w part="F">tages</w>, one peculiar to this Place. A Faſhion has
        of late <lb/>prevailed, to ſend ſuch of our Youth as are deſigned for the <lb/>Profeſſion of
        Phyſic, to foreign Academies, which, though <lb/>far inferior to our own in every other
        Reſpect, have been <lb/>thought ſuperior in this. The Reaſon of a Cuſtom ſo <lb/>injurious
        to the Intereſt of our Country, and the Honour of <lb/>our Seats of Learning, is far from
        being ſatisfactory; <w part="I">how-</w><lb/><w part="F">ever</w>, by the preſent
        Inſtitution, the very Shadow of it is <pb xml:id="page_11" n="13"/><lb/>removed. Important
        as every public Infirmary muſt be, <lb/>the Importance of this is ſtill more extenſive. It
        affords <lb/>not only the beſt Aſſiſtance to the ſick and diſabled, but <lb/>likewiſe the
        beſt Opportunities of Obſervation and <w part="I">Improve-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w> to
        young Students in the medical Science, on whoſe <lb/>future Skill ſo much depends. It has
        the happy, the <w part="I">ſin-</w><lb/><w part="F">gular</w> Excellence of at once
        relieving the Miſery of <w part="I">Indivi-</w><lb/><w part="F">duals</w>, and making that
        Miſery beneficial to the Community. <lb/>We now, at length, may juſtly boaſt that ours is
        the moſt <lb/>compleat Seminary in <hi rend="italic">Europe</hi> for ſo important a Study,
        <lb/>whether we regard Botany, Anatomy, the Theory or <lb/>Practice of Medicine. To no
        Profeſſion is Learning more <lb/>neceſſary: and here Students can beſt conſult the rich
        <lb/>Treaſures of Antiquity, and the Parents of the healing <lb/>Art: here they may add
        every liberal Accompliſhment, and <lb/>acquire that general and extenſive Knowledge for
        which <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Engliſh</hi> Phyſicians are deſervedly diſtinguiſhed. When
        <lb/>we conſider the general and local Advantages of the <w part="I">Infir-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">mary</w> here erected, what public Honours and Benefits may <lb/>we not date from
        this auſpicious Æra? May we not foretell, <lb/>that as our <hi rend="italic">Alma Mater</hi>
        already reckons in the liſt of her <pb xml:id="page_12" n="14"/><lb/>Sons, the greateſt
        Names in Medicine, ſhe will now add to <lb/>the glorious Catalogue, and ſee in her Train
        future <lb/><hi rend="italic">Linacres, Willis's, Radcliffes,</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
          >Friends,</hi> who ſhall emulate <lb/>the Science and Reputation of thoſe who have gone
        before <lb/>them? </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">But</hi> enough perhaps has been ſaid to prove how much
        <lb/>theſe Inſtitutions concern the public Intereſt and Honour: <lb/>Indeed one would think
        it impoſſible that any Perſons <lb/>ſhould object to, or refuſe ſupporting theſe excellent
          <w part="I">Under-</w><lb/><w part="F">takings</w>, which are ſo beneficial in all their
        Views: one <lb/>would think it, I ſay, impoſſible. But if any ſuch ſhould <lb/>be, with ſuch
        we will not contend. Let Avarice refuſe its <lb/>Aſſiſtance, and, if poſſible, its Applauſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Though</hi> publick Infirmaries have political Advantages
        <lb/>ſo undeniable and ſelf-evident, yet we may ſafely affirm <lb/>that they ſtand on a
        firmer Baſis, that they are ſupported <lb/>by Arguments ſtronger than the Deductions of
        Reaſon; <lb/>Arguments which every generous Breaſt muſt feel. When <lb/>we reflect on the
        Malignity of the Diſeaſes, the Weight <pb xml:id="page_13" n="15"/><lb/>of the complicated
        Afflictions which they are intended to <lb/>relieve, we are, we cannot but be intereſted and
        diſpoſed <lb/>to compaſſionate the Sufferers, partly from the <w part="I"
          >Conſciouſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ness</w> of being liable to the ſame Evils, and partly
        from <lb/>thy nobler Impulſes, O Benevolence! Here the truly <lb/>humane Mind, like a
        well-tuned Inſtrument of Muſick, <lb/>obeys the ſudden Touches of Pity, and the ſweet
        Harmony <lb/>of its ſocial Affections, wholly paſſive in the Sympathy <lb/>of its own
        Goodneſs. While the Rich and Powerful <lb/>indulge the tender Senſations of Humanity, and
        promote <lb/>ſuch well-plann'd Works of Beneficence as the preſent <lb/>Inſtitution, they at
        once communicate Happineſs to <lb/>others, and inexpreſſibly augment their own. They feel,
        <lb/>that they are obeying the Dictates of pureſt Nature, and <lb/>wiſeſt Reaſon; that they
        are fulfilling the Ends of <w part="I">So-</w><lb/><w part="F">ciety</w>, and the Will of
        its great Author, whoſe darling <lb/>Attribute is Mercy, whoſe very Eſſence is Love. Moſt
        <lb/>wiſely did he diſtribute Men into theſe ſubordinate Ranks, <lb/>and implant theſe
        generous Principles. </p>
      <q rend="quotes size(0.5)"><lb/><l>—"He form'd a Whole, the Whole to bleſs, </l>
        <lb/><l>On mutual Wants built mutual Happineſs." </l></q>
      <pb xml:id="page_14" n="16"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Whatever</hi> may be the Vices of the preſent Age, the
        <lb/>moſt cenſorious Cynick muſt allow that it has its Share <lb/>of that Philanthropy and
        Tenderneſs which we would <lb/>here recommend. Hiſtory informs us that it was the
        <lb/>barbarous Policy of ſome ancient States to expoſe Infants <lb/>if infirm, to abandon
        diſeaſed Perſons, and even to deſtroy <lb/>thoſe who were rendered uſeleſs to the Community
        by <lb/>Age and Decrepitude. But poliſhed Times and Nations <lb/>are Strangers to ſuch
        unfeeling Sentiments. A Diſpoſition <lb/>to Compaſſion and to Offices of Kindneſs will ever
        gain <lb/>Ground in Proportion to Civilization, and improved <w part="I">Ele-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">gance</w> of Manners. Perhaps this Virtue expands itſelf <lb/>moſt, when the
        Powers of the Mind are ſoftened by <lb/>Luxury, and all other Virtues are in the Wane. It is
        <lb/>certain that the earlieſt Societies had leſs of it; Warriors <lb/>and Heroes were their
        greateſt Characters. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">However</hi> this may be, I need not heſitate to <w
          part="I">congra-</w><lb/><w part="F">tulate</w> my Country, ſince a bountiful and
        beneficent <lb/>Spirit is, and has ever been its national Characteriſtick. <lb/>For this, I
        may appeal even to the ruder Ages of Ignorance <pb xml:id="page_15" n="17"/><lb/>and
        Superſtition, to thoſe hoſpitable and intentionally <lb/>Religious, to thoſe venerable and
        princely Foundations, <lb/>over whoſe general undiſtinguiſhed Ruins, Humanity and <lb/>Piety
        muſt for ever mourn. Through the miſtaken Zeal <lb/>of our Anceſtors, theſe abounded more in
        our Iſle than <lb/>in any other Chriſtian Country. And if at their <w part="I"
          >Diſſo-</w><lb/><w part="F">lution</w>, theſe noble Edifices and Endowments had been
        <lb/>applied to the Uſes which the publick Intereſt required; <lb/>Poverty, Sickneſs, and
        decrepit Age had never wanted an <lb/>Aſylum, nor had the ſacred Will of the Dead been ſo
        <lb/>flagrantly violated, or their Aſhes ſo impiouſly diſturbed. <lb/>Some of them it muſt
        be owned in the Capital, by the <lb/>Care and Earneſtneſs of an excellent Prelate, were
        ſaved <lb/>from the ſacrilegious Talons of Court-Harpies, and <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ſecrated</w> to the Relief of Miſery and Diſeaſe. But ſo ſmall <lb/>was the
        Number, that it ſeemed only to point out how <lb/>much might and ought to have been done,
        had the leaſt <lb/>Degree of publick Spirit, Juſtice, or Honour influenced <lb/>thoſe
        infamous Plunderers. Here then was loſt the grand <lb/>Opportunity of eſtabliſhing
        Receptacles for Diſtreſs in <lb/>every Part of the Kingdom; and with equal Indignation <pb
          xml:id="page_16" n="18"/><lb/>and Sorrow muſt we look back on this deep, this indelible
        <lb/>Stain of the Annals of our Reformation. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">But</hi> now indeed we ſee fairer and brighter Proſpects
        <lb/>around us. A Spirit of Charity has diffuſed itſelf amongſt <lb/>all Ranks of People,
        amongſt our Merchants, our <w part="I">Law-</w><lb/><w part="F">givers</w>, and Nobles. The
        Liberality of our Forefathers <lb/>is at leaſt equalled, and their Wiſdom in chooſing
        Objects <lb/>of that Liberality much ſurpaſſed. In our Metropolis, <lb/>almoſt every Species
        of Diſtreſs has been conſidered, <lb/>pitied, and relieved. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> deſerted Infant, whoſe Misfortunes begin with its
        <lb/>Exiſtence, meets that Redreſs for which it cannot petition. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> unhappy Proſtitute, though ſhe has ſurvived <w
          part="I">Inno-</w><lb/><w part="F">cence</w>, finds ſhe has not ſurvived Compaſſion, ſhe
        ſees an <lb/>hoſpitable Retreat open for her Miſery and Shame, ſees a <lb/>friendly Hand
        reached out to recover her ſtumbling Feet <lb/>to the Paths of Virtue and Peace. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_17" n="19"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>I <hi rend="sc">might</hi> lead your Attention to that Manſion within
        <lb/>whoſe Walls we behold the noble Fabrick of the Human <lb/>Mind in its melancholy
        Ruins.—But this is a Sight of <lb/>all others, the moſt humiliating and painful. For Perſons
        <lb/>in a State ſo conſummately calamitous, the bleeding Pity <lb/>of their Fellow-Citizens
        has made a munificent Proviſion; <lb/>—like the wounded Tree of <hi rend="italic"
          >Arabia,</hi> it weeps healing <lb/>Balm. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Worthy</hi> the Kings of a martial and generous People
        <lb/>are thoſe royal Foundations, which receive the maimed <lb/>Veteran, who has fought the
        Battles of his Country. <lb/>There after all his Toils and Dangers he ſits down to
        <lb/>recite in the honeſt Loquacity of Age his hardy Deeds, <lb/>and count his glorious
        Scars.—Brave Man! Peaceful ſhall <lb/>be the Evening of a Life expoſed in the Service of <hi
          rend="italic">Britain;</hi>
        <lb/>—thy hoary Head is covered with well-earned Laurels! </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>I <hi rend="sc">need</hi> not mention the various Infirmaries and <w
          part="I">Hoſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">pitals</w> for the Sick. Enough has already been ſaid on
        the <lb/>Excellence of theſe Houſes of Mercy; and this is a Species <pb xml:id="page_18"
          n="20"/><lb/>of patriotick Charity which has not been confined to our <lb/>chief City. In
        other Parts of the Kingdom, Receptacles <lb/>have been eſtabliſhed for thoſe who groan under
        the <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">plicated</w> Wretchedneſs of Poverty and Diſeaſe.
        And every <lb/>one of this illuſtrious Audience, every one (I doubt it not) <lb/>will join
        me in wiſhing that the Streams of Beneficence <lb/>may ſtill flow in ſo uſeful a Channel,
        and that each of <lb/>our provincial Towns may be bleſt with ſuch an Inſtitution <lb/>as
        that which <hi rend="italic">Oxford</hi> at length enjoys. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Whilst</hi> the benevolent Speculatiſt, the ſincere Lover
        <lb/>of his Country contemplates all theſe Eſtabliſhments as <lb/>the Monuments of national
        Virtue, and the Sources of <lb/>innumerable Advantages to the State; the Lover of the
        <lb/>Arts will conſider them in an additional Point of View, <lb/>will regard the Structures
        which are deſtined to the <w part="I">Pur-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſes</w> of public
        Munificence as exhibiting to foreign <lb/>Nations and to Poſterity, the moſt ſtriking Proofs
        of the <lb/>Taſte and Magnificence of his Countrymen and <w part="I">Contem-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">poraries</w>. The Houſes of private Citizens (however <lb/>opulent) are ſeldom
        equal in the Beauty of their Structure <pb xml:id="page_19" n="21"/><lb/>to Edifices of
        publick Uſe and Contrivance. Where the <lb/>Purpoſes of private and domeſtick Utility are
        only to be anſwered, the Genius of the Artiſt is neceſſarily <w part="I">circum-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ſcribed</w>: He may indeed in theſe give Proofs of the <lb/>Elegance of his
        Taſte, and the Correctneſs of his Ideas; <lb/>but from the Grand and Magnificent he is
        unavoidably <lb/>precluded. But public Edifices of every Kind, have moſt <lb/>of all,
        contributed to diſplay the Arts of Deſign in their <lb/>full Luſtre, in every Age and
        Country where thoſe Arts <lb/>have been cultivated. To them we owe the Memory <lb/>both of
        laudable Actions and of illuſtrious Artiſts; and <lb/>by them the flouriſhing Nations of
        Antiquity have <w part="I">tranſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">mitted</w> to us the moſt durable
        Records of their former <lb/>Splendor and Greatneſs. To them the firſt, and moſt
        <lb/>celebrated Cities of the World at this Day owe their chief <lb/>Ornament. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> Number of magnificent Churches, Colleges, and
        <lb/>other publick Buildings throughout the Chriſtian <w part="I">Boun-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >daries</w>, and eſpecially in <hi rend="italic">Italy,</hi> have afforded an ample Field
        <lb/>to the Genius of the Architect, the Statuary, and the <pb xml:id="page_20" n="22"
        /><lb/>Painter. In one City only, the immenſe Fabrick of <hi rend="italic">St.
          <lb/>Peter</hi>'s, the Church of <hi rend="italic">St. John Lateran,</hi> the <hi
          rend="italic">Vatican</hi>
        <lb/>Library, the Hoſpital of the <hi rend="italic">Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and almoſt
        <lb/>innumerable other Edifices of public Uſe, will always <lb/>preſent <hi rend="italic"
          >Rome,</hi> though fallen from her ancient Glories, <lb/>as highly deſerving the Attention
        of the curious Traveller, <lb/>and will immortalize the Names as well of thoſe Artiſts
        <lb/>who contributed their Talents to their Erection and <w part="I">Embel-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">liſhment</w>, as of the Popes their Patrons. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi>
        <hi rend="italic">Spain,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">France,</hi> in our own Country, and in
        every <lb/>Nation where the Arts have fixed their Reſidence, their <lb/>Influence is moſt
        conſpicuous in the Beauty and <w part="I">Gran-</w><lb/><w part="F">deur</w> of publick
        Structures. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>No City or People can be more indebted for <w part="I"
          >Decora-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w> of this Kind to the Munificence of a private
        Citizen, <lb/>than we are to that admirable Perſon, from whoſe <w part="I">exten-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ſive</w> Benefactions to this Seminary hath ariſen the Deſign <lb/>and
        Eſtabliſhment of an Infirmary in this Place. It would <lb/>therefore be unjuſt to cloſe
        theſe Reflections without ſome <lb/>Tribute to his Memory. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_21" n="23"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Superior</hi> to the common Views of a lucrative
        Profeſſion, <lb/>he eſteemed Wealth only valuable, as it enabled him to <lb/>extend his good
        Offices to Mankind. Hence the vaſt <lb/>Fortune which he acquired by his ſingular Talents in
        the <lb/>important Science of Phyſick, was while he lived, a Fund <lb/>of Charity and
        Beneficence; and the noble Bequeſts made <lb/>by him at his Death to this Place of his
        Education, will <lb/>continue the good Effects of his Liberality and his <w part="I"
          >Grati-</w><lb/><w part="F">tude</w> to the remoteſt Times. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">He</hi> was a Man undoubtedly born for the Benefit and
        <lb/>Ornament of his Country. His Virtues were of that <lb/>Kind whoſe Luſtre will appear
        more amiable to the <lb/>undazzled Eye of Wiſdom than the Trophies of <w part="I"
          >Con-</w><lb/><w part="F">querors</w>, and the ſplendid Qualities of thoſe whom the
        <lb/>ill-judging Multitude calls Great. Amongſt the military <lb/>Honours of ancient <hi
          rend="italic">Rome,</hi> the only one perhaps, with <lb/>which a benevolent Man would wiſh
        to intwine his Brow, <lb/>is the Civic Crown. And if he who preſerved the Life <lb/>of a
        ſingle Citizen deſerved to be ſo diſtinguiſhed, what <lb/>Crowns muſt we weave for <hi
          rend="sc">Radcliffe</hi>?—Such was <pb xml:id="page_22" n="24"/><lb/>the Wiſdom which
        guided his beneficent Soul, ſuch was <lb/>the Propriety which regulated the Diſpoſition of
        his Wealth, <lb/>that though dead he ſtill remedies the Diſtreſſes and <w part="I"
          >Diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">eaſes</w> of Men, and claims from them a daily-increaſing
        <lb/>Tribute of grateful Applauſe. The helpleſs Objects, who <lb/>are relieved from Miſery,
        or reſcued from Death by his <lb/>Bounty, ſhall hang around his Monument, the uſeleſs
        <lb/>Crutch, and the votive Tablet.—Even thoſe on whom <lb/>Providence has beſtowed
        Affluence, though they are not <lb/>affected by his Munificence, may be animated by his
        <lb/>Example. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">But</hi> it is unneceſſary to expatiate on Merit ſo <w
          part="I">tranſcen-</w><lb/><w part="F">dent</w>, and I will not obſcure his Praiſes by my
        feeble <lb/>Attempts to diſplay them. As the Benefits reſulting <lb/>from his well-directed
        and boundleſs Liberality, will <lb/>aſſuredly extend to future Ages, we may ſafely truſt his
        <lb/>Fame to Poſterity. </p>
      <trailer rend="align-center"><lb/>FINIS. </trailer>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
