<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Bowen: An historical account of the origin, progress, and present
          state of Bethlem Hospital </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Thomas Bowen</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">An historical account of the origin, progress, and present state of
              Bethlem Hospital, founded by Henry the Eighth, for the cure of lunatics, and Enlarged
              by subsequent Benefactors, for the Reception and Maintenance of incurables. </title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T36299</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T36299"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed in the Year, M.DCC.LXXXIII.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1783</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="4"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="16"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW101960639</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Public welfare and institutional"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="4"/>
    <body>
      <pb n="1"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>AN <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">HISTORICAL ACCOUNT </hi>
        <lb/>OF THE <lb/><hi rend="size(2.0) space">Origin, Progreſs, and Preſent State </hi>
        <lb/>OF <lb/><hi rend="size(2.0)">BETHLEM HOSPITAL. </hi>
      </head>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>A long horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HOSE <hi rend="sc">ancient foundations</hi>, which have been
        eſtabliſhed <lb/>in the city of <hi rend="sc">London</hi> by the munificence of our <hi
          rend="sc">monarchs</hi>, <lb/>for the relief and maintenance of the <hi rend="sc">diseased
          poor</hi>, have always <lb/>been conſidered as objects worthy of public ſupport. The care
        of <hi rend="sc">indi- <lb/>gent lunatics</hi> is attended with peculiar difficulties, and,
        as much im- <lb/>mediate evil muſt ariſe from the neglect of them, the community cannot
        <lb/>but be nearly intereſted in the welfare and proſperity of thoſe places <lb/>which are
        provided for their reception. It may not therefore be <lb/>thought improper to give ſome
        account of the origin, progreſs, and <lb/>preſent ſtate of Bethlem Hoſpital. </p>
      <pb n="2"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">The Hospital of Bethlem</hi> owes it's name and original eſta-
        <lb/>bliſhment to the piety of a <hi rend="sc">citizen of London</hi>. In the year
        <lb/>1247, in the 39th of Henry the third, <hi rend="sc">Simon Fitz Mary</hi>, who had
        <lb/>been ſheriff, influenced by the prevailing ſuperſtition of the age, was <lb/>deſirous
        to found a religious houſe. Accordingly, he appropriated by <lb/>a deed of gift, which is
        ſtill extant, all his lands in the pariſh of <lb/>St. <hi rend="sc">Botolph</hi> without <hi
          rend="sc">Bishopsgate</hi>, being the ſpot now known by <lb/>the name of <hi rend="sc">Old
          Bethlem</hi>, to the foundation of a priory. The <lb/>prior, canons, brethren and ſiſters,
        for whoſe maintenance he pro- <lb/>vided, were diſtinguiſhed by a ſtar upon their mantles,
        and were eſ- <lb/>pecially directed to receive and entertain the <hi rend="sc">Bishop of St.
          Mary <lb/>of Bethlehem</hi>, and the canons, brothers, and meſſengers of that <lb/>their
        mother church, as often as they might come to England. Such <lb/>was the original deſign of
        this foundation, a deſign as far ſhort of <lb/>the uſes to which it has been ſince
        converted, as the contracted views <lb/>of monkiſh hoſpitality are exceeded by the more
        enlarged ſpirit of <lb/><hi rend="sc">protestant benevolence</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">We</hi> hear but little more of this houſe for the ſpace of two hun-
        <lb/>dred years. When the vaſt fabric of papal ſuperſtition in England <lb/>began to totter,
        and the votaries of <hi rend="sc">Rome</hi> were expelled from their <lb/>ancient
        retirements, it was ſeized by <hi rend="sc">Henry the eighth</hi>, who, in <lb/>the year
        1547, granted the hoſpital of Bethlem, with all it's revenues, <lb/>to the mayor,
        commonalty, and citizens of London, from which time <lb/>it became an <hi rend="sc">hospital
          for the cure of lunatics</hi>. </p>
      <pb n="3"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> is moſt probable that the city of London had felt great in-
        <lb/>convenience from the want of a proper receptacle for thoſe unhappy <lb/>objects, who
        were afflicted by the moſt deplorable malady incident <lb/>to the human frame. The retired
        ſituation of the hoſpital of Bethlem, <lb/>and it's contiguity to the city pointed it out as
        a fit place for the <lb/>deſired purpoſe. Accordingly, we find from authentic documents,
        <lb/>that, in the year 1523, Stephen Gennings, merchant-taylor, gave forty <lb/>pounds by
        will towards the purchaſe of this hoſpital, and, that the <lb/>mayor and commonalty had
        taken ſome ſteps to procure it, a very <lb/>ſhort time before they derived their right to it
        from royal munifi- <lb/>cence. What were the revenues which it then enjoyed does not now
        <lb/>appear: it is certain, they were inadequate to the neceſſities which <lb/>they were
        intended to remedy; for, five years after the royal grant <lb/>had paſſed, letters patent
        were iſſued to John Whitehead, proctor <lb/>to the hoſpital of Bethlem, to ſolicit donations
        within the counties of <lb/>Lincoln and Cambridge, the city of London, and the iſle of Ely. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> the infant ſtate of this charity, no other proviſion was made
        <lb/>for the unfortunate patient, beſides confinement and medical relief. <lb/>His friends,
        if they had ability, or the pariſh, of which the wretched <lb/>lunatic was an inhabitant,
        were obliged to contribute to his ſupport. <lb/>It remained for the judicious benevolence of
        ſucceeding times to <lb/>improve the good work, and to ſupply that comfortable ſubſiſtence,
        <lb/>and tender care, which, through the bleſſing of the divine providence, <lb/>have
        reſtored ſo many diſtracted objects to their families, and to ſociety. </p>
      <pb n="4"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">There</hi> is no account of donations received before the year 1632.
        <lb/>They were not, for ſome time, conſiderable, but the manifeſt utility of <lb/>the
        inſtitution, and perhaps the detriment which the public ſuffered, ſoon <lb/>induced them to
        attend to the ſecurity of thoſe members, who, <lb/>through the viſitation of God, were
        become dangerous to the commu- <lb/>nity. Accordingly, the growing charity was cheriſhed not
        only by ci- <lb/>tizens, upon whoſe notice it more immediately preſſed, but by others
        <lb/>who had judgment to ſelect proper objects of their attention, and <lb/>ability to
        aſſiſt them. And here the mind, which rejoices to indulge <lb/>the pleaſing ſenſations of
        benevolence, cannot but feel the warmeſt <lb/>glow, when it perceives how much the hoſpital
        of Bethlem has been <lb/>indebted to ſecret, unknown benefactors. Private charity may not
        <lb/>perhaps excite and animate others ſo much as public benefactions, <lb/>but it affords
        the ſtrongeſt recommendation of the inſtitution which it <lb/>favors. He who conceals his
        good deeds cannot poſſibly be influ- <lb/>enced by any other than the pureſt motives: it is
        the merits of <lb/>the objects only that he regards; theſe he weighs well before he
        <lb/>gives his alms, and he is ſeldom miſtaken in their application. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">About</hi> the year 1644, it was under conſideration to enlarge the
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">old hospital</hi>; but the ſituation was too cloſe and confined to
        <lb/>allow of its being rendered a commodious aſylum for the numerous <lb/>diſtracted
        perſons of both ſexes that claimed it's protection, and pro- <lb/>bably the dreadful
        commotions of that period checked the idea of <lb/>improvement. When peace and legal
        government were reſtored, and <lb/>England had reſt from the violence with which it had been
        con- <lb/>vulſed, the concerns of civil ſociety were again attended to, and it <lb/>became a
        matter of ſerious deliberation to build a <hi rend="sc">new hospital</hi>. <pb n="5"/>
        <lb/>In April 1675 this great work was begun. The lord-mayor, alder- <lb/>men, and
        common-council of the city of London, allotted to the <lb/>governors a large piece of ground
        near London-Wall, on the ſouth <lb/>ſide of the lower quarter of Moorfields, where the
        hoſpital of Bethlem <lb/>now ſtands. The expedition, with which this ſtately fabric was com-
        <lb/>pleted, challenges our admiration. For, from an inſcription over the <lb/>arch facing
        the entrance into the hoſpital, it appears that it was <lb/>finiſhed in July, in the
        following year. So active was the zeal that <lb/>quickened the growth of this noble
        ſtructure! The generoſity of the <lb/>contributors muſt have been equal to their attention,
        for the charge <lb/>of the building amounted to no leſs a ſum than £17,000. And <lb/>never,
        it may be truly aſſerted, were expence and trouble better be- <lb/>ſtowed: the hoſpital of
        Bethlem ſtands an illuſtrious monument of <lb/>Britiſh charity; and, whether we conſider the
        becoming magnifi- <lb/>cence of the building, the commodious arrangement of the interior
        <lb/>apartments, or the effectual relief which it reaches out to the poor <lb/>objects whom
        it ſhelters, we may ſafely pronounce, that it is not to <lb/>be parallelled in the whole
        world. <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* The deſign of the building was taken from the Chateau de Tuilleries, <unclear>in
              Verſailles</unclear>. Louis <lb/>XIV. it is ſaid, was ſo much offended that his palace
            ſhould be made a model for an hoſpital, <lb/>that, in revenge, he ordered a plan of St.
            James's to be taken for offices of a very inferior <lb/>nature. The figures of the two
            lunatics over the gates of the hoſpital, an engraving of which is pre- <lb/>fixed to
            this account, were the work of <hi rend="sc">Cibber</hi>, the father of the comedian. <q
              rend="diple quotes">My father <lb/>Caius Gabriel Cibber was a native of Holſtein, who
              came into England, ſome time before <lb/>the reſtoration of king Charles II. to follow
              his profeſſion, which was that of a ſtatuary. The <lb/>baſſo relievo on the pedeſtal
              of the great column in the city, and the two figures of the <lb/>lunatics, the Raving,
              and the Melancholy, over the gates of Bethlem hoſpital, are no ill <lb/>monuments of
              his fame as an artiſt. </q>
            <hi rend="italic">Cibber's Apology for his own Life</hi>. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>There is a tradition that the perſon repreſented by the figure of the melancholy
            lunatic, was <lb/>porter to Oliver Cromwell. </p>
        </note>
      </p>
      <pb n="6"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> the cloſe limits within which the old hoſpital was confined, it
        <lb/>was impracticable to reſerve room for thoſe forlorn beings, of whoſe <lb/>return to the
        comforts of a ſound mind there were no hopes. The <lb/>increaſing multitude of curable
        objects juſtly demanded admittance; <lb/>nor did it ſeem reaſonable that they ſhould be
        excluded from the <lb/>proſpect of enjoying a bleſſing which the former could not attain.
        <lb/>When the <hi rend="sc">new house</hi> was erected, it was hoped that ſome provi-
        <lb/>ſion might be made for ſuch as were deemed <hi rend="sc">incurable</hi>, and at the
        <lb/>ſame time dangerous to the public. But the great influx of inſane <lb/>perſons, from
        all parts of the kingdom, into the hoſpital, fruſtrated <lb/>theſe expectations, and gave
        reaſon to ſuppoſe, that few, if any, of <lb/>its numerous apartments, would, at any, time be
        vacant. It was <lb/>therefore found neceſſary to enlarge the building; a particular ſub-
        <lb/>ſcription was ſet on foot for the purpoſe, and, in the year 1734, two <lb/>wings were
        added to the hoſpital. This addition of room has enabled <lb/>the governors, in ſome degree,
        to anſwer the wiſhes of the public; <lb/>and there are now maintained <hi rend="sc">one
          hundred incurable patients</hi>, <lb/>fifty of each ſex, who enjoy every advantage which
        their deplora- <lb/>ble ſtate can admit. The number of patients in the houſe, who are
        <lb/>ſuppoſed capable of being relieved, commonly amounts to about <hi rend="sc">one
          <lb/>hundred and seventy</hi>, and of theſe, it has been found upon an <lb/>average, that
        nearly two out of three are reſtored to their underſtanding. <lb/>To ſuch a degree of
        perfection have the liberal benefactions of the well- <lb/>diſpoſed (for it is by
        benefactions that the deficient revenues of this <lb/>hoſpital have been, and muſt be
        ſupplied) advanced this noble inſti- <lb/>tution! And ſuch is the ſolid and ſubſtantial
        good, which it derives <lb/>to individuals and to the community! </p>
      <pb n="7"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">But</hi> while the benevolent heart feels a ſenſible joy in reflecting
        <lb/>upon the load of human wretchedneſs that is lightened by the ac- <lb/>commodations of
        this friendly manſion, it cannot but expreſs a wiſh, <lb/>that the benefits of the hoſpital
        might be rendered more extenſive. <lb/>It is an object much to be deſired, that the many
        diſtracted perſons, <lb/>whoſe diſorder no medicine can reach, might continue to find pro-
        <lb/>tection within theſe walls, and not be returned to their friends, a <lb/>burthen, very
        often too heavy for them to bear. The number of <lb/>incurables, which the hoſpital can at
        preſent contain, is ſmall, when <lb/>compared with thoſe who wait their turn of admiſſion.
        Perhaps it <lb/>would not be ſuppoſed that there are generally more than <hi rend="sc">two
          <lb/>hundred</hi> upon what is called the incurable liſt; <note place="bottom" n="*"
          rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* When a patient, after ſufficient trial, is judged incurable, he is diſmiſſed from
            the hoſ- <lb/>pital, and if he is pronounced dangerous either to himſelf or others, his
            name is entered into <lb/>a book, that he may be received in turn among the incurables
            maintained in the houſe, <lb/>whenever a vacancy ſhall happen. </p>
        </note> and, as inſtances <lb/>of longevity are frequent in inſane perſons, it commonly
        happens <lb/>that the expectants are obliged to wait ſix or ſeven years, after <lb/>their
        diſmiſſion from the hoſpital, before they can be again received. <lb/>During this long
        interval, they muſt be ſupported either by their <lb/>reſpective friends, or pariſhes. The
        expence of maintaining and pro- <lb/>perly ſecuring them far exceeds the allowance that is
        uſually made <lb/>for paupers; and in middling life, where the feelings of a worthy ſon
        <lb/>or huſband revolt at the idea of a near relation becoming an object <lb/>of parochial
        alms, the diſtreſs and difficulties of the lunatic's unhappy <lb/>friends muſt be greatly
        aggravated. Beſides, for want of due care <pb n="8"/>
        <lb/>and ſecurity, accidents, far too ſhocking to be related, have ſome- <lb/>times
        happened. <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* There are now in Bethlem hoſpital two patients who have committed deeds of the
            moſt <lb/>horrid kind. </p>
        </note>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">These</hi> manifeſt evils, that ariſe from the want of a proper pro-
        <lb/>viſion for ſo great a number of incurable patients, have induced many <lb/>benevolent
        perſons to wiſh, that, the hoſpital might be enlarged. <lb/>Indeed, many have appropriated
        their benefactions ſolely to the <lb/>incurables; and it is hoped that others will forward
        and complete <lb/>their good intentions. True policy muſt join with humanity in the
        <lb/>wiſh, that, this may not any longer be, what at preſent it is, almoſt <lb/>the only
        branch of charity in this great city that wants a ſufficient <lb/>eſtabliſhment. Beſides,
        there ſeems a peculiar degree of generoſity <lb/>in aſſiſting thoſe who muſt burthen, but
        can never benefit ſociety, <lb/>and who, ſo far from recompenſing, cannot even feel the
        leaſt gra- <lb/>titude to their benefactors. <note place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>† It may not be improper here to rectify a miſtaken notion that has gone forth into
            the <lb/>world. It has been preſumed by many, that the hoſpitals of <hi rend="sc"
              >Bethlem, and St. Luke</hi> are <lb/>connected: the latter, it has been thought, is
            appointed for the reception of incurables diſcharged <lb/>by the former; and ſo
            prevalent has been this opinion, that the ſteward of Bethlem hoſpital has <lb/>often
            received letters from perſons of education and credit, who were intereſted for patients
            <lb/>diſcharged incurable, deſiring to know, <hi rend="italic">when they would be ſent
              to St. Luke's</hi>. How ſuch an idea <lb/>could have obtained, except from the
            nearneſs of their ſituation to each other, it is not eaſy to <lb/>ſay; certain it is,
            that it has not the leaſt foundation in truth. Both hoſpitals are engaged in the
            <lb/>ſame good work, have the ſame object in view, the reſtoration of reaſon to the
            diſtracted; and <lb/>both admit a limited number of incurables; but the <hi rend="sc"
              >governors</hi>, <hi rend="sc">officers</hi>, and <hi rend="sc">funds</hi> of
            <lb/>each charity are totally <hi rend="sc">separate</hi> and <hi rend="sc"
              >distinct</hi>. </p>
        </note>
      </p>
      <pb n="9"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">The conduct and management</hi> of this hoſpital is more im-
        <lb/>mediately intruſted to a committee of forty-two governors, ſeven <lb/>of whom, together
        with the treaſurer, phyſician, and other officers, <lb/>attend every Saturday, in monthly
        rotation, for the admiſſion of pati- <lb/>ents, and for the regulation of ſuch other
        matters, as may concern <lb/>the eaſe, welfare, and convenience, of ſo large a family. And,
        as <lb/>the committee is open to every governor, it receives all the benefit <lb/>which it
        can derive from the prudence and information of perſons <lb/>of different habits of life,
        reſpectable citizens who are engaged in, <lb/>or have retired from buſineſs, gentlemen of
        the medical profeſſion, <lb/>and others of independent fortune, whoſe leiſure or benevolence
        may <lb/>lead them to attend. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">As</hi> ſoon as the lunatic is judged a fit object for this charity, he
        <lb/>is delivered to the ſteward, who, under the direction of the phyſician, <lb/>aſſigns
        him ſuch a degree of care and confinement as his caſe may <lb/>require. The wards are
        ſpacious and airy, <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* The length of each ward or gallery is 321 feet, the width 16 feet 2 inches, and
            the heigth <lb/>13 feet. There are 275 cells, each of which meaſures 12 feet 6 inches by
            8 feet. </p>
        </note> and the convenience of <lb/>the apartments allotted to each unhappy individual,
        together with the <lb/>order, decency, and cleanlineſs that are conſpicuous through the
        whole <lb/>houſe, cannot but ſtrike the curious and charitable viſitant: and, though
        <lb/>the various ſpectacles of wretchedneſs, which there preſent themſelves, <lb/>muſt
        agitate the mind that feels for the woes of humanity, the pain, <lb/>which they occaſion,
        will rarely fail of being mitigated by the view <lb/>of that relief which is adminiſtered to
        the wretched. </p>
      <pb n="10"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> is ſcarce neceſſary to aſſert, that the unhappy patients enjoy
        <lb/>the ableſt medical aſſiſtance adminiſtered with the greateſt humanity. <note
          place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* The phyſician to the hoſpital is Dr. <hi rend="sc">Monro</hi>, and the ſurgeon,
            Mr. <hi rend="sc">Richard Crowther</hi>. </p>
        </note>
        <lb/>The proviſions of the hoſpital, the vegetables, milk, beer, &amp;c. are all
        <lb/>excellent in their kind: <note place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>† The committee have lately allowed vegetables and a better ſort of ſmall beer.
            This libera- <lb/>lity has produced the moſt ſalutary effects upon the general health of
            the patients, as the medical <lb/>officers have obſerved, that the patients have not
            been ſince ſo much afflicted with ſcurvy, or <lb/>fluxes as formerly. </p>
        </note> they are carefully inſpected by the ſteward, <note place="bottom" n="‡"
          rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>‡ Mr. <hi rend="sc">Henry White</hi>. </p>
        </note>
        <lb/>who is reſident, and frequently viewed by gentlemen of the committee. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">But</hi> perhaps an explanation of the regular plan of diet, eſtabliſhed
        <lb/>in this numerous houſhold, may not prove unacceptable to thoſe who <lb/>deem no
        particulars trivial or unintereſting, that tend to alleviate human <lb/>diſtreſs. The
        conſtant breakfaſt allotted the patients throughout the <lb/>year, is water-gruel, with
        bread, butter and ſalt. They have meat <lb/>for dinner three days in a week. Beef is the
        Sunday's fare; mut- <lb/>ton is their Tueſday's dinner, and they have veal on Thurſdays,
        <lb/>but the laſt only from Lady-day to Michaelmas; during the win- <lb/>ter months, mutton
        or pork is ſubſtituted in it's place. They have <lb/>alſo a ſufficient quantity of broth;
        and that every indulgence, which <lb/>œconomy permits, may be given to the poor patients, on
        the meat <lb/>days one gallery <note place="bottom" n="§" rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>§ The houſe is divided into five. </p>
        </note> is always gratified with roaſt meat. The quan- <lb/>tity of ſolid meat, beſides
        vegetables and a pint of ſmall beer, <lb/>allowed each individual, is eight ounces. On the
        days in which they <lb/>have no meat, and which are called banyan days, they have milk- <pb
          n="11"/>
        <lb/>pottage, or rice-milk, with bread and cheeſe. Their conſtant ſup- <lb/>per is bread and
        cheeſe, with a pint of ſmall beer; and twelve out <lb/>of each gallery, in their turn, have
        butter if they prefer it. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> cells are viſited early every morning by the ſervants of the
        <lb/>houſe: theſe make their report to the apothecary, <note place="bottom" n="*"
          rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Mr. <hi rend="sc">John Gozna</hi>: he has apartments in the hoſpital, and is
            conſtantly reſident. </p>
        </note> who goes round <lb/>about eight o'clock to inſpect them himſelf, and to give ſuch
        orders <lb/>and directions as may be neceſſary. The phyſician viſits the hoſpi- <lb/>tal
        three days in a week. There are certain days fixed for the proper <lb/>medical operations;
        and the cold, or hot bath is uſed in thoſe caſes <lb/>where it is judged to be ſalutary.
        Every patient is indulged with <lb/>that degree of liberty which is found conſiſtent with
        his own, and <lb/>the general ſafety. In the winter there are certain rooms with com-
        <lb/>fortable fires, <note place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>† Theſe to prevent miſchief, are defended by large guard-irons. </p>
        </note> where thoſe, who are in a convaleſcent ſtate, meet <lb/>and aſſociate; and in the
        ſummer, they walk in the large adjoining <lb/>court-yards, and ſometimes amuſe themſelves
        with ſuch diverſions as <lb/>are deemed not improper to quiet their ſpirits, and compoſe the
        agi- <lb/>tation of their minds. The hoſpital uſed formerly to derive a revenue, <lb/>of at
        leaſt £400 a year, from the indiſcriminate admiſſion of viſitants, <lb/>whom, very often, an
        idle and wanton curioſity drew to theſe regi- <lb/>ons of diſtreſs. But this liberty, though
        beneficial to the funds of the <lb/>charity, was thought to counteract it's grand deſign, as
        it tended to <lb/>diſturb the tranquillity of the patients. It was therefore judged pro-
        <lb/>per, in the year 1770, no longer to expoſe the houſe to public view; <lb/>and now, it
        is ſcarce ever open to ſtrangers, unleſs they are intro- <pb n="12"/>
        <lb/>duced by a particular order. The friends of the poor objects have <lb/>a limited acceſs
        to them. At the admiſſion of a patient, a ticket is <lb/>delivered, which authorizes the
        bearer of it to come to the hoſpital, <lb/>on Mondays and Wedneſdays, between the hours of
        ten and twelve. <lb/>And here, it may not be amiſs to contradict a moſt injurious notion,
        <lb/>that has been adopted, chiefly indeed by that claſs of people, who <lb/>are moſt prone
        to form prejudices againſt eleemoſynary inſtitutions, <lb/>which is, that the patients in
        Bethlem hoſpital are beaten, and in other re- <lb/>ſpects ill treated, in order to compel
        them to ſubmit to the neceſſary ope- <lb/>rations. This idea is abſolutely erroneous. No
        ſervant is allowed ſo <lb/>wanton an abuſe of the authority that is given him; and it is
        ſtrictly en- <lb/>joined, that, a patient ſhall never be ſtruck, except in caſes of ſelf-de-
        <lb/>fence. Indeed it is notorious, that, the members of this family are ma- <lb/>naged with
        that lenity which their ſituation claims. If the known hu- <lb/>manity and attention of the
        officers of the houſe were not itſelf a ſuffici- <lb/>ent ſecurity for their being well
        treated, the frequent inſpection which <lb/>the hoſpital undergoes from a large proportion
        of the governors, who, <lb/>at different times, ſerve upon the Bethlem committee, would at
        once <lb/>invalidate the ſuſpicion that has been mentioned. In ſhort, ſuch is the
        <lb/>comfortable ſubſiſtence, kind treatment, and able medical aid, which <lb/>the patients
        here meet with, that many, who are intimately acquainted <lb/>with the conduct of the houſe,
        have declared, that if ever God ſhould <lb/>be pleaſed to viſit them with inſanity, <hi
          rend="sc">Bethlem hospital</hi> is the place, <lb/>into which they would wiſh to be
        admitted. <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* It is worthy of remark, that the patients themſelves are often known to prefer
            Bethlem to <lb/>private mad-houſes. </p>
        </note>
      </p>
      <pb n="13"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">The admission of patients</hi> into Bethlem hoſpital is attend- <lb/>ed
        with very little difficulty. It is firſt neceſſary to conſider, whether <lb/>the caſe of the
        ſuppoſed lunatic includes any of thoſe circumſtances <lb/>which the prudence of the hoſpital
        regards as objections to admiſſi- <lb/>on. Theſe are few in number; and the wiſdom and
        propriety of <lb/>them will be eaſily allowed. Mopes, perſons afflicted with the palſy,
        <lb/>or ſubject to convulſive or epileptic fits, and ſuch as are become <lb/>weak through
        age, or long illneſs, are excluded. Objects of this deſcrip- <lb/>tion, it is preſumed, may
        be ſufficiently protected and ſecured by their <lb/>friends, or in a pariſh workhouſe. It is
        peculiarly deſerving notice <lb/>that no perſon is conſidered as diſqualified for admiſſion
        here, who <lb/>may have been diſcharged uncured from any other lunatic hoſpital. <lb/>When
        the friends of a lunatic are ſatisfied that he is a proper object <lb/>of the charity, and
        the petition and certificates of the patient's legal <lb/>pariſh ſettlement are prepared,
          <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* The forms of theſe are readily obtained by an application at Bethlem, or at the
            clerk's <lb/>office in Bridewell hoſpital; and a governor's recommendation is <hi
              rend="italic">never refuſed</hi> to the friends of <lb/>any proper object. </p>
        </note> it then becomes neceſſary to procure <lb/>a governor's recommendation. The hoſpital
        alſo requires, that, upon <lb/>admiſſion, two houſe-keepers reſiding in or near London,
        ſhall enter <lb/>into a bond to take the patient away when diſcharged by the com-
        <lb/>mittee, and pay the expence of clothes, and of burial in caſe of <lb/>death. If the
        lunatic is ſent by a pariſh, or any other public body, <lb/>the ſum of three pounds four
        ſhillings is paid for bedding, but if he <lb/>is placed there by friends, the hoſpital,
        anxious to lighten their <lb/>burthen, reduces the ſum to two pounds five ſhillings and ſix-
          <pb n="14"/>
        <lb/>pence. <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* When an incurable patient is finally ſettled in the houſe, the ſum of half a
            crown per week <lb/>is paid to the hoſpital by his friends, or the pariſh to which he
            belongs. </p>
        </note> It is expected that the patient ſhould be ſupplied with <lb/>clothing; in failure of
        ſuch ſupply, the hoſpital provides proper gar- <lb/>ments at the loweſt rate, and the
        bondſmen repay the expence. <note place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>† BETHLEM HOSPITAL. Ordered, That the apparel wanting for the patients, may be pro-
            <lb/>vided by their friends; but, if not done, the ſteward ſhall furniſh what the weekly
            committee <lb/>ſhall order, at the following prices: </p>
          <cb type="footnote" n="1"/>
          <table rows="10" cols="2">
            <head rend="sc align-center">
              <lb/>For Men. </head>
            <row>
              <cell>A coat </cell>
              <cell rend="align-right">£0 16 6 </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>A waiſtcoat </cell>
              <cell rend="align-right">0 6 4 </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>A pair of breeches </cell>
              <cell rend="align-right">0 9 4 </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>A ſhirt </cell>
              <cell rend="align-right">0 3 11 </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>A pair of ſhoes </cell>
              <cell rend="align-right">0 4 6 </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>A pair of ſtockings </cell>
              <cell rend="align-right">0 2 3 </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>A cap </cell>
              <cell rend="align-right">0 1 0 </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>A blanket gown </cell>
              <cell rend="align-right">0 10 6 </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>A ſtrait waiſtcoat </cell>
              <cell rend="align-right">0 13 6 </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Buckles</cell>
              <cell rend="align-right">0 0 8 </cell>
            </row>
          </table>
          <cb type="footnote" n="2"/>
          <table rows="10" cols="2">
            <head rend="sc align-center">
              <lb/>For Women. </head>
            <row>
              <cell>A blanket gown </cell>
              <cell rend="align-right">£0 10 6 </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>A gown and petticoat </cell>
              <cell rend="align-right">0 19 0 </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>An under petticoat </cell>
              <cell rend="align-right">0 3 3 </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>A ſhift </cell>
              <cell rend="align-right">0 3 4 </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>A pair of ſhoes </cell>
              <cell rend="align-right">0 3 1 </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>A pair of ſtockings </cell>
              <cell rend="align-right">0 1 10 </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>A cap </cell>
              <cell rend="align-right">0 1 0 </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>A handkerchief </cell>
              <cell rend="align-right">0 1 3 </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>An apron </cell>
              <cell rend="align-right">0 2 2 </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Buckles </cell>
              <cell rend="align-right">0 0 8 </cell>
            </row>
          </table>
          <cb type="footnote" n="1 2"/>
        </note>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">There</hi> is no particular time limited for the continuance of a pa-
        <lb/>tient in the hoſpital, who is under cure. It is generally ſeen in a <lb/>twelvemonth,
        whether the caſe will admit relief; and ſometimes in <lb/>a few months health and reaſon are
        reſtored. Nor does the care of <lb/>the governors ceaſe when the recovered lunatic is
        diſmiſſed from the <lb/>hoſpital. At the time of diſcharge, he is interrogated as to the
        treat- <lb/>ment which he has received, and, if he has had cauſe of complaint, <lb/>required
        to declare it. He is encouraged to apply occaſionally to the <lb/>medical officer, who gives
        him ſuch advice and medicines as are <lb/>proper to prevent a relapſe, and, if it ſhould
        appear that his circum- <lb/>ſtances are particularly diſtreſſing, the treaſurer and
        phyſician poſſeſs <lb/>a diſcretionary power to relieve him with a ſmall ſum of money at
        <lb/>his departure. </p>
      <pb n="15"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Happy</hi> is it for the individual, for his friends, and for ſociety,
        <lb/>when thus the divine bleſſing gives efficacy to the means uſed for <lb/>his
        reſtoration! The wiſhes of the benevolent are gratified, and the <lb/>ſucceſs of the
        inſtitution is ſo far complete! How then muſt we la- <lb/>ment the caſe of the incurable
        lunatic, diſmiſſed from the protection <lb/>to which he had been accuſtomed, and thrown upon
        his diſtreſſed un- <lb/>fortunate friends! <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* The caſe is particularly hard when the patient, as it often happens, is ſent to
            London from <lb/>a remote county. </p>
        </note> The hopes indeed of his return to his aſylum are <lb/>not entirely cut off, but the
        proſpect of it is too remote to alleviate, <lb/>in any degree, preſent ſuffering. A long
        period muſt elapſe be- <lb/>fore he can be re-admitted. In the mean time the frantic maniac,
        and <lb/>the deſponding lunatic muſt be ſecured from doing violence to them- <lb/>ſelves,
        and others. The loweſt annual expence, in thoſe houſes where <lb/>pariſh objects are
        maintained, exceeds twenty pounds: where the for- <lb/>lorn being is ſupported by his
        friends, the expenditure ſcarce ever <lb/>falls ſhort of thirty. The feeling and conſiderate
        mind, that can judge <lb/>of the œconomy which is requiſite in humble life, and knows how to
        <lb/>eſtimate its wants and neceſſities, will eaſily calculate the weight and <lb/>effect of
        ſo heavy an expence;—will imagine how ſevere a ſtruggle <lb/>it muſt often occaſion between
        neceſſity and pity, between natural <lb/>affection and the pride of honeſt induſtry, which
        is ſometimes reduced, <lb/>by exertions too great for its ability, to accept itſelf that
        relief, which <lb/>it had bluſhed to aſk for the deareſt relatives. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">How</hi> glorious then would be the work! how comprehenſive the
        <lb/>charity, that ſhould contribute to increaſe the eſtabliſhment for incu- <pb n="16"/>
        <lb/>rable lunatics! The good, that would ariſe from the improvement of <lb/>ſo excellent an
        inſtitution, is certain and undoubted, and from that <lb/>active ſpirit of humanity, and
        rational benevolence which peculiarly <lb/>adorns the Britiſh name, we may hope, that, this
        great work will not <lb/>be left defective and incomplete. The government of the royal hoſ-
        <lb/>pitals, as lately eſtabliſhed by parliament, affords ample ſecurity to the
        <lb/>charitable benefactor, that his good intentions will receive their accom-
        <lb/>pliſhment. <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* A conteſt had long ſubſiſted between the common-council of the city of London and
            the <lb/>acting governors of all the royal hoſpitals; the former claiming a right to be
            admitted govern- <lb/>ors in virtue of the ſeveral royal charters. This diſpute has been
            happily ſettled by a compro- <lb/>miſe which allows the admiſſion of twelve of the
            common-council to each hoſpital. Application <lb/>was made to parliament in 1782, and a
            bill paſſed, which fully eſtabliſhes this agreement, and <lb/>the friends of theſe noble
            charities have now the ſatisfaction to be aſſured that the government of <lb/>them is
            ſettled in a mode beſt calculated to promote their proſperity. </p>
        </note> The wealthy and munificent <hi rend="sc">city of London</hi>, aſſoci- <lb/>ated with
        the guardians of each charity, cheriſhes in her boſom, and <lb/>foſters with her care thoſe
        endowments, which the liberality of <hi rend="sc">Henry</hi>, <lb/>and the piety of <hi
          rend="sc">Edward</hi> committed to her adminiſtration.— <lb/>That this <hi rend="sc">happy
          union</hi> will operate to the relief of the diſtreſſed <lb/>poor, there can be little
        doubt. The friends of the hoſpital of Beth- <lb/>lem form the moſt ſanguine expectations,
        that their ability to alleviate <lb/>the greateſt of all human calamities will be enlarged
        and extended; <lb/>they hope to effect the purpoſes they have in view, and entertain full
        <lb/>confidence, that, the generous aſſiſtance of the opulent and the good, <lb/>will enable
        them, in an eminent degree, to <hi rend="sc">lessen the evils of <lb/>humanity</hi>. </p>
      <trailer rend="align-center">
        <lb/>FINIS. </trailer>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
