<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Black: An Arithmetical and Medical Analysis of the Diseases and
          Mortality of the Human Species </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>William Black</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">An arithmetical and medical analysis of the diseases and mortality of
              the human species.</title>
            <edition n="2"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">N5674</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/N5674"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for the author by John Crowder: and sold by C. Dilly, in
                  the Poultry, M.DCC.LXXXIX.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1789</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="17"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="265"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">John Rylands University Library of Manchester</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110786508</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Public welfare and institutional"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="17"/>
    <body>
      <pb n=""/>
      <figure>
        <figDesc>A horizontal double-line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <head rend="sc align-center space">
        <lb/>an <lb/><hi rend="size(1.25)">ANALYSIS </hi>
        <lb/>of <lb/>DISEASES and MORTALITY. </head>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>A long horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
      <div type="chapter">
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>CHAP. I. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">F</hi>ROM the compound motions of the earth, <lb/>and of the moon;
          from the external ele- <lb/>ments with which the earth and the hu- <lb/>man ſpecies are
          inveſted; from their different <lb/>habitations on the earth; from their different
          <lb/>ages; from their different original tempera- <lb/>ments, claſs, or genus; from their
          different <lb/>ranks and habits of life; from their habitations <lb/>in city or in
          country; from the difference of <lb/>the ſexes, and their ſeparation or intercourſe, <pb
            n="2"/>
          <lb/>myriads of diſeaſes and deaths enſue, and are <lb/>peculiarly attached to theſe
          various modifica- <lb/>tions of mankind. Of each of theſe we are to <lb/>take a tranſient
          glance in the preſent chapter, as <lb/>alſo of the aggregate number of the human
          <lb/>ſpecies. They are bungling empiricks or auda- <lb/>cious proſtitutes in medical
          criticiſm, who miſ- <lb/>repreſent the above as ſpeculative and uſeleſs <lb/>propoſitions
          in medicine, and who cannot diſcern <lb/>the practical tendency of this Introductory Ana-
          <lb/>lyſis of the Human Species. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A morbid hiſtory of the inhabitants of the <lb/>earth is interwoven with the
          rudiments of aſtro- <lb/>nomy, geography, and natural philoſophy. Our <lb/>planet is a
          ſmall link, member, or key of one <lb/>univerſal and harmonious ſyſtem. The vault of
          <lb/>Heaven is ſtudded with a profuſion of thoſe bril- <lb/>liant orbs; of the ſun, and
          its ſeven planets, <lb/>with ten or more of the latter's ſubordinate <lb/>ſatellites, or
          moons; and of 21 comets. Our <lb/>ultimate views are loſt in the remote and bound-
          <lb/>leſs diſtances of the fixed ſtars, amounting to <lb/>ſome thouſands, or perhaps, with
          their revolv- <lb/>ing planets, to ſome millions. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>One of the ſeven planets in our ſolar ſyſtem, <lb/>the earth, this ſmall domain of
          reſtleſs mortals, is <lb/>diſtant from the ſun 95,000,000 miles. It has ſeveral
          <lb/>inceſſant and compound motions. In the ſpace <lb/>of 365<formula notation="fraction"
            >1/4</formula> days it completes its annual circle round <lb/>the ſun, which is the
          length of our year; and <lb/>throughout that orbit is whirled with the amaz- <lb/>ing
          rapidity of 68,000 miles hourly; whereas the <lb/>ſwiftneſs of a cannon ball, in the ſame
          interval, <lb/>is only 480 miles. Its diurnal rotation every <lb/>24 hours, like a
          ſuſpended wheel upon its axis, <pb n="3"/>
          <lb/>is, at the equator, at the rate of 1035 miles <lb/>hourly. Its two remaining motions
          are the al- <lb/>ternate ſpiral inclination and declination of its <lb/>north and ſouth
          poles, to and from the ſun at <lb/>different periods of the year; and the ſmall
          <lb/>monthly circle round the common centre of <lb/>gravity with the moon. From theſe
          combined <lb/>terreſtrial motions enſue day and night, ſum- <lb/>mer and winter, the
          equinoxes and ſolſtices. <lb/>The earth is attended by an inferior, and not <lb/>very
          diſtant ſatellite, the moon, its reflecting <lb/>lamp of night, whoſe influence on the
          ocean <lb/>and tides, and in ſome diſeaſes, are univerſally <lb/>conſpicuous. The ancient
          aſtrological ſyſtems <lb/>ſeem to be derived from influences too remote <lb/>and faint. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Our planet and its inhabitants are inveſted <lb/>with a few elements, the great and
          very uni- <lb/>verſal agents both of natural good and evil. <lb/>Heat and light are
          derived from one common <lb/>parent, the ſun: their negative qualities, dimi- <lb/>nution
          or privation are cold and darkneſs. From <lb/>the equator to the poles are all the
          gradations <lb/>of heat and cold, the extremes of which are <lb/>ſometimes conſiderably
          above the human tem- <lb/>perature, or 97 of Fahrenheit's thermometer, <lb/>and ſometimes
          ſunk conſiderably below 1 or 0 <lb/>of the ſame ſcale. In both theſe inſtances, as
          <lb/>alſo in duration, recurrence and changes, and <lb/>independent of latitudes,
          prodigious variations <lb/>will reſult from the perpendicular or the oblique
          <lb/>direction of the ſolar rays, their duration, ab- <lb/>ſorption, or retention, from
          elevations, ſoils, <lb/>ſituations, ſeaſons, days, and nights. But with- <lb/>in the
          equatorial limits the variations in the <pb n="4"/>
          <lb/>thermometer and ſeaſons are much leſs conſiden- <lb/>able than without the tropicks. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The earth floats in a ſubtile, elaſtick, and ſo- <lb/>norous fluid, the atmoſphere,
          or air, with which <lb/>it is circumfuſed on all ſides to the diſtance of <lb/>more than
          45 miles; from whoſe agitations and <lb/>currents enſue all the diverſity of winds; and
          <lb/>whoſe gravity upon the human body, except <lb/>in elevated ſituations, and in certain
          changes of <lb/>weather, amounts to thirty-two thouſand pounds, <lb/>as is proved by the
          air-pump and barometer. <lb/>Its noxious effects may be traced to many <lb/>ſources, to
          pollution, ſtagnation, unelaſticity, <lb/>levity, nocturnal chill; the points from whence
          <lb/>winds blow, their conſtancy, irregularity, re- <lb/>currence, velocity. — Another
          ſubtile, and active <lb/>agent in the machinery of nature is the electri- <lb/>cal
          emanation; the fabulous artillery and thun- <lb/>der-bolts of Omnipotence. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>From the ſun's heat, and the ſucceſſive <lb/>ſtreams of air and winds, a prodigious
          evapora- <lb/>tion is carried on from the ſurface of the earth, <lb/>the ocean, and
          vegetables. This accumulated <lb/>vapour, to which, according to ſome, the air <lb/>alſo
          contributes, is collected into miſts and <lb/>clouds, and ſuſpended in the atmoſphere, at
          no <lb/>great diſtance from the earth, is again diſ- <lb/>charged into the terreſtrial
          ciſtern in moiſture, <lb/>fluid or condenſed, as rain, ſnow, hail, but in <lb/>quantity,
          duration, recurrence, extent, and con- <lb/>tamination, diverſified by a number of
          collateral <lb/>cauſes. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Without the concurrent ſupport of theſe dif- <lb/>ferent elements, animal and
          vegetable life would <lb/>ſoon be annihilated. From each of their ſimple <pb n="5"/>
          <lb/>depravities, morbid modifications, defect, or <lb/>exceſs, but infinitely more from
          their complex <lb/>combinations, intermixtures, and undue aſſimi- <lb/>lations are
          engendered, and inflict a multitude <lb/>of human diſeaſes. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In ſhape the earth has more reſemblance to a <lb/>turnip than to a globe. Its
          circumference is <lb/>24,840 Engliſh miles. Its ſurface is compoſed <lb/>of dry land and
          of water, of which the ocean, <lb/>without including lakes and rivers, occupies <lb/>more
          than double the extent of the land. The <lb/>dry land is diverſified by plains and
          elevations, <lb/>none of which aſcend to five perpendicular miles. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Creator has bountifully ſtored the earth <lb/>and the ocean with animals and
          vegetables. <lb/>Our attention is here circumſcribed to the moſt <lb/>exalted claſs, the
          Human Species; leaving to <lb/>the naturaliſt a deſcription of quadrupeds, birds,
          <lb/>fiſhes, inſects, and vegetables. By far the <lb/>largeſt proportion of the human
          ſpecies are ſta- <lb/>tioned to the north ſide of the equator, and <lb/>even to the north
          of the tropick of cancer. <lb/>The populous continents, or rather the one vaſt <lb/>united
          continent, of Europe and Aſia, and the <lb/>adjacent iſlands, comprehending moſt of the
          <lb/>powerful kingdoms in our planet, are in the <lb/>northern hemiſphere. Within the
          tropical cir- <lb/>cles and furnace of the earth, are ſtationed the <lb/>next conſiderable
          hive of mankind. To the <lb/>ſouth of Capricorn there are few inhabitants. <lb/>An immenſe
          orbicular ſegment of this hemi- <lb/>ſphere furniſhes habitation for fiſhes only. But,
          <lb/>in the oppoſite hemiſphere, ſome wretched hu- <lb/>man beings are ſcattered through
          dreary waftes <pb n="6"/>
          <lb/>of ice and ſnow within the northern polar <lb/>circles. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Calculators differ enormouſly reſpecting the <lb/><hi rend="italic">number of the
            Human Species</hi>. Some ſink the <lb/>collected herd ſo low as three hundred million,
          <lb/>whilſt others exaggerate them to treble and <lb/>quadruple that amount. It forms no
          part of <lb/>my ſcheme to inveſtigate the comparative po- <lb/>pulation of the earth, one,
          two, and three thou- <lb/>ſand years ago. Europe, in all probability, <lb/>ſince the era
          of Roman grandeur, has, toge- <lb/>ther with advancement in civilization, likewiſe
          <lb/>added to the number of its inhabitants. <lb/>Thoſe parental nurſeries of the arts and
          ſciences <lb/>in Aſia and Africa, have no doubt undergone <lb/>various revolutions in
          population. If we were <lb/>to draw any inferences from the numerous <lb/>Aſiatic armies,
          during the ſucceſſive deſpotiſm <lb/>of Aſſyrian, Babylonian, Medean, and Perſian
          <lb/>monarchies, we ſhould conclude that, in remote <lb/>ages, the ſouth of Aſia abounded
          in men. The <lb/>extenſive empire of China, at this day, reſem- <lb/>bles an induſtrious
          bee-hive, and is gorged with <lb/>mankind. We have ſtill more averſion to <lb/>plunge into
          the myſterious archives of Africa, <lb/>and with critical affectation to pronounce upon
          <lb/>the population of that quarter before the decay <lb/>of its political, commercial,
          and literary fame <lb/>with Thebes, Carthage, and Alexandria. That <lb/>modern-diſcovered
          tranſatlantic continent, from <lb/>the cruelties and deſolation of its firſt conquer-
          <lb/>ors, and of a loathſome, infectious diſeaſe <lb/>exchanged for another, has probably
          ſuffered <lb/>conſiderable diminution of its original feeble <lb/>hive, notwithſtanding
          the recruit from Europe; <pb n="7"/>
          <lb/>and in the ſcale of population America as yet <lb/>aſcends to a very ſubordinate rank
          amongſt the <lb/>other continents. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The moſt probable calculations eſtimate the <lb/>whole human race at eight hundred
          million; of <lb/>which number Europe, the moſt diminutive in <lb/>ſize, can boaſt of a
          hundred and thirty mil- <lb/>lion. The great ſwarm is in Aſia, amounting <lb/>to between
          four and five hundred million. Africa <lb/>is ſuppoſed to contain one third or fourth of
          <lb/>the latter number. Over the fertile wilderneſs <lb/>of America, which ſtands
          dignified in ſuperior <lb/>magnitude, are ſcattered not altogether twenty <lb/>million. On
          the other hand, in vegetable pro- <lb/>duction Europe is the leaſt prolifick. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But if in London alone, where regiſters of <lb/>various kinds may be conſulted,
          calculators are, <lb/>notwithſtanding, at variance reſpecting its po- <lb/>pulation
          upwards of one hundred thouſand, and <lb/>in the whole iſland more than a million; it may
          <lb/>be reaſonably ſuſpected, that in forming a groſs <lb/>eſtimate of the aggregate
          terreſtrial inhabitants, <lb/>we may err perhaps one, two, or even three <lb/>hundred
          million. As well might we expect a <lb/>correct liſt of the lions, crocodiles, and mon-
          <lb/>kies of Africa, as of the outcaſt human race in <lb/>thoſe burning and illiterate
          regions. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>To determine the amount of inhabitants in <lb/>any city, town, or kingdom,
          calculators from <lb/>choice, and oftener from neceſſity, have adopted <lb/>ſeveral
          methods. The firſt, and moſt uner- <lb/>ring, by a numerical ſurvey through every
          <lb/>houſe. The ſecond, by the number of houſes, <lb/>and by allotting 5 or 4<formula
            notation="fraction">1/2</formula> inhabitants to each <lb/>houſe, which, at a general
          average, including <pb n="8"/>
          <lb/>town and country, was found to be the ſtandard <lb/>in many parts of Europe. But
          unfortunately <lb/>in ours, and in many other national regiſters of <lb/>houſes and
          ſeparate dwellings, there is great in- <lb/>accuracy; and in ſome European cities the in-
          <lb/>habitants are double and treble beyond this pro- <lb/>portion: The third and far the
          moſt fallacious <lb/>method, both on account of the neceſſary data, <lb/>and proceſs, is
          by multiplying the uſual decre- <lb/>ment of life, or expectation of an infant at
          <lb/>birth in that city or country, whoſe population <lb/>we wiſh to aſcertain, by the
          general medium of <lb/>chriſtenings. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The aſſemblages of the human race are <lb/>greatly diverſified by their ages. Dr.
          Price <lb/>ſuppoſes nearly an equal proportion are living <lb/>under 16, and above that
          age; but however, <lb/>that the latter are moſt numerous. Davenant <lb/>ſtates 20 as the
          partianal number. Dr. Halley <lb/>ſuppoſed the number living under 16 to com- <lb/>priſe
          about one third; and thoſe between 20 and <lb/>42 another third of the community. The fol-
          <lb/>lowing table is founded upon a numerical ana- <lb/>lyſis of the inhabitants merely of
          England, by <lb/>Davenant. Our table embraces the whole in- <lb/>habitants of Europe,
          ſtating them here at <lb/>132,000,000. Each diviſion or group is in the <lb/>proportion of
          13 to 1 more than the inhabitants <lb/>of the ſame age in Britain and Ireland; and
          <lb/>about 1 to 6 fewer than the whole inhabitants <lb/>of the earth of a ſimilar
          deſcription. It is eaſy <lb/>to adapt them, <q rend="quotes">ad libitum,</q> to any
          numerical <lb/>extent. We ſhall hereaſter ſee that the females <lb/>are conſiderably more
          numerous than the males; <lb/>and that majority is much more conſpicuous in <pb n="9"/>
          <lb/>the laſt great diviſion of life, that is, after 20 <lb/>years of age. In this adult
          and aged diviſion <lb/>of life, the predominance both of males and <lb/>females, as
          contraſted with thoſe under 20, is alſo <lb/>more conſpicuous in cities than in the
          country. <lb/>It is hereaſter obſerved, that between one third <lb/>and fourth of the
          whole population of Europe <lb/>are inhabitants of cities and towns. </p>
        <table>
          <head rend="space align-center">
            <lb/><hi rend="sc">A Table</hi> of the <hi rend="sc">Inhabitants</hi> of <hi rend="sc"
              >Europe</hi>, <lb/>claſſed according to their Ages. </head>
          <row>
            <cell><hi rend="italic">Ages. </hi></cell>
            <cell><hi rend="italic">Numbers. </hi></cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Under 1 year — </cell>
            <cell>4,080,000 </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>5 years — </cell>
            <cell>19,680,000 </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>10 years — </cell>
            <cell>36,000,000 </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Total under 16 years — </cell>
            <cell>53,760,000 </cell>
            <cell><hi rend="dc(3)">}</hi> 132,000,000 </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Total from 16 years to the <lb/>extreme of exiſtence</cell>
            <cell><hi rend="dc(2)">}</hi> 78,240,000 </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>The proportion beyond 60 years </cell>
            <cell>14,200,000 </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Of theſe last the males </cell>
            <cell>6,280,000 </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>The females </cell>
            <cell>7,920,000 </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
        </table>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>It appears from this Table, that the living <lb/>under 1 year, are four million;
          between 1 and <lb/>5 years, 15 million; between 5 and 10 years, <lb/>17 million; between
          10 and 20 years, 29 mil- <lb/>lion. That is in all, under 20 years 66 million, <lb/>or
          about one half of the inhabitants. Between <lb/>20 and 60 years, there are 50 million;
          from 60 <lb/>to 100 years and upwards, 14 million. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Extending our views over the ſurface of the <lb/>globe, we perceive ſtriking
          diſtinctions between <lb/>the human ſpecies; not only in the four great <lb/>Continents,
          but alſo in different parts of the <lb/>ſame continent. Theſe differences are princi- <pb
            n="10"/>
          <lb/>pally manifeſt in the colour of the ſkin; in the <lb/>complexion, countenance,
          phyſiognomy, hair, <lb/>form and ſtature. We attend here merely to <lb/>corporeal
          diſtinction, without including the in- <lb/>tellectual. Theſe great claſſes of mankind may
          <lb/>be divided into the European, the Laplander, <lb/>the Tartar, the Chineſe, the
          African-negro, and <lb/>the native American. The modern-diſcovered <lb/>inhabitants in the
          iſlands of the Pacific ocean, <lb/>ſeem to have no remarkable caſt of countenance <lb/>or
          figure to ſever them into a ſeparate claſs. <lb/>Mankind, excluſive of their original
          mould, as <lb/>iſſued from the mint of the Creator, are after- <lb/>wards not only
          diverſified by climate, ſoil, diet, <lb/>government, religion, aſſociation, occupation,
          <lb/>habit; but throughout a conſiderable extent of <lb/>the globe, from conqueſt,
          emigration, coloni- <lb/>zation, and commercial intercourſe, many na- <lb/>tions are now
          blended and aſſimilated into one; <lb/>and the elementary characteriſtic features of the
          <lb/>aborigines, whether corporeal or mental, more <lb/>faintly imprinted. Beſides, every
          one's expe- <lb/>rience and obſervation will inſtruct him, that in <lb/>populous kingdoms
          theſe claſſes branch out into <lb/>innumerable intermixtures, orders, and genera; <lb/>and
          that the ſpecies and varieties are as nume- <lb/>rous as the individuals of the human
          race. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It is of eſſiential importance, not only in an <lb/>enlarged political, but alſo in a
          medicinal light, <lb/>to contemplate the various conſtituent portions <lb/>of human
          communities; to analyſe the different <lb/>members and pieces of theſe animated political
          <lb/>ſtructures. In a ſtate of nature there are few <lb/>gradations in ſociety; few
          profeſſions, or me- <lb/>chanical arts. But by civilization, mankind are <pb n="11"/>
          <lb/>arranged and connected into an infinite ſeries <lb/>of deſcending and dependent
          links. Mr. Vol- <lb/>taire makes only two great diviſions of civilized <lb/>mankind; the
          oppreſſors, and the oppreſſed. <lb/>Deſcending the mole-hill and ladder from the
          <lb/>throne to the cottage, we may trace a multitude <lb/>of gradations in the ſcale of
          poliſhed communi- <lb/>ties. We deſcend through nobility and gentry <lb/>of independent
          fortunes, in lands or money; <lb/>through literary profeſſions, including divinity,
          <lb/>medicine, law, and various other branches of <lb/>practical or ſpeculative ſcience;
          all of which <lb/>united conſtitute, even in the moſt opulent na- <lb/>tions, but a ſmall
          portion of the community. <lb/>We next deſcend to a fertile hive of huſband- <lb/>men and
          artizans, laborious drudges in mecha- <lb/>nical trades, arts, manufactories, and com-
          <lb/>merce: to a numerous claſs of retailers or ven- <lb/>ders of merchandize, and of the
          neceſſaries of <lb/>life: to apprentices and clerks throughout the <lb/>various arts and
          profeſſions: to ſoldiers, ſailors, <lb/>dlomeſtick ſervants: to no inconſiderable mul-
          <lb/>titude buried under ground, and occupied in <lb/>digging metals and fuel from the
          bowels of the <lb/>earth: to infirm, cripples, diſeaſed, puerperal, <lb/>aged; and to many
          other links and gradations, <lb/>which muſt be prodigiouſly diverſified by the
          <lb/>variety in governments, religion, climate, na- <lb/>tional genius, induſtry,
          commerce, and other <lb/>cauſes which will occur to philoſophers, and to <lb/>gentlemen of
          reflection. They will alſo trace a <lb/>multitude of diſeaſes not only to theſe ranks,
          <lb/>diſtinctions, and employments, but alſo to the <lb/>active or ſedentary nature of the
          different pro- <lb/>feſſions and arts. </p>
        <pb n="12"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The inhabitants crowded into cities and <lb/>towns, and thoſe diſperſed in ſmall
          villages, and <lb/>in the country, conſtitute other large groups of <lb/>ſociety. If the
          reſult of Suſmilch's reſearches <lb/>and materials, collected throughout Germany, <lb/>can
          be depended upon as a criterion for other <lb/>European nations, the inhabitants in the
          country <lb/>are to thoſe in cities and towns as 3<formula notation="fraction"
            >1/2</formula> to 1. <lb/>Great cities, if we except Rome and Conſtanti- <lb/>nople, are
          of modern date in moſt kingdoms of <lb/>Europe. In the ninth century, a few towns had
          <lb/>been built in Germany, but in England, cor- <lb/>porations and conſiderable towns are
          poſterior <lb/>to the Norman invaſion. In both ancient and <lb/>modern times neceſſity
          alone would naturally <lb/>collect numbers into thoſe rendezvouſes of ſecu- <lb/>rity and
          defence. Cities, aſſociated communi- <lb/>ties, and towns, during the religious frenzy of
          <lb/>cruſading, and after the termination of this epi- <lb/>demical diſtemper, were
          aſylums from ariſto- <lb/>cratic tyranny; and when of moderate ſize, are <lb/>feats of
          politeneſs, refinement, emulation, arts, <lb/>and ſociety: but when overgrown, they check
          <lb/>population; they are drains of the human ſpe- <lb/>cies, the graves of infants, and
          nurſeries of <lb/>vices. Unfortunately alſo for ſucceeding gene- <lb/>rations, numerous
          cities, towns, and harbours, <lb/>have been founded upon low, unhealthy ſitua- <lb/>tions,
          ſurrounded by moraſſes and hills. Moſt <lb/>cities ſeem to have grown to maturity by acci-
          <lb/>dent and time: their ſtreets are narrow, irregu- <lb/>lar, not ſufficiently
          ventilated, and the inhabi- <lb/>tants abſurdly and perniciouſly thronged toge- <lb/>ther.
          There are moderate-ſized towns, and <lb/>even country diſtricts, whoſe ſituations are ſo
            <pb n="13"/>
          <lb/>noxious, as to make the burials exceed the <lb/>births: for proofs of which, we need
          not travel <lb/>to new uncultivated continents and iſlands, nor <lb/>to rank tropical
          climates. In the regular con- <lb/>ſtruction and economy of their reſpective cities,
          <lb/>vain man is far ſurpaſſed by bees. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Two large and important Claſſes are formed <lb/>in ſociety, by the diſtinction of the
          Sexes into <lb/>male and female. So ſoon as the organs of ge- <lb/>neration are completely
          evolved; that is, when <lb/>the two ſexes arrive at puberty, they are in- <lb/>flamed with
          a new paſſion and pleaſing ſenſe. <lb/>In moſt warm climates, this generative period
          <lb/>is ſomewhat earlier than in northern latitudes; <lb/>and in the former alſo, women
          are ſaid to be <lb/>more prolifick. We ſhall therefore devote a few <lb/>words to the
          union of the ſexes, from whence <lb/>enſue procreation and births. We cannot poſ-
          <lb/>ſibly form any correct judgment of the waſte <lb/>and expenditure of mankind by
          diſeaſes and ca- <lb/>ſualties, without a comparative ſtatement of the <lb/>recruit. This
          is an obvious medical, political, <lb/>and commercial axiom. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The mean ages at which marriages in this <lb/>iſland commence, is computed from 32 to
          35 <lb/>on the ſide of the man, and 25 on that of <lb/>the woman: but in this eſtimate
          ſecond and <lb/>third marriages are included. Some calcu- <lb/>lators have computed, that
          amongſt five mil- <lb/>lion and an half of inhabitants in England, <lb/>there are annually
          about forty-one thouſand le- <lb/>gal marriages: of which one ſixth part are <lb/>widows
          or widowers; about one marriage to <lb/>every one hundred and four inhabitants; and <pb
            n="14"/>
          <lb/>the annual marriages to the births, as 1 to 4, <lb/>or 4<formula notation="fraction"
            >1/2</formula>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In cities, not only fewer enter into the ma- <lb/>trimonial ſtate, but the product
          alſo of city and <lb/>country marriages is obſerved to differ. Mar- <lb/>riages in cities,
          one with another, ſeldom pro- <lb/>duce above four, generally between three and <lb/>four,
          and ſometimes not three children: where- <lb/>as country and village marriages ſeldom pro-
          <lb/>duce leſs than four, and generally between four <lb/>and five at a medium; for ſome
          married pairs <lb/>have only one or two; others ſix, eight, twelve, <lb/>or more; and a
          ſmall remnant are unprolifick. <lb/>Whether this diſparity between the product of
          <lb/>city and country marriages is to be imputed to <lb/>diſſipation, libertiniſm, and
          incontinence, both <lb/>in the ſingle and married ſate; to the cloudy <lb/>apprehenſions
          and fears of overſtocking their <lb/>houſe; to later, fewer, and leſs frequent unions
          <lb/>in the matrimonial bond; or to all theſe and <lb/>other cauſes combined, I ſubmit to
          the reader's <lb/>conſideration. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Natural, or illegitimate children, are enrolled <lb/>in the public records of
          chriſtenings, and ſwell <lb/>their proportion to the regiſtered weddings <lb/>ſomewhat
          greater than they would appear with- <lb/>out this extraneous addition. In ſome German
          <lb/>regiſters, Dr. Short found, that of 333,655 <lb/>births, the illegitimate amounted to
          one thirty- <lb/>ſeventh part; and in an inland town of Eng- <lb/>land, that of 10,337
          births, 284, or about one <lb/>thirtieth part, were illegitimate. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Providence has wiſely ordained, that through- <lb/>out thoſe European kingdoms, of
          which we <lb/>have any regiſters, a few more males ſhould be <pb n="15"/>
          <lb/>born than females; and indeed ſuch a ſurplus <lb/>is rendered neceſſary from the
          waſte by wars, <lb/>emigration, intemperance, mechanical arts and <lb/>trades, the
          inclemency and viciſſitudes of the <lb/>weather and ſeaſons, the vices and misfortunes
          <lb/>to which political puniſhments are annexed, with <lb/>various other noxious
          caſualties, to all which the <lb/>male ſex are moſt expoſed. In Dr. Arbuth- <lb/>not's
          Table, printed in the London Philoſo- <lb/>phical Tranſactions, of the proportion between
          <lb/>the births of the ſexes, in 46 years were bap- <lb/>tized, of males 329,742; of
          females 308,644; <lb/>majority of males only 23,098. By the Lon- <lb/>don regiſters, from
          1657 to 1776, I find that <lb/>there have been chriſtened of males, 1,041,149; <lb/>of
          females, 983,061; or as 18 to 17: and <lb/>therefore, that in this long interval of 120
          <lb/>years, and comprehending two million of births, <lb/>there is only a trifling
          majority of males, <lb/>amounting to 58,088; a number which would <lb/>ſcarce recruit the
          conſumption of a few active <lb/>campaigns. In volume the 7th of the Philoſophi- <lb/>cal
          Tranſactions abridged, there is an account of <lb/>the annual births during ſeveral years
          at Vienna, <lb/>Breſlaw, Dreſden, Leipſick, and Ratiſbon; and <lb/>in thoſe cities male
          and female births were as <lb/>19 to 18. Amongſt the abortives and ſtill-born <lb/>we alſo
          find a plurality of males. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>If the regiſters can be depended upon, it ap- <lb/>pears that there are more births
          in winter than <lb/>in ſummer, not only in town but alſo in the <lb/>country. The
          increaſed population during the <lb/>winter, in cities, muſt naturally augment the
          <lb/>births. But although the fruit of the human <lb/>womb may not have arrived at
          maturity before <pb n="16"/>
          <lb/>winter, it is no proof againſt the general law <lb/>of the ſpring and ſummer
          influence on animals <lb/>and vegetables in contributing to fecundity and <lb/>generation.
          We muſt diſtinguiſh between the <lb/>ſpring and harveſt of human fertility. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>If the number of inhabitants in any kingdom, <lb/>city, or village, continues the
          ſame without in- <lb/>creaſe or decreaſe, and ſupported by their own <lb/>procreation
          only, it is evident, that there the <lb/>annual births and burials will be equal, and the
          <lb/>ſupply proportioned to the waſte; and in equal <lb/>numbers, as many will die at all
          ages as are <lb/>born in the year, on a general average; and <lb/>the numbers dying any
          year at one, two, three <lb/>years of age, and ſo on to the extreme of ex- <lb/>iſtence,
          will be juſt equal with the numbers who <lb/>ſucceſſively attain to thoſe different ages
          at which <lb/>the others die. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The total annual births amongſt five million <lb/>and an half of inhabitants in
          England, are cal- <lb/>culated by Davenant at 190,000; which is <lb/>about one birth to
          every twenty-five inhabi- <lb/>tants, and amongſt ten million of inhabitants in
          <lb/>Britain and Ireland, the annual procreation will <lb/>exceed three hundred and fifty
          thouſand; and <lb/>the annual mortality ſhould be ſomewhat infe- <lb/>rior. In the kingdom
          of Pruſſia, from the <lb/>year 1715 to 18, there were chriſtened, at an <lb/>annual
          medium, 78,826; buried, 55,852. In <lb/>the kingdom of Sweden, the annual average of
          <lb/>births during nine years, ending in 1763, was <lb/>90,240; burials, 69,125. In
          Norway, in 1761, <lb/>the chriſtenings were 11,024; burials, 6,926. <lb/>In France, during
          three years, ending in I772, <lb/>the annual average of births was 920,918; bu- <pb n="17"/>
          <lb/>rials, 780,040. In the county diſtrict of Vaux, <lb/>in Switzerland, during ten
          years, the births <lb/>were 3,155; burials, 2,504. The country, ſays <lb/>Graunt, has
          6,339 births for 5,280 burials. In <lb/>that little fertile iſland Madeira, the
          inhabitants <lb/>have been computed to double themſelves in <lb/>eighty-four years; ſo
          great is the difference be- <lb/>tween the births and burials. And in ſome <lb/>provinces
          of North America, if Dr. Franklin's <lb/>calculations are correct, the inhabitants double
          <lb/>themſelves in the ſhort ſpace of twenty-five, <lb/>twenty-two, and even fifteen
          years. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>On the other hand, in all the large cities of <lb/>Europe; in Paris, Vienna, Rome,
          Dreſden, <lb/>Berlin, Amſterdam, London, Edinburgh, Dub- <lb/>lin, and in almoſt all towns
          of conſiderable <lb/>magnitude and population, the total annual <lb/>births are inferior
          to the burials. It is calcu- <lb/>lated, that in London, within the laſt 150 years,
          <lb/>near a million more of the human ſpecies have <lb/>been waſted, beyond what were
          reared by its <lb/>own original growth and procreation. But in <lb/>ſmall villages and
          country diſtricts, the annual <lb/>births exceed the burials; and it is from this
          <lb/>redundance that a ſupply is furniſhed for the ex- <lb/>traordinary conſumption of
          armies, navies, war, <lb/>colonization, emigration; excluſive of ſickneſs, <lb/>and other
          morbid caſualties: the country and <lb/>village ſurplus prevents depopulation. There
          <lb/>are about 4<formula notation="fraction">1/2</formula> million of births annually in
          Eu- <lb/>rope, and the deaths are inferior, probably by <lb/>half a million. Wars however
          are here ex- <lb/>cepted, which will alſo detract from the <lb/>births. </p>
        <pb n="18"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But if, on one hand, large cities and high <lb/>refinement are obſtacles to
          population, a wild <lb/>ſtate of nature is ſtill more detrimental. There <lb/>are more
          inhabitants concentrated into one large <lb/>metropolis of Aſia or Europe, than could be
          <lb/>collected in many thouſand miles of the North <lb/>American Wilderneſs on its firſt
          diſcovery. A <lb/>medium ſtate between the vicious extremes of <lb/>refinement and rude
          ſavageneſs; or the middle <lb/>ſtages between the iron and golden ages of the <lb/>ancient
          philoſophers, is the moſt favourable to <lb/>the increaſe of our ſpecies. But the cauſes
          con- <lb/>ducive to population and depopulation are of <lb/>infinite compaſs, and are of a
          compound na- <lb/>ture medical and political. They are connected <lb/>with the ſtate of
          government, religion, climate, <lb/>genius, induſtry, riches, poverty, taxes, luxury,
          <lb/>refinement, diſſipation, profligacy, wars, colo- <lb/>nization, emigration, commerce,
          agriculture, <lb/>the unequal diſtribution and monopoly of pro- <lb/>perty and farms, the
          plenty, ſcarcity, and <lb/>cheapneſs of food, the encouragement or diſ- <lb/>couragement
          of matrimony, and with many <lb/>other cauſes cloſely allied to our future medical
          <lb/>inveſtigation. Once for all, I embrace the pre- <lb/>ſent opportunity to obſerve,
          that throughout <lb/>this treatiſe there are hints and ideas, each of <lb/>which draws a
          whole train after them: the full <lb/>open detail, and ample diſcovery is left to the
          <lb/>reader. </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="19"/>
      <div type="chapter">
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>CHAP. II. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">W</hi>E are now to view the human race un- <lb/>expectedly arreſted,
          and ſtruggling in <lb/>the tragical and laſt ſtages of their terreſtrial <lb/>pilgrimage.
          The viſion of human life is ſoon <lb/>at an end: we are uſhered into the world with
          <lb/>lamentable exclamation; and are too often torn <lb/>out of it in pain and agony.
          Bills of Morta- <lb/>lity, however defective and inaccurate, yet ſuf- <lb/>ficiently
          demonſtrate this awful truth, that very <lb/>few of the human ſpecies die of old age, or
          <lb/>natural decay: by far the greater proportion are <lb/>prematurely cut off by
          diſeaſes. Of all the <lb/>animal tribe, who uſually bring forth one at a <lb/>birth, none
          periſh in ſuch numbers in infancy: <lb/>almoſt one half of human mortality is under
          <lb/>five years of age. In London, Vienna, Berlin, <lb/>and every other overgrown
          metropolis of Eu- <lb/>rope, on an average, one half of the children <lb/>born, die under
          three years of age. But in <lb/>country towns and villages, the proportion of <lb/>infant
          mortality greatly abates. In ſome country <lb/>towns of England, of conſiderable magnitude
          <lb/>and population, as Mancheſter, half the chil- <lb/>dren die under five; at Norwich,
          half under <lb/>ſix; at Northampton, half under ten years of <lb/>age. London, therefore,
          will have loſt, out of <lb/>equal capitals, a number in the intermediate <lb/>ſpace,
          between three and ten, more than Nor- <lb/>thampton. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Attend next to the ſmall proportion of Infant <lb/>Mortality in open country
          diſtricts. By. Dr. <pb n="20"/>
          <lb/>Short's regiſters of ſeveral ſmall country vil- <lb/>lages in England, the major part
          born live to <lb/>the ages of 25, 27, 33, and 40. In many <lb/>healthy country pariſhes,
          half the inhabitants <lb/>born live to 40, 46, and a few even to 50 and <lb/>60; and rear
          large families of children. In <lb/>ſome extenſive country diſtricts of Switzerland,
          <lb/>ſimilar obſervations have been made by Suſ- <lb/>milch and Muret. Here, therefore, is
          an aſto- <lb/>niſhing diſparity between the proſpects of city <lb/>and country life, in
          the early ſtages of puerile <lb/>exiſtence. Infants in cities reſemble tender <lb/>plants
          excluded from freſh air, or fiſh confined <lb/>in ſtagnant water; and periſh before they
          can <lb/>acquire a ſolidity and ſeaſoning to endure the <lb/>adulterated quality of the
          ſurrounding element. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Mortality, univerſally, during the firſt year <lb/>after birth, is the moſt enormous
          in the funeral <lb/>catalogue: it is nearly one fourth of the mor- <lb/>tality of Europe.
          A London infant at birth, <lb/>has but an equal chance of living to three years <lb/>old;
          whereas in the country, as before obſerved, <lb/>half of thoſe born ſurvive to maturity.
          Upon <lb/>reaching the third year, in cities, infants are <lb/>ſomewhat ſeaſoned, and the
          hurricane of pue- <lb/>rile carnage is greatly abated. There is not af- <lb/>terwards ſuch
          a prodigious diſproportion between <lb/>city and country mortality; and, in a few years
          <lb/>after, between ſeven and ten, they approach <lb/>nearer to an equality. Death is
          earlier glutted with <lb/>ſlaughter in cities, than in the country. From <lb/>the London
          regiſters of burials, it appears that <lb/>more die in the metropolis under two years of
          <lb/>age, than from two to upwards of forty; and <lb/>more under five years of age, than
          from five <pb n="21"/>
          <lb/>to between fifty and ſixty: yet under five, there <lb/>are but an inconſiderable
          number alive, com- <lb/>pared to the latter claſs above that age: the <lb/>deaths are
          greatly diſproportioned to the liv- <lb/>ing numbers or capitals. A few more die in
          <lb/>London in the ſhort interval between five and <lb/>ten years of age, than in the
          ſucceeding double <lb/>interval from ten to twenty; and more between <lb/>twenty and
          thirty, than in the fifteen preceding <lb/>years; and the burial liſt continues turgid to
          <lb/>ſixty. Between eight and ſixteen years of age, <lb/>one of every ſeventy of the
          Chriſt School boys <lb/>is computed to die. Davenant rates the de- <lb/>crement in theſe
          years at only one <hi rend="italic">per cent</hi>. <lb/>Having ſurmounted all the dangers
          and preci- <lb/>pices of the early preceding journey, there is no <lb/>ſtage wherein the
          future proſpects of exiſtence <lb/>and longevity are ſo extenſive: during thoſe <lb/>years
          of adoleſcence, very few die in city, <lb/>town, or country. The tide of life is then at
          <lb/>the flood; and from thence to the ultimate <lb/>verge of exiſtence, vitality
          continues gradually <lb/>to ebb. Towards the meridian of life, it ſinks <lb/>to two; and
          at ſixty down to four or five <hi rend="italic">per <lb/>cent</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>One reaſon, but not the only one, as calcu- <lb/>lators alledge, of the great ſurge
          in the Lon- <lb/>don bills, from twenty up to forty, is, that <lb/>within this interval of
          life, the majority of ex- <lb/>traneous new ſettlers or recruits arrive; and
          <lb/>conſequently augment the burials in the metro- <lb/>polis, from twenty to forty,
          beyond their na- <lb/>tural proportion: the principal reaſon is, a uni- <lb/>verſal law of
          nature in every ſituation; the <lb/>cauſes and explanation of which will be found <pb
            n="22"/>
          <lb/>in the hiſtory of diſeaſes. After paſſing the <lb/>meridian, and in the evening of
          life, the ſea- <lb/>ſoned inhabitants of cities are ſaid, by Dr. <lb/>Price, to have the
          advantage of the country, <lb/>in health and longevity: that is to ſay, although <lb/>the
          number who have ſurvived in the country <lb/>to ſixty, ſeventy, and eighty, are greater
          pro- <lb/>portionally than in cities, yet the latter claſs ar- <lb/>rived at thoſe years
          in London have, compa- <lb/>ratively, ſurer expectations of life. I do not, <lb/>however,
          find this aſſertion verified in fact; the <lb/>balance, if any, vibrating alternately on
          each <lb/>ſide. Nearly one fifth of the annual mortality, <lb/>promiſcuouſly, is after 60
          years of age; and <lb/>about one half of theſe, or one tenth or twelfth <lb/>of the whole,
          are left to moulder by the irre- <lb/>mediable dilapidations of time. The propor-
          <lb/>tion of inhabitants who reach eighty years of <lb/>age are computed, in London and
          Vienna, at <lb/>one of every forty: but in country pariſhes, at <lb/>one of every
          twenty-two; and in ſome, even <lb/>one of every eleven. In both city and country, <lb/>the
          few ſurvivors at ninety, out of each thou- <lb/>ſand coetaneous births, will have loſt
          almoſt all <lb/>their fellow-travellers in the journey, long be- <lb/>fore reaching that
          goal; and about three or <lb/>four only out of each thouſand, on an average, <lb/>will be
          then left alive. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>There are indeed a few inſtances of extraor- <lb/>dinary Longevity, to 150 and 165;
          ſuch are <lb/>Jenkins and Par, in this iſland. In Bacon <lb/>Lord Verulam's Hiſtory of
          Long Livers, male <lb/>and female; their climate, diet, mode of life, <lb/>appetites,
          exerciſes, ſtudies, paſſions, diſpoſi- <lb/>tions, habits, and complexions, were exceed-
            <pb n="23"/>
          <lb/>ingly diſſimilar. It is however probable, from <lb/>obſervation and analogy, that the
          indigent and <lb/>laborious claſs of mankind do not attain to lon- <lb/>gevity in the ſame
          proportion with the middling <lb/>and more opulent ranks. The wandering Sa- <lb/>vages of
          America are notoriouſly ſhort-lived. <lb/>Throughout Europe, Aſia, Africa, and Ame-
          <lb/>rica, the rich, the poor, the inhabitants of city <lb/>and country, with very
          different complexion, <lb/>climate, ſoil, diet, and conveniences, all ſeldom <lb/>exceed
          the uſual term of life allotted to man: <lb/>ſeventy and eighty is mentioned in holy writ,
          as <lb/>the brink of our earthly duration. Since the <lb/>days of Moſes; that is, between
          three and four <lb/>thouſand years, human exiſtence has been cir- <lb/>cumſcribed within
          the ſame narrow bounds. In <lb/>the London regiſters of mortality, during a pe- <lb/>riod
          of thirty years, from 1728 to 1758, the <lb/>total mortality is 750,332; and of all this
          <lb/>number, 242 only reached beyond 100 years of <lb/>age; one of whom arrived at 138.
          Through- <lb/>out the annual mortality of Europe, which we <lb/>have eſtimated at four
          million, there are not <lb/>probably two thouſand who have compleated a <lb/>century; nor
          throughout the globe twelve thou- <lb/>ſand of this deſcription. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In ſome races and families of men, longevity <lb/>ſeems to be hereditary; and his
          age, though lit- <lb/>tle more than a dream, exceeds that of all other <lb/>living
          creatures, a few only excepted. Amongſt <lb/>the quadruped creation, the elephant
          ſurpaſſes <lb/>man in longevity: amongſt the birds, the Swan, <lb/>and a few others, have
          ſurvived upwards of a <lb/>century. The age of fiſhes is determined with <lb/>more
          ingenuity than certainty: ſome ſeem to <pb n="24"/>
          <lb/>rival man in years. But among the numerous <lb/>vegetable tribes, the oak, cheſtnut,
          and ſome <lb/>other lords of the foreſt, ſurvive centuries. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>On contraſting the mortality of Males and <lb/>Females, it appears, that,
          notwithſtanding the <lb/>ſurplus of male births, the perils of child-bear- <lb/>ing, the
          many vexatious diſeaſes peculiar to the <lb/>fair ſex, and that phyſicians and
          apothecaries <lb/>have many more patients of the latter; yet the <lb/>total aggregate
          number of living females ex- <lb/>ceeds that of males, in moſt European king- <lb/>doms.
          Upon a numerical inqueſt in Edinburgh, <lb/>and ſome other great cities, it was found,
          that <lb/>females were to males as 4 to 3: in London, as <lb/>13 to 10; and in ſome other
          cities and towns, <lb/>as 9 to 8. But in country diſtricts, Graunt and <lb/>Suſmilch
          agree, that the two ſexes approach <lb/>nearer to an equality. In the province of Jer-
          <lb/>ſey, in North America, the males were found <lb/>the majority. From 1702 to 1752;
          that is, <lb/>during a period of fifty years, I find the pro- <lb/>portion of male and
          female mortality in London <lb/>as follows: Male deaths, 618,076; Female <lb/>deaths,
          626,692. Whence, therefore, does it <lb/>happen, that female deaths preponderate over
          <lb/>the male, when more of the latter are born, <lb/>and, as calculators aſſert, the
          mortality of males, <lb/>at all ages, is greater than that of females? As <lb/>a ſolution
          of this difficulty and partial exception, <lb/>I ſhould ſuggeſt a greater exportation and
          tran- <lb/>ſportation of males to the ſea and land ſervice, <lb/>to nautical commerce, and
          to unhealthy cli- <lb/>mates. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Even in the marriage ſtate, the chance of <lb/>ſurvivorſhip ſeems conſiderably in
          favour of the <pb n="25"/>
          <lb/>wife. In Breſlaw, during eight years, five mar- <lb/>ried men died to three married
          women. Suſ- <lb/>milch, on a ſcrutiny through ſeveral kingdoms <lb/>and principalities of
          Germany, found, that three <lb/>married men died to two married women. Dr. <lb/>Price
          eſtimates the chance in favour of the wife <lb/>being the ſurvivor in marriage, as 3 to 2;
          and <lb/>this calculation is confirmed by the experience <lb/>of the general Clerical
          Society in Scotland, who <lb/>have long eſtabliſhed funds to ſupport their <lb/>widows.
          From their records, it appears that <lb/>twenty married clergymen have died to twelve
          <lb/>wives; or, as 5 to 3. By an accurate ſurvey <lb/>of ſeveral principalities and cities
          in Germany, <lb/>and collected by Suſmilch, the widows were to <lb/>the widowers as 3, and
          even 4 to 1. At mar- <lb/>riage, it ſhould be obſerved, there is generally <lb/>a
          diſparity of age; the bridegroom is from ſix <lb/>to twelve years older than the bride;
          and there- <lb/>fore ſhould, in the courſe of nature, die ſooner: <lb/>and perhaps alſo
          more widowers, comparatively <lb/>with the other ſex, enter into a ſecond marriage;
          <lb/>which tends to reduce their numbers. Beſides, <lb/>huſbands are more expoſed to the
          viciſſitudes <lb/>of the weather and ſeaſons, to exceſſive labour, <lb/>and noxious
          trades, and to many other cauſes <lb/>of diſeaſes. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Dr. Price finds, that the ſexes reſpectively <lb/>commence to be widowers and widows
          about <lb/>52 and 44; that is, men and women entering <lb/>into matrimony, on a general
          average, at the <lb/>ages of 33 and 25, will become widowers and <lb/>widows at 52 and 44:
          conſequently, that each <lb/>marriage will be diſſolved by the death of one <lb/>of them,
          in nineteen years; which is the ulti- <pb n="26"/>
          <lb/>mate term and probability of the huſband and <lb/>wife being both alive. For although
          ſome mar- <lb/>riages may be protracted forty and fifty years, yet <lb/>others may be
          diſſolved in one year, or in a <lb/>ſhorter time. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>We have not yet ſufficient information to de- <lb/>termine the comparative chances of
          Female <lb/>Longevity in the married and ſingle ſtate. At <lb/>Berlin, indeed, calculators
          have remarked, that <lb/>there were more married women alive at great <lb/>ages, than of
          thoſe who remained ſingle. But <lb/>ſuch reſult might naturally be expected from a
          <lb/>greater proportion in the decline of life of wi- <lb/>dows and wives, compared to
          antiquated vir- <lb/>gins. From the ages of fifteen to twenty-five, <lb/>married women
          likewiſe are ſaid to have the ad- <lb/>vantage of the ſingle, in whom the dictates of
          <lb/>nature are fruſtrated and violated. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Comparing the mortality of the Seaſons, Dr. <lb/>Short found, from a variety of
          country regiſters, <lb/>that mortality general begins its reign in De- <lb/>cember; that
          at March it is in its zenith; and <lb/>at May in its declenſion. In twenty-five coun-
          <lb/>try towns and pariſhes, he found the winter to <lb/>the ſummer mortality as 50 to 41.
          At Man- <lb/>cheſter, a country town of England, Dr. Per- <lb/>cival found the winter to
          the ſummer mortality <lb/>as 11 to 8. At Vevey in Switzerland, during <lb/>ſixty years,
          Mr. Muret found the burials, during <lb/>the four winter months, as 5 to 4 to thoſe of
          <lb/>the ſummer. Another proof of this is recorded <lb/>in the Recherces ſur la
          Population, par Meſſance: <lb/>The total ſick admitted into the Hotel Dieu hoſ- <lb/>pital
          in Paris, from 1724 to 1763 (forty years) <lb/>were, in the four winter months, December,
            <pb n="27"/>
          <lb/>January, February, and March, 314,824; and <lb/>in the four ſummer months, June,
          July, Au- <lb/>guſt, September, 238,522; or as 4 to 3. In <lb/>London too, the
          undertaker's harveſt is in win- <lb/>ter. There is one obvious reaſon why, in every
          <lb/>metropolis, the winter mortality ſhould exceed <lb/>that of ſummer, from the greater
          concourſe of <lb/>inhabitants of all ranks; but independent of ad- <lb/>ditional
          population in winter, the ſame law ſeems <lb/>to prevail in country places. Whether from
          <lb/>diſeaſes originally engendered in that ſeaſon, or <lb/>from its more pernicious
          effects on the lingering <lb/>and convaleſcent train of chronic and acute di- <lb/>ſeaſes,
          may be diſputed. Within the tropical <lb/>circles there is not the ſame diverſity of the
          <lb/>ſeaſons as in European regions: there the pe- <lb/>riodical hurricane and rainy
          ſeaſon, or monſoon, <lb/>is the moſt ſickly and fatal. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>On collating the annual average of deaths, <lb/>at all ages, in a ſickly year of
          London, and <lb/>other great cities, with ſickly years in the coun- <lb/>try pariſhes, Dr.
          Short found, that cities and <lb/>towns have the advantage of the country, and <lb/>are
          leſs annoyed. According to this author, in <lb/>ſpacious open country diſtriſits, where
          fatal epi- <lb/>demick diſtempers burſt out, the burials not <lb/>only exceeded the
          chriſtenings, but more died in <lb/>one year, than during 6, 10, 12, or ſometimes <lb/>15
          healthy years; whereas he adds, in London, <lb/>and ſuch other cities, not above one
          third, <lb/>fourth, or fifth, beyond the ordinary conſump- <lb/>tion, are ſwept away.
          Peſtilential mortality <lb/>alone is the ſolitary exception to the Doctor's
          <lb/>propoſition. In the London morbid regiſters <lb/>we may frequently obſerve, that in
          different <pb n="28"/>
          <lb/>months the deaths are double or treble above <lb/>equal periods of the ſame year: but
          during the <lb/>preſent century, I find no inſtance even of tri- <lb/>ple, and very rarely
          of double exceſs, in the <lb/>annual London burials. Dr. Short adds, that <lb/>mortality
          is more regular and conſtant in cities, <lb/>and not ſo many deſtroyed, <q rend="quotes"
            >per faltum,</q> from <lb/>raging epidemicks, as in the country. In pure <lb/>open air
          he ſuggeſts, that contagion and infection, <lb/>and other adulterated effluvia, are more
          virulent. <lb/>Or, perhaps he ſhould have ſaid, at leaſt have <lb/>added, that in cities
          where the atmoſphere is <lb/>charged with a load of ſmoke, and other hete- <lb/>rogeneous
          vapours, epidemical poiſons may be <lb/>blunted, decompounded, or annihilated: that
          <lb/>likewiſe in cities human bodies are more early <lb/>ſeaſoned and habituated to ſuch
          noxious impreſ- <lb/>ſions, and like doctors and nurſes, are in ſome <lb/>degree fortified
          by habit: that beſides in every <lb/>large metropolis, ſmall-pox, meaſles, nervous,
          <lb/>putrid, and ſome other febrile epidemicks, are <lb/>almoſt conſtant reſidents; and
          conſequently the <lb/>devaſtation from theſe diſeaſes is more regular <lb/>and equal than
          in the country, where there are <lb/>ſeveral years and more irregular diſtances be-
          <lb/>tween their invaſions. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Let us condenſe our calculations into a few <lb/>general abſtracts of human carnage.
          If we ſcan <lb/>the manſions of diſeaſe and woe, we find, on an <lb/>average, 1 death,
          annually, out of every 5 fa- <lb/>milies in cities: but in country towns, and open
          <lb/>diſtricts, 1 out of 7, 8, 9; and in a few healthy <lb/>places, 1 out of every 10
          families. Includ- <lb/>ing the whole aſſemblage of inhabitants in city, <lb/>town, and
          country, from birth to the extreme <pb n="29"/>
          <lb/>of exiſtence, they are computed to die in the <lb/>following annual proportion to the
          living: In <lb/>London, 1 of 21; Dublin, 1 of 22; Edinburgh, <lb/>1 of 21; Vienna, 1 of
          20; Amſterdam, 1 of <lb/>22; Berlin, 1 of 26; but, diſmal to relate, of <lb/>the oppreſſed
          negroes in the Weſt India iſlands, <lb/>1 of 7. This is nearly Dr. Price's calculation;
          <lb/>but Halley and Suſmilch compute only 1 of 22 <lb/>to 29 to die annually in cities. In
          ſmaller cities <lb/>and towns, ſuch as Norwich and Northampton, <lb/>the general average
          of deaths is 1 of 24 to 26; <lb/>but in ſeveral provinces and healthy country vil-
          <lb/>lages, 1 of 32 and 33, up to 45, 50, and even <lb/>6o, is the annual drain: 1 of 43
          to 50 was the <lb/>average in upwards of a thouſand country pa- <lb/>riſhes on the
          continent; and recorded in Suſ- <lb/>milch. Within the above ſhort intervals of <lb/>time,
          there will have died in the reſpective cities <lb/>and country places enumerated, a number
          equal <lb/>to the whole inhabitants. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The ancient Egyptians computed a century <lb/>by 3 generations; thus eſtabliſhing an
          auxiliary <lb/>regulator of chronology and hiſtory. At this day 33 <lb/>or 35 is near the
          meaſure of a generation, and the <lb/>general decreaſe of a community throughout Eu-
          <lb/>rope, comprehending all the inhabitants in city, <lb/>village, and country: that is,
          mankind ſhare <lb/>amongſt them from about 32 or 33 to 35 years <lb/>each of exiſtence:
          and within this fugitive in- <lb/>terval of time, a number equal to all the pre- <lb/>ſent
          inhabitants of this iſland, or of the whole <lb/>earth, will be exterminated. If we extend
          this <lb/>eſtimate to the whole human race, eight hun- <lb/>dred million will die in 33
          years; twenty-four <lb/>million annually; ſeventy thouſand daily; three <pb n="30"/>
          <lb/>thouſand hourly; and fifty every minute. It is <lb/>perhaps ſuperfluous to add, that,
          in the ſame <lb/>intervals, an equal or ſuperior number will be <lb/>born. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>According to De Moivre and Dr. Price, <lb/>
          <q rend="quotes diple">the probabilities or expectation of life, de- <lb/>creaſe as we
            advance from childhood to old <lb/>age, in an arithmetical progreſſion; that is, <lb/>in
            ſuch a manner that the difference is always <lb/>the ſame between the number of perſons
            liv- <lb/>ing at the beginning of any one year, and the <lb/>number living at the
            beginning of the follow- <lb/>ing year. </q> Or, in other words, leſs enve- <lb/>loped
          in mathematical obſcurity, out of any ſpe- <lb/>cified number, an hundred or a thouſand,
          the <lb/>ſame proportion will continue to die every year <lb/>until near 80 years of age
          and upwards: conſe- <lb/>quently, the probabilities of life are conſtantly
          <lb/>decreaſing; becauſe notwithſtanding the progreſ- <lb/>ſive annual drain from the
          capitals, yet the <lb/>deaths continue throughout equal. But this <lb/>proportion is
          certainly erroneous in the firſt <lb/>ſtages of life, and until about 10. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>View the above propoſition in another light. <lb/>From any given number there will be
          an equal <lb/>drain annually, until what De Moivre terms the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >complement</hi> or <hi rend="italic">maximum</hi>, or utmoſt probable ex- <lb/>treme of
          life, which he fixes at 86, all are dead. <lb/>The probability, therefore, that the whole
          of <lb/>any limited number whatſoever, or age, will all <lb/>be exterminated is the number
          of years between <lb/>86 and the year ſuch a number are all alive. Of <lb/>56 perſons
          alive at 30, they ſhould all be dead <lb/>in 56 years, becauſe 56 added to 30 amounts to
          <lb/>86, the maximum: of 46 perſons alive at 40 <pb n="31"/>
          <lb/>years of age, they ſhould all be dead in 46 <lb/>years: and 36 perſons alive at 50
          years of age, <lb/>ſhould be dead in 36 years; for 50 and 36 com- <lb/>plete the maximum.
          Again, the expectation of <lb/>any ſingle life is only half the maximum or com-
          <lb/>plement, or half the ſpace between that age and <lb/>the above ultimate term of
          exiſtence: but here <lb/>we muſt repeat the former exception, and draw <lb/>the line after
          10 years of age. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The expectation of <hi rend="italic">two</hi> equal joint lives, ac- <lb/>cording to
          De Moivre, is only one third of the <lb/>complement of life. Example: two lives, aged
          <lb/>40, have an even chance or probable proſpect <lb/>of continuing together in exiſtence
          only 15 <lb/>years; which is the third of the complement, <lb/>reckoning from 40 to 86:
          the expectation of <lb/>the ſurvivor is alſo 15 years. Or, ſuppoſe a lot <lb/>of marriages
          of perſons at 40 years of age, they <lb/>will, on an average, continue together 15<formula
            notation="fraction">1/2</formula>
          <lb/>years; and the ſurvivors the ſame time after. <lb/>This expectation, therefore, is
          the probable du- <lb/>ration of each marriage, and the ſhare of each <lb/>perſon's life.
          But it may be proper to add, <lb/>that the duration of marriages, and the value of
          <lb/>ſingle and joint lives, will, on a promiſcuous <lb/>calculation, be different from
          the regiſters of <lb/>annuitant and inſurance offices, becauſe they are <lb/>ſcrupulouſly
          vigilant to exclude all diſeaſed and <lb/>unhealthy perſons from becoming members. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The following Chart and Tables, preſent a <lb/>diſtinct proſpect of the fates
          clipping the mortal <lb/>thread, from birth to old age, in city and coun- <lb/>try. But we
          are not to ſuppoſe that in every <lb/>inſtance there will be annually a regular arith-
          <lb/>metical diminution, as marked in the different <pb n="32"/>
          <lb/>tables: ſome years will be more fatal than <lb/>others; and we are to form eſtimates
          from an <lb/>average of ſeveral years. Throughout the <lb/>Chart the firſt column points
          out the age, the <lb/>ſecond the number living at that age, the third <lb/>the number who
          die during the year; and ſo on <lb/>to the end of each table. But obſerve, that the
          <lb/>number of infants, at the beginning of the ſe- <lb/>cond column, are ſuppoſed to be
          all born toge- <lb/>ther on the firſt day of that year, and this rule <lb/>applies
          throughout all the remaining ages. <lb/>From the Chart, and from the ſubſequent dif-
          <lb/>ferent Tables may be eſtimated the annual waſte, <lb/>out of any ſpecified number, at
          all ages, the <lb/>ultimate proſpects of exiſtence, and the odds or <lb/>probability of a
          perſon in health ſurviving a <lb/>ſtated number of years. Theſe are alſo adapted <lb/>to
          all ages, and to the inhabitants of city, and <lb/>country. It would be endleſs to point
          out the in- <lb/>ſtances of their utility and practical application. <lb/>The two
          intermediate ſhort Tables demonſtrate <lb/>both the total amount, and the gradations of
          <lb/>annual mortality, at different ages, in London <lb/>and in Europe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In one of the ſhort tables juſt now alluded to, <lb/>I have attempted, as nearly as
          ſuch an intricate <lb/>and unprecedented ſubject would permit, or at <lb/>leaſt as I was
          enabled from any probably data, <lb/>to preſent at one view the <hi rend="italic">annual
            mortality</hi>, and <lb/>comparative decrement, throughout all ages, of <lb/>the
          inhabitants of Europe, including city, town, <lb/>and country. We may, in ſome degree,
          judge <lb/>of the mortality, comparatively, by the num- <lb/>bers alive in the different
          intervals of life; and <pb/>
          <pb n="33"/>
          <lb/>by an average of city and country mortality in <lb/>each of thoſe intervals. The
          annual mortality <lb/>of Great Britain and Ireland, in each of the <lb/>following
          intervals of life, will, in correſpond- <lb/>ence with the population, be inferior, as 1
          to 13, <lb/>to that of Europe; and the latter as 1 to 6, to <lb/>that of all the human
          ſpecies. (See a Table in <lb/>the preceding chapter.) </p>
        <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="33"/>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter">
        <figure rend="space">
          <figDesc>A short horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>CHAP. III. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">H</hi>AVING in the preceding Chapter endea- <lb/>voured to eſtabliſh
          the mortality of the <lb/>human ſpecies at different ages, I am now to <lb/>attempt a more
          arduous taſk; to aſcertain the <lb/>mortality by different diſeaſes and caſualties. I
          <lb/>propoſe therefore, in imitation of the geogra- <lb/>phers, to ſpread out and to
          review, in one ge- <lb/>neral Chart, the enormous hoſt of diſeaſes which <lb/>diſgorge
          their virulence over the earth, and, <lb/>with frightful rapacity, wage inceſſant
          hoſtilities <lb/>with mankind. By this means, we ſhall, to uſe <lb/>a military phraſe,
          reconnoitre more diſtinctly <pb n="36"/>
          <lb/>our enemies arranged in hoſtile front; and be <lb/>warned to make the beſt
          diſpoſition and prepa- <lb/>ration for defence where the greateſt danger is
          <lb/>apprehended, and the moſt formidable aſſaults <lb/>to be ſuſtained. Armed with
          diſeaſes, the grim <lb/>King of Terrors appears in the moſt hideous <lb/>aſpect. Under all
          theſe predatory diſguiſes and <lb/>morbifick forms, I ſhall track him grappling <lb/>with
          mankind, and with his tremendous ſcythe <lb/>mowing down generations. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I could eaſily have exhibited tables of the <lb/>Diſeaſes and Caſualties in London
          during the <lb/>greater part of the laſt century. But, com- <lb/>pared to its preſent
          magnitude, the Britiſh me- <lb/>tropolis was then inſignificant in ſize: 23 new
          <lb/>pariſhes have been ſince gradually added to the <lb/>London bills: there is alſo a
          chaſm in that cen- <lb/>tury of 10 years in which the regiſters are loſt. <lb/>Again,
          until 1665 and 6, London was infeſted <lb/>with the plague; which diſeaſe, previous to
          that <lb/>date, ſeems to have been one primary object of <lb/>the regiſters: and to adopt
          Graunt and Short's <lb/>ſentiments, theſe records, from various political <lb/>and
          religious obſtacles, were then very negli- <lb/>gently managed. During the early part of
          this <lb/>interval, the kingdom was diſtracted with civil <lb/>war; and after the great
          peſtilence in 1665, <lb/>London muſt have required ſome years to re- <lb/>cruit. Beſides,
          had I attempted to form tables <lb/>for even the latter part of the laſt century, the
          <lb/>reader would have been fruitleſly embarraſſed; <lb/>and ſuch an attempt muſt ever
          prove abortive. <lb/>For example, under one and the ſame title, in <lb/>the annually bills
          of mortality, are often con- <lb/>founded flox, ſmall pox, and meaſles: con- <pb n="37"/>
          <lb/>ſumptions and tiſſick: cancer, canker, and <lb/>thruſh: wolf, cancer, gangrene, and
          fiſtula: <lb/>cancer, gangrene, fiſtula, and mortification: gout <lb/>and ſciatica:
          vapours and water in the head: <lb/>quinſey and thruſh: teeth and worms: ſores,
          <lb/>ulcers, bruiſed and broken limbs: cough, cold, <lb/>and chincough, &amp;c. Theſe are
          a few ſpecimens <lb/>of Noſological abſurdity in the ſuperintendants <lb/>of the public
          regiſters. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Notwithſtanding this rabble of diſeaſes, in <lb/>commenting upon the London bills and
          diſeaſes <lb/>of the preſent century, I conſtantly refer back, <lb/>and contraſt them with
          the bills of the laſt thirty <lb/>years of the preceding century; ſo that, as near <lb/>as
          the imperfection of the materials will admit, <lb/>the mortality and diſeaſes of 105 years
          in Lon- <lb/>don is preſented at one view; and comprehends <lb/>the various acute and
          chronic diſeaſes, by which <lb/>about two million and a half of the human ſpe- <lb/>cies
          have been deſtroyed. The few authors who <lb/>have written on bills of mortality, have
          obſcured <lb/>their works in a cloud of figures and calcula- <lb/>tion: the reader muſt
          have no ſmall portion of <lb/>phlegm and reſolution to follow them through- <lb/>out with
          attention: they often tax the memory <lb/>and patience with a numerical ſuperfluity, even
          <lb/>to a nuiſance. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>For the above and many other reaſons, I have <lb/>compreſſed into one chart, the
          London Diſeaſes <lb/>and Caſualties of ſeventy-five years in the pre- <lb/>ſent century:
          each diſeaſe and caſualty is ar- <lb/>ranged in a progreſſive ſeries of fifteen years
            <lb/>mortality<unclear>;</unclear> and in a fifth column is added toge- <lb/>ther the
          mortality of the preceding five divi- <lb/>ſions. During this period, London has been <pb
            n="38"/>
          <lb/>more populous and ſtationary in numbers: and <lb/>by this means, the actual and
          comparative mag- <lb/>nitude, riſe, and declenſion of different diſeaſes, <lb/>will be
          more conſpicuous in each period or in- <lb/>terval: and by meaſuring the mortality with
          <lb/>the population, we are enabled, with certain <lb/>precautions and exceptions, to make
          the diſeaſes <lb/>and caſualties of London ſerve as a morbid ba- <lb/>rometer to the whole
          nation, and in ſome de- <lb/>gree to the whole univerſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The important reaſon which determined me <lb/>in forming an arrangement of fifteen
          years, in <lb/>preference to any other number or period, was, <lb/>that the annual havock
          by ſimilar diſeaſes and <lb/>caſualties, throughout this and the neighbour- <lb/>ing
          iſland, might be computed with ſome pro- <lb/>bability by each fifteen years of the London
          <lb/>bills; and thereby to elicite a new, curious, and <lb/>comprehenſive propoſition in
          medicine. For <lb/>inſtance, if we ſuppoſe the ſtanding number, on <lb/>an average, of the
          London inhabitants at ſeven <lb/>hundred thouſand; and the total inhabitants in
          <lb/>Britain and Ireland at ten million; and if the <lb/>ſame diſeaſes and caſualties were
          equally diffuſed <lb/>and fatal to this whole community, then, in <lb/>ſuch caſe, the
          London bills and our chart would <lb/>ſerve as a ſcale or index of mortality to both
          <lb/>kingdoms: as many would die annually of every <lb/>diſeaſe and caſualty throughout
          ten million, as <lb/>are cut off in fifteen years in London; for ſeven <lb/>hundred
          thouſand multiplied by fifteen, amounts <lb/>nearly to ten million. The exceſs is trifling
          in <lb/>a general calculation upon ſo large a ſcale. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But to ſupply the probable deficiency in the <lb/>annual mortality of London by
          different diſeaſes <pb n="39"/>
          <lb/>and caſualties, we muſt make an addition to each <lb/>of one fourth. To the mortality
          of ſmall-pox, <lb/>in London, during fifteen years, and rated at <lb/>thirty thouſand, we
          ſhould add one fourth more <lb/>to raiſe it to its juſt ſtandard; that is, to about
          <lb/>thirty-eight thouſand; which would be the an- <lb/>nual mortality amongſt ten million
          in Britain and <lb/>Ireland, ſuppoſing ſmall-pox equally univerſal, <lb/>one time or
          other, and deſtructive. By the ſame <lb/>hypotheſis, amongſt one hundred and thirty mil-
          <lb/>lion in Europe Variolous mortality annually, <lb/>would amount to upwards of four
          hundred thou- <lb/>ſand, and, amongſt eight hundred million, that <lb/>is the whole human
          race, to nearly two million <lb/>and a half annually. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Let us view on this great ſcale the annual ha- <lb/>vock of a few diſeaſes, aſſuming
          London as a <lb/>radix to Britain and Ireland, and the latter to <lb/>Europe. It appears,
          that the <hi rend="italic">annual devaſtation</hi>
          <lb/>from fevers remittent, nervous, and putrid, and <lb/>their ſpecies, in Britain and
          Ireland, is 60,000; <lb/>throughout Europe, 800,000; from ſmall pox <lb/>in Britain and
          Ireland, 38,000; throughout Eu- <lb/>rope, 494,000: meaſles are only one tenth of
          <lb/>ſmall-pox: conſumptions, at leaſt in this iſland, <lb/>are ſtill more deleterious
          than fevers: from <lb/>aſthma and dyſpnea, in Britain and Ireland, up- <lb/>wards of
          10,000; throughout Europe upwards <lb/>of 100,000: apoplexy is inferior by one half to
          <lb/>aſthma: from dropſy, in Britain and Ireland, <lb/>17,000; throughout Europe, 170,000:
          from <lb/>child-bed, in Britain and Ireland, 4000; <lb/>throughout Europe, 50,000: from
          dead births, <lb/>or abortions, at or near maturity, in Britain and <lb/>Ireland, 13,000;
          throughout Europe, 130,000: <pb n="40"/>
          <lb/>aged, in Britain and Ireland, 31,000; through- <lb/>out Europe, 400,000; that is,
          according to our <lb/>preceding Table in the former Chapter of the <lb/>annual mortality
          of Europe, nearly one half of <lb/>thoſe deaths beyond 60 years of age. The an- <lb/>nual
          mortality throughout the univerſe will be <lb/>in the ratio of 6 to 1 beyond Europe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>On the above ſimple principle, a ſort of me- <lb/>dical trigonometry and geometry, a
          groſs eſti- <lb/>mate may be formed of the annual havock <lb/>throughout mankind, by every
          other diſeaſe and <lb/>caſualty, taking the precaution, however, to at- <lb/>tend to the
          ſubſequent criticiſms on the London <lb/>bills, and on diſeaſes in general. From theſe
          <lb/>Tables and Commentaries we are alſo furniſhed <lb/>with a key to the comparative
          mortality of each <lb/>diſeaſe amongſt a community, and its devaſta- <lb/>tion
          numerically. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Another very curious and uſeful corollary may <lb/>be grounded on the above
          hypotheſis; which is, <lb/>from the proportion of deaths, to form a pro- <lb/>bable
          conjecture of the numbers who are an- <lb/>nually ſick, or aſſiſted with different
          diſeaſes <lb/>in a community. Example: if one of every <lb/>ſeven die of the ſmall-pox,
          and the variolous <lb/>deaths throughout Britain and Ireland are rated <lb/>at 38,000
          annually, this number, multiplied by <lb/>ſeven, amounts to 266,000 annually infected
          <lb/>in both Iſlands with variolous contagion. Apply <lb/>the ſame rule to childbed
          mortality; rate the <lb/>annual havock by parturition in the two iſlands <lb/>at 4,000: it
          will hereaſter be ſhewn, that in <lb/>London one of ſeventy-four women die in child-
          <lb/>bed: multiply therefore 4,000 by 74, the pro- <lb/>duct is 296,000, which is not very
          diſtant, al- <pb n="41"/>
          <lb/>though inferior to the total annual procreation <lb/>in both iſlands. And in theſe
          two examples, <lb/>I have ſuggeſted what may be termed an inverſe <lb/>proof of both
          propoſitions. Upon the ſame <lb/>principles a groſs eſtimate may be formed of the
          <lb/>numbers afflicted with dropſy, and with many <lb/>other diſeaſes. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Gentlemen who have not particularly at- <lb/>tended to the ſubject of morbid
          calculations (and <lb/>very few of the medical profeſſion have) will, <lb/>on better
          information, be aſtoniſhed at the fla- <lb/>grant errors daily committed by authors when
          <lb/>treating of these topicks. Out of the many ex- <lb/>amples which might be enumerated,
          I ſhall <lb/>merely ſelect one in proof. Baron Dimſdale, <lb/>in a Treatiſe on
          Inoculation, dedicated to the <lb/>preſent Empreſs of Ruſſia, calculated that, at
          <lb/>leaſt, two million were annually deſtroyed by <lb/>ſmall-pox alone in the Ruſſian
          empire; and it <lb/>was not until after the publication of my Ob- <lb/>ſervations on his
          different Inoculating Eſſays, <lb/>that this error and others were eraſed. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I would requeſt the reader's particular atten- <lb/>tion to another circumſtance:
          which is, that on <lb/>comparing the gradations of mortality in the <lb/>following chart,
          we are not to eſtimate the re- <lb/>lative number, frequency, or proportion of cer-
          <lb/>tain diſeaſes, compared to others by the abſo- <lb/>lute mortality of each. For
          inſtance, Apoplexy <lb/>kills rather more annually in London than mea- <lb/>ſles; but yet
          the latter diſeaſe is infinitely more <lb/>univerſal and diffuſed amongſt the community,
          <lb/>and conſequently leſs dangerous to life: cancer- <lb/>ous and venereal caſes are
          widely different in <lb/>the annual number afflicted with each, although <pb n="42"/>
          <lb/>the deaths are not far diſtant from an equality. <lb/>The ſame obſervation will apply
          to rheumatiſm, <lb/>compared to the dropſy, and to many other di- <lb/>ſeaſes. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>There are between eighty and ninety diſeaſes <lb/>and caſualties enumerated in the
          London bills, <lb/>which, in the ſubſequent comments, I have diſ- <lb/>entangled into
          their ſeparate genera. This will <lb/>operate as a check and correction to the public
          <lb/>regiſters; and by this, their defects and errors <lb/>will be apparent. But
          objections and difficulties <lb/>occur in our reſearches for collateral information
          <lb/>and illuſtration from hoſpital records. The di- <lb/>ſeaſes of hoſpitals are by no
          means a general <lb/>ſtandard of the diſeaſes of the metropolis, and <lb/>much leſs of the
          whole nation. The reaſons <lb/>alſo are glaring, why, in hoſpitals, diſeaſes <lb/>ſhould
          be leſs fatal; and in this reſpect, cities <lb/>ſhould have the advantage of the country.
          We <lb/>cannot therefore apply hoſpital regiſters as a ge- <lb/>neral criterion to a
          nation, neither as to the mea- <lb/>ſurement of diſeaſes, nor of cures. Whenever
          <lb/>authentic and ſyſtematic records of diſeaſes, re- <lb/>covery, and mortality, are
          kept in hoſpitals, do- <lb/>meſtick as well as military, and annually pub- <lb/>liſhed,
          whatever may be alledged reſpecting the <lb/>importance and demerits of ſuch inſtitutions,
          <lb/>the community, at all events, will derive much <lb/>uſeful information. One fourth of
          the annual <lb/>mortality of Paris is in hoſpitals. But in con- <lb/>traſting the ſucceſs
          of medical practice in dif- <lb/>ferent hoſpitals of Europe, criticks have forgot <lb/>to
          aſcertain the diſeaſes which are admitted or <lb/>excluded, and the proportion of the
          former; <lb/>conſequently their inferences are imperfect and <lb/>erroneous. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
