<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Royal Humane Society: Royal Humane Society, Instituted 1774.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">Royal Humane Society, instituted 1774.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T196821</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T196821"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName/>
              </publisher>
              <date>1790</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="2"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="69"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">Bodleian Library, Oxford</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110323560</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Public welfare and institutional"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="2"/>
    <body>
      <pb n="3"/>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">the </hi>
          <lb/>ANNIVERSARY ADDRESS <lb/><hi rend="sc">of the</hi>
          <lb/>ROYAL HUMANE SOCIETY. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc"><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE Philanthropist and the <lb/>Citizen of the
            World</hi>, whoſe <lb/>benevolent feelings are intereſted in the <lb/>welfare and
          preſervation of mankind, and <lb/>whoſe liberality is extended to the ſupport <lb/>of this
          Inſtitution, have, ever ſince its firſt <lb/>foundation, been annually preſented with
          <lb/>one of the ſublimeſt ſpectacles, to the <lb/>enjoyment of which the human heart can
          <lb/>poſſibly expand. This awful ſolemnity <lb/>of humanity—this noble repreſentation of
          <lb/>charity triumphing over death and the <lb/>grave, over misfortune and deſpair, has at
          <lb/>each ſucceeding meeting been attended <lb/>with additional circumſtances of
          exultation <pb n="4"/>
          <lb/>and gratitude, in proportion as the influence <lb/>of the Society has extended, and
          its ſucceſs <lb/>increaſed. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>On the preſent occaſion the <hi rend="sc">Managers</hi>
          <lb/>introduce the uſual triumphs of the day <lb/>with peculiar ſatisfaction; becauſe they
          <lb/>have it in their power to give additional <lb/>intereſt to the ſpectacle, by
          informing this <lb/>benevolent aſſembly of the advancing <lb/>benefits of the <hi
            rend="sc">Humane Society</hi>, and <lb/>the extenſion of its preſerving care to
          <lb/>various ſea-ports, and other parts of the <lb/>kingdom. Nor do its honours terminate
          <lb/>in its own immediate extenſion. This <lb/>original light of reſuſcitating benevolence
          <lb/>has not only penetrated the gloom of <lb/>affliction, by its own cheering beams; the
          <lb/>rays, that have emanated from it, have <lb/>warmed into exiſtence the ſeeds of
          philan- <lb/>thropy, which have burſt forth in various <lb/>parts, and are likely, ere
          long, to overſpread <lb/>the face of the globe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In ſhort, ſeveral inſtitutions upon the <lb/>ſame plan have been formed in different
          <lb/>parts of the kingdom, &amp;c. ſince the laſt <lb/>Anniverſary Feſtival, and are now
          daily <lb/>aſſiſting in the grand deſign of beneficence <pb n="5"/>
          <lb/>and diminiſhing the proportion of human <lb/>miſery, by reſtoring the apparently dead
          <lb/>to life: and not to this theatre alone is <lb/>confined the repreſentation of exalted
          and <lb/>enlightened Humanity, conducting through <lb/>the crowd of feeling ſpectators the
          grateful <lb/>train of emancipated victims, who, but <lb/>for her exertions, had been
          devoted to a <lb/>premature grave on the fallacious appear- <lb/>ances of departed
          animation. </p>
        <floatingText rend="indent italic space">
          <lb/>Exctinctá, quatenus inferre poteſt ſenſus, vitâ <note n="*" place="bottom"
            rend="size(0.75)">
            <p rend="hanging indentall roman">
              <lb/>* Death may uſurp on Nature many hours; <lb/>And yet the fire of life kindle
              again <lb/>The O'er preſt ſpirits. — <hi rend="sc alignright">SHAKSPEARE.</hi>
            </p>
          </note>. </floatingText>
        <p rend="indent space size(0.75)">
          <lb/>The Rev. <hi rend="sc">Vicessimus Knox</hi>, in his <hi rend="sc">Lucubrations</hi>
          on <lb/><hi rend="sc">Life</hi> and <hi rend="sc">Manners</hi>, obſerves, — <q
            rend="diple" type="initial">Many were the <lb/>prejudices formed againſt the Society for
            the recovery <lb/>of drowned perſons; but let any one place himſelf a <lb/>moment in the
            ſituation of a parent ſuddenly bereaved of <lb/>his child, and if he is not unfeeling in
            his nature, he <lb/>will want no argument to induce him to give it every
            <lb/>encouragement. </q> — <q rend="diple">Doubts were once entertained of <lb/>its
            ſucceſs, but they may be now removed by ocular <lb/>demonſtration. </q> — <q
            rend="diple" type="final">It is indeed a moſt affecting ſight <lb/>to behold thoſe who
            were ſnatched from the jaws of <lb/>death walking on the public days in ſolemn
            proceſſion, <lb/>and paying a grateful obedience to their reſtorers. </q>
        </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="6"/>
      <div>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>ANNUAL PUBLICATION. </head>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>1790. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="align-right">TO addreſs the publick </hi>
          <lb/>repeatedly and periodically on ſimilar <lb/>ſubject, muſt be allowed an irkſome and
          <lb/>difficult labour for the individual, to whoſe <lb/>talk it may conſtantly fall.
          Novelty is <lb/>expected from every public character, <lb/>whenever circumſtances may
          oblige him <lb/>to appear before the world. In matters <lb/>of mere entertainment, this
          expectation <lb/>perhaps is juſt and reaſonable. — But in <lb/>what relates to Charitable
          Inſtitutions <lb/>(as the calm exertions of Benevolence, <lb/>eſpecially when directed to
          a particular <lb/>object, muſt be regular and uniform) ſuch <lb/>an expectation cannot
          always be gratified. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But however ſimilar the misfortunes and <lb/>calamities of our fellow-creatures may
          be <lb/>the narratives of their relief, yet humanity <lb/>will ever liſten with the moſt
          refined of <lb/>pleaſures to the unvariegated tale of human <lb/>Beings reſtored to life;
          our various relatives, <lb/>parents, huſbans, wives, and children, <lb/>ſnatched from an
          untimely fate. To <pb n="7"/>
          <lb/>attend to the repetition of ſuch important <lb/>facts, however plainly and
          circumſtantially <lb/>related, is to the man of ſenſibility too <lb/>exalted a pleaſure to
          tire or diſguſt by an <lb/>annual recurrence. The Editor, therefore, <lb/>ſubmits himſelf
          to the candour of the <lb/>humane reader, with a confidence, inſpired <lb/>by the nature
          of his ſubject; conſcious that <lb/>the friends of this inſtitution will not explore
          <lb/>theſe few pages to gratify the deſire of <lb/>literary amuſement, but to trace the
          progreſs <lb/>of thoſe, who have been arduouſly labouring <lb/>for the real happineſs of
          their fellow <lb/>creatures, and to extend the beſt intereſts of <lb/>the community; — who
          have been applying <lb/>remedies to thoſe, who would formerly <lb/>have been deemed
          incurable; who have <lb/>been diſpenſing life to thoſe, whom ignorance <lb/>would
          otherwiſe have conſigned to the <lb/>tomb; who have been reſcuing the victim <lb/>from the
          watery grave; counteracting the <lb/>deſpair of impious ſuicide; defeating the
          <lb/>poiſonous malignity of noxious vapours; <lb/>diſarming the lightning of its deadly
          rage, <lb/>and, in ſhort, vanquiſhing the victor Death, <lb/>and baffling his efforts in a
          variety of <lb/>forms: — For ſuch have been the effects of <pb n="8"/>
          <lb/>the <hi rend="sc">Humane Society</hi>; and ſuch is the <lb/>foundation on which it
          calls upon the <lb/>benevolent and the rational part of mankind <lb/>for encouragement and
          ſupport. — Nor <lb/>can it be ſuppoſed, that the plea of ſuch <lb/>an inſtitution will be
          diſregarded, ſince <lb/>(beſides innumerable recommendations of <lb/>national utility) it
          comes home to the <lb/>ſympathy of every boſom, from the <lb/>conſideration, that its
          preſerving charity <lb/>may well be extended to all ranks and conditions <lb/>of mankind. </p>
        <floatingText rend="space italic">Gratum eſt, quod patriæ civem, populoque reddidiſti. </floatingText>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Bishop of St. David's</hi>, in his <lb/>excellent Anniverſary
          Sermon preached in <lb/>favour of this Inſtitution, obſerves, <q rend="diple">The
            <lb/>good intentions of the Society is proved by <lb/>its conſtitution; the wiſdom and
            public <lb/>utility of the undertaking are proved by <lb/>its ſucceſs. — The good
            intention, the <lb/>wiſdom, and the public utility of the <lb/>Inſtitution, give it no
            ſmall claim upon <lb/>the public for a liberal ſupport. — I muſt <lb/>particularly
            mention, that the benefit of <lb/>this Society is by no means confined to <lb/>the two
            caſes of drowning and ſuſpension. <pb n="9"/>
            <lb/>Its timely ſuccours have rouſed the <lb/>lethargy of opium, have reſcued the
            <lb/>wretched victims of intoxication — <lb/>rekindled the life extinguiſhed by the
            <lb/>ſudden ſtroke of lightning — recovered <lb/>the apoplectick — reſtored life to the
            <lb/>infant that had loſt it in the birth — and <lb/>they have proved efficacious in the
            caſes of <lb/>accidental ſmothering, and of ſuffocation <lb/>by noxious damps: inſomuch
            that no <lb/>ſpecies of death ſeems to be placed <lb/>beyond the reach of this Society's
            <lb/>aſſiſtance, where the miſchief hath gone <lb/>no further than an obſtruction of the
            <lb/>movements of the animal machine, <lb/>without any damage of the organs them-
            <lb/>ſelves. Whether an inſtitution ſo truly <lb/>beneficial to individuals, ſo
            ſerviceable <lb/>to the public, by its ſucceſs in preſerving <lb/>the lives of citizens,
            deſerve not <hi rend="sc">an <lb/>establishment</hi> and <hi rend="sc">patronage</hi>,
            to <lb/>give it the means and the authority to <lb/>proſecute its generous views with
            the <lb/>more advantage; it is for <hi rend="sc">statesmen</hi>
            <lb/>to conſider, who know the public value <lb/>of the life of every citizen in a free
            <lb/>ſtate. — <hi rend="sc">It is for us, till this <pb n="10"/>
              <lb/>public patronage be obtained, to <lb/>supply the want of it, what we <lb/>can, by
              the utmost liberality of <lb/>voluntary contribution. </hi>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>To reſtore animation, is an act that <lb/>ſeems to carry humanity beyond itſelf, and
          <lb/>to approximate to the divinity: as nothing <lb/>can possibly exceed it but creation. </p>
        <floatingText rend="space italic">Ad revocare vitam penè divinitùs fieri videtur. </floatingText>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="align-right">To preſerve the exiſtence of the</hi>
          <lb/>human race, is an obligation incumbent <lb/>upon every individual; and it is pleaſing
          <lb/>to obſerve, that the generality of mankind <lb/>naturally and chearfully engage in
          its per- <lb/>formance. But where the ſafety of others <lb/>can only be procured by
          hazarding our own <lb/>lives, ſelf-preſervation may occaſion even <lb/>the humane to
          deliberate; while the tardy <lb/>and unfeeling willingly lay hold of the <lb/>excuſe for
          their miſanthropy. The ad- <lb/>ditional motive of reward is therefore <lb/>requiſite, to
          ſtimulate the lower claſſes of <lb/>people to exertion in ſuch caſes of imminent
          <lb/>danger: and the <hi rend="sc">Humane Society</hi> has, <lb/>on that account, thought
          it neceſſary to <lb/>make it the intereſt of every one to aſſiſt <pb n="11"/>
          <lb/>in preſerving the lives of their fellow <lb/>creatures. Even if perſons, who
          occaſionally <lb/>give their aid in unfortunate circumſtances, <lb/>arrive too late to
          preſerve, or to reſtore life, <lb/>they are punctually and faithfully rewarded, <lb/>for
          their humane, though unſucceſsful <lb/>labours, by the <hi rend="sc">Managers</hi>
          <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.75)">
            <list>
              <lb/>
              <head rend="sc align-center">
                <lb/>* Managers of the Humane Society. </head>
              <lb/>
              <item rend="align-center">Dr. LETTSOM, F. R. S. and V. P. </item>
              <item rend="align-center">
                <lb/><hi rend="sc">Joseph Thompson</hi>, Eſq. V. P. </item>
              <item rend="align-center">
                <lb/>Rev. Dr. Milne, </item>
              <item rend="align-center">
                <lb/>Rev. J. Pridden, F. A. S. </item>
              <item rend="align-center">
                <lb/>Rev. H. Fly, F. R. S. </item>
              <cb n="1"/>
              <lb/>
              <item>Rev. J. B. Sanders, </item>
              <item>
                <lb/>Dr. Hawes, </item>
              <item>
                <lb/>Dr. Cooper, </item>
              <item>
                <lb/>Mr. H. Amory, </item>
              <item>
                <lb/>Mr. Beaumont, </item>
              <item>
                <lb/>Mr. Dearnes, </item>
              <cb n="2"/>
              <lb/>
              <item>Rev. A. P. Poſton, </item>
              <item>
                <lb/>John Davenport, Eſq. </item>
              <item>
                <lb/>John Dod, Eſq. </item>
              <item>
                <lb/>Mr. Ruſhforth, </item>
              <item>
                <lb/>Mr. Marſh, </item>
              <item>
                <lb/>Mr. Stokes. </item>
              <cb n="1, 2"/>
              <item>
                <lb/>Mr. Deputy Nichols. </item>
            </list>
          </note>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>By promoting communications, and <lb/>medical enquiry among gentlemen of the
          <lb/>faculty, the Society has alſo contributed <lb/>much to the advancement of
          profeſſional <lb/>ingenuity, and has of late years very <lb/>much improved the important
          ſcience of <lb/>reſuſcitation. </p>
        <pb n="12"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Since the commencement of this <lb/>Inſtitution, the <hi rend="sc">Treasurer</hi> has
          paid the <lb/>rewards in TWO THOUSAND and <lb/>FIFTEEN Caſes, viz. <lb/>
          <table>
            <row>
              <cell rend="sc">
                <lb/>Persons restored to life, who <lb/>had been drowned, or otherwise
                <lb/>suffocated. </cell>
              <cell><hi rend="dc(3)">}</hi> 890</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell rend="sc">
                <lb/>Lives preserved by the drags, <lb/>&amp;c. of the society, &amp;c. </cell>
              <cell><hi rend="dc(2)">}</hi> 611</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell rend="sc">
                <lb/>Unsuccessful cases, </cell>
              <cell>514</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell/>
              <cell>2015</cell>
            </row>
          </table>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The lives of more than 1500 perſons <lb/>preſerved and reſtored to ſociety, furniſh
          <lb/>the moſt irrefragable argument of the <lb/>importance and utility of this truly
          Humane <lb/>Inſtitution. — The parent, the child, the <lb/>wife, the relation, and the
          friend, can beſt <lb/>tell by their feelings, the many tranſports, <lb/>which muſt
          therefore have been imparted <lb/>to the boſoms of individuals; and the <lb/>philoſophic
          ſtateſman can readily determine <lb/>how conſiderable an advantage has been <lb/>conferred
          upon the ſtate. Nor do the <lb/>exertions of the <hi rend="sc">Humane Society</hi> ceaſe
          <lb/>when they have arreſted the ſtroke of <pb n="13"/>
          <lb/>death, or baffled the deſigns of meditated <lb/>ſuicide. The attention of this
          Inſtitution is <lb/>applied not only to afford oportunities of <lb/>repentance and of
          peace, but to lead thoſe, <lb/>whom it has preſerved, to the attainment <lb/>of that pious
          ſerenity, which may render <lb/>life truly valuable. — — For this <lb/>purpoſe the <hi
            rend="sc">Managers</hi> put into the hands <lb/>of the <hi rend="sc">restored</hi>,
          approved books of <lb/>piety and devotion <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.75)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* COURT <hi rend="sc">of</hi> DIRECTORS. <lb/>JOSEPH THOMPSON, <hi rend="italic"
                >Eſq. V. P. in the Chair.</hi>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent italic">
              <lb/>Reſolved unanimouſly, </p>
            <p rend="indent italic">
              <lb/>That the Thanks of this Court be preſented to the <lb/>Rev. Dr. FINCH, for his
              generous and friendly preſent of <lb/><hi rend="roman">One Hundred Religious
                Tracts</hi> to the <hi rend="sc">Humane Society</hi>, <lb/>entituled, <q
                rend="diple">An Earneſt Addreſs to Perſons recovered from <lb/>Apparent Death, in
                Caſes of Suſpended Animation: with <lb/>ſome Devotional Aids, adapted to their
                Circumſtances and <lb/>Situation. </q>
              <hi rend="align-center">Signed by Order, </hi>
              <lb/><hi rend="align-right">W. HAWES, Regiſter.</hi>
            </p>
          </note>; to which is now <lb/>added, an important <hi rend="italic">Religious Tract</hi>,
          by <lb/>the Rev. Dr. <hi rend="sc">Finch</hi>, who preached the <lb/>anniverſary Sermon
          for the year 1788. </p>
        <floatingText type="">
          <q rend="sc diple space">To snatch from Death the victim of despair, <lb/>And give the
            means of Penitence and Prayer. </q>
        </floatingText>
        <pb n="14"/>
        <p rend="indent size(0.75)">
          <lb/>In order to render thoſe perſons, who have been <lb/>reſtored to life ſenſible of the
          obligations they owe to the <lb/><hi rend="sc">Supreme Being</hi> for the great mercies
          received, they are <lb/>preſented with a <hi rend="italic">Bible</hi>, a <hi rend="italic"
            >Prayer Book</hi>, and <q rend="quotes italic">The great <lb/>importance of a religious
            life, &amp;c. </q> and it is a circumſtance <lb/>of infinite ſatisfaction to the
          benevolent and pious <lb/>characters who have favoured the <hi rend="italic">Humane
            Society</hi> with <lb/>their countenance and ſupport, that many of thoſe <lb/>reſcued
          from the watery grave, and other kinds of <lb/>premature death, appear, by their courſe of
          life, truly <lb/>ſenſible of the great mercy of Divine Providence. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>A horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="align-center italic">
          <lb/>On the Principle of <hi rend="sc">Vitality</hi> in Man, as de- <lb/>ſcribed in the
            <hi rend="sc">Holy Scriptures</hi>, and the <lb/>difference between <hi rend="sc"
            >true</hi> and <hi rend="sc">apparent</hi>
          <lb/>Death. </head>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>A horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>A SERMON, <lb/>For <hi rend="sc">the Benefit</hi> of the <lb/>ROYAL HUMANE SOCIETY,
            <lb/><hi rend="sc">By SAMUEL, LORD Bishop of St. DAVID's.</hi>
        </head>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>A horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <floatingText type="">
          <q rend="quotes">
            <lb/>Noſtris rebus ſufficiat antiquiſſimos medicos, qui ex <lb/>collatis ſibi invicem
            obſervationibus opinionem omnem <lb/>deducebant, credidiſſe principium quoddam, ab <hi
              rend="italic">elementis</hi>
            <lb/>et <hi rend="italic">materiâ</hi> diverſum animalibus ineſſe; quod eorum
            <lb/>corpora gubernaret atque conſervaret, cujuſque imperio <lb/>et energiæ motus omnes
            animalium eſſent referendi. </q>
          <lb/>
          <hi rend="align-right"><hi rend="sc">Nicholls</hi>, De Animâ Medicâ.</hi>
        </floatingText>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>THE FOURTH EDITION. </head>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>A horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <pb n="15"/>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="sc align-center">The Managers</hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="sc align-center">of the</hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="sc align-center">Royal Humane Society</hi>
          <lb/>have, by their indefatigable exertions, in <lb/>tranſmitting to the moſt diſtant
          parts the <lb/>intereſting information of the vaſt benefits <lb/>derived to ſociety from
          their Inſtitution, <lb/>excited a ſimilar ſpirit of philanthropy; <lb/>which, not
          ſatisfied with having merely <lb/>excited, they have at an immenſe expence <lb/>rendered
          effectual, by ſupplying every <lb/>neceſſary aſſiſtance to the completion of <lb/>their
          great object, the eſtabliſhment of <lb/>inſtitutions correſponding in every reſpect
          <lb/>to their own. This will appear, from the <lb/>annexed liſt of <hi rend="sc">Humane
            Societies</hi> now <lb/>eſtabliſhed and brought to maturity in <lb/>various parts of
          this kingdom, Ireland, <lb/>and the Trans-Atlantic regions. <lb/>
          <list rend="sc size(0.75)">
            <item>Lisbon, </item>
            <item>Gloucester, </item>
            <lb/>
            <cb n="1"/>
            <lb/>
            <item>Aberdeen, </item>
            <item>
              <lb/>Leith, </item>
            <item>
              <lb/>Dublin, </item>
            <item>
              <lb/>Jamaica, </item>
            <item>
              <lb/>Boston, </item>
            <item>
              <lb/>Philadelphia, </item>
            <item>
              <lb/>Worcester, </item>
            <cb n="2"/>
            <item>Shropshire </item>
            <item>
              <lb/>Northamptonshire, </item>
            <item>
              <lb/>Lancaster, </item>
            <item>
              <lb/>Bristol, </item>
            <item>
              <lb/>Whitehaven, </item>
            <item>
              <lb/>Norwich, </item>
            <item>
              <lb/>Kent, </item>
            <cb n="1, 2"/>
            <lb/>
            <item>Newcastle upon Tyne. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>⁂ <hi rend="italic">Apparatuſſes</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Drags</hi>, the <hi
              rend="italic">Reports</hi>, and ſeveral thouſand of the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
              >Plans</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Reſuſcitation</hi> have been preſented to the <hi
              rend="sc">Gentlemen of the <lb/>Faculty</hi> and others at Jamaica, Boſton,
            Philadelphia, Lancaſter, <lb/>Liſbon, &amp;c. in order to form ſimilar Inſtitutions for
            the preſervation of <lb/>the Lives of mankind. </p>
        </note>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>A horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
      </div>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="28"/>
      <pb n="44"/>
      <figure>
        <figDesc>A horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>EXTRAORDINARY CASES. </head>
        <head rend="align-center sc">Suffocation, <hi rend="italic">by Mr.</hi> Williams <hi
            rend="italic">to the</hi> Register. </head>
        <p>
          <lb/>
          <q rend="diple" part="i"><hi rend="dc(2)">M</hi>R. D. Hopkins and myſelf were called to
            <lb/>the Colliery of S. S. Eſq. where a <lb/>dreadful exploſion of the inflammable air
            happened, <lb/>and at the moment killed five of the cutters; <lb/>fourteen men agreed to
            go into the pit to get up the <lb/>remains of their fellow-labourers; but remaining
            <lb/>a long time the agents ſuſpected that they were <lb/>ſuffocated (which was
            unfortunately the caſe): <lb/>ſome more of the Colliers went down, and brought <lb/>up
            the bodies, apparently lifeleſs. </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>
          <q rend="diple" part="m">The plan of the truly <hi rend="sc">Humane Society</hi> was
            <lb/>purſued for an hour, when we diſcovered ſigns of <lb/>returning life in ſeveral of
            our ſuffocated patients, <lb/>and were ſo fortunate as to reſtore <hi rend="italic"
              >Eight of the <lb/>Colliers</hi> to their wives and children. </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>
          <q rend="diple" part="m">Meſſrs. David, John, and Ed. Martin, <hi rend="italic"
              >Agents</hi>, &amp;c. <lb/>rendered us every kind aſſiſtance. The names of <lb/>the
            men reſtored to life by a long perſeverance in the <lb/>means recommended by your
            excellent Inſtitution <lb/>are, <hi rend="italic">T. Sims</hi>, <hi rend="italic">D.
              Jones</hi>, <hi rend="italic">J. Evans</hi>, <hi rend="italic">J. Rees</hi>, <hi
              rend="italic">E. <lb/>Hobſon</hi>, <hi rend="italic">W. Morgan</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
              >W. Roſe</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">James King</hi>. </q>
        </p>
        <signed>
          <q rend="diple quotes" part="f">
            <table>
              <row>
                <cell/>
                <cell><hi rend="sc">Thomas Williams, </hi></cell>
                <cell><hi rend="dc(2)">}</hi> Surgeons. </cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell/>
                <cell><hi rend="sc">David Hopkins, </hi></cell>
                <cell/>
              </row>
            </table>
          </q>
        </signed>
        <note rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>⁂ The General Court of Directors unanimouſly reſolved, that a <lb/>certain ſum
            ſhould be ſent to the men who had brought up the bodies, <lb/>and had likewiſe aſſiſted
            in the recovery of the above eight perſons. <lb/>The reſtoration of ſo many induſtrious
            Colliers to their numerous fami- <lb/>lies are amongst the bleſſed conſequences of the
            Humane Society. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The Honorary Medal was voted to Mr. <hi rend="sc">Williams</hi>, which was
            <lb/>depoſited in the hands of Mr. Gething, one of the caſhiers of the Bank, <lb/>in
            order to be conveyed to that Gentlman at Swanſea. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It may be obſerved on the preſent occaſion, that <hi rend="sc">Medals</hi> have
            been <lb/>frequently ſtruck in honour of thoſe, who have, by fire and ſword, <lb/>laid
            waſte provinces, and depopulated kingdoms; but ſurely ſuch a <lb/>tribute of public
            approbation more properly belongs to the Benefactors <lb/>and Preſervers of the Human
            Race. </p>
        </note>
      </div>
      <pb n="45"/>
      <figure>
        <figDesc>A horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <lb/>
      <floatingText rend="hanging italic">Public Benevolence, by encouraging the art of
        reſuſcitation, <lb/>has ſucceſsfully encountered the perils of overwhelming <lb/>waters,
        peſtilential air, and elementary fire; of which <lb/>laſt circumſtance, the ſubſequent Caſes
        are moſt pleaſing <lb/>and convincing proofs. </floatingText>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="sc">Haynes</hi>, <hi rend="italic">to</hi> Dr. <hi rend="sc"
          >Hawes</hi>. </head>
        <salute rend="indent sc space">
          <lb/>Sir, </salute>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi>S an inſtance of the great neceſſity of the <lb/>Faculty not
          giving up all hopes of reſuſcitation <lb/>on the appearance of death, permit me to ſtate
          the <lb/>ſubſequent caſes. — I was called to a man who had <lb/>ſtruck dead by lightning.
          The electric fire <lb/>firſt fell upon the roof, and was conducted to <lb/>the extremity
          of the tiles, under which he was <lb/>paſſing, by a ſheeting of lead. — The perſon was to
          all <lb/>appearance dead, there being no ſigns of reſpiration or <lb/>circulation. I
          employed the various modes of treatment <lb/>which you had ſo judiciouſly recommended;
          and, <lb/>in about half an hour, feeble ſigns of reſpiration <lb/>became perceptible, and
          he was ſeized with <lb/>convulſions, attended with efforts to vomit; <lb/>upon which I
          ordered an emetic, and the con- <lb/>vulſions gradually declined. In about eight hours
          <lb/>he recovered his ſpeech and in a day or two was <lb/>perfectly reſtored to life and
          health. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I have been called to many caſes of ſudden death, <lb/>without proving ſucceſsful,
          which induced me to at- <lb/>tend your valuable lectures; and I am bound, however, <lb/>in
          juſtice to declare that my trouble has been <hi rend="italic">amply <lb/>compenſated</hi>
          by the improvement and ſatisfaction I <lb/>thereby received. To you, Sir, the world is
          much <lb/>indebted for your valuable reſearches into the art of <lb/>reſtoring ſuſpendid
          animation. <hi rend="sc align-right">Thomas Haynes.</hi>
        </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="46"/>
      <div>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>A horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="sc align-center">
          <lb/>An unfortunate Youth hanged himself. </head>
        <salute rend="indent sc space">
          <lb/>Sir, </salute>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">H</hi>APPY in being inſtrumental in reſtoring a
          <lb/>fellow-creature, and wiſhing to promote your <lb/>laudable inſtitution, I am induced
          to acquaint you <lb/>with the particulars of a youth, who was ſuſpended. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The body had the ſtrongeſt appearances of <lb/>diſſolution, the face, &amp;c. was
          livid, and neither <lb/>reſpiration, pulſation, nor ſenſation, could be per- <lb/>ceived.
          I requeſted only the neceſſary aſſiſtants <lb/>to remain. — The proceſs of re-animation,
          of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Humane Society</hi>, was commenced and vigorouſly
          <lb/>purſued, ſo that by perſeverance in the various <lb/>means for half an hour, the
          breathing became <lb/>perceptible, though laborious and convulſive; a feeble <lb/>pulſe,
          attended with convulſions ſucceeded, which <lb/>continued for three hours. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>My patient now opened his eyes, with the <lb/>ſtrongeſt ſymptoms of delirium. It
          appeared to <lb/>me at this time proper, as the power of deglutition <lb/>had returned, to
          get down ſmall and repeated doſes <lb/>of a volatile cordial medicine; and in about half
          an <lb/>hour a copious diſcharge from the ſtomach enſued, <lb/>which produced temporary
          debility, and a com- <lb/>fortable ſleep for ſix hours; when on waking he <lb/>was
          perfectly recovered. The youth is at this time <lb/>a living monument of the utility of
          the <hi rend="italic">Humane <lb/>Society</hi>. <hi rend="align-right">J. M. CHURCH.</hi>
        </p>
        <note rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>⁂ On the inſtant he had hanged himſelf his feelings were as follow: <lb/>— <q
              rend="diple">When ſtrangling be experienced a ſenſe of ſuffocation, and moſt violent
              <lb/>pain; to this, darkneſs ſucceeded; he then ſeemed to be ſurrounded with a
              <lb/>blaze of fire, and became totally inſenſible; not having the leaſt recollection
              <lb/>of any thing that afterwards occurred, till his life was perfectly reſtored. </q>
          </p>
        </note>
      </div>
      <pb n="47"/>
      <div>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>A horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="sc">Carter</hi>
          <hi rend="italic">of Shrewſbury to the</hi>
          <hi rend="sc">Register</hi>. </head>
        <salute rend="indent sc space">
          <lb/>Sir, </salute>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">W</hi>HEN I got to the place, the man who cut <lb/>the object down,
          ſtated to me that when he cut <lb/>the ſtring, ſhe ſunk about an inch, and was quite
          <lb/>motionleſs; that it was very tight about the neck, <lb/>was made with a running
          nooſe, and nearly covered <lb/>in ſome places by the ſwelling of the parts; that her
          <lb/>tongue projected about an inch, was much ſwelled, and <lb/>of a livid colour, and
          that ſhe was to all appearance <lb/>quite dead — But by a reſolute perſeverance in the
          <lb/>means recommended by the <hi rend="italic">Humane Society</hi>, in about <lb/>4 hours
          ſhe was reſtored to life, with which pleaſing <lb/>event I have now the happineſs to
          acquaint you. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>There were upwards of <hi rend="italic">one hundred ſpectators</hi>
          <lb/>who had the ſatisfaction of ſeeing the proper means <lb/>employed, which fortunately
          reſtored the young wo- <lb/>man alive to her diſconſolate friends. <lb/><hi
            rend="align-right">JOHN CARTER.</hi>
        </p>
        <note place="bottom">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>⁂ Many perſons in a deſponding ſtate have hung <lb/>themſelves, and though, on
            being cut down, the <lb/>appearances of death were ſo ſtrong as to render
            <lb/>by-ſtanders inattentive to their recovery, yet the <lb/><hi rend="sc">Medical
              Assistants</hi>, on being informed of ſuch <lb/>melancholy events, have in the moſt
            benevolent <lb/>manner commenced and ſucceſsfully employed the
              <lb/>m<unclear>eans</unclear> of Reſuſcitation. Such philanthropic exertion <lb/>have
            not only reſtored animation, but alſo a compoſed <lb/>
            <gap reason="illegible"/> ſerene ſtate of mind. </p>
        </note>
      </div>
      <pb n="48"/>
      <div>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>A horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="align-center italic">
          <lb/>An extraordinary recovery from apparent Death, by Intenſe <lb/>Cold, by <hi
            rend="roman">Mr.</hi>
          <hi rend="sc">Sheriff</hi>, <hi rend="roman">M. A.</hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi>N apprentice of Mr. Bowyer's, in a boat from <lb/>Graveſend,
          was overtaken by a violent ſtorm <lb/>accompanied with a fall of ſnow. At Erith the boy
          <lb/>dropped from the bench inſenſible, and on being <lb/>brought to Deptford, the
          by-ſtanders looked upon him <lb/>as irrecoverably loſt, and, in their uſual language, told
          <lb/>his Maſter, <q rend="quotes">he is dead enough. </q> A quarter of an <lb/>hour
          elapſed before Mr. Sheriff could attend. He <lb/>obſerved the countenance diſplayed the
          ſtrongest <lb/>marks of diſſolution. No pulſation or breathing <lb/>could be perceived —
          In addition to the uſual plan <lb/>recommended by the <hi rend="sc">Humane Society</hi>,
          the <lb/>application of ſnow appeared remarkably efficacious — <lb/>At length pulſation,
          &amp;c. returned; and in about two <lb/>hours his life was reſtored. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>After peruſing the above, there is great reaſon <lb/>to hope, that at a future period
          the body of ſome <lb/>traveller (who has miſſed his way in the pathleſs fields of
          <lb/>ſnow, and who has been obliged to ſink under the <lb/>anguiſh of a tortured mind, and
          the ſeverity of the <lb/>ſtorm) may fall in the way of ſome member of the <lb/><hi
            rend="sc">Humane Society</hi>, or friend to Humanity, who <lb/>will not leave it to be
          bleached in the northern <lb/>blaſt; but who, unawed by the ſtrong appearances <lb/>of
          death, will attempt a ſimilar mode of treatment to <lb/>that which, in the preſent
          inſtance, has been at- <lb/>tended with the moſt happy ſucceſs. </p>
        <note rend="size(0.5)" place="bottom">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>⁂ Three Perſons apparently ſtruck dead by the awful and <lb/>tremendous ſtroke of
            Lightning; and their lives reſtored by <hi rend="sc">John Mil- <lb/>ward</hi>, Eſq. Mr.
            Haynes, and Mr. <hi rend="sc">Jackson</hi>; and the above remarkable <lb/>inſtance of
            Life being reſtored by Mr. <hi rend="sc">Sheriff</hi>, demonſtratively prove <lb/>that
            Reſuſcitation is as practicable, as in thoſe of the ſuffocated, the <lb/>ſtrangled, or
            the drowned. </p>
        </note>
      </div>
      <pb n="49"/>
      <div>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>A horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>DROWNING. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="align-right">THE <hi rend="sc">Humane Society</hi> was </hi>
          <lb/>originally eſtabliſhed for the recovery of perſons <lb/>apparently dead by drowning;
          and as accidents of <lb/>this kind, in conſequence of commerce, recreation, <lb/>&amp;c.
          are very frequent, and the ſucceſs of the <hi rend="sc">Medical <lb/>Assistants</hi> is ſo
          well known to the world, by the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Biennial publication of the
            Reports</hi> it appears almoſt <lb/>unneceſſary to trouble the reader with caſes of this
          <lb/>kind; but in order to render our collection uniform, <lb/>the following ſtriking
          inſtances of reanimation are <lb/>briefly related. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/><hi rend="space">ADDRESSED </hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="sc space">to</hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="space">Dr. <hi rend="sc">Lettsom</hi>, V. P. and Treaſurer. </hi>
        </head>
        <salute rend="indent sc space">
          <lb/>Sir, </salute>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Mr. James Smith, his ſon, and W. Dudley croſ- <lb/>ſing the river, and attempting to
          reach at ſomething <lb/>which floated, by too great exertion capſized the <lb/>wherry, and
          were in the water more than ten minutes; <lb/>when ſome people in a boat, who ſaw the
          accident at <lb/>a conſiderable diſtance, came to their aid, and took <lb/>them up to all
          appearance dead: their bodies were <lb/>brought on ſhore, and lay a long time on the
          <lb/>Pier-Head without any aſſiſtance, from the ſuppoſition <lb/>that the three perſons
          were totally deprived of life. <lb/>From the time of the accident, till my attendance, <pb
            n="50"/>
          <lb/>was three quarters of an hour; when I had them <lb/>conveyed to the Three Tuns,
          employed the uſual <lb/>modes of treatment, and in an hour had the happineſs <lb/>to
          reſtore Dudley and the Son; but it was one hour <lb/>and three quarters before I could
          perceive any <lb/>ſymptoms of returning life in Mr. Smith, which <lb/>commenced with
          ſpaſms about the face, followed <lb/>by ſtrong convulſions, deep groans, and laborious
          <lb/>reſpiration. — He continued in this ſtate about two <lb/>hours. — I found it
          neceſſary to take away ſome blood, <lb/>as he is a man of plethoric habit, and had been
          much <lb/>bruiſed, by being thrown about on ſuppoſition of his <lb/>being dead; but at
          this time I have the happineſs to <lb/>ſay is perfectly reſtored to life and health,
            <lb/><hi rend="align-center">I am, </hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="align-center">Sir, </hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="align-center">Your moſt humble ſervant,</hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="italic align-left">Sheerneſs, Jan. 25.</hi>
          <hi rend="align-right">W. LAWRENCE.</hi>
        </p>
        <note place="bottom">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>⁂ The <hi rend="sc">Honorary Medal</hi>
            <lb/>being unanimouſly voted to Mr. <hi rend="sc">Lawrence</hi>, it was <lb/>agreed by
            the <hi rend="sc">General Court</hi> of Directors, that <lb/>it ſhould be conferred in
            the moſt reſpectful manner; <lb/>and therefore <hi rend="sc">Lord Stamford</hi>, our
            valuable and <lb/>amiable Preſident, with that condeſcenſion for which <lb/>he is
            eminently diſtinguiſhed, preſented the Medal <lb/>to the above Gentleman at the London
            Tavern, in <lb/>the preſence of more than <hi rend="italic">three hundred benevolent
              <lb/>characters</hi> aſſembled at the <hi rend="italic">Anniverſary Feſtival</hi> of
            the <lb/>Humane Society, who teſtified, by loud and repeated <lb/>plaudits, their
            cordial approbation. </p>
        </note>
      </div>
      <pb n="51"/>
      <div>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>A horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="align-center italic space">
          <lb/><hi rend="roman">Dr.</hi>
          <hi rend="sc">Squires</hi>, to the <hi rend="sc">Register <lb/>of the <lb/>Humane
            Society</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi> AM exceeding happy in the opportunity of <lb/>tranſmitting a
          caſe, which muſt afford you great <lb/>pleaſure; and, at the ſame time, evince to the
          public, <lb/>of what extenſive utility the Society's plan is capable, <lb/>for ſure I am,
          in various caſes of apparent death, <lb/>many lives might have been preſerved (which have
          <lb/>been given up as loſt) if proper methods had been <lb/>uſed. — The following relation
          and ſucceſs proves <lb/>demonſtratively the importance of your judicious <lb/>plan of
          Reſuſcitation. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center sc space">
          <lb/>The Case. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>A young woman, in a fit of deſpair, attempted to <lb/>deſtroy herſelf by hanging, in
          which ſtate ſhe was <lb/>diſcovered and cut down, in a quarter of an hour from <lb/>the
          time it was ſuppoſed ſhe had been ſuſpended. <lb/>A meſſenger was dispatched to my houſe,
          a mile <lb/>diſtant from the ſcene of action. On entering the <lb/>houſe ſeveral women
          appeared much terrified and <lb/>alarmed; ſaid that the poor girl was certainly dead,
          <lb/>and they were unwilling to remain with her. She <lb/>had no beating of the heart, no
          pulſation, her <lb/>reſpiration likewiſe totatlly ceaſed, her face ſwoln and <lb/>livid. I
          ordered the body to be put down between warm <lb/>blankets, frictions to be employed, and
          blowing <lb/>ſtrongly into the lungs, by applying a mouth to that <lb/>of the unfortunate
          woman; which operation I could <pb n="52"/>
          <lb/>with difficulty perſuade any of them to undertake, <lb/>till the idea of the medium
          of an handkerchief was <lb/>ſuggeſted, on which one of the women applied with <lb/>great
          earneſtneſs to the buſineſs; a warming-pan, <lb/>heated, was rubbed over the back for ſome
          time; <lb/>the feet and legs were immerſed in warm water, <lb/>volatiles to the noſe and
          temples were likewiſe applied. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>By perſiſting in the uſe of theſe various means <lb/>for twenty minutes, ſigns of
          returning life appeared, <lb/>ſuch as ſighing and ſmall twitchings; convulſive
          <lb/>motions followed, with the action of the heart, and <lb/>a return of the natural
          colour and warmth. It <lb/>was then judged proper to take away blood, to <lb/>prevent the
          effects of preſſure on the brain, which <lb/>might happen from a ſurcharge of blood forced
          <lb/>into the veſſels by her unhappy attempt to deſtroy <lb/>herſelf.— From that time ſhe
          gradually recovered, and <lb/>I this day took leave of her, perfectly reſtored in
          <lb/>body and mind, and ſincerely penitent. — This caſe <lb/>demonſtrates the good effects
          of <hi rend="sc">Perseverance</hi>
          <lb/>in the methods. — <hi rend="italic">Lateat Scintilsull Forſan</hi> ſhould be
          <lb/>ever preſent to the mind when we are called for <lb/>under theſe unhappy
          circumſtances. That conſideration <lb/>will animate us in the moſt deſperate caſes of ſuſ-
          <lb/>pended animation. — ln the preſent caſe, the aſſiſtants <lb/>and bye-ſtanders were ſo
          aſtoniſhed, that they conſidered <lb/>the matter more like a reſurrection than a
          recovery." </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I truſt, Sir, you will excuſe the prolixity of <lb/>this narrative, knowing that
          communications of ſuch <lb/>inſtances of ſucceſs may prove highly beneficial to the
          <lb/>public, by exciting others, on ſimilar occaſions, to <lb/>uſe their utmoſt efforts,
          to ſave the lives of their fel- <lb/>low-creatures. <hi rend="align-right">J.
            SQUIRES.</hi>
        </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="53"/>
      <div>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>A horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc space">on the </hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="space"><hi rend="sc space">Absurdity of an Opinion</hi>,</hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="space">
            <q rend="diple space">THAT DEAD BODIES ARE NOT TO <lb/>BE REMOVED UNTIL THE CORONER
              <lb/>HAS HELD AN INQUEST ON THEM. </q></hi>
        </head>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>CASE. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Royal Humane Society</hi> for the recovery <lb/>of perſons from
          apparent death, among many laudable <lb/>exertions for the reſtoration of life, have
          publiſhed <lb/>their ſucceſsful modes of practice, which have been <lb/>preſented <hi
            rend="italic">gratis</hi> to the publick for ſeveral years. But <lb/>their benevolent
          views have, in ſome inſtances, been <lb/>fruſtrated, from an idea that it is contrary to
          law to <lb/>meddle with dead bodies until the Coroner's Jury <lb/>have taken an
          Inquiſition; by which delay <hi rend="italic">frequent <lb/>inſtances</hi> have occurred
          wherein lives, otherwiſe re- <lb/>deemable, have been totally loſt. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="sc align-center space">
          <lb/>Question. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Are there any and what ſtatutes, or other laws, <lb/>now in exiſtence, in any manner
          prohibiting perſons, <lb/>other than the Coroner and his Jury, from inter- <lb/>meddling
          with human bodies dead, or apparently <lb/>dead, from drowning, ſuffocating, ſtrangling,
          &amp;c. </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="54"/>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center sc space">
          <lb/>Answer. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>
          <q rend="quotes space">It is a miſdemeanor by the common law, and an <lb/>indictable
            offence, to prevent the Coroner from doing <lb/>his duty, or to obſtruct him in the
            execution of it. <lb/>But the meddling with a body apparently dead, for <lb/>the purpoſe
            of preſerving life, is not a tranſgreſſion <lb/>of the law in either of theſe reſpects;
            nor do I know <lb/>any ſtatute by which ſuch an act is prohibited. In <lb/>ſuch caſes
            the Coroner ought certainly to be called <lb/>in as ſoon as it is evident that the body
            is dead. If <lb/>this precaution be taken, it is not probable that the <lb/>removing of
            a dead body from the place where it is <lb/>found, for the benevolent purpoſe
            above-mentioned, <lb/>ſhould ever be made the ſubject of a criminal <lb/>proſecution;
            but if it ſhould be, the party would <lb/>undoubtedly be acquitted, upon proving that
            his <lb/>interpoſition was with the deſign of preſerving life, <lb/>and that the Coroner
            had an opportunity of taking <lb/>an inqueſt on the body as ſoon as that interpoſition
            <lb/>appeared to be in vain. </q>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>REWARD </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>To Publicans and others, who have been <lb/>deterred from receiving bodies apparently
          dead into <lb/>their houſes, under an apprehenſion of being liable <lb/>to penalties and
          expences, are informed that they <lb/>will be indemnified by the HUMANE SOCIETY, <lb/>and
          from the charges of burial in unſucceſsful caſes <lb/><hi rend="align-right">W. HAWES,
            Regiſter.</hi>
        </p>
        <pb n="55"/>
        <p rend="hanging sc">
          <lb/>The Manager, Governors, and the Public <lb/>are under particular Obligations to the
          <lb/>Medical Assistants, who, upon all Occa- <lb/>sions, attend drowned or otherwise suf-
          <lb/>focated persons, without Fee or Reward; <lb/>and, in so doing, afford the strongest
          <lb/>proofs of their professional Zeal for the <lb/>preservation of the lives of mankind. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The Biſhop of St. David's obſerves in his Anni- <lb/>verſary Sermon, <q rend="diple"
            >that the Medical Pr<unclear>a</unclear>ctioners ac- <lb/>cept no pecuniary recompence
            for the time which <lb/>they devote to a difficult and tedious proceſs; for <lb/>the
            mortification which they too often undergo, <lb/>when death, in ſpite of their efforts,
            at laſt carries <lb/>off his prey. Their ſole reward is in the holy joy <lb/>of doing
            good. Of an inſtitution thus free in its <lb/>plan, renouncing ſelf-intereſt in every
            ſhape, <lb/>Philanthropy muſt be the only baſis. The good <lb/>intention therefore of
            the Society is proved by its <lb/>Conſtitution; the Wiſdom and Public Utility of
            <lb/>the Undertaking are proved by its Succeſs. </q>
        </p>
        <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="5"/>
      </div>
      <pb n="61"/>
      <div>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>A horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="align-center sc space">
          <lb/><hi rend="roman">ROYAL HUMANE SOCIETY,</hi>
          <lb/>for the recovery of drowned persons; <lb/>also in the various other cases of sudden
          <lb/>or apparent death, <lb/>viz. apoplectic and convulsive fits, <lb/>suffocation by
          damps, or noxious vapours <lb/>proceeding from coal mines, <lb/>the confined air of wells,
          cisterns, caverns, <lb/>the must of fermenting liquors, <lb/>intoxication, hanging,
          intense cold; <lb/>and of those by the tremendous stroke of <lb/>lightning. </head>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>A horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="align-center sc space">
          <lb/>directions for the recovery of the <lb/>apparently dead. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>I. The <hi rend="sc">restoration</hi> of <hi rend="sc">heat</hi> is of the greateſt
          <lb/>conſequence for the return of <hi rend="sc">life</hi>: when, therefore, <lb/>the body
          is taken out of the water, the cloaths ſhould <lb/>be ſtripped off; or, if naked at the
          time of the <lb/>accident, it muſt be covered with two or three coats, <lb/>or a blanket.
          The body ſhould then be carefully <lb/>conveyed to the neareſt houſe, with the head a
          little <lb/>raiſed. In <hi rend="italic">cold</hi> and <hi rend="italic">damp</hi> weather
          the perſon ſhould <lb/>be laid on a bed, &amp;c. in a room that is moderately <lb/>heated:
          — In <hi rend="italic">ſummer</hi>, on a bed expoſed to the rays of <lb/>the ſun, and not
          more than ſix perſons admitted, as <lb/>a greater number may retard the return of life.
          The <pb n="62"/>
          <lb/>body is to be well <hi rend="italic">dried</hi> with warm cloaths, and gently
          <lb/>rubbed with flannels, ſprinkled with rum, brandy, <lb/>gin, or muſtard. — <hi
            rend="sc">Fomentations</hi> of ſpirits may <lb/>be applied to the pit of the ſtomach
          with advantage. <lb/>— A warming-pan covered with flannel ſhould be <lb/>lightly moved up
          and down the back; bladders, or <lb/>bottles filled with hot water, heated bricks, or
          tiles <lb/>wrapped up in flannel, ſhould be applied to the ſoles <lb/>of the feet, palms
          of the hands, and other parts of <lb/>the body. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>II. <hi rend="sc">Respiration</hi> will be promoted, by cloſing <lb/>the mouth and
          one noſtril, while, with the pipe of a <lb/>bellows, you blow into the other with
          ſufficient force <lb/>to inflate the lungs; another perſon ſhould then preſs <lb/>the
          cheſt gently with his hands, ſo as to expel the air. <lb/>If the pipe be too large for the
          noſtrils, the air may <lb/>be blown in at the mouth. Blowing the breath can <lb/>only be
          recommended when bellows cannot be <lb/>procured. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>III. The <hi rend="sc">bowels</hi> ſhould be inflated with the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >fumes</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Tobacco</hi>, and repeated three or four times
          <lb/>within the firſt hour; but, if circumſtances prevent <lb/>the uſe of this vapour,
          then <hi rend="sc">clysters</hi> of this herb, <lb/>or other <hi rend="italic">acrid
            infuſions with ſalt</hi>, may be thrown up <lb/>with advantage. — The <hi rend="sc"
            >fumigating machine</hi>
          <lb/>is ſo much improved as to be of the higheſt impor- <lb/>tance to the Public; and if
          employed in every inſtance <lb/>of apparent death, it would reſtore the lives of many
          <lb/>of our fellow creatures, as it now anſwers the <lb/>important purpoſs of <hi
            rend="italic">fumigation</hi>, <hi rend="italic">inſpiration</hi>, and <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">expiration</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>IV. <hi rend="sc">Agitation</hi> has proved a powerful auxiliary <lb/>to the other
          means of recovery; one or more of the <pb n="63"/>
          <lb/>Aſſiſtants ſhould therefore, take hold of the legs and <lb/>arms, particularly of
          boys, and ſhake their bodies <lb/>for five or ſix minutes; this may be repeated ſeveral
          <lb/>times within the firſt hour. When the body is wiped <lb/>perfectly dry, it ſhould be
          placed in bed between two <lb/>healthy perſons, and the friction chiefly directed, in
          <lb/>this caſe, to the left ſide, where it will be moſt likely <lb/>to excite the motion
          of the heart. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>V. When theſe Methods have been employed for <lb/>an hour, if any brewhouſe,
          bakehouſe, or glaſshouſe <lb/>be near, where <hi rend="italic">warm grains</hi>, <hi
            rend="italic">aſhes</hi>, <hi rend="italic">lees</hi>, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
          can be <lb/>procured, the body ſhould be placed in any of theſe, <lb/>moderated to a
          degree of heat very little exceeding <lb/>that of the perſon in health. If the warm bath
          can <lb/>be conveniently obtained, it may be advantageouſly <lb/>uſed in conjunction with
          the earlieſt modes of <lb/>treatment. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>VI. <hi rend="sc">Electricity</hi> ſhould be early employed, as <lb/>it will increaſe
          the beneficial effects of the other <lb/>means of recovery on the ſyſtem. <q rend="diple"
            type="initial">The <hi rend="sc">electrical <lb/>shock</hi>, </q> ſays Mr. <hi rend="sc"
            >Kite</hi> in his <hi rend="italic">Eſſay</hi> on the <hi rend="italic">Recovery</hi>
          <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">apparently dead</hi>, <q rend="diple" type="final">is to be
            admitted as the teſt <lb/>or diſcriminating characteriſtic of any remains of <lb/>animal
            life; and ſo long as that produces <hi rend="italic">contractions</hi>, <lb/>may the
            perſon be ſaid to be in a <hi rend="italic">recoverable</hi> ſtate; <lb/>but when that
            effect has ceaſed, there can no doubt <lb/>remain of the party being abſolutely and
            poſitively <lb/>dead. </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>VII. If convulſions, or other ſigns of returning <lb/>life appear, a tea ſpoonful or
          two of warm water may <lb/>be put into the mouth; and if the power of ſwallowing <lb/>be
          returned, a little warm wine or brandy and water <lb/>may be given. When this gradual
          approach towards <pb n="64"/>
          <lb/>recovery is obſerved, and breathing returned, let the <lb/>perſon be put into a warm
          bed, and if diſpoſed to <lb/>ſleep, as is generally the caſe, give no diſturbance,
          <lb/>and he will awake, almoſt perfectly recovered. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The above methods are to be uſed with vigor for <lb/>3 or 4 hours, for it is a vulgar
          and dangerous opinion <lb/>to ſuppoſe that perſons are irrecoverable, becauſe life
          <lb/>does not make its appearance; an opinion that <lb/>has conſigned an immenſe number to
          the grave, who <lb/>might have been <hi rend="sc">restored to life</hi> by <hi
            rend="italic">reſolution</hi>
          <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">preſerverance</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Bleeding should never be employed in <lb/>such cases, unless by the
            direction of one <lb/>of the medical assistants, or some other <lb/>respectable
            gentleman of the faculty, <lb/>who has paid attention to the subject of <lb/>suspended
            animation</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>On the firſt alarm of any perſon being drowned, <lb/>let <hi rend="italic">hot
            water</hi>, <hi rend="italic">flour of muſtard</hi>, <hi rend="italic">warm
            blankets</hi>, <hi rend="italic">hot flannels</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">flat bottled
            filled with hot water</hi>, <hi rend="italic">a heated warming-pan</hi>, <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">bellows</hi>, <hi rend="italic">brandy</hi>, <hi rend="italic">hartſhorn
            drops</hi>, and an <hi rend="italic">electrifying <lb/>machine</hi>, be procured. Theſe
          articles being immedi- <lb/>ately employed, may be productive of reſtoring many
          <lb/>uſeful and valuable lives. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The common people will often reſtore life by <lb/>purſuing the plans now recommended;
          but if <lb/><hi rend="sc">gentleman of the faculty</hi> can be obtained, <lb/>their
          aſſiſtance ſhould be immediately requeſted; as <lb/>their ſkill will lead them judiciouſly
          to vary the <lb/>methods of treatment; and, in a variety of accidents, <lb/>many more
          lives will be reſtored to the community <lb/>and to their families. </p>
        <pb n="65"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The above means of reſtoration have proved <lb/>efficacious in <hi rend="sc">Apparent
            sudden death</hi>, by <lb/><hi rend="italic">convulſions</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
            >intoxications</hi>, <hi rend="italic">hanging</hi>, <hi rend="italic">intenſe
          cold</hi>, and the <lb/><hi rend="italic">tremendous ſtroke of lightning</hi>. — — When
          perſons are <lb/><hi rend="sc">frost bitten</hi> they ſhould be rubbed with <hi
            rend="italic">ſnow</hi>, <lb/>previous to their being brought into a warm room, <lb/>In
            <hi rend="sc">suffocation</hi>, occaſioned by the <hi rend="italic">fumes</hi> of <hi
            rend="italic">ſulphur</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">charcoal</hi>, &amp;c. daſhing the
          face and breaſt with <hi rend="italic">cold <lb/>water</hi> has been known to reſtore
          life. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">In order to excite an earnest attention <lb/>to the apparently
            dead</hi>, it may be proper to <lb/>obſerve that ſince the eſtabliſhment of the <hi
            rend="sc">Humane <lb/>society, more than two thirds</hi> of thoſe, who <lb/>a few years
          ago would have been interred as <hi rend="italic">inanimate <lb/>corſes</hi>, are now
          reſtored to their joyful relations and <lb/>friends! Among theſe many were <hi
            rend="italic">induſtrious heads of <lb/>numerous families</hi>, who would have become a
          parochial <lb/>charge, had not their valuable lives been thus <lb/>preſerved! Many were
            <hi rend="italic">heedleſs infants</hi>, wandering <lb/>from their parents, who, but for
          this inſtitution, <lb/>would never have returned! Others were <hi rend="italic"
            >Suicides</hi>, <lb/>ruſhing into eternity in a ſtate of mind the moſt unfit <lb/>to
          appear before the tribunal of their Judge! </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="66"/>
      <div>
        <head rend="sc align-center space">REFLECTIONS <lb/>on <lb/>APPARENT DEATH <lb/>and the
          <lb/>RETURN of LIFE. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Rev. Dr. <hi rend="sc">Franklin</hi> in his <lb/><hi rend="sc">Anniversary
            Sermon</hi> for this Society, has expreſſed <lb/>himſelf on this intereſting ſubject as
          followers: </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>
          <q rend="diple quotes">Suppoſe yourſelves in an evening walk of rural <lb/>retirement, on
            the borders of a delightful ſtream, <lb/>imagine your contemplations interrupted by a
            ſtrange <lb/>and uncommon appearance. </q>— <q rend="diple" part="i">At a little
            diſtance <lb/>behold a buſy, buſtling croud of induſtrious labourers <lb/>encircling the
            body of their hapleſs companion, <lb/>whom they have taken out of the neighbouring
            river, <lb/>and dragged to the ſhore without life or motion, his <lb/>eyes cloſed and
            ſunk, his face pale and livid, his <lb/>limbs torpid and motionleſs; without the leaſt
            ſigns <lb/>life they convey him in hopeleſs deſpondency to <lb/>his own home. </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>
          <q rend="diple quotes" part="f">One of the <hi rend="sc">Medical Assistans</hi> of this
            <lb/>Inſtitution hears of the event, he flies like the good <lb/>Samaritan to the
            chamber of ſorrow, he ſtops the <lb/>retreating multitude, calls on the moſt vigorous
            and <lb/>active amongſt them to aſſiſt him, applies with zeal <lb/>and alacrity thoſe
            means of Reſuſcitation which <lb/>reaſon and ſucceſs dictate as the moſt proper to
            <lb/>animate, if poſſible, the lifeleſs maſs, and purſues them <lb/>with ceaſeleſs toil
            and unwearied aſſiduity. </q>— <q rend="diple quotes">Death <lb/>ſeems to ſmile at the
            ineffectual labour and ſkill, till <lb/>at length, ſubdued by fortitude and
            perſeverance, he <lb/>gives up the conteſt. </q>— <q rend="diple quotes">A ray of hope
            breaks in <lb/>upon the gloom, and lights up every countenance. </q>
          <lb/>— <q rend="quotes">Behold! again he <hi rend="sc">Moves, Breathes, Lives.</hi>
          </q>
          <lb/>— <q rend="diple quotes">What follows is not within the power of <lb/>language to
            deſcribe; imagination alone can ſuggeſt <lb/>to you the delightful ſcene of wonder and
            <lb/>aſtoniſhment, of mutual joy, tranſport and felicity. </q>
        </p>
        <pb n="67"/>
        <p rend="hanging space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Art. x.</hi> Cologne. <hi rend="italic">Nouvelle Découverse d'une
            Méthode <lb/>pen couteuſe, efficace, &amp; aſſurée de traiter tous les <lb/>Hommes
            décédés, &amp;c.</hi> New Diſcovery of a cheap, <lb/>efficacious, and approved Method of
          treating Men <lb/>at their Deceaſe, in order to reſtore to Life thoſe <lb/>who are only
          apparently dead. By J. G. C. A. <lb/>Baron de Hupſch, Member of ſeveral Academies,
          <lb/>&amp;c. 1789. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Some years ago, baron de H. recommended <lb/>electrifying all perſons ſuppoſed to be
          dead; and the <lb/>ſucceſsful trial of the experiment on a lady of <lb/>diſtinction, laſt
          year, has induced him to publiſh <lb/>this pamphlet, in French and German, in which are
          <lb/>given ample directions for its application. <lb/><hi rend="align-right">Annalytical
            Review for Dec. 1789. p. 502.</hi>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>A horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>The Electric Shock, a Teſt of remaining Life. <lb/>Reports of the Humane Society,
            <lb/><hi rend="roman">1787, 1788, and 1789</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Baron de Hupsch</hi> has diſcovered, that a <lb/>human body,
          apparently dead, may be reſuſcitated by <lb/>being electrified. The idea is ſo ſimple, and
          ſo eaſily <lb/>put in practice, that it would be waſting words to <lb/>paint the merit of
          the diſcovery or to recommend it <lb/>to general employment. I haſten merely to throw
          <lb/>out the notice, and recommend it to the faculty to <lb/>make experiments. I recommend
          it to the humane <lb/>to ſpread the notice; I recommend it to ſelf-love to <lb/>guard
          itſelf with ſuch a buckler againſt the moſt <lb/>dreadful of all deaths, a falſely
          ſuppoſed one. The <lb/>clergy, no doubt, will concur in eſtabliſhing the uſe <lb/>of ſo
          important a preſervative; and no ſuppoſed <lb/>corpſe ought to be interred without an
          atteſtation of <lb/>its having been electrified, eſpecially if the reputed <lb/>death was
          ſudden. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center sc space">
          <lb/>Reports <hi rend="italic">of the</hi> Humane Society <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Tranſlated into the</hi>
          <lb/>Portuguese Language. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>While the greater part of the inhabitants of the <lb/>Continent are attracting the
          attention of the reſt <lb/>of Europe by their inteſtine troubles and civil
          <lb/>commotions, the Editor of this publication is happy <lb/>to ſee Great Britain
          diſtinguiſhed among her <lb/>neighbours by their attempts to imitate her in the <lb/>arts
          of induſtry or humanity. Among the latter may <lb/>be claſſed a Portugueſe tranſtation,
          which he has <lb/>recently ſeen, of the <q rend="quotes">Reports of the Humane
            <lb/>Society. </q> The title is, <q rend="diple">
            <q rend="quotes italic">Aviſos Interiſſantes a <lb/>Humanidade ou Colleccao Dealguns
              arrigos conceruantes <lb/>a reſtauracao da vida dos aſſigados, eutros de morte
              <lb/>apparante ou nimacao ſuſpenſad, extratudos dos <lb/>Eſcriptos publicadotum
              Engleterre por ordemdu Sociedade <lb/>Humma. </q> Edudoſa luz na lingua Portugueze par
            <lb/>diligendare a cuſta de Carlos Murray, Conſul Geral <lb/>de S. Mageſtade Beitannica
            na Ilha da Madeira. </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Translator</hi> has annexed to the <hi rend="sc">Reports</hi>,
          <lb/>the modes of treatment for the recovery of the <lb/>apparently dead; together with
          the ſentiments of <lb/><hi rend="sc">Dr. Hawes on sudden death</hi>, as well as an
          <lb/>account of <hi rend="italic">thoſe diſeaſes</hi> in which a. ſuſpenſion of <lb/>the
          vital faculties may take place; and has alſo <lb/>tranſlated the Anniverſary Sermons
          preached by <lb/>the Rev. Servington Savery, 1785, and the Rev. <lb/>Sethe Thompſon, 1787. </p>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>A horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
      </div>
      <pb n="69"/>
      <div>
        <head rend="space">
          <lb/>SUBSCRIPTIONS AND BENEFACTIONS. </head>
        <head rend="space italic align-center">
          <lb/>For carrying on this national and benevolent Deſign, are <lb/>received by the
          following Bankers, <hi rend="roman">&amp;c.</hi>
        </head>
        <list rend="align-center">
          <lb/>
          <item>The Hon. Baron <hi rend="sc">Dimsdale, Sons</hi>, and <hi rend="sc">Barnard</hi>.
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Langtons</hi>, <hi rend="sc">Towgoods</hi>, and <hi rend="sc"
              >Amory</hi>. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="sc">Down</hi>, <hi rend="sc">Thornton</hi>, and <hi rend="sc">Free</hi>. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="sc">Drummonds</hi> and Co. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item>Rev. <hi rend="sc">Russell Scott</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Porſmouth</hi>. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="sc">B. C. Collins</hi>, Eſq. <hi rend="italic">Saliſbury.</hi>
          </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="sc">R. Thompson</hi>, Eſq. <hi rend="italic">Rocheſter.</hi>
          </item>
          <lb/>
          <item>Dr. <hi rend="sc">Lettsom</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Sambrook-houſe.</hi>
          </item>
          <lb/>
          <item>Dr. <hi rend="sc">Hawes</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Bury-ſtreet</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
              >St. Mary-Axe.</hi>
          </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="sc">and the</hi>
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">London Coffee-houſe.</hi>
          </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="space">TEN GUINEAS <lb/>Conſtitute a <hi rend="italic">Director</hi> for
              Life; and </hi>
            <lb/><hi rend="space">ONE GUINEA <lb/>Per Annum, an <hi rend="italic">Annual
                Director</hi>. </hi>
          </item>
        </list>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>A picture of a crown. </figDesc>
        </figure>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
