<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Stanger: A justification of the right of every well educated
          physician</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Christopher Stanger</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">A justification of the right of every well educated physician of fair
              character and mature age, residing within the jurisdiction of the College of
              Physicians of London, to be admitted a fellow of that corporation, if found competent,
              upon examination, in learning and skill. Together with an account of the proceedings
              of those licentiates who lately attempted to establish that right; including the
              pleadings of the counsel, and the opinions of the judges, as taken in short-hand by
              Mr. Gurney. </title>
            <edition n=""/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T140650</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T140650"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed by C. Whittingham, for J. Johnson, St. Paul's Church Yard;
                  and J. Butterworth, Fleet Street, 1798.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1798</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="10"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="499"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW107830266</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Public welfare and institutional"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="10"/>
    <body>
      <head rend="sc size(0.5) align-center space">
        <lb/>A <lb/><hi rend="size(2.0)">JUSTIFICATION </hi>
        <lb/>of the <lb/><hi rend="italic size(2.0)">RIGHTS OF THE LICENTIATES, </hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
      </head>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>A short horizontal double-line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> CORPORATE monopoly in a liberal and <lb/>ſcientific profeſſion,
        which depreciates the <lb/>great body of that profeſſion, without the ſlighteſt
        <lb/>evidence of their inferiority or diſqualification, <lb/>would ſcarcely be ſuppoſed to
        exiſt at the cloſe of <lb/>the eighteenth century, in the enlightened metro- <lb/>polis of
        Great Britain. But, extraordinary and diſ- <lb/>graceful as it is, a great majority of the
        phyſicians <lb/>of London, equal in talents, education, acquire- <lb/>ments, ſkill, and
        conduct, to any body of the <lb/>faculty in Europe, are only tolerated and licenſed <lb/>to
        practiſe under the authority and controul of a <lb/>narrow corporation. The College of
        Phyſicians, <lb/>originally founded for the moſt beneficent and <lb/>liberal purpoſes, for
        the ſecurity of the public, <lb/>and the advantage of the faculty of phyſic, by
        <lb/>reſtraining illiterate and unprincipled practitioners, <pb n="2"/>
        <lb/>and by diſtinguiſhing and rewarding ſkilful and <lb/>upright phyſicians, is now in the
        poſſeſſion of an <lb/>inconſiderable and intereſted party. A few in- <lb/>dividuals,
        entitled fellows, who have graduated in <lb/>Oxford and Cambridge, where their profeſſion
        <lb/>cannot be learned, have aſſumed the right of con- <lb/>fining admiſſion to their own
        claſs, or of extending <lb/>it arbitrarily to ſuch of the faculty only, who have
        <lb/>obtained their degrees elſewhere, as intereſt or <lb/>partiality may induce them. The
        great body of <lb/>phyſicians of London, though poſſeſſed of every <lb/>claim, which
        ability, acquirements, and character <lb/>can give, who have ſtudied and graduated in the
        <lb/>beſt medical univerſities in Europe, are excluded <lb/>and degraded under the
        appellation of licentiates. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>It is the object of this treatiſe to prove, that every <lb/>well educated phyſician, of
        unimpeached character, <lb/>reſiding within the juriſdiction of the college, is
        <lb/>entitled, independently of local ſtudy and local gra- <lb/>duation, to be examined for
        admiſſion into the <lb/>fellowſhip of the college; and if found competent <lb/>in character,
        learning, and ſkill, entitled alſo to be <lb/>incorporated. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>This will be attempted to be eſtabliſhed in <lb/>equity, in law, and in expediency,
        after a previous <lb/>ſtatement of the immediate benefits of admiſſion, <lb/>and the
        indirect and prejudicial conſequences of <pb n="3"/>
        <lb/>excluſion. In equity, by a comparative ſtatement <lb/>of the claims of the licentiates
        and fellows. In law, <lb/>by the ſtrict letter and obvious meaning of the char- <lb/>ter and
        acts of parliament relating to the college; <lb/>by the original incorporation; by the early
        and long <lb/>continued uſage; and by all the authorities on the <lb/>ſubject, prior to the
        late deciſion. In expediency, <lb/>by the advantages, which would accrue to the
        <lb/>corporation, the profeſſion, and the community. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>It will be ſhewn, that two bye-laws, which have <lb/>been alledged to extenuate the
        injuſtice of the <lb/>college, and alleviate the injury ſuffered by the <lb/>licentiates,
        are an aggravation of both. That <lb/>one of them, under which admiſſion has been con-
        <lb/>ceded through favour, is partial, arbitrary, and <lb/>unjuſt: calculated to depreciate
        thoſe admitted <lb/>under it, to divide, depreſs, and impoveriſh the <lb/>great body of
        licentiates, and to exalt and enrich <lb/>the fellows. That the other bye-law is inadequate
        <lb/>and rigorous, and apparently only intended, as it <lb/>has hitherto been employed, to
        deceive. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>It will be finally ſhewn, that the licentiates have <lb/>it in their power, by uniting
        and forming a ſociety <lb/>of their own, to retaliate the wrongs they ſuffer, <lb/>and
        redreſs their grievances, to eclipſe, if not ex- <lb/>tinguiſh the college. </p>
      <pb n="4"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The very able, elaborate, and concluſive argu- <lb/>ments of the counſel for the
        claimant, might well <lb/>be relied on to eſtabliſh the juſtice of the demands <lb/>of the
        licentiates. But the writer of this addreſs is <lb/>impelled by motives which he cannot
        reſiſt, to ex- <lb/>patiate upon this ſubject. After having dedicated <lb/>many years in the
        beſt ſchools of phyſic, to the ſtudy <lb/>of a laborious and expenſive profeſſion, it is
        ſcarce- <lb/>ly poſſible not to feel the injury of being debarred <lb/>its fair advantages.
        On ſeeing others of ſuperior <lb/>pretenſions, and the higheſt qualifications, de-
        <lb/>prived of a juſt privilege, by a party, many of <lb/>whom have neither had the means
        nor the powers <lb/>of attaining equal acquirements; it is impoſſible <lb/>not to feel
        indignation. From the oſtenſible <lb/>ſituation in which the writer has been placed,
        <lb/>his inquiri<unclear>es</unclear>
        <gap reason="illegible"/> the ſubject have been extended, <lb/>his
          conv<unclear>iction</unclear>
        <unclear>of</unclear> the juſtice of the cauſe con- <lb/>ſequently confirmed, and his zeal
        to eſtabliſh the <lb/>right animated. He has been led to inveſtigate <lb/>the queſtion with
        attention, and to diſcuſs it with <lb/>thoſe, who were moſt competent to judge of the
        <lb/>legality, the equity, and the expediency of the <lb/>claim, all which have been
        uniformly corroborated, <lb/>both by inquiry and diſcuſſion. The conviction <lb/>of its
        juſtice has not been ſhaken by the objections <lb/>of the able counſel employed to oppoſe,
        nor even <lb/>by the opinions of the learned judges, who decided <lb/>againſt it. He remains
        firmly convinced, that <pb n="5"/>
        <lb/>both the letter and ſpirit of the charter and act of <lb/>parliament, the original
        incorporation, the early <lb/>uſage, the intereſts of the community, all unite to <lb/>give
        as clear a title to what the licentiates de- <lb/>mand, as ever was brought forward to a
        corporate <lb/>right, in a court of law. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>It may perhaps be thought preſumptuous to <lb/>impeach the deciſion of men of great
        legal weight. <lb/>But the contrary opinion of men of at leaſt equal <lb/>authority would
        alone jutify the meaſure, and re- <lb/>fute the imputation. Beſides, where the ground of
        <lb/>equity, on which a deciſion is founded, is ex- <lb/>plained, every man of common
        underſtanding can <lb/>judge of its rectitude. To expound the true <lb/>meaning of perplexed
        and complicated ſtatutes, <lb/>and to develope the real points of analogy betwixt <lb/>the
        multifarious and intricate caſes, which con- <lb/>ſtitute common law, and queſtions to be
        decided <lb/>by them, require the diſcernment of an expe- <lb/>rienced lawyer. But the
        principles of equity, <lb/>when ſet forth, on which both ſtatutes are enacted <lb/>and caſes
        are decided; and the relation of the <lb/>former, and the analogy of the latter, with points
        <lb/>determined by them, when ſtated, are level to <lb/>common ſenſe. The expediency alſo of
        deciſions <lb/>may, in many inſtances, be better underitood by <lb/>the perſons they affect,
        than by thoſe who deliver <lb/>them. It will ſcarcely be diſputed that a phy- <pb n="6"/>
        <lb/>ſician is more competent to decide what influence <lb/>a monopoly, or an extenſion of
        privileges, in a <lb/>medical corporation, will have, both upon the <lb/>profeſſion and the
        community, than a lawyer. <lb/>There may alſo be caſes where political appre- <lb/>henſions,
        where opinions formerly given, though <lb/>not judicially, where hereditary partiality im-
        <lb/>bibed in infancy and long inculcated, where pre- <lb/>dilection for the feats of
        education <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.75)" n="*">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* It is very remarkable, and perhaps unfortunate, that one <lb/>of the judges, who
            preſided on this trial, had been employed <lb/>when a counſel to ſanction the very
            bye-laws, which were con- <lb/>tended againſt by the licentiates; and that the father of
            another <lb/>of thoſe judges was preſident of the college when they were <lb/>made. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Three of the ſame judges were graduates of the univerſities, <lb/>whoſe excluſive
            privileges were contended againſt. </p>
        </note>, preference <lb/>for thoſe to whoſe ſkill health is conſided, par- <lb/>donable
        biaſes when they do not prejudice the <lb/>rights of others, may imperceptibly warp the beſt
        <lb/>intentioned men, when they venture to decide <lb/>legal claims upon the fallacious
        ground of con- <lb/>ſtructive expediency. The ableſt men are ſome- <lb/>times betrayed into
        error, and the moſt upright <lb/>miſled, when partialities combine with prepoſſeſ-
        <lb/>ſions to influence their judgment. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>When we are unwillingly impelled by a con- <lb/>viction of right, and an obligation of
        duty, to <pb n="7"/>
        <lb/>arraign a deciſion of men of unimpeached in- <lb/>tegrity, and of great ability and
        ſuperior learn- <lb/>ing, it affords an apology to others, and a ſatiſ- <lb/>faction to
        ourſelves, that our opinion is ſupported <lb/>by the higheſt authorities, which can be
        reſorted <lb/>to on the ſubject. That ſatisfaction is heightened <lb/>when peculiar
        circumſtances are diſcoverable, <lb/>which might obſcure the views of ſuch high
        <lb/>characters, on a particular ſubject, on which we <lb/>are endeavouring to invalidate
        their determina- <lb/>tion, without any imputation againſt their inte- <lb/>grity. Beſides
        the motives of preference, which <lb/>it has been alledged might influence the Court <lb/>of
        King's Bench in favour of the college, a de- <lb/>ceptive bye-law was brought forward, which
        <lb/>profeſſed to extend the right of admiſſion, under <lb/>certain reſtrictions, to the
        licentiates. It was <lb/>under the impreſſion that the right of incor- <lb/>poration was in
        an extended to them, and <lb/>that the bye-law requiring previous graduation <lb/>at Oxford
        and Cambridge, illegal when ſtanding <lb/>alone, was qualified and legalized by this
        pretended <lb/>ſource of admiſſion, that the court ſuſtained the <lb/>bye-laws taken
        together. They could not ſuſpect <lb/>the good faith of ſuch a grave body as the College;
        <lb/>much leſs believe them capable of ſuch duplicity, <lb/>as to advance a bye-law in a
        court of juſtice, as <lb/>a mere pretext to deceive. They not only con- <pb n="8"/>
        <lb/>ceived that it was to be honeſtly and fairly <lb/>adhered to, but apparently hoped that
        it might be <lb/>relaxed. This bye-law, as will be ſhewn, is <lb/>totally inadequate to the
        rights of the licentiates, <lb/>and by no means reconciles the deciſion with <lb/>the real
        juſtice of the caſe: but it certainly does, <lb/>when coupled with other circumſtances, in
        ſome <lb/>rneaſure account for, and render it leſs excep- <lb/>tionable. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Previous to any argument to eſtabliſh the equi- <lb/>table claim of the licentiates,
        and to prove that <lb/>both the letter and ſpirit of the charter and act of <lb/>Parliament
        are deciſive in their favour; that the <lb/>original incorporation, the early and long con-
        <lb/>tinued uſage, and the undiſputed joint poſſeſſion <lb/>demonſtrate their right; that
        the opinions of the <lb/>court, in their favour, on the former trials, are ſtrict- <lb/>ly
        in point; and that a liberal conſtruction and en- <lb/>larged expediency, accord with law
        and equity to <lb/>re-eſtabliſh their privileges; it may be proper to <lb/>ſtate the motives
        which have induced the licenti- <lb/>ates, engaged in the conteſt, to endeanour to regain
        <lb/>them. Such a ſtatement will obviate erroneous no- <lb/>tions, hazarded by ſuperficial
        obſervers, that the <lb/>diſputed object is of inconſiderable importance. It <lb/>will
        refute the intereſted objections, under the ſame <lb/>pretext, of thoſe who endeavoured to
        damp the <pb n="9"/>
        <lb/>zeal of the licentiates who ſtood forward; <lb/>and the prudential ones of thoſe, who
        wiſhed to <lb/>excuſe a paſſive acquieſcence in a degrading <lb/>excluſion, by pretending to
        undervalue what they <lb/>were conſcious of being under a profeſſional <lb/>obligation to
        contend for. It will alſo ſupply <lb/>an anſwer to many ſuppoſitions of the ſame
        <lb/>nature, which fell from both the bar and the <lb/>bench. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The College of Phyſicians is an inſititution <lb/>which derives dignity from the
        importance of its <lb/>objects, which are, the ſafety of the public; the <lb/>advancement of
        the ſcience of phyſic; and the <lb/>guardianſhip and promotion of the honour and
        <lb/>intereſts of the profeſſion. It becomes venerable <lb/>from its antiquity, having been
        eſtabliſhed nearly <lb/>three centuries, by a charter confirmed by act of <lb/>Parliament,
        during which period its privileges <lb/>have been repeatedly extended by the legiſlature.
        <lb/>It derives celebrity from the many eminent phy- <lb/>ſicians, who have been its
        members, and luſtre <lb/>from the dignity of their ſtations, as they have <lb/>always filled
        and now enjoy the moſt honourable <lb/>and lucrative profeſſional appointments in this
        <lb/>kingdom. The college poſſeſſes a noble edifice <lb/>for its meetings: A medical
        library, which it has <lb/>the means of rendering the firſt in Europe. It <lb/>enjoys,
        within itſelf, degrees of rank to diſtinguiſh <pb n="10"/>
        <lb/>and reward merit; lectureſhips and literary ap- <lb/>pointments to excite emulation,
        and afford an <lb/>honourable field for the diſplay of genius and <lb/>learning; and the
        diſpoſal of gratuities to re- <lb/>munerate exertion. It eſtabliſhes an advantage- <lb/>ous
        intercourſe betwixt riſing merit and mature <lb/>experience, and enables the deſerving
        aſpirer to <lb/>obtain the friendſhip and profit by the good <lb/>offices of his ſeniors,
        who are the beſt judges of <lb/>his claims, and the moſt able to promote his <lb/>intereſts.
        It raiſes its members to rank and <lb/>precedency in the profeſſion, and conſequently,
        <lb/>elevates them in the eſtimation of the public, and <lb/>facilitates their ſucceſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Theſe direet advantages, which the college <lb/>confer upon its members, are too
        important to <lb/>the intereſts of a phyſician to be paſſively relin- <lb/>quiſhed. But
        when, under the intereſted manage- <lb/>ment of a party, all their indirect conſequences
        <lb/>are conſidered, their influence in promoting the <lb/>fellows, and depreſſing the
        licentiates, will be <lb/>found ſo powerful, that it becomes an obligation <lb/>of private
        intereſt, as well as of profeſſional hon- <lb/>our, to regain, if poſſible, the right of
        admiſſion. <lb/>From the operation of the college monopoly, a <lb/>prejudice is diffuſed
        that its members, it not the <lb/>only real phyſicians in London, are, at leaſt, greatly
        <lb/>ſuperior in education, learning, and ſkill, as well <pb n="11"/>
        <lb/>as rank, to thoſe whom they only tolerate. This <lb/>is by no means an extraordinary
        deluſion, when <lb/>countenanced and inſinuated, by a body, who, <lb/>actuated by a
        corporate ſpirit and intereſted <lb/>zeal, unite with collegiate power and rank, with
        <lb/>diſtinctions, titles, and ceremonies, the ſymbols of <lb/>ſuperiority, the actual
        poſſeſſion of the moſt dig- <lb/>nified and lucrative appointments. This preju- <lb/>dice,
        however unfounded, is too ſpecious not <lb/>to miſlead a great part of the public, too
        beneſi- <lb/>cial to the fellows not to be encouraged by them, <lb/>and too flattering not
        to deceive even themſelves. <lb/>This prepoſſeſſion neceſſarily leads to the aſſump-
        <lb/>tion of that ſimulated ſuperiority, which promotes <lb/>the deluſion; and the habit of
        oſtentation not <lb/>unfrequently betrays the actor into a notion of <lb/>the actual
        exiſtence of the rank he attempts to <lb/>diſplay. The college monopoly has thus the
        <lb/>ſtrongeſt tendency, and frequently the effect, of <lb/>inflating the fellows with
        arrogance, and of humi- <lb/>liating and depreſſing the licentiates, of exciting <lb/>mutual
        jealouſies, of raiſing an obſtacle to all <lb/>bonds of friendſhip, and even to a liberal
        and <lb/>ſocial intercourſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>In addition to the vulgar grounds of prejudice, <lb/>apothecaries, who have ſo much
        influence on the <lb/>ſucceſs of phyſicians, have peculiar motives for <pb n="12"/>
        <lb/>preferring members of the college. They them- <lb/>ſelves form a corporation, and
        corporate bodies <lb/>ſympathize with each other. The charter of the <lb/>apothecaries was
        obtained with the concurrence <lb/>and by the joint intereſt of the college, to which
        <lb/>it ſecures great authority and controul. The two <lb/>corporations have always been
        intimately con- <lb/>nected, and the apothecaries accuſtomed to con- <lb/>ſider the fellows
        of the college as their ſuperiors <lb/>and patrons. Beſides, the natural pride of man
        <lb/>unwillingly allows priority of rank, where pre- <lb/>tenſions are of a ſimilar nature,
        if the line of <lb/>diſtinction is faintly drawn; more eſpecially, <lb/>where the admiſſion
        implies ſuperiority in learn- <lb/>ing, judgment, and ſkill. Apothecaries naturally
        <lb/>prefer thoſe who confer, and who can extend to <lb/>them, the privilege of acting as
        phyſicians, to a <lb/>ſubordinate claſs, only practiſing by permiſſion, <lb/>whom they are
        encouraged to conſider as ſcarcely <lb/>raiſed above themſelves. There can be no doubt
        <lb/>that men of diſcernment and candour, and parti- <lb/>cularly apothecaries of that
        deſcription, who are <lb/>acquainted with the licentiates, do juſtice to their <lb/>merits,
        and rank them with the ableſt of the pro- <lb/>feſſion. But however numerous the exceptions,
        <lb/>the multitude will always be influenced by names, <lb/>appearances, pretenſions, and
        faſhion. Indepen- <lb/>dently of their real power and advantages, the <pb n="13"/>
        <lb/>oſtenſible and aſſumed ſuperiority of the fellows <lb/>operates forcibly and
        extenſively to the prejudice <lb/>of the licentiates. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The preference ariſing from this unjuſt pre- <lb/>poſſeſſion, is not the only unfair
        advantage de- <lb/>rived from their monopoly. In conſequence of <lb/>a community of
        intereſts, a combination of in- <lb/>fluence, and uniformity of ſyſtem, they have alſo
        <lb/>got poſſeſſion of the moſt lucrative and dignified <lb/>appointments and ſituations in
        the profeſſion; <lb/>which they transfer, tranſmit, and perpetuate, in <lb/>their own party.
        For this their powers are nearly <lb/>as infallible, as their conduct is invariably directed
        <lb/>by the corporate intereſt. Their dominion in me- <lb/>dical appointments is ſo
        extenſive, that they can <lb/>generally decide the conteſts of licentiates for thoſe
        <lb/>inferior ſituations, which fellows decline, in favour <lb/>of the candidate they
        patronize. The ſucceſs of <lb/>a licentiate, however ſuperior his merit, againſt
        <lb/>another ſupported by the college, is very rare; <lb/>againſt a fellow, almoſt without
        example. But <lb/>if they ſhould even fail in obtaining for a mem- <lb/>ber of the college
        any appointment, which is <lb/>conteſted, they can aſſociate the ſucceſsful opo- <lb/>nent,
        and transfer his power and credit to their <lb/>own party, if intereſt inclines them. The
        ſame <lb/>corporate ſpirit and common intereſt, which ce- <lb/>ment the fellows in obtaining
        for each other <pb n="14"/>
        <lb/>public appointments, render them equally zea- <lb/>lous in advancing each other, in
        private practice, in <lb/>preference to the licentiates. If they do not abſo- <lb/>lutely
        enter into an engagement to recommend each <lb/>other excluſively on conſultations, as
        ſubſtitutes, <lb/>as ſucceſſors, in every ſituation of advantage, their <lb/>attachment to
        the corporate intereſt has all the <lb/>force of a bond. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>It is ſcarcely conceivable what influence a <lb/>public body, endowed with power,
        poſſeſſed of <lb/>wealth, elevated by popular prepoſſeſſion, and <lb/>united by intereſt,
        has, to promote their joint and <lb/>individual intereſts. Their power and profits are
        <lb/>equally concentrated. What the individual loſes <lb/>or declines, the corporation
        preſerves. The <lb/>licentiate is carefully excluded. After the fruit- <lb/>leſs toils and
        diſappointed expectations of many <lb/>years, he ſtill ſees a new ſucceſſion of younger
        <lb/>fellows exalted above him, by college influence. <lb/>No wonder while he has to
        ſtruggle againſt ſo <lb/>powerful and zealous a combination, if his ad- <lb/>vancement be
        ſlow, and his deſert unrewarded. <lb/>No wonder if the fellow be raiſed into diſtinction
        <lb/>and affluence, while the licentiate is depreſſed by <lb/>neglect, or even pines in
        indigence. There can be <lb/>no doubt that ſome of the licentiates enjoy a bene- <lb/>ficial
        practice, and that many fill reſpectable and <lb/>even profitable ſituations. The fellows
        are too <pb n="15"/>
        <lb/>few to engroſs every thing. Extraordinary ta- <lb/>lents, exertions, connections, or
        fortune, ſome- <lb/>times advance licentiates to advantageous ap- <lb/>pointments and
        lucrative practice, in oppoſition <lb/>to college influence. But the exceptions only
        <lb/>confirm the grievance. It is manifeſt that the <lb/>college, as now conſtituted, is a
        partial ſource of <lb/>rank, power, and gain to the fellows, and a grie- <lb/>vous cauſe of
        oppreſſion, degradation, and po- <lb/>verty to the licentiates. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Having ſhewn the powerful motives, which the <lb/>licentiates have to emancipate
        themſelves from <lb/>the college yoke, and regain admiſſion, it may be <lb/>proper to give a
        general deſcription of both the <lb/>fellows and licentiates, as diſtinct claſſes of phy-
        <lb/>ſicians. Many, who are but little acquainted <lb/>with the contending parties, may wiſh
        to be <lb/>informed of their comparative merits and equi- <lb/>table pretenſions; how far
        they are reſpectively <lb/>qualified to diſcharge the duties of a profeſſional
        <lb/>corporate truſt; and entitled to ſhare in thoſe <lb/>advantages, which the legiſlature
        has conferred <lb/>upon all competent phyſicians, previous to a <lb/>diſcuſſion of their
        legal right to them. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The fellows are a body conſiſting at preſent <lb/>of forty-four phyſicians, forty of
        whom have gra- <lb/>duated at Oxford or Cambridge, and four have <pb n="16"/>
        <lb/>been admitted, through favour, out of the claſs <lb/>of licentiates; rather more than
        half of theſe only, <lb/>reſide in London. Thoſe phyſicians who graduate <lb/>in the Engliſh
        univerſities, are, frequently, men of <lb/>ſufficient hereditary fortune to purſue ſuch
        orna- <lb/>mental ſtudies, and reſide in ſuch faſhionable <lb/>ſeminaries as are moſt
        agreeable to their inclina- <lb/>tions, and flattering to their vanity, and where
        <lb/>pleaſure, ambition, and contingent advantages <lb/>allure them. After the preliminary
        education of <lb/>public or private ſchools, they, for the moſt part, <lb/>without any
        previous ſtudy of pharmacy, anato- <lb/>my, or any branch of medicine, immediately re-
        <lb/>move to the univerſity. Many of them go there, <lb/>without any fixed future
        deſtination, for improve- <lb/>ment in polite literature and general knowledge, <lb/>and to
        obtain the degree of batchelor in arts, <lb/>previous to the choice of a profeſſion. They
        are <lb/>then induced to prefer the profeſſion of phyſic, <lb/>after a prudential
        comparative view of its ad- <lb/>vantages, or from ſome promiſing expectancy, as <lb/>may
        beſt ſuit their inclinations and intereſts. <lb/>Many, no doubt, go with an original
        deſtination <lb/>for the faculty of medicine, under an impreſſion, <lb/>that the
        opportunities of general inſtruction, the <lb/>chance of forming profitable connections, the
        <lb/>proſpect of procuring valuable fellowſhips, and <lb/>the privilege of future admiſſion
        into the college <lb/>of phyſicians, may more than compenſate the de- <pb n="17"/>
        <lb/>ficient opportunities of acquiring medical know- <lb/>ledge, and the protracted period
        of arriving at a <lb/>doctor's degree. After they have been admitted <lb/>of ſome college in
        one of theſe univerfities, eleven <lb/>years muſt elapſe before that degree can be ob-
        <lb/>tained. The previous degrees of bachelor in arts, <lb/>maſter of arts, and bachelor in
        phyſic, muſt alſo <lb/>be conferred on them, before they can be cre- <lb/>ated doctors in
        phyſic. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Such a period for ſtudy and to many honours <lb/>ſeem to imply conſiderable literary
        and medical <lb/>attainments, and theſe, in many inſtances, are un- <lb/>doubtedly,
        attained. The period of actual reſi- <lb/>dence may be, however, and generally is, abridged
        <lb/>to leſs than one third of the nominal time, and <lb/>to a ſhorter period than the
        licentiates uſually <lb/>reſide in approved medical ſchools. Though exa- <lb/>minations,
        preliminary to each of the above- <lb/>mentioned degrees, are required, they alſo may
        <lb/>be, and often are, in a great meaſure, eluded. <lb/>With the aid of preparatory
        ſchemes, containing <lb/>technical and formal anſwers, which are very <lb/>commonly uſed,
        very little real knowledge is re- <lb/>quiſite to perform them. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The opportunities of improvement in Oxford <lb/>and Cambridge in languages, in abſtract
        ſciences, <lb/>and polite literature, are conſiderable, and phyſi- <pb n="18"/>
        <lb/>cians educated in either of thoſe univerſities, are <lb/>frequently accompliſhed
        ſcholars. But the pre- <lb/>ſumptive claims of ſuch phyſicians to a medical
        <lb/>inftitution, eſtabliſhed by the legiſlature for the <lb/>incorporation of every
        competent phyſician, with- <lb/>out limitation to the graduates of thoſe univer-
        <lb/>ſities, muſt depend on their means of improve- <lb/>ment as ſchools of phyſic. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>What then are their reſources for medical <lb/>inſtruction? Are they ſo pre-eminently
        ſuperior <lb/>as to ſuperſede intirely the pretenſions of phyſi- <lb/>cians educated in
        every other univerſity? They <lb/>are, in every branch of the art, totally inadequate,
        <lb/>and comparatively contemptible. Bodies for <lb/>diſſection and anatomical demonſtration
        can only <lb/>be procured from London, at an expence and <lb/>with difficulties, which
        almoſt preclude the ſtudy <lb/>of anatomy. There are ſcarcely any opportuni- <lb/>ties for
        inveſtigating the ſymptoms of diſeaſes, <lb/>and obſerving the effects of medicines. There
        are <lb/>but few, if any, clinical lectures for explaining <lb/>them. There are no lectures
        for teaching the theory <lb/>or the practice of phyſic. There are no libraries <lb/>or
        collections of importance appertaining pecu- <lb/>liarly to the profeſſion; no ſocieties for
        diſcuſſing <lb/>ſubjects, which relate to it. There are not ſtu- <lb/>dents to excite the
        exertions of the profeſſors, or <lb/>to animate and improve each other. <pb n="19"/>
        <lb/>So totally inadequate are the means of medical <lb/>improvement, that ſcarcely more
        than one ſtudent <lb/>graduates in phyſic, annually, in either of the <lb/>Engliſh
        univerſities. There are indeed profeſſors <lb/>endowed with ſalaries, men of learning and
        ta- <lb/>lents. Some of them alſo give lectures on collate- <lb/>ral branches, calculated to
        give general notions of <lb/>the ſubjects they treat of; but by no means adapt- <lb/>ed to
        medical ſtudents. Their lectures, even on <lb/>theſe acceſſary ſciences, muſt neceſſarily be
        ac- <lb/>commodated to the ſuperficial views of their au- <lb/>ditors, ſtudents of general
        literature, whoſe pur- <lb/>ſuits will not allow them to penetrate into ſciences, <lb/>with
        which their intereſts are only remotely con- <lb/>nected. Were their lectures adapted to
        medical <lb/>ſtudents, they would probably be only attended <lb/>by a ſolitary candidate for
        the doctoral honours <lb/>and advantages. The graduates in medicine, at <lb/>Oxford and
        Cambridge, are therefore reduced to <lb/>the neceſſity of acquiring their profeſſional know-
        <lb/>ledge, for which their own univerſities do not <lb/>afford the means, in real medical
        ſchools. They <lb/>are obliged to make the knowledge of their pro- <lb/>feſſion ſubſidiary
        to thoſe collateral and orna- <lb/>mental branches, which they have an opportunity <lb/>of
        acquiring; and thus, what ought to be their <lb/>principal object of purſuit is poſtponed,
        and be- <lb/>comes only the acceſſary. Notwithſtanding the <pb n="20"/>
        <lb/>eſſential deficiency of their early education, and <lb/>while they remain in the
        Engliſh univerſities, <lb/>by ſuperadding the inſtruction of real medical <lb/>ſchools, many
        of them become eminently learned <lb/>and ſkilful phyſicians, as well as accompliſhed
        <lb/>ſcholars. Their right to participate in the higheſt <lb/>profeſſional honours is not
        diſputed. But that <lb/>they ſhould monopolize them excluſivcly, becauſe <lb/>they have
        graduated where their profeſſion can- <lb/>not be learned, is repugnant to equity and common
        <lb/>ſenſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The licentiates are a claſs, amounting at pre- <lb/>ſent to one hundred and ten
        phyſicians, who have <lb/>had nearly ſimilar educations with all thoſe in <lb/>the Britiſh
        dominions, the few from Oxford and <lb/>Cambridge only excepted. Their hereditary for-
        <lb/>tunes are, in general, leſs conſiderable than thoſe <lb/>of the fellows. Their love of
        eaſe, or predilection <lb/>for elegant purſuits remotely connected with the <lb/>knowledge
        and duties of their profeſſion, cannot <lb/>be ſo eaſily indulged. They cannot ſo conve-
        <lb/>niently prolong their reſidence in the moſt expen- <lb/>ſive and diſſipated ſchools,
        where a knowledge of <lb/>medicine cannot be acquired; nor protract the pe- <lb/>riod of
        determining on their profeſſion, and of de- <lb/>riving emolument from their exertions, to
        procure <lb/>adventitious honours. They are, however, with few <pb n="21"/>
        <lb/>exceptions, men of ſufficient fortune to obtain all <lb/>the important advantages of
        education. They are <lb/>early placed in the beſt ſchools, where they com- <lb/>monly remain
        till they have acquired that ele- <lb/>mentary knowledge of languages and ſciences,
        <lb/>which enables them to proſecute their various <lb/>profeſſional ſtudies, and often to
        become emi- <lb/>nently diſtinguiſhed for general learning. They <lb/>are afterwards uſually
        placed with an apothe- <lb/>cary, for inſtruction in pharmacy; a ſituation not <lb/>ſo
        flattering to vanity, nor ſo favourable for polite <lb/>accompliſhments, as a college, but
        highly ad- <lb/>vantageous and neceſſary for the preliminary in- <lb/>ſtruction of a
        phyſician. They learn there to <lb/>diſtinguiſh, ſelect, and preſerve, and alſo to pre-
        <lb/>pare and compound, thoſe materials, with which <lb/>they are chiefly to accompliſh all
        that future <lb/>learning and ſkill can enable them, in curing <lb/>or alleviating diſeaſe.
        An accurate knowledge <lb/>of medicines, the primary and indiſpenſible <lb/>part of the
        education of every practitioner of <lb/>phyſic, can only be obtained by actually prepar-
        <lb/>ing them. The pupil of an apothecary is early <lb/>habituated, not only to diſtinguiſh
        and prepare, <lb/>but alſo to obſerve the quantities and propor- <lb/>tions adminiſtered,
        and the operation and powers <lb/>of remedies. In addition to theſe important
        <lb/>advantages, and that of learning pharmaceutic <lb/>chymiſtry, the ſituation generally
        admits of much <pb n="22"/>
        <lb/>reading, frequently of anatomical inſtruction, and <lb/>ſometimes of attending
        lectures. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The real ſtudents in medicine, after having <lb/>thus acquired the elements of medical
        knowledge, <lb/>proceed to thoſe ſchools, which ſupply the beſt <lb/>opportunities of
        further inſtruction in their pro- <lb/>feſſion. They ſelect univerſities and ſeminaries,
        <lb/>where medicine flouriſhes, regardleſs of antiquity <lb/>of eſtabliſhments, local
        prejudices, oſtentatious <lb/>diſtinctions, titular honours, or aſſumed privi- <lb/>leges.
        They purſue their inquiries where they <lb/>are not clogged by unprofitable reſtrictions,
        and <lb/>idle formalities and ceremonies, the ſuperſtitious <lb/>and exploded uſages of dark
        ages, ſtill retained <lb/>in Oxford and Cambridge, which conſume time, <lb/>enhance expence,
        and abridge improvement. <lb/>They proſecute their reſearches where diſeaſe <lb/>ſupplies
        its martyrs for inveſtigating its cauſes and <lb/>its cure; and death its victims, to
        inſtruct the <lb/>future guardian of health to arreſt its fatal pro- <lb/>greſs. They ſtudy
        where experienced and cele- <lb/>brated profeſſors, large and well regulated hoſpi-
        <lb/>tals, extenſive and choice collections of natural <lb/>productions and artificial
        preparations appertain- <lb/>ing to medicine, and where copious and acceſſible <lb/>medical
        libraries offer the fulleſt means of inſtruc- <lb/>tion: where ſocieties for diſcuſſing
        profeſſional <lb/>ſubjects ſtimulate inquiry and promote communi- <pb n="23"/>
        <lb/>cation; where the thronged claſs calls forth all <lb/>the powers of the teacher, and
        emulation ani- <lb/>mates the ſcholar <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Edinburgh enjoys all theſe advantages, and is annually <lb/>attended by more
            medical ſtudents, than have ſtudied either at <lb/>Oxford or Cambridge during any two
            centuries ſince their <lb/>foundation. </p>
        </note>. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>But though medicine, which includes ſo many <lb/>branches of ſcience, engages their
        chief attention, <lb/>they muſt of neceſſity learn the dead languages, na- <lb/>tural
        hiſtory and natural philoſophy, and are ſeldom <lb/>entirely unacquainted with the more
        abſtruſe <lb/>ſciences, polite literature, and modern languages. <lb/>Theſe, however, they
        cultivate as ſubordinate to <lb/>the more immediate branches of their profeſſion, <lb/>and
        they generally find, and frequently avail them- <lb/>ſelves of the moſt ample means of
        inſtruction in <lb/>them, where medicine is at the ſame time beſt <lb/>taught. Wherever the
        beſt opportunities of in- <lb/>ſtruction are preſented, they in general purſue <lb/>it,
        without being confined to any ſchool or any <lb/>country <note n="†" rend="size(0.75)"
          place="bottom">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>† Many of the licentiates, after having accompliſhed their <lb/>degree at home,
            have ſtudied in foreign ſchools, where there <lb/>are excellent opportunities of medical
            improvement. </p>
        </note>. If a genuine medical education, in <lb/>the purſuit of which the accompliſhments of
        the <lb/>ſcholar and the gentleman are not neglected, can <lb/>complete the phyſician, the
        licentiates are indiſ- <lb/>putably intitled to rank with the higheſt claſs of <lb/>the
        profeſſion, either at home or abroad. For <pb n="24"/>
        <lb/>their moral conduct, there is every ſecurity, which <lb/>reſpectable connections and
        the conſequent ad- <lb/>vantages of good example, and the early initia- <lb/>tion of good
        principles can produce, ſtrengthened <lb/>by habits of induſtry, liberal purſuits, and
        ſociety, <lb/>and the dependence of future ſucceſs upon irre- <lb/>proachable character.
        From men animated by <lb/>ſuch inducements, improved by ſuch culture, and <lb/>reſtrained by
        ſuch obligations, much undoubtedly <lb/>might be expected. Experience will be found <lb/>to
        confirm what their advantages promiſe, that no <lb/>body of phyſicians contains a greater
        proportion <lb/>of members diſtinguiſhed by highly cultivated <lb/>talents, active and
        uſeful exertions, valuable pub- <lb/>lications and diſcoveries, and upright and honour-
        <lb/>able conduct, than the excluded licentiates. They <lb/>do not reſt their equitable
        claims to ſhare their <lb/>profeſſional honours of their country, impartially <lb/>provided
        by the legiſlature for every competent <lb/>phyſician, on preſumptive grounds of merit,
        <lb/>though it is indiſputable that they poſſeſs thoſe, <lb/>which give the ſtrongeſt
        claims. In addition to <lb/>theſe grounds, they appeal to experience whe- <lb/>ther they
        have not always been as able, active, <lb/>and efficient in improving every branch of their
        <lb/>profeſſion, and in practiſing it ſucceſsfully and <lb/>beneficially for the community
        as the graduates <lb/>of Oxford and Cambridge. They alſo appeal to <lb/>experience, whether
        thoſe of their body, who <pb n="25"/>
        <lb/>have obtained that admiſſion into the college, <lb/>through favour, which they were
        entitled to by <lb/>right, have not diſcharged the duties and truſts of <lb/>the corporation
        with equal ability and integrity. <lb/>When their education, their talents, their acquire-
        <lb/>ments, are conſidered; when their labours, diſco- <lb/>veries, and publications, their
        private worth and <lb/>public ſervices are eſtimated; when their compa- <lb/>rative merits
        are weighed; when it is admitted <lb/>that they have the ſame pretenſions as nearly all
        <lb/>the phyſicians in the kingdom, and that they <lb/>actually form the great body of the
        faculty in <lb/>the metropolis; can any candid, any equitable, <lb/>any honourable man, deny
        their right, in point of <lb/>juſtice, to be admiſſible into a medical corpora- <lb/>tion?
        into an inſtitution, the only objects of which <lb/>are, to ſecure the public from
        illiterate and un- <lb/>principled impoſtors in phyſic, and to promote <lb/>the honour and
        intereſt of learned, upright, and <lb/>able phyſicians? </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Under what equitable pretence can the few <lb/>graduates from Oxford and Cambridge,
        ſcarcely <lb/>ſufficient to perform the neceſſary duties of the <lb/>college, monopolize
        ſuch an inſtitution in a free <lb/>and enlightened country? How can they juſtify <lb/>the
        libel, implied by rejection, upon the edu- <lb/>cation of nearly every Britiſh phyſician?
        upon <pb n="26"/>
        <lb/>every real medical univerſity? How palliate <lb/>the rejection, with all its
        humiliating and inju- <lb/>rious conſequences, of ſuch a body as the licen- <lb/>tiates, who
        with all the preſumptive proofs of <lb/>fitneſs, which the almoſt uniform education of
        <lb/>their profeſſion ſupplies; challenge and ſolicit any <lb/>equal teſts of learning and
        ſkill that can be <lb/>eſtabliſhed? </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Oxford and Cambridge are ſeminaries, where <lb/>men of the moſt exalted genius and
        profound <lb/>erudition, where the wiſeſt and beſt men that ever <lb/>honoured this or any
        country have been educated. <lb/>But of all the ſciences, perhaps medicine alone <lb/>has
        never flouriſhed in either. It is ſcarcely known <lb/>that medicine is taught in them even
        in this <lb/>country, and unknown upon the continent that <lb/>ſuch ſchools of phyſic exiſt.
        Can there be a more <lb/>deciſive proof of their inſignificancy, than that, in <lb/>general,
        not more than one or two doctors in <lb/>phyſic graduate annually at either, even notwith-
        <lb/>ſtanding the temptation of their indirect and con- <lb/>tingent beneficial
        conſequences. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Were they as celebrated as they are obſcure, as <lb/>medical ſchools; were there no
        others, which af- <lb/>ford adequate opportunities of inſtruction exiſt- <lb/>ing; there
        would, even then, be only the ſame <pb n="27"/>
        <lb/>plea for excluding thoſe from the college, who had <lb/>not been educated in them, that
        there is now for <lb/>rejecting thoſe, whoſe education has been confined <lb/>to theſe
        univerſities. But the means of medical <lb/>improvement are ſo inconſiderable, that there
        pro- <lb/>bably never was a member of the college, whoſe <lb/>education was ſo confined. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>At the period when the charter was originally <lb/>granted, Italy was the chief ſeat of
        medical in- <lb/>ſtruction. France, Holland, and Germany, have <lb/>been ſucceſſively
        diſtinguiſhed by the moſt cele- <lb/>brated medical ſchools, as Scotland is at preſent.
        <lb/>But in the viciſſitudes of revolving centuries, the <lb/>Engliſh univerſities have
        never emerged from ob- <lb/>ſcurity as the theatres of medicine. It is, how- <lb/>ever, from
        Oxford and Cambridge, that the col- <lb/>lege candidates aſſume their title to ſhare in the
        <lb/>monopoly, whilſt it is in the ſchools of the licen- <lb/>tiates that they learn their
        profeſſion. Medical <lb/>ſcience muſt be courted where ſhe reſides: with <lb/>Boerhaave, in
        Holland; in Germany, with Haller; <lb/>or, with Cullen, at Edinburgh. Let the metro-
        <lb/>polis of England and the college of London <lb/>concentrate her rays from every quarter
        of the <lb/>globe, and not be confined to the glimmerings of <lb/>ſchools, where medicine is
        unknown. Suppoſe <lb/>the univerſities of Oxford and Cambridge ſhould <lb/>ceaſe to teach
        phyſic; be entirely deſerted by <pb n="28"/>
        <lb/>medical ſtudents; or be totally aboliſhed as public <lb/>ſeminaries; muſt the college
        of phyſicians and <lb/>the ſtate of medicine in the metropolis depend <lb/>on their caprice;
        decline with their decay; and <lb/>the college be annihilated by their extinction?
        <lb/>Could the legiſlature ever intend, or, at this pe- <lb/>riod, give its ſanction to ſuch
        an abſurdity? </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>It is melancholy to obſerve, how frequently in- <lb/>ſtitutions, founded in virtue and
        wiſdom, and con- <lb/>fided to men, whoſe education, abilities, and <lb/>ſituation in
        ſociety, impoſe on them the ſtrongeſt <lb/>obligations to diſcharge their truſt with
        integrity <lb/>and fidelity; it is lamentable to reflect, how often <lb/>they are narrowed
        by jealouſy and avarice, and <lb/>perverted by ſelfiſhneſs, ſo as even to counteract
        <lb/>diametrically their original and manifeſt intention, <lb/>and, from ſources of
        beneficence and utility, to be <lb/>converted into inſtruments of injutice and op-
        <lb/>preſſion. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>As a pretext to extenuate their conduct, the <lb/>graduates of Oxford and Cambridge
        boaſt of <lb/>ſuperior knowledge of the dead languages, and <lb/>in the preliminary and
        ornamental branches of <lb/>education. Are then the vehicle and embelliſh- <lb/>ment of
        medical knowledge of more importance <lb/>to a phyſician than the ſcience and practice of
        <lb/>medicine? Is there not the ſame probability that <pb n="29"/>
        <lb/>the licentiates excel in the latter, as that the fel- <lb/>lows are ſuperior in the
        former? </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Admit their pretenſions in the dead lan- <lb/>guages, can it be aſſerted that the
        licentiates are <lb/>not ſufficiently acquainted with theſe for the <lb/>purpoſes of medical
        learning? Do they not un- <lb/>dergo repeated examinations, on various ſubjects, <lb/>in the
        Latin language; and do they not challenge <lb/>any teſts of knowledge of the Greek, which
        the <lb/>fellows will undertake? </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>If it be conceded that the fellows may boaft a <lb/>more critical knowledge of the dead
        languages, <lb/>an aſſumption, which can only be allowed with <lb/>many exceptions, it will
        ſcarcely be queſtioned <lb/>that the licentiates are more converſant in the <lb/>modern
          <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* The period, which muſt elapſe before the degree of doctor <lb/>in medicine can be
            obtained in the Engliſh univerſities, is an <lb/>obſtacle to ſtudying in foreign
            ſchools. </p>
        </note>; in which medical information has for <lb/>ſometime been chiefly conveyed, and to
        which, <lb/>in future, it is likely to be principally confined. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>How ridiculous for men of acknowledged eru- <lb/>dition to be ſcrupulouſly balancing
        their ſeparate <lb/>acquirements and pretenſions, which muſt vary in <lb/>each, as genius,
        opportunity, or inclination have <pb n="30"/>
        <lb/>directed. Medicine is connected with ſo many <lb/>branches of knowledge, that the
        ſhortneſs of life <lb/>and imbecillity of human efforts are unequal to <lb/>their
        attainment. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The greateſt names in which the profeſſion can <lb/>glory, are monuments, at the ſame
        time, of know- <lb/>ledge and ignorance, of wiſdom and error. Hip- <lb/>pocrates lamented
        the brevity of life, the extent <lb/>of art, the tranſientneſs of opportunity, and the
        <lb/>fallacy of experience. Boerhaave adopted as his <lb/>motto <note n="*" place="bottom"
          rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Simplicitas ſigillum veritatis. </p>
        </note>, <q rend="quotes">ſimplicity is the ſymbol of truth; </q> and <lb/>Cullen with equal
        modeſty, <q rend="quotes diple">to be free from folly <lb/>is the beginning of wiſdom <note
            n="†" place="bottom" rend="size(0.75)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>† Initium ſapientiæ ſtultitia caruiſſe. </p>
          </note>. </q> And ſhall a <lb/>few individuals, with vain preſumption, mono- <lb/>polize a
        public ſcientific inſtitution, under a diſ- <lb/>puted claim of ſuperior knowledge in
        collateral <lb/>and ſubordinate branches, which, if conceded, <lb/>renders it probable that
        they are inferior in the <lb/>fundamental and eſſential departments of their
        <lb/>profeſſion? The queſtion is not whether the gra- <lb/>duate of Cambridge excels in
        mathematics, of <lb/>Oxford in polite literature, or of Edinburgh in <lb/>the theory and
        practice of phyſic? it is whether <lb/>the candidate for admiſſion into the college, is
        <lb/>competently learned and ſkilful in phyſic? </p>
      <pb n="31"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Without then diſputing their ſeparate advan- <lb/>tages, and their reſpective
        attainments, there can <lb/>be no doubt that both claſſes are highly cul- <lb/>tivated, and
        that neither is intitled to arrogate <lb/>ſuperiority, much leſs to deprive the other of
        thoſe <lb/>equal rights, which, if not reſtricted by law, <lb/>ought, in equity, to be
        extended to every well <lb/>educated and well qualified phyſician. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>It has alſo been alledged, in juſtification of the <lb/>monopoly, that it is difficult
        to aſcertain the ſuf- <lb/>ficiency of a candidate for a medical college, <lb/>without an
        adequate knowledge both of his pre- <lb/>vious opportunities of improvement, and alſo of
        <lb/>his attainments and conduct. It is aſſerted, that <lb/>graduation in the Engliſh
        univerſities, is a pre- <lb/>ſumptive proof of fitneſs, both in learning and <lb/>morals;
        and that phyſicians who graduate elſe- <lb/>where, having no fixed plan of education, do not
        <lb/>poſſeſs the ſame preliminary recommendation. <lb/>Leaving out of the conſideration the
        total in- <lb/>adequacy of Oxford and Cambridge as ſchools of <lb/>phyſic; admitting that a
        degree from either is <lb/>intitled to all the weight that a preſumptive proof, <lb/>drawn
        from local ſtudy and graduation, can have; <lb/>ought it as ſuch to be excluſively intitled
        to at- <lb/>tention? While nearly all the phyſicians in the <lb/>kingdom, and dominions of
        Great Britain, are <lb/>induced to ſtudy and graduate in other univer- <pb n="32"/>
        <lb/>ſities; are there not preſumptive proofs beſides, <lb/>which may intitle a candidate to
        have his qualifi- <lb/>cations even examined? Is it not juſt that cor- <lb/>roborating
        evidence of ſufficiency in any profeſ- <lb/>ſion ſhould be deduced from the actual period of
        <lb/>the candidate's ſtudies; and from his efficient op- <lb/>portunities of improvement, in
        that art or ſcience <lb/>of which he claims the privileges, independently <lb/>of local
        reſidence? The licentiates ſtudy in public <lb/>ſeminaries, where their application,
        improvement, <lb/>and moral conduct are obſerved, both by their <lb/>teachers and
        cotemporary ſtudents; and where <lb/>their reſpective characters are well known. Their
        <lb/>diplomas are certificates, and evidence of their <lb/>probity, as well as learning. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>If the mere time required to attain a doctor's <lb/>degree in Oxford or Cambridge be a
        reaſon why <lb/>men, who have obtained theirs in other univer- <lb/>ſities, in a ſhorter
        period, ſhould not be admitted, <lb/>immediately after graduating, to equal privileges;
        <lb/>cannot an additional period for improvement and <lb/>probation, and to equalize the
        pretenſions of the <lb/>latter in this reſpect, be added to that they have <lb/>previouſly
        paſſed, and given certificates of, in ap- <lb/>proved medical ſchools? </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Where actual teſts of competency can be re- <lb/>ſorted to, preſumptive and acceſſary
        proofs may <pb n="33"/>
        <lb/>be in a great meaſure diſpenſed with: but the <lb/>licentiates do not object to every
        candidate being <lb/>obliged to prove that he has ſtudied an adequate <lb/>time, in good
        medical ſchools, and received from <lb/>thence certificates of probity and learning. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>It has indeed been objected to their claim, that <lb/>there are phyſicians, who have
        purchaſed degrees <lb/>without having ever ſtudied in any univerſity. <lb/>Such degrees are
        undoubtedly intitled to very <lb/>little reſpect, and, affording no preſumptive proof
        <lb/>of fitneſs, might juſtify, if not the rejection of <lb/>perſons claiming to be examined
        for admiſſion <lb/>under them, the ſtricteſt application of the real <lb/>teſts, and an
        extended period of probation. But <lb/>thoſe, who have procured ſuch nominal degrees
        <lb/>are only exceptions, which cannot prejudice the <lb/>rights of the great body of well
        educated phyſi- <lb/>cians: of phyſicians who have ſtudied longer, in <lb/>the beſt medical
        ſchools, than the graduates of <lb/>Oxford or Cambridge have, in general, either ſtu-
        <lb/>died medicine, or reſided in thoſe univerſities. The <lb/>licentiates are as zealous as
        the fellows can be, <lb/>that ſtrict precaution ſhould be obſerved in the <lb/>admiſſion of
        members. They wiſh that undoubted <lb/>teſts of ability and learning ſhould be indiſpenſibly
        <lb/>required. They do not object to reſtrictions ex- <lb/>acting a certain period of ſtudy
        in approved <lb/>medical ſchools, and a mature period of life to <pb n="34"/>
        <lb/>be attained before admiſſion into the college. <lb/>Whatever impartial regulations,
        wiſdom can dic- <lb/>tate and juſtice ſanction, they approve. But they <lb/>contend that, as
        far as is conſiſtent with the <lb/>intereſts of the college, the rights of phyſicians
        <lb/>ought to be impartially admitted. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>It has been ſhewn that the phyſicians of Ox- <lb/>ford and Cambridge are few in number,
        ſcarcely <lb/>ſufficient to perform the neceſſary duties of the <lb/>college and keep up the
        ſucceſſion <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* The number of offices, with duties annexed, almoſt equals <lb/>the number of
            efficient members. </p>
        </note>: that <lb/>thoſe univerſities are totally inadequate to a <lb/>medical education,
        and therefore cannot entitle <lb/>their graduates to any preference, much leſs to <lb/>an
        excluſive monopoly of a medical corporation <lb/>inſtituted for public purpoſes. It has been
        <lb/>ſhewn that the licentiates are a numerous body, <lb/>of the ſame claſs, ſimilarly
        educated, and poſſeſſed <lb/>of the ſame pretentions with nearly all the phy- <lb/>ſicians
          <note n="†" place="bottom" rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>† The number of phyſicians who have graduated at Oxford <lb/>and Cambridge, and who
            are not members of the college, is very <lb/>inconſiderable. </p>
        </note> in Great Britain, Ireland, and the Britiſh <lb/>dominions: that they, in general,
        have had the <lb/>beſt medical education which can be obtained, <lb/>either at home or
        abroad, and are in fact learned, <lb/>ſkilful, and upright phyſicians. It has alſo been <pb
          n="35"/>
        <lb/>ſhewn, that every objection againſt them, whether <lb/>real, or even only alledged, may
        be obviated by <lb/>regulations <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* A candidate might be required to have attained his <lb/>thirtieth year; to have
            employed ſeven years in the ſtudy of <lb/>phyſic in approved ſchools; to have graduated
            in a reſpectable <lb/>univerſity, where previous reſidence and teſts of learning and
            <lb/>probity are required. But with ſuch preſumptive claims he <lb/>ought to be admitted
            by right to examination: and it approved, <lb/>admitted by right to incorporation, on
            having completed his <lb/>year of probation as a candidate. </p>
        </note> which, with the actual teſts of <lb/>examination, would amply ſecure the intereſts
        <lb/>and dignity of the college, and allow their right <lb/>of admiſſion on equitable terms.
        Having eſtabliſh- <lb/>ed theſe premiſes, it is manifeſt that the equitable <lb/>right of
        every phyſician of mature age to be <lb/>examined, who has had an adequate medical
        <lb/>education, without regard to local ſtudy or local <lb/>graduation, is incontrovertible.
        His right to be <lb/>afterwards admitted a member of the college, if <lb/>found competent,
        is alſo equally indiſputable. <lb/>It remains to be conſidered, whether the right ſo
        <lb/>eſtabliſhed in equity is barred in law. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>In order to eſtabliſh the legal right of the <lb/>licentiates to have their
        qualifications for ad- <lb/>miſſion into the college of phyſicians examined, <lb/>it is
        important to premiſe ſome rules of law, with <lb/>regard to the conſtruction of charters and
        ſtatutes, <pb n="36"/>
        <lb/>and reſpecting the evidence, which ought to <lb/>govern deciſions both on individual
        and corporate <lb/>rights. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>As legal axioms, the following are perhaps <lb/>ſufficiently obvious: but it is
        neceſſary to ſtate <lb/>them as premiſes of a concluſion,which invalidates <lb/>the deciſion
        of a court of juſtice. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Conſiſtency, ſtability, and ſecurity require, that <lb/>the letter of legiſlative acts
        ſhould ſtrictly and <lb/>rigidly govern the deciſions of courts of law, in <lb/>caſes where
        the intention of the legiſlature is <lb/>clearly expreſſed. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Where the language of an act is not explicit, <lb/>with regard to any point under
        deciſion, the <lb/>true legal meaning, when it can be clearly <lb/>deduced from the context,
        is equally binding. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Where the intention of the legiſlature is doubt- <lb/>ful, with regard to any litigated
        point under deci- <lb/>ſion, the court ought to conſtrue it liberally, for <lb/>the benefit
        of the community. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Where the intention of a party, who obtained <lb/>a parliamentary grant, can be
        aſcertained, it is a <lb/>ſtrong evidence of the intention of the legiſlature <lb/>with
        regard to that party. </p>
      <pb n="37"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Where uſage is reſorted to, in order to illuſ- <lb/>trate the nature and extent of a
        grant, the <lb/>uſage of thoſe who obtained it, of their co- <lb/>temporaries, and immediate
        ſucceſſors, is moſt <lb/>deciſive. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Where parties have fully and unconditionally, <lb/>during a long period, and jointly
        and equally <lb/>enjoyed the ſame privileges, under one common <lb/>grant, it is a mutual
        conceſſion and ſtrong evi- <lb/>dence that they are equally intitled. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>When a court of law, after full and repeated <lb/>hearings, deliberately, repeatedly,
        and without <lb/>diſſent, lays down the law, with regard to the <lb/>real points at iſſue
        between two parties; and <lb/>when theſe opinions are legally reported, they <lb/>conſtitute
        a high legal authority; though the <lb/>deciſion upon the caſe might turn upon errors
        <lb/>in the proceedings, or upon circumſtances foreign <lb/>to its real merits. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Where the letter and ſpirit of a grant, illuſtrated <lb/>by the original intent, uſage,
        and joint poſſeſſion <lb/>of the parties, cannot be made obvious to the <lb/>bench, and
        former opinions are got rid of as not <lb/>being abſolute deciſions in point; when judges
        <lb/>aſſume from neceſſity or choice, the province of <lb/>legiſlators, and regulate what is
        to be law, on <pb n="38"/>
        <lb/>grounds of expediency, their views ought to be <lb/>liberal and comprehenſive, and
        their determina- <lb/>tions, made for the many not for the few, <lb/>ought to extend, not
        abridge, the privileges of <lb/>thc community. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Theſe are rules, with regard to the deciſion of <lb/>caſes, which may be conſidered as
        eſtabliſhed <lb/>legal maxims. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The following poſitions, reſpecting the nature <lb/>of corporations, and their rights
        and duties, are, <lb/>it may he preſumed, equally indiſputable. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>An aggregate corporation is a politic body, <lb/>conſtiting of ſeveral individuals,
        united together <lb/>for public purpoſes, and their own advantage; <lb/>inveſted with
        privileges and immunities, and <lb/>bound by duties according to its charter and <lb/>acts
        of Parliament concerning it. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>A corporation is bound to act up, to the de- <lb/>ſign for which it was inſtituted. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Perpetual ſucceſſion is an inherent right, and a <lb/>main end, of every corporate
        body. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Every corporation is bound to admit all, who <lb/>are eligible under the letter, and
        true meaning <pb n="39"/>
        <lb/>and intent of its charter, and of acts of parlia- <lb/>ment concerning it. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Corporations may make bye-laws for the regu- <lb/>lation of their proceedings, but they
        cannot <lb/>change the nature of the ſucceſſion, and give <lb/>themſelves a new mode of
        exiſtence. They can- <lb/>not ſuperadd qualifications for admiſſion not re- <lb/>quired by
        their charter and acts of parliament <lb/>concerning them. They cannot narrow the num-
        <lb/>ber of the eligible. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>It is taken for granted that the above poſitions, <lb/>as well as thoſe, which precede
        them, reſpecting <lb/>the rules of evidence and the grounds of deciſions, <lb/>are ſettled,
        indiſputable legal maxims, which <lb/>ought to govern courts of law in their determina-
        <lb/>tion of cauſes reſpecting corporate rights. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>We ſhall next proceed to prove, by deciſive <lb/>evidence, that the letter and ſpirit
        of the charter, <lb/>which originally incorporated the phyſicians of <lb/>London, and of the
        act of parliament which <lb/>confirmed it, clearly demonſtrate, that the crown <lb/>and the
        legiſlature did thereby grant and convey, <lb/>in perpetuity, to every competent phyſician,
        the <lb/>right of being admitted a member of the corpora- <lb/>tion, if found, upon
        examination, poſſeſſed of the <lb/>qualifications required by the charter and act of <pb
          n="40"/>
        <lb/>parliament. It will alſo be ſhewn, that all prior <lb/>and ſubſequent ſtatutes and
        charters, whether <lb/>completed or only intended, confirm this to have <lb/>been the
        manifeſt intention of the crown and <lb/>of parliament. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The firſt ſtatute which has been diſcovered <lb/>relative to practitioners in phyſic,
        was enacted <lb/>in the ninth year of the reign of Henry V. <lb/>The preamble, after
        reciting the miſchiefs ariſing <lb/>from illiterate practiſers, ſtates, that <q
          rend="diple quotes">if no man <lb/>practiſed therein but al only connynge men <lb/>and
          approved ſufficicntly, y learned in art, <lb/>filoſofye, and fiſyk, <hi rend="italic">as
            it is kept in othur londes and <lb/>roialmes</hi>, ther ſhuld many man that dyeth for
          <lb/>defaute of helpe, lyve, and no man periſh by <lb/>unconnyng. </q> The petition goes
        on to pray, <lb/>that no perſon be allowed to practiſe phyſic <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes diple">bot he have long time y uſed the ſcoles of fiſyk, <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">within ſome univerſitee</hi>, and be graduated in the <lb/>ſame. </q> In
        this firſt act of the legiſlature is <lb/>found the ſame juſt and impartial ſpirit, which
        <lb/>pervades all ſubſequent acts, relative to the pro- <lb/>feſſion. Every phyſician, who
        had employed his <lb/>time, and labour, and money, in ſtudying his pro- <lb/>feſſion, where
        it was properly taught, who had <lb/><hi rend="italic">uſed the ſchools of phyſic and
          graduated</hi>, was, without <lb/>limitation to particular univerſities, entitled to all
        <lb/>the privileges of his profeſſion. The wiſe re- <pb n="41"/>
        <lb/>gulations of other realms are referred to, from <lb/>which the ſuperiority of their
        ſchools of phyſic, <lb/>at that period, and the conſequent higher eſtima- <lb/>tion, in
        which thoſe, who had graduated abroad, <lb/>were held, might be inferred, if not eſtabliſhed
        by <lb/>ample teſtimony. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The next ſtatute, reſpecting phyſicians, was en- <lb/>acted in the third year of the
        reign of Henry <lb/>VIII. After enumerating the ignorant and dan- <lb/>gerous perſons who
        practiſed phyſic, with <q rend="diple quotes">great <lb/>infamy to the faculty, and the
          grievous hurt, <lb/>damage, and deſtruction of many of the king's <lb/>liege people, </q>
        it enacts, <q rend="diple quotes">that no perſon within <lb/>the City of London, nor within
          ſeven miles of <lb/>the ſame, take upon him to exerciſe and occupy <lb/>as a phyſician or
          ſurgeon, except he be firſt <lb/>examined, approved, and admitted by the <lb/>Biſhop of
          London, or by the Dean of Paul's, <lb/>for the time being, calling to him, or them,
          <lb/>four doctors of phyſic; and for ſurgery, other <lb/>expert perſons in that faculty,
          and for the firſt <lb/>examination, ſuch as they ſhall think con- <lb/>venient, and
          afterward, alway <hi rend="italic">four of them that <lb/>have been ſo approved</hi>. </q>
        Here again we find no <lb/>partial limitation. All thoſe, who practiſed as <lb/>phyſicians,
        within the preſcribed juriſdiction, were <lb/>equally ſubject to be examined; and ſuch, as
        were <lb/>approved, were equally intitled not only to prac- <pb n="42"/>
        <lb/>tiſe, but they might alſo perform the higher duty <lb/>of examining and deciding upon
        the qualifications <lb/>of others. This act remained in force ſeven years, <lb/>during which
        period, every phyſician legally prac- <lb/>tiſing in London, and within ſeven miles round
        <lb/>it, muſt neceſſarily have been examined and ap- <lb/>proved. Such approved and legal
        phyſicians <lb/>formed an incomplete politic body, poſſeſſed of the <lb/>excluſive right of
        practiſing, and jointly with the <lb/>Biſhop of London, or Dean of Paul's, the power <lb/>of
        examining others, and of admitting them, if <lb/>competent, both to practiſe and examine.
        This <lb/>ſtatute was ſufficient for confining the practice of <lb/>the metropolis and its
        environs to ſuch as were <lb/>duly qualified. It contained the ſame proviſion for
        <lb/>examination, by four approved examiners or cen- <lb/>ſors, afterwards adopted in the
        ſubſequent charter, <lb/>and alſo the power of impoſing a penalty on ſuch <lb/>as practiſed
        without their approbation. It thus <lb/>provided for the main end of the legiſlature, the
        <lb/>ſafety of the community, in a ſimilar manner. The <lb/>charter was modelled upon this
        ſtatute, and adopt- <lb/>ed its proviſions with regard to the public. It only <lb/>enlarged
        them with reſpect to phyſicians, and muſt <lb/>be conſidered as a continuation and extenſion
        of <lb/>this act. The additional privileges conferred by <lb/>the charter were granted
        chiefly for the beneſit of <lb/>thoſe, who obtained it, and of their ſucceſſors, for
        <lb/>the intereſt and dignity of the faculty of phyſic. <pb n="43"/>
        <lb/>They hitherto only poſſeſſed the right of prac- <lb/>tiſing, and together with the
        Biſhop of London <lb/>or Dean of Paul's, the power of keeping up <lb/>a ſucceſſion of legal
        practitioners. But they en- <lb/>joyed no other legal franchiſe. They had no <lb/>officers
        legally conſtituted, no common ſeal, no <lb/>power of holding property as a body, of ſuing
        <lb/>and being ſued, or making binding regulations, <lb/>which are incident to corporations. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>A charter was therefore petitioned for by ſix <lb/>phyſicians named in the petition,
        under the pa- <lb/>tronage of Cardinal Wolſey, then Chancellor of <lb/>England, who is alſo
        therein named as a petition- <lb/>er. The ſix petitioning phyſicians muſt neceſ- <lb/>ſarily
        have been legally authorized to exerciſe <lb/>their profeſſion. It alſo cannot be doubted
        that <lb/>their application, which was to obtain honours <lb/>and privileges for all of
        their own body, who were <lb/>duly qualified, was made with the concurrence, <lb/>and
        ſupported by the influence of thoſe legal <lb/>phyſicians, who were to ſhare equally with
        the <lb/>petitioners in the beneſits of the grant. Keeping <lb/>in view then that the
        petitioners for the charter <lb/>were members of a body conſtituted by a prior <lb/>statute;
        that every member of that body had <lb/>an intereſt and equal title to what was applied for,
        <lb/>and muſt have exerted a joint influence to obtain <lb/>it; that it was granted by the
        ſame king, and <pb n="44"/>
        <lb/>under the patronage of the ſame miniſter, during <lb/>whoſe reſpective reign and
        influence the prior <lb/>ſtatute had been enacted; that it contained ſimilar <lb/>proviſions
        for the public, and additional ones <lb/>chiefly for the profeſſion. With theſe illuſtrative
        <lb/>facts before us, let us now conſider the words and <lb/>intent of the charter itſelf,
        with regard to the <lb/>perſons incorporated, and the deſcription of per- <lb/>ſons intended
        to keep up the ſucceſſion and per- <lb/>petuate the corporation. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The charter of the college of phyſicians was <lb/>granted by Henry VIII. in the tenth
        year of <lb/>his reign. It ſets forth: <q rend="diple quotes">That in order to re-
          <lb/>ſtrain the temerity of wicked men, who prac- <lb/>tiſe phyſic from avaricious
          motives, to the <lb/>great detriment of the ignorant and credulous; <lb/>therefore, partly
          in imitation of <hi rend="italic">well regulated <lb/>ſtates in Italy, and many other
            countries</hi>. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>We find here in the preamble of the charter, <lb/>as before in the ſtatute of the ninth
        of Henry <lb/>V. a convincing proof of the high eſtimation <lb/>in which the regulations of
        foreign countries, <lb/>with regard to medicine, were held by the crown, <lb/>as well as by
        the parliament. This affords a <lb/>ſtrong preſumption, that the privileges of phy-
        <lb/>ſicians in England were, as under the former acts <lb/>of parliament, to be extended to
        ſuch as had <pb n="45"/>
        <lb/>ſtudied and graduated in countries where medi- <lb/>cine flouriſhed; and of which the
        wiſe regulations, <lb/>with regard to it, influenced the crown and the <lb/>legiſlature to
        imitate them. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The charter goes on to ſtate, that, <q rend="quotes diple">partly in <lb/>compliance
          with the petition of the grave and <lb/>learned men, John Chambre, Thomas Linacre,
          <lb/>Ferdinand de Victoria, the king's phyſicians; <lb/>and of Nicholas Halſewell, John
          Francis, and <lb/>Robert Yaxley, phyſicians, the king eſtabliſhes, <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >collegium perpetuum doctorum &amp; gravium virorum, <lb/>(a perpetual college of ſedate
            and learned men)</hi>
          <lb/>who may publicly practiſe phyſic in our City <lb/>of London, and its ſuburbs, within
          ſeven miles <lb/>in circumference. </q> This is the conciſe, yet <lb/>definite and
        comprehenſive deſcription of thoſe <lb/>phyſicians, who were to conſtitute the corporate
        <lb/>body. Integrity and learning were the only re- <lb/>quiſites. Having pointed out the
        qualifications, <lb/>the charter proceeds to ſtate the duties of the <lb/>members: <q
          rend="diple quotes">whoſe care it will be, as we hope, <lb/>as well out of regard to their
          own honour, as to <lb/>public utility, to diſcourage by their own ex- <lb/>ample and
          authority, the ignorance and raſhneſs <lb/>of thoſe crafty people, whom we have made
          <lb/>mention of, and to puniſh them, both by our <lb/>laws lately made public, and by
          decrees to be <lb/>eſtabliſhed by the college itſelf. </q> The ſame <pb n="46"/>
        <lb/>legal phyſicians, who had given teſts of their <lb/>gravity and learning, and had acted
        under the <lb/>prior ſtatute, here referred to, were to accompliſh <lb/>the ſame objects,
        within the ſame juriſdiction, <lb/>by the ſame and ſimilar means only. The charter <lb/>goes
        on to ſtate: <q rend="diple quotes">In order that theſe ends may <lb/>be more readily
          accompliſhed, we grant to the <lb/>aforeſaid John Chambre, Thomas Linacre, &amp;c.
          <lb/>phyſicians, <hi rend="italic">quod ipſi omneſque homines ejuſdem fa- <lb/>cultatis de
            &amp; in civitate predicta ſint in re &amp; nomine <lb/>unum corpus &amp; comunitas
            perpetua ſive collegium per- <lb/>petuum.</hi>
        </q>
        <hi rend="italic">(That they, and all men of the ſame <lb/>faculty, of and in the aforeſaid
          city, be in fact and in <lb/>name one body and perpetual commonalty, or perpetual
          <lb/>college.)</hi> Need there a comment? Can dulneſs <lb/>miſtake, or caſuiſtry evade?
        Can language and <lb/>intention be more explicit? A charter is granted <lb/>to ſix perſons
        therein named, that they and all <lb/>other men of the ſame faculty ſhall conſtitute one
        <lb/>body and perpetual corporation. Can it be a <lb/>queſtion, whether men of the ſame
        faculty, with <lb/>the qualifications required by the charter in the <lb/>higheſt degree, in
        the preciſe ſituation with reſ- <lb/>pect to claims of thoſe who obtained it, are
        <lb/>legally entitled to the corporate franchiſes? <lb/>Their right, under the expreſs terms
        and letter <lb/>of the charter, is too clear to require to be <lb/>illuſtrated by additional
        facts, or enforced by fur- <lb/>ther arguments. <pb n="47"/>
        <lb/>The charter, having pointed out its objects, the <lb/>qualifications and general duties
        of the members <lb/>of the college, the perſons of whom it ſhould <lb/>then, and for ever
        afterwards conſiſt, proceeds to <lb/>eſtabliſh the officers it ſhall have and their duties,
        <lb/>and the farther privileges it ſhall enjoy. <q rend="diple quotes">The <lb/>college
          ſhall have power to elect annually, for <lb/>ever, out of their own body, one diſcreet and
          <lb/>ſkilled in the faculty of medicine, to be pre- <lb/>ſident of the ſaid college; to
          ſuperviſe, regulate, <lb/>and govern, for the year, the ſaid college or <lb/>commonalty,
          and all men of the ſame faculty, <lb/>and their affairs. </q> The power, here conferred
        <lb/>on the preſident, extends not only to the corpo- <lb/>rators, but to all men of the
        ſame faculty. The <lb/>charter wiſely provides, that thoſe, who are in- <lb/>capable of
        becoming members, or who refuſe to be <lb/>incorporated, ſhall not be exempted from its
        juriſ- <lb/>diction. Otherwiſe, the very evils, it was granted <lb/>to ſuppreſs, would be
        ſanctioned by it. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The power of perpetual ſucceſſion, of having a <lb/>common ſeal, of purchaſing lands,
        of ſuing and <lb/>being ſued, are next conceded; and the charter <lb/>goes on to grant: <q
          rend="diple quotes">that the college may hold <lb/>lawful aſſemblies among themſelves, and
          make <lb/>ſtatutes and regulations for the <hi rend="italic">wholeſome govern- <lb/>ment,
            ſuperviſing and correction</hi> of the ſaid college <lb/>or commonalty, and of all men
          exerciſing the <pb n="48"/>
          <lb/>ſame faculty in the ſaid city, and within ſeven <lb/>miles round the ſame. </q> The
        power of making <lb/>bye-laws of regulation is inherent in all corpora- <lb/>tions. It is
        here expreſsly granted, with the re- <lb/>ſtriction of their being ſalutary, which enforces
        a <lb/>condition to be always preſumed in law. But <lb/>can a bye-law, which changes the
        nature of the <lb/>ſucceſſion, which diſinherits the legitimate ſuc- <lb/>ceſſors, which
        ſhuts out a majority of the eligible, <lb/>which ſubverts the conſtitution of the
        corporation, <lb/>which endangers its extinction, be conſidered, in <lb/>contemplation of
        law, as a mere regulation <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* The bye-law confining the right of examination for ad- <lb/>miſſion, into the
            claſs of candidates and ſubſequent incorpora- <lb/>tion, to the graduates of Oxford and
            Cambridge, is attended <lb/>with all theſe evils. </p>
        </note>? If <lb/>it could be ſo ſtrained and perverted, could preju- <lb/>dice diſtort it
        into a ſalutary regulation? </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The next clauſe of the charter grants to the <lb/>college: <q rend="diple quotes">that
          no one ſhould exerciſe the ſaid <lb/>faculty in the ſaid city, or ſeven miles round it,
          <lb/>unleſs admitted to this privilege by the ſaid <lb/>preſident and commonalty, or their
          ſucceſſors, <lb/>for the time being, by letters of the preſident <lb/>and college, given
          under their common ſeal. </q>
        <lb/>It is manifeſt from the clauſes, authorizing the <lb/>preſident to ſuperviſe the
        college and all men of <lb/>the ſame faculty, empowering the college to <pb n="49"/>
        <lb/>make bye<unclear>-</unclear>laws for their own body and all others <lb/>of the ſame
        faculty; and from this laſt recited <lb/>clauſe, enabling them to puniſh all, who practiſed
        <lb/>medicine without their permiſſion; that there <lb/>were perſons, in the contemplation
        of the charter, <lb/>who might be allowed to practiſe without being <lb/>entitled to be
        admitted members. The juriſdiction <lb/>of the college extended to all who practiſed me-
        <lb/>dicine in any line or degree; whether as phyſi- <lb/>cians, as ſurgeons, or
        apothecaries; as oculiſts, or <lb/>partial practiſers in any branch of the profeſſion.
        <lb/>lt is evident that the metropolis muſt always have <lb/>contained a numerous body, who
        would not come <lb/>within the deſcription and meaning of the charter <lb/>as eligible for
        admiſſion, and who might, notwith- <lb/>ſtanding, be permitted to practiſe under the ſuper-
        <lb/>intendence and controul of the college. It is, in <lb/>fact, proved from their own
        annals, that ſuch per- <lb/>ſons were ſo permitted. But can a power of ex- <lb/>cluding ſuch
        as are incompetent in education or <lb/>learning, or unfit, from the partial and inferior
        lines <lb/>of the profeſſion they have choſen, authorize the <lb/>rejection of thoſe, who
        have <hi rend="italic">long time uſed the ſchools <lb/>of phyſic, and graduated in the
          ſame</hi>, as required by <lb/>the ſtatute of Henry V? of thoſe of the ſame
        <lb/>deſcription, who were admitted <hi rend="italic">both to practiſe and <lb/>examine</hi>
        under the ſtatute of Henry VIII? of thoſe <lb/>who poſſeſs the <hi rend="italic">learning
          and diſcretion</hi> required <lb/>by the charter, and <hi rend="italic">are groundedly
          learned and <pb n="50"/>
          <lb/>deeply ſtudied in phyſic</hi>, as required by the confirma- <lb/>tory act of
        parliament? If this be jutiſiable, the <lb/>power of thoſe, in poſſeſſion of the college, of
        <lb/>admitting others is perfectly arbitrary. They <lb/>could alſo at pleaſure, and with
        comparative pro- <lb/>priety, exclude the very deſcription of phyſicians <lb/>they now
        admit. The dictates of reaſon, the <lb/>rules of equity, the maxims of law, would, in
        <lb/>this caſe, be perfectly nugatory, as applied to the <lb/>conſtruction of this charter.
      </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
