<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Bell: Observations on the mode of attendance of the surgeons of
          Edinburgh</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Benjamin Bell</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">Observations on the mode of attendance of the surgeons of Edinburgh
              on the Royal Infirmary; in a letter addressed to the Royal College of Surgeons; by
              Benjamin Bell.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">N10022</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/N10022"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Edinburgh</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: printed by Adam Neill and Company, 1800.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1800</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="24"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">National Library of Medicine</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3308559432</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K005796.000 </idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Public welfare and institutional"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front> </front>
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_2"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>OBSERVATIONS, &amp;c. </head>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">O</hi>N returning lately from a long journey, I found on my <lb/>table
        various communications from the College of Sur- <lb/>geons, reſpecting the Chirurgical
        Department of the Royal <lb/>Infirmary, a ſubject highly intereſting to the College, to the
        <lb/>Hoſpital, and to the Public, in ſo far as, whatever relates to <lb/>the ſtudy and
        practice of Surgery in this place, will, in a con- <lb/>ſiderable degree, be found to depend
        on it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Theſe communications were accompanied with a requeſt, <lb/>that any plan which I wiſhed
        to ſuggeſt for regulating the <lb/>attendance of Surgeons on the Infirmary, might be
        delivered <lb/>by the 27th of laſt month:—This it was not in my power to <lb/>accompliſh;
        but I may not yet be too late in communicating <lb/>my opinion; and in doing ſo in a matter
        which involves ſuch <lb/>variety of intereſt, I judge it right to ſtate ſome of the reaſons
        <lb/>on which it is founded. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_3" n="4"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In thus addreſſing a letter to the Members of the College <lb/>of Surgeons, I have not
        the vanity to think, that I ſhall have much influence on their deciſions; but in a matter of
        ſuch im- <lb/>portance as this undoubtedly is, I conſider it as a duty incum- <lb/>bent on
        every individual of our number, to let his opinion be <lb/>clearly ſtated: ſo that the
        ſubject may be fully conſidered, <lb/>and in every variety of view, before the College, as a
        public <lb/>body, ſhall take an important ſtep which cannot be recalled, <lb/>as muſt be the
        caſe if it ever ſhall collectively adopt and de- <lb/>clare, any opinion or reſolution, on a
        queſtion ſo nearly con- <lb/>nected with the intereſt of the public. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In regard to the legal right of the College of Surgeons to attend the Infirmary in
        rotation, the conſequence of an agree- <lb/>ment entered into, upwards of ſixty years ago,
        between the <lb/>Members of the College at that time, and the Managers of <lb/>the
        Infirmary; as very oppoſite opinions have been given of it <lb/>by good lawyers, it would be
        preſumption in others, not ver- <lb/>ſant in the law, to judge of it. But with this
        difference of <lb/>opinion among the counſel who have been conſulted, on the <lb/>only point
        upon which the claim of the College of Surgeons <lb/>reſts; with much uncertainty,
        therefore, of ſucceſs, were it to <lb/>become a queſtion at law; we are all entitled to
        judge of any <lb/>meaſure that ſhall pledge the funds of the College, or rather <lb/>the
        property of our poor, on the event of an expenſive—doubt- <lb/>ful litigation, which might
        not be brought to a concluſion du- <lb/>ring the exiſtence of any of our preſent number. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Even in this view of the buſineſs, and thinking, as I do, <lb/>that the tranſaction on
        which the claim of the College of <lb/>Surgeons reſts, was unguardedly entered into on the
        part of <lb/>thoſe Managers of the Infirmary by whom it was conducted, <lb/>who in this
        matter appear to have done what their charter <lb/>does not warrant, I am clearly of
        opinion, if the Managers <pb xml:id="page_4" n="5"/>
        <lb/>are now reſolved on making it a queſtion, as ſeems to be their <lb/>intention, that the
        College ought to depart from it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But were the legal rights of the College on this point even <lb/>eſtabliſhed, I would
        ſay, as on all occaſions I have done, that <lb/>we ought freely, and of our own accord, to
        relieve the Mana- <lb/>gers of the Infirmary, from the effect of a tranſaction which
        <lb/>ought never, in my opinion, to have taken place; which I <lb/>have always conſidered as
        prejudicial to the Infirmary, with- <lb/>out anſwering any good purpoſe to us; whilſt it did
        not tend <lb/>to afford ſuch advantages to the pupils who daily reſort to the <lb/>Infirmary
        for improvement, as there is reaſon to ſuppoſe they <lb/>might have reaped from the practice
        being conducted by a <lb/>limited number of Surgeons, ſelected for the purpoſe, and pla-
        <lb/>ced on a fixed eſtabliſhment; inſtead of being under the di- <lb/>rection of any ſet of
        practitioners changed in rotation every <lb/>two or three months, or on any ſyſtem of
        rotation that can <lb/>be propoſed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Thus ſituated, the College of Surgeons, have, in every re- <lb/>ſpect, acted as well as
        the ſame number of practitioners, un- <lb/>der ſimilar circumſtances, any where could have
        done; and I <lb/>doubt not of the Managers of the Infirmary being clearly of <lb/>this
        opinion: But I alſo believe, that the buſineſs would have <lb/>been conducted with more
        accuracy and care, if it had been <lb/>left entirely to a few: If, however, the majority of
        our num- <lb/>ber are not of this opinion, the meaſure to which I allude, <lb/>that of our
        departing voluntarily from the right which hi- <lb/>therto we have claimed, to attend the
        Infirmary in rotation, <lb/>will neceſſarily be rejected; which moſt ſincerely I ſhall de-
        <lb/>plore, as to me it appears, that in adopting the conduct which <lb/>I have propoſed,
        the College would act more conſiſtently with <lb/>its character as a public body, and, on
        the whole, that more <lb/>ſatisfaction would reſult from it, than is ever likely to be the
        <lb/>caſe, from their entering on a tedious lawſuit with the Ma- <pb xml:id="page_5" n="6"/>
        <lb/>nagers of a public charity; in defence of their own rights; <lb/>on a point in which
        the public are materially intereſted; <lb/>which they will not therefore regard with
        indifference; and <lb/>which, after many years of litigation, might probably be <lb/>decided
        againſt us. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Before the College ſhall reſolve on a point of ſuch import- <lb/>ance, attended, as it
        probably would be, with conſequences <lb/>which all of us might regret, they ought to
        conſider, that the <lb/>Managers of the Infirmary, were they even ultimately to loſe
        <lb/>the queſtion in a court of law, might ſtill defeat entirely the <lb/>views of thoſe who
        wiſh for frequent changes in our attend- <lb/>ance, and yet adhere to the very words of
        their agreement <lb/>with the College of Surgeons; by allowing them to attend in
        <lb/>rotation, but inſtead of a change at the end of every two or <lb/>three months, that it
        ſhould only take place every twelfth or <lb/>fifteenth year, as at one period they meant to
        have done. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From every view, therefore, that can be taken of the queſ- <lb/>tion; the uncertainty
        of our prevailing in a trial at law; the <lb/>important loſs which the expence of a tedious
        lawſuit would <lb/>occaſion to our poor, who are ill able to bear it; the power <lb/>which
        the Managers of the Infirmary poſſeſs, whatever the <lb/>event of the litigation may be, of
        diſappointing thoſe who <lb/>wiſh for frequent changes; and the ſatisfaction that we all
        <lb/>would derive, from the Chirurgical Department of the Infir- <lb/>mary being put under
        the direction of ſuch a ſmall proportion <lb/>of our number, as would tend to improve all
        that relates to it; <lb/>I am, from all theſe conſiderations, induced to hope, that the
        <lb/>College will reſolve on reſigning voluntarily all thoſe rights <lb/>in this matter, to
        the Managers of the Infirmary, which hi- <lb/>therto we have claimed; inſiſting on no
        conditional attend- <lb/>ance, and on no other terms but a reſtitution of that ſum
        <lb/>which the College originally gave to the Infirmary, on the <pb xml:id="page_6" n="7"/>
        <lb/>agreement firſt taking place, and to which the Managers will <lb/>not probably diſpute
        their claim. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>While, by this liberal conduct, the College would be entit- <lb/>led to the warmeſt
        thanks of the public, and of all who are <lb/>able to judge of its importance, they will
        alſo derive ſatisfac- <lb/>tion from a ready compliance with the requeſt of the Mana-
        <lb/>gers of the Infirmary, in ſuggeſting that plan for their conſi- <lb/>deration, which,
        in this intereſting buſineſs, ſhall to a majori- <lb/>ty of our number, appear to be the
        beſt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On a point of ſuch general intereſt, ſubmitted to the conſi- <lb/>deration of a large
        Society, much variety of opinion muſt pre- <lb/>vail, and many ſchemes be propoſed; but it
        will be the duty <lb/>of the College to decide on that plan, which they wiſh to re-
        <lb/>commend to the Managers, who will carry it into effect, ei- <lb/>ther in the form in
        which they ſhall receive it, or under ſuch <lb/>modifications as to them it ſhall appear to
        require. It may <lb/>likewiſe be ſufficiently proper for the College to tranſmit to <lb/>the
        Managers of the Infirmary all thoſe plans of attendance, <lb/>whether printed or in
        manuſcript, which individuals of our <lb/>number may incline to ſuggeſt; as I ſhall take the
        charge of <lb/>doing with this. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Having premiſed this explanation of my opinion, and think- <lb/>ing it probable that
        the Managers of the Infirmary may not <lb/>yet be determined whether the Surgeons ſhould be
        put on a <lb/>permanent appointment or not; but of which they will not <lb/>probably remain
        long in doubt; the following articles of a <lb/>plan for a limited courſe of attendance,
        liable to ſuch altera- <lb/>tions as the College ſhall wiſh to propoſe, is in the mean time
        <lb/>offered to their conſideration. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">On</hi> all the Members now on the liſt of the College of Sur- <lb/>geons
        having attended in the preſent courſe of rotation, but <lb/>not till then, Four ſenior and
        Two junior Surgeons ſhall be <pb xml:id="page_7" n="8"/>
        <lb/>elected by the Managers, and to their charge the whole Chi- <lb/>rurgical Eſtabliſhment
        of the Infirmary ſhall be intruſted. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The two eldeſt of this nomination to attend daily when not <lb/>prevented by diſeaſe,
        or ſome other neceſſary cauſe of abſence, <lb/>for the ſpace of ſeven, eight, or ten years,
        as may be agreed <lb/>on,—the longer, in my opinion, the better; each to have the
        <lb/>charge of one ſide of every ward, in the ſame manner as has <lb/>long been the caſe
        with the Phyſicians, and to perform all the <lb/>operations on his own patients, which
        during that period ſhall <lb/>occur. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In abſence of either or both of the acting Surgeons, the <lb/>buſineſs to be done by
        one or both of the two other ſenior <lb/>Surgeons; and in the event of their being alſo
        abſent, by the <lb/>firſt junior Surgeon who can be got. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>No operation of importance to be performed, but with the <lb/>ſanction of a
        conſultation, at which all the ſix Surgeons may <lb/>attend, but which neceſſarily ſhall
        conſiſt of three, the acting <lb/>Surgeons for the time always conſtituting two; if it be
        not in <lb/>accidents requiring immediate aſſiſtance, and when the ſenior <lb/>Surgeons
        cannot be got. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>One of the junior Surgeons to attend daily at the uſual hour <lb/>of receiving
        patients, by which a ſufficient number for con- <lb/>ſultation will always be at hand; and
        to his care all diſſec- <lb/>tions to be intruſted. This attendance of the junior Surgeons
        <lb/>to be regulated by their own convenience, either on changes <lb/>of two, three, or ſix
        months. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>At the end of the period to which their appointment ſhall <lb/>extend, the two acting
        Surgeons ſhall reſign their places to <lb/>the other two ſenior Surgeons, who being
        ſucceeded by the <lb/>two junior or aſſiſtant Surgeons, two juniors muſt be elected <lb/>by
        the Managers: And thus, with an election, every ſeven, <lb/>eight, or ten years, as the
        Managers ſhall prefer, of Two ju- <lb/>nior Surgeons, the whole buſineſs will be conducted:
        it be- <pb xml:id="page_8" n="9"/>
        <lb/>ing underſtood, that every vacancy ariſing from death or re- <lb/>ſignation, or any
        other cauſe, ſhall be immediately occupied, <lb/>by the Surgeon, who, in ſeniority, is next
        to him who previ- <lb/>ouſly held the place; and in no inſtance, that a newly elected
        <lb/>Surgeon ſhall be preferred. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> advantages of this ſcheme are, that while it avoids <lb/>all the
        inconveniences which reſult from frequent changes <lb/>of practitioners, no Surgeon, after
        thoſe who are firſt ap- <lb/>pointed, will ever have charge of any important part of the
        <lb/>buſineſs, till, by attending for a conſiderable time as aſſiſtant, <lb/>he has acquired
        experience; nor will any practitioner be <lb/>allowed to occupy the appointment till he is
        too much ad- <lb/>vanced in years. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It alſo would ſecure a regular conſultation daily, with lit- <lb/>tle trouble to the
        practitioners,—an object of much import- <lb/>ance in every plan that can be propoſed, and
        from which, <lb/>much advantage would accrue to the Infirmary: for by this <lb/>arrangement,
        every patient would receive an immediate opi- <lb/>nion,and would not be admitted in the
        view of a future con- <lb/>ſultation, as on the preſent plan of attendance is frequently
        <lb/>found to happen, with caſes for which nothing can be done, <lb/>and by which patients
        are often kept in the Hoſpital, with <lb/>much inconvenience to themſelves, and loſs to the
        funds of <lb/>the inſtitution. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On this plan, all the inconveniences ariſing from conſulta- <lb/>tions being too
        numerous, would likewiſe be avoided. It <lb/>might indeed be an improvement of this, and of
        every plan that <lb/>can be propoſed, to have the number on conſultations limited <lb/>to a
        very few; probably to three: for while all the advanta- <lb/>ges of conſultation are
        obtained from a ſmall number, as <lb/>very univerſally is allowed to be the caſe in private
        practice, <lb/>it would in the ſureſt manner tend to obviate thoſe objections <lb/>to which
        large conſultations are almoſt in all circumſtances <pb xml:id="page_9" n="10"/>
        <lb/>found to be liable; which commonly are ſo great, that few <lb/>Surgeons of experience,
        and in full employment, would enter <lb/>on any charge in which they ſhould be obliged to
        ſubmit to <lb/>them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The chief deficiency indeed of the plan which I thus <lb/>ſuggeſt for your
        conſideration, and for that of the Managers <lb/>of the Infirmary, is, that it does not
        ſecure to the Infirmary, <lb/>ſo long as in various circumſtances might be deſirable, the
        <lb/>exertion of thoſe Surgeons, who, from their abilities, expe- <lb/>rience, and
        reputation, the Managers might ſtill wiſh to re- <lb/>tain: and this I muſt acknowledge is a
        very important ob- <lb/>jection to every ſcheme in which it occurs: for all mankind,
        <lb/>and patients in Hoſpitals among others, are abundantly ſen- <lb/>ſible of the various
        advantages which in every branch of <lb/>the medical preſeſſion are derived from experience,
        when <lb/>conjoined with ſufficient abilities, humanity and attention; <lb/>without which
        indeed it ſignifies nothing. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In every ſimilar inſtitution of importance of which we <lb/>have any account, whether
        in England or other parts, ſuch <lb/>value is placed on the advantages which experience
        affords, <lb/>that the Surgeons in almoſt the whole of them are now put <lb/>on a permanent
        footing; and for this very obvious reaſon, <lb/>that no Surgeon with a riſing reputation,
        ſuch as the Mana- <lb/>gers of any public inſtitution would wiſh their practitioners <lb/>to
        poſſeſs, would conceive it to be either for his credit or in- <lb/>tereſt, to accept of the
        appointment under any other con- <lb/>dition; and we all know how feeble thoſe exertions
        common- <lb/>ly are, where the credit and intereſt of thoſe by whom they <lb/>are made, do
        not in a conſiderable degree depend on them: <lb/>and in judging from matter of fact, the
        progreſs which the <lb/>art of ſurgery makes where theſe permanent appointments <lb/>have
        taken place, is ſo evident and great, that we cannot <lb/>doubt of their utility. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_10" n="11"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Before we attempt, therefore, to oppoſe what in a matter of <lb/>this importance other
        large communities have done, who, with <lb/>equal opportunities of judging, and the ſame
        capability of <lb/>doing ſo, have uniformly departed from the limited appoint- <lb/>ment of
        Surgeons to Hoſpitals, and put them on a fixed eſta- <lb/>bliſhment, the moſt ſubſtantial
        reaſons ſhould be ſet forth for <lb/>it; which, ſo far as I know, has neither been done nor
        at- <lb/>tempted. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Of the few objections which have been made to Surgeous <lb/>of large Hoſpitals being
        permanently fixed, the foſlowing <lb/>only ſeem to require notice: That they muſt be apt to
        become <lb/>indolent, to neglect their duty, and, on the approach of old <lb/>age, to do
        harm to the eſtabliſhment of which they have the <lb/>charge, by continuing to operate after
        being unfit for it; and <lb/>as theſe opinions have made an impreſſion on ſome part of
        <lb/>our number, and perhaps alſo on the Managers of the Inſir- <lb/>mary, who may not
        therefore as yet be induced either to <lb/>alter the mode of our attendance ſo completely as
        to render <lb/>it permanent, or to reduce the number of Surgeons ſo much <lb/>as in my
        opinion ought to be done; in offering the foregoing <lb/>plan for their conſideration, I
        have endeavoured to make <lb/>it retain in a conſiderable degree the chief advantages of a
        <lb/>permanent appointment, with a moderate number of practi- <lb/>tioners, without
        ſtretching the principles on which it is found- <lb/>ed too far. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I am not, however, of opinion, that this, or any other li- <lb/>mited attendance of
        Surgeons, will ever prove ſo uſeful to <lb/>the Infirmary, or the City of Edinburgh, as
        permanent ap- <lb/>pointments in other places have done; chiefly for this rea- <lb/>ſon,
        that no practitioners can be ſuppoſed to enter with much <lb/>zeal on this or any other
        appointment, which they know will <lb/>terminate in a few years, and from which, after
        having ſpent <lb/>thoſe years, often the moſt valuable of their lives, in the <lb/>charge
        of, they muſt be turned off, never to be connected <pb xml:id="page_11" n="12"/>
        <lb/>with it again: and if the zeal of thoſe to whom the care <lb/>of any department is
        committed be not fully excited and <lb/>encouraged, thoſe who are beſt acquainted with human
        na- <lb/>ture will admit, that every branch of it will be in the risk of <lb/>being carried
        on with languor, and of ſuffering from want of <lb/>exertion. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This opinion of the permanent appointment of Surgeons <lb/>to large Hoſpitals, being
        apt to leſſen their aſſiduity, and <lb/>in other circumſtances alſo to do harm, in a great
        degree ap- <lb/>pears to be ſpeculative, and not ſupported by experience of <lb/>the effects
        of it: for wherever appointments of this kind <lb/>have taken place, the ſtate of ſurgery
        has been greatly im- <lb/>proved, while in thoſe Hoſpitals which long ago have car-
        <lb/>ried the meaſure into effect, we are not accuſtomed to per- <lb/>ceive that any part of
        the buſineſs is more liable to fall into <lb/>neglect than it is in others; or, in ours,
        where the ſyſtem of <lb/>attending in rotation has been at its height, and of long du-
        <lb/>ration, that it has met with more attention than that which <lb/>Surgeons on permanent
        appointments commonly give to it: <lb/>both plans may occaſionally be ill conducted, and
        every <lb/>mode of attendance that can be propoſed may be produc- <lb/>tive of much harm if
        any important duties are omitted, <lb/>which thoſe in the charge of them ſhould perform; but
        <lb/>without full evidence of the fact, we are not entitled to ſay, <lb/>that the plans of
        attendance which other Hoſpitals have <lb/>adopted, and continue to prefer, are worſe, and
        liable to great- <lb/>er difficulties, than our own. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Thoſe who have been induced to ſupport a different opi- <lb/>nion, ſhould recollect,
        that the bad effects which they ſeem <lb/>to dread from permanent appointments in Hoſpitals,
        are <lb/>powerfully counteracted by many cauſes: the credit of the <lb/>practitioners with
        the public; their real intereſt; and that <lb/>laudable pride which we are bound to believe
        that every man <lb/>muſt feel in the honeſt diſcharge of his duty, whom the Ma- <lb/>nagers
        of a public charity could be ſuppoſed to elect; are all <pb xml:id="page_12" n="13"/>
        <lb/>ſtrong pledges for its being done: beſides which, the conduct <lb/>of practitioners in
        this ſituation, being at all times under the <lb/>direct obſervation of the Managers by whom
        they were e- <lb/>lected,and by whom they can be turned off; before we ven- <lb/>ture to
        aſſert that improprieties from this cauſe take place in <lb/>other Hoſpitals, or that they
        are either likely to happen, or <lb/>to be long permitted to exiſt in ours, we muſt ſuppoſe,
        what <lb/>we are not entitled to do, that the Managers of our public <lb/>charities act
        their parts with groſs miſconduct indeed; as <lb/>would ſurely be the caſe, were they, for
        any length of time, to <lb/>allow the buſineſs of any department, whether that of the
        <lb/>Surgeons, or any other under their charge, to be either ne- <lb/>glected or improperly
        performed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The inconveniences which ſome have ſuppoſed muſt reſult <lb/>from Surgeons with fixed
        appointments in Hoſpitals, being <lb/>apt to continue in the diſcharge of their duty till
        too late a <lb/>period, muſt be equally liable to happen on every plan of at- <lb/>tendance
        in which no reſtriction from age has taken place, as hitherto has been the caſe in ours: but
        in almoſt every Hoſpi- <lb/>tal in which fixed appointments have occurred, theſe incon-
        <lb/>veniences are guarded againſt, by a young practitioner be- <lb/>ing elected as
        aſſiſtant to every ſenior Surgeon, who takes <lb/>charge of all ſuch parts of the duty as
        the other may not be <lb/>able to perform, and who, from being long trained to the bu-
        <lb/>ſiness, is commonly fit for every part of it when it devolves <lb/>on him at laſt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In this manner, and with no expence being incurred by it, <lb/>for ſalaries are ſeldom
        given to aſſiſtants, all the benefit is re- <lb/>tained which the experience and obſervation
        of ſenior prac- <lb/>titioners afford; while, from their being permitted to attend <lb/>as
        long as they incline, every appearance of that ſeverity is <lb/>removed, to which all men
        muſt feel that they are expoſed, <lb/>on being forced to retire from a department of which
        they <lb/>have for a conſiderable time had the ſole charge, and which <lb/>they are ſtill
        both able and willing to continue; a degree of <pb xml:id="page_13" n="14"/>
        <lb/>ſeverity, I may ſafely venture to aſſert, to which no ſet of men, <lb/>intruſted with
        buſineſs of this importance, will in any other <lb/>ſituation be found to be liable. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But while, in the management of other Hoſpitals, it has <lb/>been an object from which
        they never wiſh to depart, to re- <lb/>tain the Surgeons whom they employ as long as they
        incline <lb/>to continue, and thus to obtain the advantages which long <lb/>experience
        gives; in ſaying to the Managers of the Royal In- <lb/>firmary, as many at this time have
        done, that they ſhould li- <lb/>mit the attendance of their practitioners to a few months,
        or <lb/>at moſt to a few years, we deſire them to do the very reverſe, <lb/>and only to
        permit the Surgeons to attend till in ſome degree <lb/>they ſhall have acquired experience;
        then to be diſmiſſed for <lb/>ever, and their places to be ſupplied by young men: thus
        <lb/>tending to produce and to perpetuate a worſe ſyſtem, by a <lb/>great deal, than that
        which they wiſh to be removed; for <lb/>while many inconveniences reſult from attendance in
        rota- <lb/>tion, it does not prevent any of our number from attending, <lb/>and giving their
        aſſiſtance. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Before adopting this opinion, the Managers of the Infir- <lb/>mary will do well to
        advert to this and other bad conſequen- <lb/>ces that may reſult from the Surgeons being
        placed on ſhort <lb/>appointments; and if they are not yet convinced of the <lb/>propriety
        of putting them on a permanent footing, they will <lb/>not readily doubt of protracting
        their attendance to a pe- <lb/>riod of many years. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Were this even to be done, the Managers will not proba- <lb/>bly come under any
        agreement for the ſame plan being con- <lb/>tinued; for, however favourably ſome part of
        their number <lb/>may at preſent think of a limited attendance for the Sur- <lb/>geons,
        there is much reaſon to believe, that, in the courſe of <lb/>a ſhort time, they will wiſh to
        place them on permanent <lb/>appointments. They will alſo, in the conſideration of this <pb
          xml:id="page_14" n="15"/>
        <lb/>point, advert to the difficulty of changing any plan when it <lb/>has been once acted
        upon; that half meaſures ſeldom anſwer <lb/>the purpoſe for which they are meant; and while
        they never <lb/>completely ſatisfy any of the parties concerned in them, they <lb/>are
        commonly more difficult to carry into effect, than others <lb/>that would more fully anſwer
        the purpoſe from the firſt, and <lb/>which of neceſſity are commonly adopted at laſt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the diſcuſſion of this queſtion, it has been alleged, <lb/>that a frequent
        ſucceſſion of Surgeons, whether for two <lb/>months at once, as hitherto has been the caſe
        in the Infir- <lb/>mary, or for ſix months; or, as ſome have propoſed, for two <lb/>or three
        years; would be productive of much advantage to the <lb/>public, which never could ariſe
        from their being put on a <lb/>permanent footing; by affording, as they conceive that li-
        <lb/>mited appointments would do, to a conſiderable number of <lb/>Surgeons, opportunities
        for acquiring experience, and thus <lb/>rendering them more able to diſcharge their duty in
        private <lb/>practice than otherwiſe could be the caſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But it ought to be noticed, that the whole import of this <lb/>argument implies, that
        we are to acquire experience, by <lb/>means which the Managers of the Infirmary are not
        likely <lb/>to admit, and ſhould not therefore be ſtated as a motive for <lb/>the Surgeons
        being put on ſhort appointments; for the mean- <lb/>ing of it certainly is, that from the
        period of our becoming <lb/>Members of the College of Surgeons, we ſhould all be entitled
        <lb/>to attend on frequent changes, and to acquire knowledge and <lb/>dexterity in
        operations, by practiſing on the patients of the <lb/>Infirmary. But while it may be greatly
        for the intereſt of the <lb/>patients that a few Surgeons ſhould be allowed to derive this
        <lb/>advantage from their attendance, with the view of their be- <lb/>ing retained on
        permanent appointments, the Managers will <lb/>not readily be induced to think, that the
        ſame privilege ſhould <lb/>be given to others, or to more than the ſurgical department <pb
          xml:id="page_15" n="16"/>
        <lb/>of the Hoſpital requires; and if this conſideration ſhall be <lb/>allowed to have
        weight, it will be equally obvious, that the <lb/>utility of any plan of attendance which
        they may adopt, muſt <lb/>in a conſiderable degree depend on the period to which it is
        <lb/>made to extend; ſo that, inſtead of appointments of this kind <lb/>being made of ſhort
        duration, few will doubt of the propriety <lb/>of their being protracted to a great length. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Even on the plan which I have propoſed, were the acting <lb/>Surgeons to continue in
        employment only for ſeven years, as <lb/>the aſſiſtants would always be young men, almoſt
        every Sur- <lb/>geon would be ſet aſide by the age of forty-five; often ſome <lb/>years
        ſooner: whilſt, by every other plan which the College <lb/>has received at this time, all of
        which limit the attendance <lb/>of the acting Surgeons to three years, their connection
        <lb/>with the Hoſpital would very commonly end at more ear- <lb/>ly periods, ſomewhere from
        the thirtieth to their thirty- <lb/>fifth year; an age, at which it would undoubtedly be
        more <lb/>for the intereſt of the Hoſpital that they ſhould be retain- <lb/>ed, than to have
        the buſineſs again put under the charge <lb/>of a younger claſs of practitioners.—The
        objections in- <lb/>deed to which all of theſe plans are on this conſideration <lb/>liable,
        appear to me ſo very important, that I am induced to <lb/>believe that they have not been in
        the view of thoſe Gentle- <lb/>men by whom they were propoſed; for they amount preciſe-
        <lb/>ly, as I have already obſerved, to this, that the whole buſineſs <lb/>of Surgery in the
        Infirmary ſhould at all times be in the <lb/>hands of young men, and every practitioner be
        obliged to re- <lb/>tire, never to appear in it again, at the very beſt and moſt uſe-
        <lb/>ful period of his life; conſequences, which they could not <lb/>poſſibly mean to reſult
        from them, and to which it is not <lb/>probable that the Managers will ever oblige the
        patients of <lb/>the Infirmary to ſubmit. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_16" n="17"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But whatever the views of the Managers on this important <lb/>part of the queſtion
        ſhall be, it may eaſily I think be ſhown, <lb/>that while much harm would reſult to the
        Public from the <lb/>Surgeons of the Infirmary being put on ſhort appointments, <lb/>that no
        benefit could ariſe from it to the College of Sur- <lb/>geons. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By the whole chirurgical department of the Infirmary be- <lb/>ing given on a permanent
        appointment to two acting Sur- <lb/>geons, with two junior Surgeons as their aſſiſtants, a
        number <lb/>perfectly ſufficient for every part of it, there is ſurely much <lb/>reaſon to
        believe that the buſineſs would be done with more <lb/>accuracy and attention than it is
        ever likely to be if the num- <lb/>ber to whom it is given ſhall be large; and while the
        prac- <lb/>tice which they would thus poſſeſs in operations might be ſuf- <lb/>ficient for
        adding greatly to the inſtruction of this limited <lb/>number, and might thus render them
        expert Surgeons, yet all <lb/>who advert to the ſmall number of operations which Hoſpitals
        <lb/>not larger than the Royal Infirmary can afford, will admit, <lb/>that if theſe
        operations were divided among many practition- <lb/>ers, liable to frequent changes, their
        effects would be in a <lb/>great meaſure, if not entirely, loſt; and, therefore, that the
        <lb/>Public, as well as the Infirmary, would ſuffer in a very eſſen- <lb/>tial manner, were
        this ever to happen; while no benefit could <lb/>accrue from it to us. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>At all times, it has been my opinion, that, in this view, <lb/>the permanent
        appointment of a few Surgeons to the In- <lb/>firmary, would prove highly uſeful to the City
        of Edin- <lb/>burgh, which in this manner would be ſupplied with a ſuffi- <lb/>cient number
        of Surgeons, in the frequent practice of opera- <lb/>tions, by which alone due perfection in
        the art of performing <lb/>them can either be acquired or preſerved; a poſition which
        <lb/>none will doubt who are able to judge of it. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_17" n="18"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Of the very important advantages which Surgeons derive <lb/>from frequent employment in
        operations, the public indeed are <lb/>ſufficiently aware; and, ſo far as it has been in
        their power, <lb/>they have long done preciſely what the Managers of the In- <lb/>firmary
        ought long ago to have done, by employing a few <lb/>practitioners only as Surgeons: for all
        of us know, and the <lb/>public knows well, that in ſpite of the influence which the
        <lb/>frequent attendance of every member of the College of Sur- <lb/>geons in the Royal
        Infirmary might be ſuppoſed to have, and <lb/>as ſome have alleged that it neceſſarily muſt
        have in this mat- <lb/>ter, ſtill a large proportion of all chirurgical operations per-
        <lb/>formed in Edinburgh, are done by a very ſmall part of our <lb/>number. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Nor is this ſtate of our ſurgery peculiar to the preſent <lb/>times; for it always has
        been the caſe, and as long as the pu- <lb/>blic are able to judge between right and wrong,
        which in all <lb/>that relates to their own ſafety and advantage they are abun- <lb/>dantly
        capable of doing, it will ſtill continue to be ſo: that <lb/>is, till the Managers of the
        Infirmary ſhall reſolve on doing <lb/>what their predeceſſors ought to have done, and ſhall
        appoint <lb/>a few Surgeons to the permanent charge of the ſurgery of <lb/>the Infirmary, to
        the number perhaps of four, the public will <lb/>give a large ſhare of their employment in
        operations, even <lb/>to a leſs number than this, by chiefly reſorting, as hitherto
        <lb/>they have commonly done, to one or two. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A very few Surgeons I believe to be perfectly ſufficient for <lb/>all the real practice
        in ſurgery that Edinburgh is ever likely <lb/>to afford; and for the reaſons that I have
        given, I alſo be- <lb/>lieve, that a very conſiderable part of it will continue to be
        <lb/>done by one or two, till the event to which I allude ſhall take <lb/>place,—the
        appointment of the number that I have mentioned <lb/>to the ſurgical department of the
        Infirmary. If this num- <lb/>ber of Surgeons ſhall be put in poſſeſſion of this department,
          <pb xml:id="page_18" n="19"/>
        <lb/>all of them would be heard of as operators, and each would <lb/>receive that ſhare of
        employment from the public, to which, <lb/>from the general eſtimation in which he might be
        held, he <lb/>ſhould be entitled. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But if many Surgeons ſhould be appointed to this charge <lb/>in the Infirmary, while no
        benefit would reſult from it to the <lb/>inſtitution, the public, for the reaſons I have
        endeavoured to <lb/>enforce, would ſtill continue to give nearly the whole of <lb/>their
        employment to a very few. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Hence, if the views which I have given in this queſtion are <lb/>well founded, and they
        chiefly reſt on facts which few will <lb/>readily diſpute, while very important advantages
        would re- <lb/>ſult to the Infirmary and to the public from their being <lb/>carried into
        effect, by putting the ſurgery of that inſtitution <lb/>under the charge of a few, on
        appointments of long dura- <lb/>tion; it does not appear, that any detriment would reſult
        from <lb/>it to the reſt of our number, who ſtill would continue in the <lb/>very ſame
        employment, which they would otherwiſe poſſeſs; <lb/>which would neither be leſſened or
        extended by this mea- <lb/>ſure; and without performing one operation more or leſs than
        <lb/>they do at preſent, or of incurring the risk, either of their <lb/>emoluments, or
        importance in ſociety, being diminiſhed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Nay, the arrangement to which I allude would ſoon in a <lb/>high degree prove
        ſatisfactory to the whole of our number; <lb/>for being frequently obliged by our patients,
        and we ourſelves, <lb/>in various inſtances, alſo wiſhing, to apply for the aſſiſtance
        <lb/>and advice of thoſe who are more in the habit of performing <lb/>operations, it would
        very commonly be agreeable, and often <lb/>uſeful, rather to have three or four to make
        choice of, than be <lb/>under the neceſſity, as hitherto has very commonly been the
        <lb/>caſe, of reſorting to one or two. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But there is ſtill another very important benefit that would <lb/>reſult from this
        arrangement, which I have always earneſtly <pb xml:id="page_19" n="20"/>
        <lb/>wiſhed were the caſe, which, at no diſtant period, it will pro- <lb/>bably be, and
        which the Managers of the Infirmary have at <lb/>this moment greatly in their power to
        promote, I mean the <lb/>total ſeparation in this place, as already has happened in al-
        <lb/>moſt every large city but our own, of the operative part of <lb/>ſurgery from other
        branches of the profeſſion. Whenever this ſhall be done, and not till then, ſurgery will be
        put on that <lb/>foundation on which alone it ſhould reſt. Other parts of the <lb/>practice
        will then be conducted by one part of our number; a <lb/>nd thoſe by whom the nice and
        important operations of ſur- <lb/>gery are performed, being relieved from the practice of
        every <lb/>other branch of medicine, would, with more certainty be <lb/>enabled to diſcharge
        their duty properly, and to ſtudy with <lb/>due accuracy and attention, thoſe improvements
        which their <lb/>profeſſion might require, than otherwiſe can be in their <lb/>power. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Whatever the reſolution of the Managers of the Infirmary <lb/>on this important point
        may be, no difference will ariſe from <lb/>it to the ſenior part of our Members, all of whom
        will continue <lb/>to poſſeſs the ſame practice which hitherto they have done, <lb/>without
        being affected by any change that can be made in the <lb/>chirurgical department of the
        Infirmary: but this would <lb/>not be the caſe with the younger part of our number; for ſuch
        <lb/>of them as may reſolve on confining their views to ſurgery, <lb/>would advance more
        ſpeedily into employment and notice, <lb/>than commonly happens where every individual is
        attempting <lb/>to act in every branch of the profeſſion, each of which, from <lb/>its
        importance, is ſufficient for any one of us: Nor does this <lb/>opinion reſt on ſpeculation,
        for wherever the meaſure has ta- <lb/>ken place, of ſeparating as much as it can be done,
        the practice <lb/>of ſurgery from that of other branches of the profeſſion, thoſe <lb/>who
        have confined their attention to chirurgical purſuits, <lb/>have arrived much more early in
        life at the height of their <pb xml:id="page_20" n="21"/>
        <lb/>practice and reputation than otherwiſe could probably have <lb/>been the caſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the diſcuſſion of this queſtion, much additional argument <lb/>might have been
        adduced on every part of it, if all that relates <lb/>to it had not already been clearly
        ſtated, and ably conſidered, <lb/>in the Memorial which Dr GREGORY has lately taken the
        <lb/>trouble to write on it, and which the whole of our number <lb/>muſt probably have read. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This Memorial indeed ſets forth in ſtrong colours, and in <lb/>much variety of view,
        every argument that can well be ima- <lb/>gined on the buſineſs to which it relates: but,
        while ſome <lb/>complain of the length to which it extends, and of the aſpe- <lb/>rity of
        manner with which it is written, we ſhould recollect, <lb/>that a very conſiderable part of
        it is employed in reply to <lb/>thoſe arguments which our predeceſſors appear to have
        brought <lb/>forth in ſupport of a diſputed right; that on the queſtion arri- <lb/>ving at
        the ſtate in which it now is, and aſſuming a form <lb/>which muſt bring it to a deciſion,
        theſe arguments came in <lb/>the firſt place, and of neceſſity, to be refuted; that this is
        <lb/>neither the firſt nor the ſecond attempt which the Managers <lb/>of the Infirmary have
        made for the purpoſe of being relieved <lb/>from their agreement with the College of
        Surgeons,—a cir- <lb/>cumſtance, of which many who complain of the length of <lb/>this
        Memorial have not probably been informed; that having, <lb/>on all former occaſions failed
        with means of a different nature, <lb/>and deſpairing of greater ſucceſs from any other mode
        of at- <lb/>tempting it, the Managers appear now to conſider it as their <lb/>duty, freely
        and fully, to ſtate the whole to the public, pro- <lb/>bably as a prelude to that queſtion
        of right which they ſup- <lb/>poſe the College of Surgeons may ſtill endeavour to maintain,
        <lb/>but of which, for the reaſons that I have given, I would glad- <lb/>ly hope, that a
        majority of our number will not approve. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_21" n="22"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>We ought alſo to conſider, that nothing but the beſt and <lb/>pureſt motives could
        actuate Dr <hi rend="sc">Gregory</hi> in this matter: <lb/>having no private intereſt to
        ſerve, nothing but the public <lb/>good could have induced him to appear in it. As a Manager
        <lb/>of a public Charity, labouring under an agreement which the <lb/>Managers for the time
        being, have for theſe fifty years paſt <lb/>conſidered as hurtful, and have often, with much
        anxiety, en- <lb/>deavoured to remove, he, with an unuſual degree of public <lb/>ſpirit, has
        publiſhed one of the moſt convincing papers which <lb/>at any period perhaps has appeared,
        and has placed the matter <lb/>in diſpute in ſuch a light, as muſt of neceſſity accompliſh
        the <lb/>end which he had in view from it: and if he has done this, <lb/>without meaning to
        give offence to individuals, or to degrade <lb/>either our College as a public body, or the
        profeſſion in which <lb/>we are engaged, which I firmly believe to have been the <lb/>caſe,
        inſtead of ſpeaking of his attempt in the manner which <lb/>ſome, I am informed, have done,
        we ought to applaud the <lb/>views which made him engage in it, as well as the abilities
        <lb/>with which it has been conducted. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This intereſting paper being ſufficiently able to ſupport it- <lb/>ſelf, I have no
        other motive for ſpeaking of it, but that of <lb/>wiſhing it to be read with that attention
        which it deſerves, <lb/>particularly by all who wiſh for information on the queſtion <lb/>to
        which it immediately relates; and I can venture to pre- <lb/>dict, that few by whom this
        ſhall be done, will require fur- <lb/>ther evidence of the neceſſity of ſome plan for
        regulating <lb/>the connection of the College of Surgeons with the Royal <lb/>Infirmary,
        being ſpeedily carried into effect. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>With no other views than thoſe which I have ſtated, that <lb/>the practice in which I
        am engaged, the art of ſurgery, <lb/>ſhould be conducted on a plan, which I have reaſon to
        <lb/>think would ſecure to the Royal Infirmary, to the pu- <pb xml:id="page_22" n="23"/>
        <lb/>blic, and to the College of Surgeons, all thoſe advantages <lb/>which could not fail to
        reſult from this important branch of <lb/>our profeſſion being improved; I have freely ſet
        forth thoſe <lb/>ſentiments which I have long entertained of it, leaving it to <lb/>the
        Managers of the Infirmary finally to reſolve on what ap- <lb/>pears to be moſt for the
        intereſt of the charge with which <lb/>they are intruſted. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In a matter which involves ſuch various intereſts, many of <lb/>our number may incline
        to ſtate their opinions to the Ma- <lb/>nagers of the Infirmary, whatever the views may be
        which <lb/>the College, as a public body, may adopt; and if this ſhall be <lb/>generally
        done, and with the ſame freedom of obſervation as <lb/>my ſentiments have thus been given,
        much important infor- <lb/>mation would be obtained by the Managers, which otherwiſe
        <lb/>they may never poſſeſs: I mean the views of thoſe, who, <lb/>from ſeriouſly conſidering
        the ſubject, and being intimately <lb/>acquainted with every part of it, ought to be beſt
        able to <lb/>judge of it: But, while much benefit might accrue from this <lb/>information,
        the Managers will not probably reckon it ſuffi- <lb/>cient. In judging of ſuch an important
        meaſure, the moſt in- <lb/>tereſting, perhaps, which has ever occurred to them, they will
        <lb/>ſcarcely reſt ſatisfied with the opinions which individuals of <lb/>this place may form
        of it: and if they ſhall apply for infor- <lb/>mation, as they probably will do, from London
        and other <lb/>places, in which the ſurgery of Hoſpitals is confined to a <lb/>ſmall number,
        and the whole chirurgical practice of the <lb/>place conducted by a few, they will not fail
        to diſcover, that <lb/>great advantages have been derived from it; and there- <lb/>fore,
        that in fixing on a plan for this important object of <lb/>their attention, they will have
        the aid of experience to de- <lb/>pend on, inſtead of truſting, as otherwiſe they muſt have
        done, <lb/>to diſcordant opinions and vague ſpeculations. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_23" n="24"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>With the Managers of the Infirmary, therefore, the buſi- <lb/>ness now muſt reſt, who,
        having the public intereſt only at <lb/>heart, will do in this matter, without regard to any
        other con- <lb/>ſideration, what is moſt for the intereſt of the Charity of <lb/>which they
        have the charge; and acting on this ſtrong <lb/>ground, as undoubtedly they will do, they
        will not fail to re- <lb/>ceive, as on all occaſions they have done, the moſt ample
        <lb/>proofs of public ſupport and approbation. </p>
      <lb/>
      <dateline rend="size(0.5)"><hi rend="sc">Nicolson's Street</hi>, <lb/>16th October 1800. </dateline>
      <trailer rend="align-center">
        <lb/>FINIS </trailer>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
